<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Frequently Asked Questions</title>
                <title type="short">FAQs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="state-records">
                <head>How can I access Department of State records?</head>
                <p>The Office of the Historian is not the repository for Department of State
                    records.</p>
                <p>Department of State permanent records that are more than 30 years old are
                    transferred to the National Archives and Records Administration (NARA). NARA
                    offers <ref target="https://www.archives.gov/research/foreign-policy">a guide to
                        conducting research in its foreign policy-related holdings</ref>. NARA also
                    provides information about <ref
                        target="https://www.archives.gov/research/foreign-policy/state-dept/agency-records"
                        >its various collections of Department of State agency records, including
                        non-textual media records</ref>. In addition, you can learn about digitized
                    and “born-digital” Department of State records available online <ref
                        target="https://www.archives.gov/findingaid/stat/discovery/59">through
                        NARA’s website</ref>.</p>
                <p>NARA handles personnel records differently than agency records. Information about
                    accessing personnel records is available from <ref
                        target="https://www.archives.gov/st-louis/civilian-personnel">the National
                        Archives at St. Louis</ref>.</p>
                <p>The Office of Information Programs and Services manages more recent Department of
                    State permanent records (those less than 30 years old) that have been “retired”
                    from operational use. To access these records, or very recent records that
                    remain in the custody of their originating bureau or office, you will need to
                    use the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) process. To learn about FOIA and to
                    submit a request electronically, visit <ref target="https://foia.state.gov/">the
                        Department of State’s FOIA website</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="what-is-frus">
                <head>Where can I find information about the <title level="s">Foreign Relations of
                        the United States</title> (<title level="s">FRUS</title>) series?</head>
                <p>The Office of the Historian produces the <title level="s">Foreign Relations of
                        the United States</title> (<title level="s">FRUS</title>) series, which is
                    the U.S. Government’s official documentary history of foreign policy
                    decision-making and significant diplomatic activity. You can <ref
                        target="$app/historicaldocuments/about-frus">learn more about <title
                            level="s">FRUS</title> on our website</ref>.</p>
                <p>We also maintain information about the current status of every <title level="s"
                        >FRUS</title> volume that <ref
                        target="$app/historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series"> is currently in
                        production or published recently</ref>. This page also identifies the
                    volumes that we anticipate publishing this year.</p>
                <p>All published volumes are available online and as downloadable ebooks. You can
                    also <ref target="$app/historicaldocuments/">browse, search, and read our <title
                            level="s">FRUS</title> collection online</ref>. Some recently published
                    volumes may also be available for purchase as printed books from the <ref
                        target="https://bookstore.gpo.gov/catalog/foreign-relations-united-states-series-frus"
                        >Government Publishing Office’s bookstore</ref>.</p>
                <p>Information in <title level="s">FRUS</title> is in the public domain and can be
                    used, copied, and distributed without seeking permission from the Office of the
                    Historian, the Department of State, or any other component of the U.S.
                    Government. <ref target="$app/historicaldocuments/citing-frus">For information
                        about citing <title level="s">FRUS</title> in your own work, please consult
                        our recommendations</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="why-called-state">
                <head>Why is the Department called the Department of State?</head>
                <p>On September 15, 1789, Congress passed “An Act to provide for the safe keeping of
                    the Acts, Records, and Seal of the United States, and for other purposes.” This
                    law changed the name of the Department of Foreign Affairs to the Department of
                    State because certain domestic duties were assigned to the agency. These
                    included:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Receipt, publication, distribution, and preservation of the laws of the
                        United States;</item>
                    <item>Preparation, sealing, and recording of the commissions of Presidential
                        appointees;</item>
                    <item>Preparation and authentication of copies of records and authentication of
                        copies under the Department's seal;</item>
                    <item>Custody of the Great Seal of the United States; and</item>
                    <item>Custody of the records of the former Secretary of the Continental
                        Congress, except for those of the Treasury and War Departments.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Other domestic duties that the Department was responsible for at various times
                    included issuance of patents on inventions, publication of the census returns,
                    management of the mint, control of copyrights, and regulation of immigration.
                    Most domestic functions have been transferred to other agencies. Those that
                    remain in the Department are: storage and use of the Great Seal, performance of
                    protocol functions for the White House, drafting of certain Presidential
                    proclamations, and replies to public inquiries.</p>
                <p>More information on the Great Seal and its history can be found <ref
                        target="https://diplomacy.state.gov/exhibits/explore-online-exhibits/the-great-seal"
                        >at the National Museum of America Diplomacy’s online exhibit</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="secretaries-of-state">
                <head>Where do I find information on past Secretaries of State?</head>
                <p>Our website offers a list of the <ref
                        target="$app/departmenthistory/people/secretaries">Secretaries of
                        State</ref>, their years of service and biographical information, as well as
                    information on their <ref target="$app/departmenthistory/travels/secretary"
                        >official travels</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="department-and-personnel">
                <head>Where can I find information about the history of the Department and its
                    personnel?</head>
                <p>For information about the history of the Department, including key developments
                    in its personnel, visit our website’s <ref
                        target="$app/departmenthistory/timeline">Administrative Timeline</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Where can I find information about diplomatic relations between the United
                    States and other countries?</head>
                <p>Our website provides information on <ref target="$app/countries">U.S. relations
                        with the countries of the world from 1776</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="us-ambassadors-chiefs-of-mission">
                <head>Where can I find information about U.S. Ambassadors and Chiefs of
                    Mission?</head>
                <p>Our website provides <ref
                        target="$app/departmenthistory/people/chiefsofmission/by-country">a listing
                        of U.S. Ambassadors by country</ref>.</p>
                <p>The rank of Ambassador was first used by the United States in 1893: <ref
                        target="$app/departmenthistory/people/bayard-thomas-francis">Thomas F.
                        Bayard</ref> was appointed Ambassador to Great Britain on March 30 and <ref
                        target="$app/departmenthistory/people/eustis-james-biddle">James B.
                        Eustis</ref> was appointed Ambassador to France on April 18. Prior to this
                    date, the highest-ranking U.S. diplomats held the rank of Minister.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
