<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Frequently Asked Questions</title>
                <title type="short">FAQs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="AWM" role="editor">
                        <persName>Aaron W. Marrs</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#AWM" when="2012-09-13">Initial overhaul of text to delete old material and
                insert new questions/answers as approved by Tiffany and Amy.</change>
            <change who="#AWM" when="2012-09-19">Edited text based on response from
                Tiffany.</change>
            <change who="#AWM" when="2013-01-22">Updated NARA contact information on the basis of
                information from David Langbart (via Tiffany).</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="state-records">
                <head>Documents on the History of U.S. Foreign Relations</head>
                <div type="question" xml:id="where-are-state-records">
                    <head>I am interested in doing research in Department of State records. Where
                        can I find Department documents?</head>
                    <p>The Office of the Historian is not the repository for Department records.</p>
                    <p>The Office does publish selected records in its series <title level="s"
                            >Foreign Relations of the United States</title>. For records not
                        published in <title level="s">FRUS</title>, documents can generally be found
                        in one of two locations:</p>
                    <p>Most Department records prior to the mid-1970s have been retired to the <ref
                            target="https://www.archives.gov">U.S. National Archives and Records
                            Administration</ref> (NARA). NARA is located at <ref
                            target="https://maps.google.com/maps?q=8601+Adelphi+Road,+College+Park,+MD+20740&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;hnear=8601+Adelphi+Rd,+College+Park,+Maryland+20740&amp;gl=us&amp;t=m&amp;z=16"
                            >8601 Adelphi Road, College Park, MD 20740</ref>. You may contact NARA
                        by e-mail at <ref target="mailto:archives2reference@nara.gov"
                            >archives2reference@nara.gov</ref>, or by postal mail at the above
                        address, sent to the attention of the "Archives II Reference Branch (RDT2)."
                        Additional forms of contact are available at the National Archives and
                        Records Administration's <ref target="https://www.archives.gov/contact"
                            >website</ref>.</p>
                    <p>Records not yet retired to the National Archives are controlled by the
                        Department of State’s Office of Information Programs and Services (IPS). IPS
                        oversees Freedom of Information Act requests for the Department. Information
                        about IPS is available <ref target="https://www.state.gov/m/a/ips/"
                            >here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="where-are-employee-records">
                    <head>I am interested in information about the career of a former Department
                        employee. Where can I find information on employee records?</head>
                    <p>The Office of the Historian is not the repository for Department records.</p>
                    <p>Records of retired employees are held by the National Archives and Records
                        Administration’s <ref
                            target="https://www.archives.gov/st-louis/archival-programs/civilian-personnel-archival/index.html"
                            >National Personnel Records Center</ref>. The National Personnel Records
                        Center is located at <ref
                            target="https://maps.google.com/maps?q=1+Archives+Drive,+Saint+Louis,+MO+63138&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;hnear=1+Archives+Dr,+St+Louis,+Missouri+63138&amp;gl=us&amp;t=m&amp;z=16"
                            >1 Archives Drive, Saint Louis, MO 63138</ref>. You may contact the
                        National Personnel Records Center by email at <ref
                            target="mailto:stlarr.archives@nara.gov">stlarr.archives@nara.gov</ref>
                        or by phone at 314-801-0850.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="where-are-state-photos">
                    <head>I am interested in historical photographs of the Department of State.
                        Where can I find them?</head>
                    <p>The Office of the Historian is not the repository for Department records.</p>
                    <p>The National Archives and Records Administration in College Park, Maryland,
                        holds photographic materials retired from federal agencies in its Still
                        Pictures branch. You may contact this branch by email at <ref
                            target="mailto:stillpix@nara.gov">stillpix@nara.gov</ref> or by
                        telephone at 301-837-0561. Videos, from which still pictures can be
                        obtained, are held by the Motion Picture and Sound Branch. You may contact
                        this branch by email at <ref target="mailto:mopix@nara.gov"
                            >mopix@nara.gov</ref> or by telephone at 301-837-3520.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="what-is-frus">
                    <head>What is <title level="s">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</title>?</head>
                    <p><title level="s">Foreign Relations of the United States</title> is the
                        official documentary record of U.S. foreign policy. More information about
                        the series is available <ref target="$app/historicaldocuments/about-frus"
                            >here</ref>.</p>
                    <p>The series celebrated its sesquicentennial in 2011. More information about
                        the history of the series is available <ref
                            target="$app/historicaldocuments/frus-history">here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="how-to-purchase-frus">
                    <head>I would like to purchase a <title level="s">FRUS</title> volume. How can I
                        do so?</head>
                    <p><title level="s">FRUS</title> volumes are sold by the Government Printing
                        Office. You may contact the Government Printing Office <ref
                            target="https://bookstore.gpo.gov">here</ref>, or by telephone at
                        202-512-1800.</p>
                    <p><title level="s">FRUS</title> volumes are also available in electronic format
                        free of charge. Please click <ref target="#frus-formats">here</ref> for more
                        information.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="frus-formats">
                    <head>What formats are <title level="s">FRUS</title> volumes available
                        in?</head>
                    <p><title level="s">FRUS</title> volumes are available in a variety of formats.
                        While not all volumes are available in all formats, the Office of the
                        Historian is working actively to expand the digitization of its <title
                            level="s">FRUS</title> catalog.</p>
                    <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item><hi rend="strong">Print:</hi> many volumes in the series are available
                            in print and sold by the <ref target="https://bookstore.gpo.gov"
                                >Government Printing Office</ref>.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="strong">Ebook:</hi> newer <title level="s">FRUS</title>
                            volumes are available as ebooks, compatible with popular readers such as
                            the Kindle and iPad. Click <ref target="$app/historicaldocuments/ebooks"
                                >here</ref> for more information on the ebook program.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="strong">Online:</hi> newer <title level="s">FRUS</title>
                            volumes are available in full on our website. Click <ref
                                target="$app/historicaldocuments">here</ref> for a list of volumes with
                            links to the full text.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="strong">PDF:</hi> newer <title level="s">FRUS</title>
                            volumes are available in Adobe’s Portable Document Format (PDF), which
                            you can download from our website. Click <ref
                                target="$app/historicaldocuments">here</ref> for a list of volumes with
                            links to the PDFs.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="when-will-frus-be-published">
                    <head>When will the <title level="s">FRUS</title> volume on … be
                        published?</head>
                    <p>Information about forthcoming volumes is available <ref
                            target="$app/historicaldocuments/status-of-the-series">here</ref>.</p>
                    <p>If you would like to be notified of future releases when they are available,
                        please follow the Office of the Historian’s Twitter feed, <ref
                            target="https://twitter.com/HistoryAtState">@HistoryAtState</ref>.</p>
                    <p>The Office of the Historian also maintains an electronic mailing list for its
                        press releases, which are issued when a new volume is available. To be added
                        to this list, please send a request to <ref
                            target="mailto:history@state.gov">history@state.gov</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="pemission-needed-to-quote">
                    <head>Do I need to request permission to quote from a <title level="s"
                            >FRUS</title> volume?</head>
                    <p>No. Information in <title level="s">FRUS</title> is in the public domain and
                        can be copied and distributed without permission. For more information on
                        copyright, please click <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright">here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="how-should-i-cite-frus">
                    <head>How should I cite documents from the <title level="s">FRUS</title>
                        series?</head>
                    <p>Please see the guidelines in “<ref
                            target="$app/historicaldocuments/citing-frus">Citing the <title
                                level="s">Foreign Relations</title> series</ref>.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="about-paho">
                <head>About the Office of the Historian</head>
                <div type="question" xml:id="paho-employment">
                    <head>How can I get a job in the Office of the Historian?</head>
                    <p>Any job openings at the Office of the Historian will be posted to the Office
                        of Personnel Management’s website, <ref target="https://www.usajobs.gov/"
                            >USAJobs</ref>. Jobs at the Office are generally posted under job series
                        0170, Historian.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="paho-internships">
                    <head>Does the Office of the Historian offer internships?</head>
                    <p>From time to time, the Office of the Historian has interns working in its
                        Washington, DC office. All applications must be submitted through the
                        Department of State’s internship program. Please click <ref
                            target="https://www.careers.state.gov/intern">here</ref> for deadlines
                        and more information.</p>
                    <p>The Office of the Historian also participates in the Department’s Virtual
                        Student Foreign Service program. Please click <ref
                            target="https://www.state.gov/vsfs/">here</ref> for deadlines and more
                        information.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="paho-updates">
                    <head>Can I receive updates on activities at the Office of the Historian?</head>
                    <p>Follow us on Twitter! The Office of the Historian routinely posts updates on
                        its activities at <ref target="https://twitter.com/HistoryAtState"
                            >@HistoryAtState</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="state-department-history">
                <head>Department History</head>
                <div type="question" xml:id="why-called-state">
                    <head>Why is the Department called the Department of State?</head>
                    <p>On September 15, 1789, Congress passed <q>An Act to provide for the safe
                            keeping of the Acts, Records, and Seal of the United States, and for
                            other purposes.</q> This law changed the name of the Department of
                        Foreign Affairs to the Department of State because certain domestic duties
                        were assigned to the agency. These included:</p>
                    <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>Receipt, publication, distribution, and preservation of the laws of
                            the United States;</item>
                        <item>Preparation, sealing, and recording of the commissions of Presidential
                            appointees;</item>
                        <item>Preparation and authentication of copies of records and authentication
                            of copies under the Department's seal;</item>
                        <item>Custody of the Great Seal of the United States;</item>
                        <item>Custody of the records of the former Secretary of the Continental
                            Congress, except for those of the Treasury and War Departments.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Other domestic duties that the Department was responsible for at various
                        times included issuance of patents on inventions, publication of the census
                        returns, management of the mint, control of copyrights, and regulation of
                        immigration. Most domestic functions have been transferred to other
                        agencies. Those that remain in the Department are: storage and use of the
                        Great Seal, performance of protocol functions for the White House, drafting
                        of certain Presidential proclamations, and replies to public inquiries.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="great-seal">
                    <head>Why does the Department of State have possession of the Great Seal of the
                        United States?</head>
                    <p>The Department of State acquired possession of the Great Seal through an Act
                        of Congress on September 15, 1789, entitled, “An Act to provide for the safe
                        keeping of the Acts, Records, and Seal of the United States, and for other
                        purposes.” In the fulfillment of its duties, the Department of State uses
                        the Great Seal in the preparation, sealing, and recording of the commissions
                        of Presidential appointees, on instruments of ratification of treaties and
                        in the preparation and authentication of copies under the Department’s
                        Seal.</p>
                    <p>For more information about the Great Seal, please see <q><ref
                                target="https://www.state.gov/documents/organization/27807.pdf">The
                                Great Seal of the United States</ref>.</q></p>
                    <p>For more information on copyright and use of the Great Seal, please click
                            <ref target="https://www.state.gov/misc/87529.htm#copyright"
                        >here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-relations">
                <head>Diplomatic Relations</head>
                <div type="quesiton" xml:id="when-did-US-start-relations">
                    <head>When did the United States start/break off relations with …?</head>
                    <p>For information on the history of U.S. relations with other countries, please
                        click <ref target="$app/countries">here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-to-recognize-US">
                    <head>What country was the first to recognize the United States?</head>
                    <p><ref target="$app/countries/france">France</ref> recognized the United States as
                        an independent state on February 6, 1778.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="who-was-first-US-consul">
                    <head>Who was the first U.S. Consul?</head>
                    <p>William Palfrey of Massachusetts was the first U.S. consul. Prior to his
                        appointment as Consul to France on November 4, 1780, he had been a
                        lieutenant colonel and Paymaster-General of the Continental Army. He was
                        lost at sea on his way to his post. His name is the first on the memorial
                        plaque in the lobby of the Department of State that honors U.S. diplomats
                        who lost their lives under heroic or tragic circumstances.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="when-first-US-treaty">
                    <head>When was the first U.S. treaty signed?</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. treaty to be signed was a Treaty of Amity and Commerce with
                            <ref target="$app/countries/france">France</ref> that was signed in Paris on
                        February 6, 1778.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="when-first-non-European-treaty">
                    <head>What was the first U.S. treaty with a non-European nation?</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. treaty with a non-European nation was a Treaty of Friendship
                        and Amity that was signed with <ref target="$app/countries/morocco"
                            >Morocco</ref> on June 23, 1786. Thomas Barclay, the U.S. Consul General
                        in Paris, negotiated it. It was valid for fifty years and was renewed in
                        1837.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-treaty-under-constitution">
                    <head>What was the first U.S. treaty to be ratified under the
                        Constitution?</head>
                    <p>A consular convention with <ref target="$app/countries/france">France</ref> was
                        signed at Versailles on November 14, 1788. President George Washington
                        submitted to the Senate on June 11, 1789, the Senate approved it on July 29,
                        and it entered into effect on January 6, 1790.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-consular-post">
                    <head>When and where was the first U.S. consular post established?</head>
                    <p>The first U.S. consular post was established in Bordeaux, France, in March
                        1778. It was closed in 1995 and reopened in 2000 as an <ref
                            target="https://bordeaux.usconsulate.gov/">American Presence
                        Post</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="secretaries-of-state">
                <head>The Secretaries of State</head>
                <div type="question" xml:id="how-many-secretaries">
                    <head>How many Secretaries of State have there been?</head>
                    <p>For a list of all Secretaries, click <ref
                            target="$app/departmenthistory/people/secretaries">here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="foreign-service-secretary">
                    <head>Has any member of the Foreign Service served as Secretary of State?</head>
                    <p>The only member of the Foreign Service to have served as Secretary of State
                        was <ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/eagleburger-lawrence-sidney"
                            >Lawrence S. Eagleburger</ref>, who served from December 8, 1992 until
                        January 19, 1993. Eagleburger had served as Acting Secretary of State from
                        August 23, 1992.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-female-secretary">
                    <head>Who was the first woman to serve as Secretary of State?</head>
                    <p><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/albright-madeleine-korbel">Madeleine
                            K. Albright</ref> was the first woman to serve as Secretary of
                        State.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-African-American-secretary">
                    <head>Who was the first African American to serve as Secretary of State?</head>
                    <p><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/powell-colin-luther">Colin
                            Powell</ref> was the first African American to serve as Secretary of
                        State.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="secretaries-before-constitution">
                    <head>Were there equivalents to the Secretary of State prior to the
                        Constitution?</head>
                    <p>There were two Secretaries of Foreign Affairs under the Continental Congress.
                            <ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/livingston-robert-r">Robert R.
                            Livingston</ref> served from October 20, 1781 until June 4, 1783. <ref
                            target="$app/departmenthistory/people/jay-john">John Jay</ref> served from
                        May 7, 1784 until March 4, 1789.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-secretary-to-travel">
                    <head>Who was the first Secretary of State to travel outside the United States
                        while in office?</head>
                    <p><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William H.
                            Seward</ref> took a working vacation in the Caribbean between January 1
                        and January 28, 1866. He met with <ref target="$app/countries/denmark"
                            >Danish</ref> colonial officials in the Virgin Islands, with the
                        Presidents of the <ref target="$app/countries/dominican-republic">Dominican
                            Republic</ref> and <ref target="$app/countries/haiti">Haiti</ref>, and with
                            <ref target="$app/countries/spain">Spanish</ref> colonial officials in
                        Cuba.</p>
                    <p>For general information on the travel of the Secretary of State, please click
                            <ref target="$app/departmenthistory/travels/secretary">here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-travel-on-business">
                    <head>Who was the first Secretary of State to travel outside the United States
                        on official business?</head>
                    <p>The first official travel by a Secretary of State outside the United States
                        was by <ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/root-elihu">Elihu Root</ref>
                        in 1906. Root left the United States on July 4 and attended the Third
                        International Conference of American States in Rio de Janeiro, <ref
                            target="$app/countries/brazil">Brazil</ref>, after which he visited <ref
                            target="$app/countries/uruguay">Uruguay</ref>, <ref
                            target="$app/countries/argentina">Argentina</ref>, <ref
                            target="$app/countries/chile">Chile</ref>, <ref target="$app/countries/peru"
                            >Peru</ref>, <ref target="$app/countries/panama">Panama</ref>, and <ref
                            target="$app/countries/colombia">Colombia</ref>.</p>
                    <p>For general information on the travel of the Secretary of State, please click
                            <ref target="$app/departmenthistory/travels/secretary">here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="ambassadors-and-chiefs-of-mission">
                <head>Ambassadors and Chiefs of Mission</head>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-ambassador-to-country">
                    <head>Who was the first Ambassador to …?</head>
                    <p>A listing of U.S. Ambassadors by country can be found <ref
                            target="$app/departmenthistory/people/chiefsofmission/by-country"
                        >here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="who-were-first-ambassadors">
                    <head>Who were the first U.S. Ambassadors?</head>
                    <p>The rank of Ambassador was first used by the United States in 1893. <ref
                            target="$app/departmenthistory/people/bayard-thomas-francis">Thomas F.
                            Bayard</ref> was appointed Ambassador to Great Britain on March 30. <ref
                            target="$app/departmenthistory/people/eustis-james-biddle">James B.
                            Eustis</ref> was appointed Ambassador to France on April 18. Prior to
                        this date, the highest-ranking U.S. diplomats were Ministers.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="ambassadors-killed">
                    <head>How many U.S. Ambassadors have been killed by militants?</head>
                    <p>Since World War II, the following U.S. Ambassadors have been killed by
                        militants:</p>
                    <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/mein-john-gordon">John Gordon
                                Mein</ref>, Ambassador to Guatemala, August 28, 1968. Mein was <ref
                                target="$app/historicaldocuments/frus1964-68v31/d114">killed by a gunman
                                in Guatemala City</ref>.</item>
                        <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/noel-cleo-allen">Cleo A. Noel,
                                Jr.</ref>, Ambassador to Sudan, March 1, 1973. Noel was taken
                            hostage in Khartoum and <ref
                                target="$app/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76ve06/d217">killed by his
                                kidnappers</ref>.</item>
                        <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/davies-rodger-paul">Rodger P.
                                Davies</ref>, Ambassador to Cyprus, August 19, 1974. Davies was <ref
                                target="$app/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v30/d139">shot during a
                                demonstration</ref> at the Embassy in Nicosia.</item>
                        <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/meloy-francis-edward">Francis
                                E. Meloy, Jr.</ref>, Ambassador to Lebanon, June 16, 1976. Meloy was
                            killed by a gunman in Beruit.</item>
                        <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/dubs-adolph">Adolph Dubs</ref>,
                            Ambassador to Afghanistan, February 14, 1979. Dubs was captured in Kabul
                            and was killed during the rescue attempt.</item>
                        <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/stevens-john-christopher">J.
                                Christopher Stevens</ref>, Ambassador to Libya, September 11, 2012.
                            Stevens was killed in an attack on the Mission in Benghazi.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The American Foreign Service Association maintains a list of foreign service
                        officers killed in the line of duty <ref
                            target="http://www.afsa.org/afsa_memorial_plaque_list.aspx"
                        >here</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreign-service">
                <head>The Foreign Service</head>
                <div type="question" xml:id="origin-of-foreign-service">
                    <head>What was the origin of the Foreign Service?</head>
                    <p>Article II, section 2 of the Constitution authorized the President to
                        appoint, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, <q>Ambassadors,
                            other public Ministers, and Consuls.</q> From 1789 until 1924, the
                        Diplomatic Service, which staffed U.S. Legations and Embassies, and the
                        Consular Service, which was primarily responsible for promoting American
                        commerce and assisting distressed American sailors, developed
                        separately.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="origin-of-consular-service">
                    <head>When was the Consular Service established?</head>
                    <p>The first Act of Congress providing for U.S. consuls abroad was passed on
                        April 14, 1792. Except for the consuls appointed to the Barbary States of
                        North Africa (who enjoyed quasi-diplomatic status when Muslim countries did
                        not maintain permanent missions abroad), U.S. consuls received no salary and
                        were expected to earn their livings from private trade or from fees charged
                        for official services. It was not uncommon for consuls to have been
                        merchants with business connections in the cities to which they had been
                        appointed. They did not have to be U.S. citizens.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-consul-salary">
                    <head>When did U.S. consuls first receive a salary?</head>
                    <p>An Act of Congress of August 18, 1856 established two schedules of consular
                        posts. Consuls appointed to Schedule B posts were paid between $1,000 and
                        $7,500 per year. They could still collect fees, but could no longer engage
                        in trade. Schedule C appointees received between $500 and $1,000 per year
                        and could engage in trade. Non-citizens might be appointed to consular
                        posts, but could not be paid.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="first-professional-consuls">
                    <head>Who were the first professional consular appointees?</head>
                    <p>The Act of August 18, 1856 provided for the appointment of up to 25
                            <q>consular pupils,</q> who would take an examination before their
                        appointment and be assigned to consulates at the discretion of the
                        President. This provision was repealed during the next session of Congress.
                        On June 20, 1864, Congress authorized 13 consular clerks. Between 1864 and
                        1896, 64 consular clerks were appointed. Only 8 were promoted to consul;
                        most preferred a small ($1,000) salary and security to a larger one of
                        uncertain duration.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="foreign-service-examination">
                    <head>What was the forerunner of the Foreign Service Examination?</head>
                    <p>President Grover Cleveland issued an Executive Order on September 20, 1895
                        that required appointees to consular positions with salaries between $1,000
                        and $2,500 to be either a qualified officer of the Department, or to pass a
                        written examination on consular regulations and an oral examination that
                        included demonstrating proficiency in a foreign language. Executive orders
                        issued by President Theodore Roosevelt on November 10, 1905 and June 27,
                        1906 instituted examinations for the lower grades of the Consular Service
                        and for secretaries in the Diplomatic Service.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone unit="question" rend="hr"/>
                <div type="question" xml:id="rogers-act">
                    <head>When was the present-day Foreign Service established?</head>
                    <p>The Rogers Act (named for Representative <ref
                            target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=R000400"
                            >John Jacob Rogers of Massachusetts</ref>) of May 24, 1924 amalgamated
                        the Diplomatic and Consular Services into a unified Foreign Service. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="women-in-the-foreign-service">
                <head>Women in the Foreign Service</head>
                <p>Notable firsts:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>Lucile Atcherson was the first woman in the Foreign Service. She passed
                        the Diplomatic Service examination in 1922 with the third-highest score, and
                        was appointed a secretary in the Diplomatic Service on December 5, 1922. She
                        was assigned as Third Secretary of the Legation in Berne, Switzerland, on
                        April 11, 1925. She resigned on September 19, 1927, in order to get
                        married.</item>
                    <item>Pattie H. Field was the first woman to enter the Foreign Service after
                        passage of the <ref target="#rogers-act">Rogers Act</ref>. She was sworn in
                        on April 20, 1925, served as a Vice Consul at Amsterdam, and resigned on
                        June 27, 1929, to accept a job with the National Broadcasting
                        Company.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/owen-ruth-bryan">Ruth Bryan
                            Owen</ref> was the first woman to be chief of a U.S. diplomatic
                        mission.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/anderson-helen-eugenie-moore">Helen
                            Eugenie Moore Anderson</ref> was the first woman to hold the rank of
                        Ambassador.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/willis-frances-elizabeth">Frances
                            E. Willis</ref> was the first female Foreign Service Officer to become
                        an Ambassador.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/laise-caroline-clendening">Carol C.
                            Laise</ref> was the first woman to become an Assistant Secretary of
                        State.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/benson-lucy-wilson-peters">Lucy
                            Wilson Benson</ref> was the first woman to become Under Secretary of
                        State.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="african-americans-in-the-foreign-service">
                <head>African Americans in the Foreign Service</head>
                <p>Notable firsts:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/bassett-ebenezer-don-carlos"
                            >Ebenezer Don Carlos Bassett</ref> was the first African-American
                        diplomat.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/wharton-clifton-reginald">Clifton
                            R. Wharton</ref> was the first African American to join the Foreign
                        Service. He was also the first African American appointed as chief of a
                        diplomatic mission to a European country.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/dudley-edward-richard">Edward R.
                            Dudley</ref> was the first African American to hold the rank of
                        Ambassador.</item>
                    <item><ref target="$app/departmenthistory/people/harris-patricia-roberts">Patricia
                            Roberts Harris </ref>was the first African American woman to hold the
                        rank of Ambassador.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="diplomatic-and-consular-posts">
                <head>Diplomatic and Consular Posts, 1781-2010</head>
                <p>Diplomatic Posts includes Embassies and Legations only; does not include Embassy
                    Branch Offices, U.S. Liaison Offices, U.S. Interests Sections, and Missions to
                    International Organizations. Consular Posts includes Consulates and Consulates
                    General only; does not include Consular Agencies.</p>
                <table rows="24" cols="3">
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Year</cell>
                        <cell>Diplomatic Posts</cell>
                        <cell>Consular Posts</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1781</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1790</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1800</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1810</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1820</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1830</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>141</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1840</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>152</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1850</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>197</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1860</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>282</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1870</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>318</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>303</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1890</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>323</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1900</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>318</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1910</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>324</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1920</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>368</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1930</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>299</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1940</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>264</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1950</cell>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                        <cell>179</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1960</cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                        <cell>166</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1970</cell>
                        <cell>117</cell>
                        <cell>122</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1980</cell>
                        <cell>133</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1990</cell>
                        <cell>145</cell>
                        <cell>97</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                        <cell>161</cell>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2010</cell>
                        <cell>168</cell>
                        <cell>89</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="department-personnel">
                <head>Department Personnel, 1781-2010</head>
                <p>Domestic personnel includes both Civil Service and Foreign Service. Overseas
                    personnel includes Foreign Service only.</p>
                <table rows="24" cols="4">
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Year</cell>
                        <cell>Domestic</cell>
                        <cell>Overseas</cell>
                        <cell>Total</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1781</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1790</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1800</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1810</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1820</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>96</cell>
                        <cell>111</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1830</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>153</cell>
                        <cell>176</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1840</cell>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>170</cell>
                        <cell>208</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1850</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>218</cell>
                        <cell>240</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1860</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>281</cell>
                        <cell>323</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1870</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>804</cell>
                        <cell>869</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>977</cell>
                        <cell>1,067</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1890</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>1,105</cell>
                        <cell>1,181</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1900</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                        <cell>1,137</cell>
                        <cell>1,228</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1910</cell>
                        <cell>234</cell>
                        <cell>1,043</cell>
                        <cell>1,277</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1920</cell>
                        <cell>708</cell>
                        <cell>514</cell>
                        <cell>1,222</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1930</cell>
                        <cell>714</cell>
                        <cell>633</cell>
                        <cell>1,347</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1940</cell>
                        <cell>1,128</cell>
                        <cell>840</cell>
                        <cell>1,968</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1950</cell>
                        <cell>8,609</cell>
                        <cell>7,710</cell>
                        <cell>16,319</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1960</cell>
                        <cell>7,116</cell>
                        <cell>6,178</cell>
                        <cell>13,294</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1970</cell>
                        <cell>6,983</cell>
                        <cell>5,865</cell>
                        <cell>12,848</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1980</cell>
                        <cell>8,433</cell>
                        <cell>5,861</cell>
                        <cell>13,962</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1990</cell>
                        <cell>10,063</cell>
                        <cell>6,783</cell>
                        <cell>16,846</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                        <cell>11,530</cell>
                        <cell>7,374</cell>
                        <cell>18,904</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2010</cell>
                        <cell>16,565</cell>
                        <cell>10,581</cell>
                        <cell>27,146</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
