<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Views From the Embassy: The Role of the U.S. Diplomatic
                    Community in France, 1914</title>
                <title type="short">Views From the Embassy</title>
                <author>Lindsay Sarah Krasnoff</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Preview Edition</p>
                <p>September 2014</p>
                <p>Born digital. Adapted from MS Word manuscript to TEI.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage type="main">
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="short">Views From the Embassy</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="subtitle">The Role of the U.S. Diplomatic Community in France,
                        1914</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docEdition>Preview Edition</docEdition>
                <byline>
                    <name>Lindsay Sarah Krasnoff</name>
                </byline>
                <docImprint>
                    <publisher>Office of the Historian<lb/>Bureau of Public Affairs<lb/>U.S.
                        Department of State</publisher>
                    <lb/>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <lb/>
                    <docDate>2014</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="section" xml:id="about">
                <head>About the Preview Edition</head>
                <p>The Office of the Historian has generated this electronic preview edition of
                    “Views From the Embassy: The Role of the U.S. Diplomatic Community in France,
                    1914.” This is a preview edition. We advise all those citing this version to
                    specify “Preview Edition, September 15, 2014” in their references.</p>
                <p>Several documents referenced in “Views From the Embassy” are highlighted on U.S.
                    Embassy France’s World War I Centennial website, located at <ref
                        target="https://fr.usembassy.gov/news-events/ww1-centenary/"
                        >fr.usembassy.gov/news-events/ww1-centenary/</ref>. Readers may view full
                    copies of these unclassified documents through links on that page’s “Interactive
                    Timeline.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Disclaimer: Although this volume was prepared in the Department
                        of State’s Office of the Historian, the views expressed here are those of
                        the author and do not necessarily represent those of the Office of the
                        Historian, the Department of State, or the U.S. Government.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="executive-summary">
                <head>Executive Summary</head>
                <p>To commemorate the First World War Centenary, U.S. Embassy France and the Office
                    of the Historian investigated the role of the U.S. diplomatic community in
                    France from 1914 until 1918. Much is known about the United States’ actions and
                    contributions following its April 1917 entry into the conflict as a belligerent
                    power associated with the Allies. Yet, the stories of France-based U.S.
                    diplomats, consuls, and their family members prior to April 1917 have long been
                    overshadowed by subsequent events of the twentieth century.</p>
                <p>“Views From the Embassy” sheds light on often unknown or overlooked aspects of
                    diplomatic work, such as the everyday tasks involved in the execution of policy.
                    It also sketches out how U.S. diplomats, consuls, and their family members
                    responded to a myriad of crises. While the “Views From the Embassy” story
                    occurred one hundred years ago, it exemplifies certain perennial tensions, such
                    as difficulties between politically appointed Chiefs of Mission and their
                    career-diplomat colleagues as well as commonalities, including the varied ways
                    in which people react to situations of extreme stress.</p>
                <p>Our research revives a fascinating account of how actions spearheaded by U.S.
                    diplomats and U.S. citizens in France during 1914, when the German Army
                    threatened Paris, significantly strengthened U.S.-France relations in unique,
                    unprecedented ways.</p>
                <p>This is an important consideration, given that until the late nineteenth century,
                    despite a long history of diplomatic relations, the French and U.S. publics had
                    relatively little direct, personal interaction with each other (when compared,
                    for example, with the extensive contacts with Irish or Italian expatriate
                    communities). As Yves-Henri Nouailhat noted, French public opinion often
                    stereotyped “Americans” as caring too much for money, and felt that U.S.
                    citizens knew and cared little about France, its people, or culture. At the same
                    time, U.S. public opinion tended to associate the Third Republic and the French
                    with the decadence and laicité typified in popular memory of the Belle
                        Époque.<note n="1" xml:id="fn1">Yves-Henri Nouailhat, <hi rend="italic">La
                            France et Les États-Unis Août 1914–Avril 1917</hi>, (Paris :
                        Publications de la Sorbonne, 1979), 43.</note> An influx of U.S.
                    businessmen, heiresses, and students to France at the turn of the twentieth
                    century began to foster greater cultural, commercial, and personal ties between
                    the two countries.<note n="2" xml:id="fn2">See Nancy Green, <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Other Americans in Paris: Businessmen, Countesses, Wayward Youth,
                            1880–1941</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2014).</note>
                    While impressions about the United States began to change, by 1914 many older,
                    preconceived notions remained.</p>
                <p>The response of the U.S. diplomatic and expatriate communities in France,
                    particularly during 1914, did much to change French views towards the United
                    States. From the first days of war, U.S. diplomats and consuls provided food,
                    shelter, and funds to in-need U.S. citizens waiting to be evacuated safely to
                    the United States. They also took care of German and Austro-Hungarian interests
                    and subjects in France, obligations handed over to the Swiss Government upon
                    U.S. entry into the conflict in 1917. These actions mirrored those undertaken by
                    U.S. diplomats and consuls in the United Kingdom, Belgium, Germany,
                    Austria-Hungary, Serbia, and Russia during the fall of 1914. Thus, “Views From
                    the Embassy” also imparts how, prior to 1917, the United States served as the
                    preferred neutral power representative for war-torn Europe.</p>
                <p>In addition to these “official duties,” the responsibilities of U.S. Ambassador
                    to France Myron T. Herrick and his staff grew once the Government of France
                    departed Paris for Bordeaux on September 2, 1914. Herrick, with the blessing of
                    French President Raymond Poincaré, remained in Paris to protect U.S. interests
                    and citizens. Accounts differ whether Herrick also pledged to protect Parisian
                    monuments and museums or whether it was merely the Government of France’s hope
                    that the U.S. Ambassador’s presence in the capital as a neutral government
                    representative would deter any possible German Army destruction of the city’s
                    treasures. Thus throughout autumn 1914, while other Embassies and Legations were
                    dark, the U.S. Embassy was a beehive of activity on multiple fronts. In addition
                    to diplomatic duties, the unofficial roles of U.S. diplomats expanded
                    exponentially as the war continued.</p>
                <p>The Embassy became a nucleus of partnerships that provided financial relief and
                    medical aid to those in France impacted by the war. Those measures caused some,
                    including the German and French Governments, to question the degrees of
                    neutrality maintained by the U.S. Embassy in Paris.<note n="3" xml:id="fn3"
                        >Ibid.</note> Yet, such actions were undertaken with the approval of the
                    Department of State. Assisted by a corps of U.S. citizens who volunteered their
                    time, energy, and funds, U.S. diplomats and consuls developed new relationships
                    with each other, the Government of France, and the French public. Their actions
                    shaped public memory of the U.S.-France partnership in 1914, and laid a firm
                    foundation of friendship that weathered the tests of subsequent decades.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="part" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction: Prelude to War</head>
                <p>The modern world was sufficiently developed by 1914 that twenty-first century
                    readers would recognize many elements of daily life. The seismic changes in
                    science and technology of the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries
                    transformed the industrialized world in a short time and fueled globalization.
                    Far-flung places around the globe were connected to the main hubs of business
                    and finance through the telegraph, telephone, and ever-faster trains and ships.
                    Automobiles were common for the wealthy, buses and taxis cluttered the streets
                    of Paris, and underneath the city the Metropolitan (Métro) shuttled people
                    around via several subterranean train lines. The film industry was in its early
                    years. Newspapers were prevalent, cheap, and frequent. French remained the <hi
                        rend="italic">lingua franca</hi> of diplomacy, but English rapidly became
                    the language of business and commerce around the world.</p>
                <p>In the summer of 1914, France was preoccupied with many things, least among them
                    the events in the Balkans. It was a seminal year, the centennial of Napoleon’s
                    first defeat and forced exile to the island of Elba as well as the 125th
                    anniversary of the 1789 Revolution. Paris was titillated by the trial of Madame
                    Caillaux and enraptured by the June visit of former U.S. President Theodore
                        Roosevelt.<note n="4" xml:id="fn4">Roosevelt stocked up on reading material
                        at Bretano’s on Avenue de l’Opera, saw the “Mona Lisa” at the Louvre and
                        other sites such as Malmaison, and lunched with French and U.S. citizens
                        such as academic Gabriel Hanotaux, Herrick, Bliss, former French President
                        Alexandre Felix Ribot, and Secretary of the French-Amérique Committee Louis
                        Jaray, among others. “Roosevelt Busy in Seeing Paris,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Chicago Daily Tribune</hi>, June 7, 1914, p. 2.</note> The city was
                    also abuzz with the June 27 world heavyweight championship fight between U.S.
                    boxers Frank Moran and Jack Johnson at the Velodrome d’Hiver. Against this
                    backdrop, the members of the U.S. diplomatic community in France went about
                    their daily business.</p>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="us-diplomats-and-consuls">
                    <head>U.S. Diplomats and Consuls</head>
                    <p>The assemblage of U.S. diplomats, consuls, and family members in France was
                        part of a small collective that constituted the U.S. Diplomatic and Consular
                        Services in the early twentieth century. Prior to the 1924 Rogers Act, which
                        combined the two services to create one professionalized Foreign Service,
                        U.S. representational presence around the world was relatively small. In
                        1910 there were only 1,043 overseas personnel attached to the Department,
                        despite the growing involvement of the United States in international
                            relations.<note n="5" xml:id="fn5">Office of the Historian, “Department
                            Personnel, 1781–2010,” Office of the Historian Website, <ref
                                target="https://history.state.gov/about/faq/department-personnel"
                                >history.state.gov/about/faq/department-personnel</ref>.</note> The
                        U.S. Embassy in Paris was maintained by one ambassador, three diplomats, a
                        few military and naval attachés, and a handful of support staff (clerks,
                        secretaries, messengers, and the ambassador’s private secretary).</p>
                    <p>At the helm in June 1914 was U.S. Ambassador to France Myron T. Herrick,
                        former Republican Governor of Ohio and appointee of President William Taft.
                        Herrick and his wife Carolyn arrived in Paris in April 1912. They asked
                        departing U.S. Ambassador to France Robert Bacon and his wife to remain with
                        them at the Ambassador’s residence, at 5, rue François Ier, a mansion owned
                        by the Count de Ganay, for a few extra days to help them acclimate. Bacon
                        was a close friend and confidante of Roosevelt, a former member of
                        Roosevelt’s famed “tennis cabinet” which also included French Ambassador to
                        the United States Jean-Jules (“J.J.”) Jusserand. A good friend of France,
                        Bacon was fluent in the language and much-beloved by Parisians for his
                        assistance during the 1910 flood of the Seine. The Bacons obliged the
                        Herricks in April 1912, postponed their return, and gave up their scheduled
                        transatlantic crossing—aboard the <hi rend="italic">Titanic</hi>.</p>
                    <p>During his years in France, Herrick charmed the French and learned the
                        language. He forged strong personal friendships, including one with
                        President Raymond Poincaré. Such relations served the Ambassador well. When
                        Herrick learned on June 2, 1914, that he would be relieved by his successor,
                        William Graves Sharp, later that summer, he prepared his return to the
                        United States with a mixed heart—happy to return home, sad to leave his dear
                        new friends.</p>
                    <p>The Herricks’ return to the United States was much delayed. When President
                        Woodrow Wilson took office in 1913, Herrick followed the usual custom of
                        submitting his letter of resignation. However, there were difficulties in
                        locating someone to take the position. One of the names put forward to
                        succeed Herrick was George T. Marye, a California banker and lawyer. The
                        Government of France, however, objected based on Marye’s advocacy of
                        California wine interests against those of the French in a congressional
                        tariff bill debate. Instead, Marye was appointed to serve as U.S. Ambassador
                        to Russia in June 1914. Wilson thus asked Herrick to remain at post until a
                        suitable candidate could be nominated, confirmed, and dispatched to
                        Paris.</p>
                    <p>Wilson eventually appointed Sharp to fill the post of U.S. Ambassador to
                        France on June 19, 1914. A lawyer and three-term Congressman from Ohio,
                        Sharp was deeply interested in the sciences and was known as the “astronomer
                        of Congress.” After his nomination, Sharp did not immediately sail for
                        France as his wife was too ill to travel. Nevertheless, Herrick began his
                        farewell rounds in Paris while Carolyn oversaw the packing of their
                        belongings for overseas shipment.</p>
                    <p>There were three diplomats who helped Herrick tend to Embassy business during
                        the summer of 1914. Embassy First Secretary and Counselor Robert Woods Bliss
                        was a career diplomat who arrived in Paris in February 1912 after serving as
                        Secretary at the U.S. Legation in Buenos Aires. Married to his stepsister
                        Mildred Barnes, heiress of the Castoria patent medicine fortune, Bliss
                        relished his work at the Embassy. He was aided by Second Secretary Arthur
                        Hugh Frazier, whose studies at the Royal College of Viticulture in
                        Geisenheim, Germany, and former career as a vineyard owner in California
                        were assets in France. Third Secretary Louis A. Sussdorff Jr., who arrived
                        in Paris for his first diplomatic assignment earlier that spring, rounded
                        out the Diplomatic Service members at the Embassy in 1914. Their work was
                        augmented by Military Attaché Maj. Spencer Cosby, an engineer well-known for
                        his work designing the White House’s Oval Office and overseeing the planting
                        of Washington D.C.’s cherry trees, who filed reports on military
                        matters.</p>
                    <p>Ann Singleton, an Embassy clerk, was a rare professional woman in the
                        Diplomatic Service at the time. Appointed to U.S. Embassy France on
                        September 1, 1912, Singleton wished to travel the world and worked as a
                        clerk and secretary to save money for her dreams. In the summer of 1914,
                        Singleton prepared to depart Paris and embark upon an around-the-world trip.
                        Her fellow clerk, Augustus Biesel, was a naturalized U.S. citizen originally
                        from Saarbrucken, Germany, who had served the Embassy since his June 4,
                        1872, appointment as a messenger.</p>
                    <p>The work of U.S. diplomats in Paris was enhanced by the work of their
                        Consular Service colleagues posted in major French ports and commercial
                        cities. Through the 1910s, U.S. consuls were selected for political reasons
                        and, as Paris Vice Consul in 1914 DeWitt Clinton Poole Jr. noted, “there
                        were a very good number of bums who were sent abroad by families who wanted
                        them to drink themselves to death somewhere away from the home town.”<note
                            n="6" xml:id="fn6">The Reminiscences of DeWitt Clinton Poole Jr.,
                            January–March 1952, 57, in the Columbia Center for Oral History
                            Collection.</note> This began to change around 1906 when the
                        “undesirable element” was “shaved off.”<note n="7" xml:id="fn7">Ibid.</note>
                        Many U.S. consuls in France during the 1914–1918 period proved their mettle
                        and the benefits of a merit-based system.</p>
                    <p>The U.S. Consulate in Paris in 1914 fell under the leadership of recently
                        appointed Consul General Alexander M. Thackara, who worked closely with the
                        American Chamber of Commerce in Paris to strengthen French and U.S. business
                        interests. His wife Ellie Sherman Thackara, daughter of U.S. Civil War
                        General William T. Sherman, built a vibrant social life that included French
                        and U.S. friends. Poole, the new Vice Consul and close friend of the
                        Thackaras, arrived in Paris that June. Business continued as usual for U.S.
                        Consul at St. Étienne William H. Hunt, the only African-American consular
                        official serving in France that summer. U.S. Consul at Reims William Bardel
                        was occupied by the Champagne industry, and concern over the increased price
                        of Champagne, a result of a much smaller crop the previous year.<note n="8"
                            xml:id="fn8">The crop of 1913 was about one-third the usual size due to
                            poor weather and quality, but Bardel encouraged U.S. investors, noting,
                            “it is nevertheless thought it will prove to be excellent because of the
                            great care exercised in picking the grapes.” “From Here and There,” <hi
                                rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, June 7, 1914, p. SM7.</note>
                        In addition to these, there were several other U.S. Consulates within the
                        mainland <hi rend="italic">métropole</hi> as well as throughout the French
                            Empire.<note n="9" xml:id="fn9">The U.S. Consulate at Reims was selected
                            as it was one of the ones most directly impacted—and later, closed—due
                            to the German Army’s advance into France, while the U.S. Consulate at
                            St. Étienne was selected for research as its Consul, William H. Hunt,
                            was the only African-American U.S. representative serving in Europe at
                            the time.</note> For this study, the posts at Paris, Reims, and St.
                        Étienne were selected as the focus of research, reflecting their importance
                        in trade (Paris and St. Étienne) or history of the war (Reims).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="us-diplomatic-presence-in-france" height="481px" width="624px"/>
                        <head>U.S. Diplomatic and Consular Presence in Metropolitan France Over
                            Time</head>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="paris-on-the-precipice">
                    <head>Paris on the Precipice</head>
                    <p>On June 28, Herrick, Poincaré, much of the diplomatic community, and Parisian
                        society attended the races at Longchamp. Herrick noted that Austro-Hungarian
                        Ambassador to France Count Nicholas Szecsen, a “tall, handsome man” who
                        Herrick thought “in appearance precisely my ideal of a real Ambassador,” was
                        in attendance. In the middle of the day’s entertainment, word reached
                        Ambassador Szecsen of Austrian Archduke Franz Ferdinand’s assassination by
                        Black Hand militant Gavrillo Princep in Sarajevo.<note n="10" xml:id="fn10"
                            >Myron T. Herrick. Chapter One of Myron T. Herrick Remembrances, 1920s
                            but undated, unpublished, 2. (Western Reserve Historical Society,
                            Cleveland, Ohio, Myron T. Herrick Papers, MS 2925, Container 3, Folder
                            3)</note> Yet, few thought such political intrigues of special
                        significance. That evening Poole was at the Café de Paris when the evening
                        newspapers spread word of the assassination. “It was accepted by almost
                        everybody as simply another Balkan assassination,” he recalled.<note n="11"
                            xml:id="fn11">Poole, 59.</note></p>
                    <p>Life continued. Philippe Thys won the twelfth competition of the Tour de
                        France and the social season in Paris wound down as everyone prepared for or
                        embarked upon vacation. Thousands of wealthy and middle class U.S. citizens
                        fanned out to the far corners of France and Europe for sightseeing and
                        repose. Wilson’s sister, Annie Wilson Howe, vacationed in France. Further
                        afield, Mildred Barnes Bliss went to Switzerland to unwind. U.S. Minister to
                        the Argentine John Work Garrett was on home leave in the United States while
                        his wife Alice and their children summered in St. Moritz, Switzerland (the
                        Garretts were good friends of the Blisses). Poole set out for his father’s
                        house in Madison, Wisconsin, while U.S. Ambassador to Italy Thomas Nelson
                        Page began his voyage to the United States via Paris. Ambassador Jusserand
                        and his wife Elise (a French-born U.S. citizen), already on home leave, were
                        frequent companions of the Herricks that month in Paris as the U.S.
                        Ambassador, his wife, and their dog Billy awaited their homeward journey on
                        August 8.<note n="12" xml:id="fn12">Jusserand had served as the French envoy
                            in Washington D.C. since 1902, and by 1914 was Dean of the Diplomatic
                            Corps.</note> The relaxing summer plans of U.S. and French officials
                        were quickly laid aside after the July 28, 1914, Austro-Hungarian
                        declaration of war on Serbia and the subsequent diplomatic crises.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="from-peace-to-war">
                    <head>From Peace to War</head>
                    <p>Few foresaw how quickly war would arrive. On the afternoon of July 28,
                        Herrick hosted a reception for a group of U.S. businessmen and local
                        Parisian officials at his residence. The event was bittersweet, serving as
                        one of Herrick’s last official duties prior to presenting his recall letter
                        and sailing home. The fête came to an abrupt halt later that evening with
                        the arrival of Bliss, fresh from the Quai d’Orsay, who imparted news of the
                        Austro-Hungarian declaration of war on Serbia. Eric Fisher Wood, a 25-year
                        old U.S. student at the École des Beaux Arts, noted that in Paris, “the
                        atmosphere of the city became so surcharged with excitement that to persist
                        in study was difficult.”<note n="13" xml:id="fn13">Eric Fisher Wood, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Note-Book of an Attaché: Seven Months in the War
                                Zone</hi> (New York: The Century Co., 1915), 4.</note></p>
                    <p>Events unfolded rapidly thereafter. Herrick reevaluated his departure plans
                        since Sharp was still in the United States. On July 31, Herrick cabled the
                        Department of State that “on account of unusual pressure of business at the
                        Embassy I have arranged postponement of presentation of letter of recall
                        until just before sailing.”<note n="14" xml:id="fn14">Telegram from Herrick
                            (Paris) to Secretary of State (Washington DC) Received July 31, 1914,
                            5:12pm. (National Archives, RG 59 123 H 43/36)</note> Secretary of State
                        William Jennings Bryan agreed. In an August 1 cable, Bryan instructed
                        Herrick “in view of the critical situation in Europe you will please remain
                        until Ambassador Sharp arrives.”<note n="15" xml:id="fn15">Telegram from
                            Secretary of State (Washington DC) to Herrick (Paris) August 1, 1914,
                            9pm. (National Archives, RG 59 123 H 43/37a)</note></p>
                    <p>Orders for general French mobilization were issued on Saturday, August 1.
                        Elizabeth Dryden, who lived in Paris for nearly a decade prior to the war’s
                        outbreak, wrote that the morning after mobilization orders were announced,
                        the entire city of Paris was charged with activity. “People were hurrying,”
                        she noted in her diary, “so I thought I must be in New York.”<note n="16"
                            xml:id="fn16">Elizabeth Dryden, <hi rend="italic">Paris in Herrick
                                Days</hi> (Paris: Dorbon-Ainé, 1915), 11.</note></p>
                    <p>As it became clear that war would not be averted this time, the Embassy
                        rapidly became a beehive of activity. People began to prepare for the
                            worst.<note n="17" xml:id="fn17">At the first orders of mobilization,
                            Marie Curie canceled her vacation in Brittany in order to remain in
                            Paris and offer assistance.</note> France entered into a state of war
                        with Germany at 6:45pm on August 3, 1914. That evening the German Ambassador
                        to France, Baron Wilhelm von Schoen, departed the country. Herrick informed
                        the Quai d’Orsay that the United States was now responsible for German
                        interests in France.<note n="18" xml:id="fn18">Raymond Poincaré, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Memoirs of Raymond Poincaré (1913­–1914)</hi>,
                            translated by Sir George Arthur (London: William Heinemann Ltd., 1938),
                            284.</note> The war spread as the United Kingdom entered the foray on
                        August 4. That same day, Wood went to the Embassy at 5, rue de Chaillot and
                        volunteered his assistance. “I was put to work with such suddenness,” he
                        wrote, “that no time was spent in determining my official status. I cannot
                        say whether I am the doorman or an Attaché. At present the duties of the two
                        seem to be identical.”<note n="19">Ibid, 8.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part" xml:id="embassy-amid-crisis">
                <head>Embassy Amid Crisis: August 1914</head>
                <p>Thousands of U.S. citizens in Europe were stranded as the Continent passed from
                    peace to belligerency within a week. The crisis was compounded for those in
                    France by their inability to withdraw funds from banks. The wealthy were just as
                    helpless as their middle-class compatriots. School teachers who saved their
                    earnings to take a Cook’s travel tour were stuck. So, too, was Wilson’s sister,
                    Annie Wilson Howe. As France was the port of call for travelers stuck in Germany
                    and Switzerland, thousands of U.S. citizens descended upon the Embassy in Paris
                    in those early days.</p>
                <p>It was not just U.S. citizens whose vacations were interrupted and found
                    themselves with a dearth of transportation options. Diplomats of various
                    nationalities scrambled to return to their posts. The Department of State
                    immediately cabled the Embassy in Paris and instructed Ambassador Page, still in
                    transit and in Paris, to cancel his leave and return to Rome. The Jusserands,
                    anxious to return to Washington, departed Paris by car in order to sail for the
                    United States on August 3. The couple stored some of their luggage with the U.S.
                    Embassy for safekeeping. On August 22, nearly three weeks later, the Jusserands
                    arrived on U.S. soil after an arduous voyage via Le Havre and London that
                    included traveling under false names.<note n="20" xml:id="fn20">Jusserand was
                        considered “dangerous cargo” at sea and thus had to travel on a false
                        passport. Letter from Jusserand (Washington) to Delcassé (Paris), August 30,
                        1914. (Ministry of Foreign Affairs Archives. Guerre 1914–1918, États-Unis;
                        Dossier General Vol. 489, Août–Octobre 1914)</note> Jusserand’s August 30
                    report to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs detailed a voyage likely more normal
                    than extraordinary in those early days of chaos. (See Appendix III) On the other
                    side of the Atlantic Ocean, Poole arrived at his father’s home just hours before
                    he was summoned to Washington and dispatched to Paris on the U.S.S <hi
                        rend="italic">North Carolina</hi> alongside other U.S. diplomats bound for
                        Europe.<note n="21" xml:id="fn21">Poole, 60.</note></p>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="money-matters">
                    <head>Money Matters</head>
                    <p>Between July 28 and mid-August, inability to access funds presented a major
                        problem for foreigners as French banks refused to cash traveler’s checks so
                        as to retain currency and gold reserves. Such measures were not
                        unprecedented. In previous international crises, French banks preserved
                        their gold holdings. Thousands of tourists and expatriate residents in
                        France were thus rendered temporarily penniless. The fiscal crisis hit all
                        strata, including the diplomatic corps. Herrick lent the German Ambassador
                        to France nearly 25,000 francs to help tide over German citizens affected by
                        the financial crisis.<note n="22" xml:id="fn22">Herrick (Paris) to Secretary
                            of State (Washington), August 2, 1914. See <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations of the United States, 1914, Supplement, The World
                                War,</hi> p. 33. <ref
                                target="https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1914Supp/pg_33"
                                >history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1914Supp/pg_33</ref>.</note>
                        By July 31, cafés in Paris refused to change 50- and 100-franc notes.<note
                            n="23" xml:id="fn23">William J. Guard, <hi rend="italic">Soul of Paris:
                                Two Months in the French Capital During the War of 1914</hi>, (The
                            Sun Printing &amp; Publishing Co., 1914), 7.</note>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> of London reported that “English and
                        American millionaires were wandering round Paris with their pocket-books
                        full of bank notes, unable to purchase a meal at any restaurant.”<note
                            n="24" xml:id="fn24">“Paris Under the German Menace,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Times History of the War</hi>, Volume II (London: 1915),
                            440.</note> To alleviate the suffering of U.S. citizens, the Herricks
                        opened their home and fed those who had nothing, funded in those early days
                        from their own fortune.</p>
                    <p>Word of the fiscal strain reached the United States. Poole was instructed to
                        bring as much gold with him as possible upon his return to Paris. At the
                        Riggs National Bank in Washington, D.C., he purchased all the gold that his
                        small savings allowed, roughly a few hundred dollars. He also purchased a
                        chamois belt to hold this treasure. Poole recalled that, “this was August
                        fourth or fifth in Washington and it was a very hot day. I remember this
                        gold principally because by the end of the day I was saddled and would
                        gladly have thrown the gold away.”<note n="25" xml:id="fn25">Poole,
                            60–61.</note></p>
                    <p>In the meantime, back in Paris, Herrick convened a committee of U.S.
                        businessmen at his residence on August 2. He appointed Judge E.H. Gary as
                        Chairman and banker Hermann Harjes, head of Morgan, Harjes &amp; Co., as
                        Secretary. Other members of this initial committee included Laurence Benet,
                        Frederick R. Coudert, James Deering, Chauncey M. Depew, future Secretary of
                        State Frank B. Kellogg, and Vice President of the American Chamber of
                        Commerce in Paris Percy Peixetto.</p>
                    <p>Herrick charged the group with devising a way for U.S. citizens to access
                        funds. Their plan hinged upon the fact that the French government needed a
                        way to pay for war-related goods purchased in the United States. Thus,
                        facilitated by Harjes, an account was created at Morgan, Harjes &amp; Co. in
                        Paris through which U.S. citizens could withdraw French francs while a
                        reciprocal account was established at J.P. Morgan &amp; Co. in New York so
                        that the Government of France could pay for its U.S.-based purchases.<note
                            n="26" xml:id="fn26">For further information on this and the role of
                            J.P. Morgan and Morgan, Harjes &amp; Co. in the war, please see Martin
                            Horn, “A Private Bank at War: J.P. Morgan &amp; Co. and France,
                            1914–1918,” <hi rend="italic">The Business History Review</hi> 74.2
                            (Spring 2000): 85–112.</note> The program enabled funds to flow to U.S.
                        citizens in France by mid-August. While the details were hashed out, the
                        committee established a fund for U.S. citizens in need in France. In order
                        to receive this money, distributed by Maj. Cosby, each recipient pledged to
                        take the first available transport back to the United States.</p>
                    <p>Currency and liquidity problems also plagued Embassy staff and volunteers.
                        Wood wrote that when war broke out, he only had 300 francs of his personal
                        funds available. Help arrived on August 14, when he received six $10 gold
                        pieces from his family back home. “When the first one arrived I had spent
                        virtually all the money which I had on hand at the beginning of the war,” he
                        wrote. “This good American gold will tide me over until drafts can be sent
                        through to Paris.” Sixty dollars was a small amount that normally would not
                        last long in New York. In wartime France, however, Wood noted, “300 francs
                        in gold looks a small fortune. At least, it insures plenty of good
                            food.”<note n="27" xml:id="fn27">Wood, 25.</note></p>
                    <p>The committee of U.S. businessmen organized transportation home for U.S.
                        citizens and planned ways to protect U.S. property and citizens. These
                        volunteers of the first hour greatly aided the small Embassy staff, which
                        seemed to do a million things at once. In order to comply with new French
                        regulations, the Embassy issued emergency passports and certificates of
                        nationality. Previously, the only European countries that U.S. citizens
                        required a passport to visit were Russia and the Ottoman Empire. That
                        August, the Embassy went into overdrive and produced 4,500 new passports in
                        a week.<note n="28" xml:id="fn28">Craig Roberts Stapleton (with Louise
                            French McCready), <hi rend="italic">Where Liberty Dwells, There Is My
                                Country: The Story of Twentieth-Century American Ambassadors to
                                France</hi> (Lanham, MD: Hamilton Books, 2010), 10.</note> At one
                        point, Herrick joked that the Embassy functioned as a bank, relief society,
                        and railway exchange rolled into one.<note n="29" xml:id="fn29">Bentley
                            Mott, “Myron Herrick, Friend of France,” <hi rend="italic">World’s
                                Work</hi>, November 1929, p. 73.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="germans-and-austro-hungarians">
                    <head>Germans and Austro-Hungarians</head>
                    <p>It was not just U.S. citizens that the Embassy contended with as tensions
                        quickly escalated. Responsibility to care for German subjects fell to the
                        U.S. Embassy, as previously agreed upon between Washington and Berlin (with
                        the acquiescence of Paris) in the event of a Franco-German war. Stranded
                        Germans, many on vacation in France, were in a delicate situation. Events,
                        Wood wrote, “caught them like rats in a trap and exposed them to the
                        doubtful fate of being lost in an enemy’s country during war time.”<note
                            n="30" xml:id="fn30">Wood, 10.</note> Many feared for their safety,
                        concerns reaffirmed by the early looting of German- and
                        Austro-Hungarian-owned stores in Paris. In the city’s “German” section along
                        rue d’Hauteville near the rue Lafayette, most shops were quickly
                        shuttered.</p>
                    <p>Germans flocked to the U.S. Embassy by the hundreds for assistance and
                        protection. Wood described the chaos on the building’s ground floor, which
                        was converted into an “impromptu German Embassy,” and noted “German women
                        sank down in corners of the halls or on the stairs, weeping for joy to have
                        found a haven of refuge.”<note n="31" xml:id="fn31">Ibid, 19.</note> He
                        found that “each day is now a haze of Germans and their troubles.”<note
                            n="32" xml:id="fn32">Ibid, 22.</note> The Germans required food,
                        lodging, protection, and papers from the French police. Embassy officials
                        gave each German a few francs with which to purchase food, and Herrick
                        organized temporary lodging at the Lycée Condorcet in rue du Havre. The
                        school was “a great barn of a place” and was guarded by a police squad.<note
                            n="33" xml:id="fn33">Ibid.</note> After Austria-Hungary went to war with
                        France on August 10, Embassy employees and volunteers added Austro-Hungarian
                        subjects to their roster of charges. German and Austro-Hungarian civilians
                        were removed and interned in one of 12 detention camps by August 21.<note
                            n="34" xml:id="fn34">The camps were located in Limoges, Gueret, Cahors,
                            Libourne, Périgueux, Saintes, Le Blanc, La Roche-sur-Yon, Chateauroux,
                            Saumur, Anger, and Flers. Ibid, 21.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="staffing-us-embassy-paris">
                    <head>Staffing U.S. Embassy Paris</head>
                    <p>The exponentially increased duties and responsibilities of the Embassy
                        strained the small staff. The ground floor of the chancellery was converted
                        from the military attaché offices to those charged with caretaking German
                        and Austro-Hungarian interests as well as the “Fund Distributing Committee.”
                        The first floor housed all operations related to assisting U.S.
                        citizens.</p>
                    <p>The Embassy relied significantly on volunteers, diplomats’ family members,
                        and other U.S. expatriates living (or stranded) in Paris. To alleviate the
                        staffing burden, on August 6 the Department of State assigned John Work
                        Garrett as Special Agent to the American Ambassador at Paris. Several
                        retired diplomats also volunteered to aid their colleagues in Paris, but
                        that measure soon proved insufficient. On August 13, Herrick cabled the
                        Department of State and requested clerks fluent in English and French to
                        help alleviate the workload.</p>
                    <p>Despite the additional assistance supplied by volunteers like Wood and
                        sculptor Herbert Hazeltine,<note n="35" xml:id="fn35">Herbert Hazeltine was
                            an American sculptor who volunteered at the U.S. Embassy in Paris for
                            many months during World War I.</note> the Embassy struggled to keep up.
                        Staff, volunteers, and Herrick reported for work at 5, rue de Chaillot
                        before 9 a.m. each day, including Sundays, and did not leave until after
                        midnight. According to Wood, “meals are hurriedly swallowed at odd moments
                        and at irregular hours.”<note n="36" xml:id="fn36">Wood, 22.</note></p>
                    <p>The work was stressful and fatiguing. Some fell ill, including Herrick,
                        Carolyn, and both Blisses. “We do look a little forelorn [sic] at the
                        Embassy,” Carolyn wrote.<note n="37" xml:id="fn37">Letter from Carolyn
                            Herrick to Agnes &amp; Parmely Herrick, September 14, 1914. (Western
                            Reserve Historical Society, Cleveland, Ohio, Myron T. Herrick Papers, MS
                            2925, Container 15, Folder 234).</note> Others were unable to cope with
                        the stress. On August 22 Herrick notified the Department of State that one
                        of the Embassy clerks was granted a leave of absence because the gentleman
                        was believed to have become temporarily unhinged. Nobody imagined that
                        things would get worse.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="life-in-paris">
                    <head>Life in Paris, August</head>
                    <p>With France fully engaged in the war, life in and around Paris quickly
                        changed. Much of the city’s bustling life abruptly halted as men mobilized
                        and shipped off to the frontlines. In their place, wives, daughters,
                        sisters, and mothers filled the labor gap. Many shops closed, though those
                        selling food and other daily provisions remained open. Several of Paris’ big
                        hotels, devoid of guests and much of their staff, transformed themselves
                        into hospitals.</p>
                    <p>The Tour Eiffel, at the time one of the highest wireless masts in the world,
                        was overnight turned from a wonder into a vital, strongly defended
                        communications hub.<note n="38" xml:id="fn38">Ibid, 13.</note> As the
                        structure exchanged messages with Washington and St. Petersburg, many feared
                        it might be subject to attack. It was guarded against sabotage on the ground
                        and encircled by a ring of heavy barbed wire, while a system of
                        anti-aircraft guns defended the towering structure from German airplanes and
                            zeppelins.<note n="39">Ibid.</note></p>
                    <p>Another protective measure undertaken by French officials was imposition of
                        an 8pm curfew and blackout. Wood wrote on August 4, that “all night the
                        beams of searchlights comb the sky for invaders and cast a tragic reflected
                        glow upon the city beneath.”<note n="40" xml:id="fn40">Ibid, 18.</note>
                        Later that month he relayed,</p>
                    <p>It is an uncanny experience to walk through a great city which is absolutely
                        dark. The Champs-Elysées is probably at present the darkest avenue on earth.
                        All those monumental lamp-posts which used to stand like beacons in the
                        midst of the stream of traffic now shine no more. The sun seldom rises
                        without revealing the ruins of one of these lamps and of an automobile, the
                        two having mutually destroyed each other in the darkness.<note n="41"
                            xml:id="fn41">Ibid, 31.</note></p>
                    <p>People adjusted to the new rhythm of life. The racetrack at Auteil was
                        converted into a cow pasture, and sheep en route to the eastern-bound train
                        stations were a common sight. While fruits and vegetables were in decent
                        supply, government officials put restrictions on certain commodities. By
                        August 8, the government regulated the milk industry and by August 12
                        controlled grains and flours. U.S. journalist William J. Guard bemoaned,</p>
                    <p>No more fancy bread! The police stopped that. No more of those delicious
                        croissants and crisp rolls that we enjoy so much with our early morning
                        coffee. The making of them means waste of flour, butter, and milk. The only
                        bread to be had is just common ordinary bread.<note n="42" xml:id="fn42"
                            >Guard, 17.</note></p>
                    <p>There were other impositions upon daily life. The August 12, 1914, edition of
                            <hi rend="italic">The Day Book</hi> (Chicago, Ill.), reported that
                        Herrick, while talking on the telephone in Paris, was cut off for speaking
                        in English. “War regulations are that all telephone conversations must be in
                        French,” the paper noted.<note n="43" xml:id="fn43">“Odd War Bits,” <hi
                                rend="italic">The Day Book</hi> (Chicago, Ill.), August 12, 1914.
                                <ptr
                                target="https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1914-08-12/ed-1/seq-32/"
                            />http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1914-08-12/ed-1/seq-32</note>
                        The French-language restrictions were imposed upon the diplomatic community
                        for several years. First Secretary and Embassy Counselor Robert Woods Bliss
                        was not given official permission to speak on the telephone in English until
                            1916.<note n="44" xml:id="fn44">Official Correspondence from the French
                            Ministry of War to U.S. Embassy Paris, April 8, 1916. (Harvard
                            University Archives, Cambridge, Massachusetts, Papers of Robert Woods
                            Bliss and Mildred Barnes Bliss, HUGFP 76.14 Box 1 Diplomatic
                            Correspondence Paris: 1912–1919).</note></p>
                    <p>Another of the war’s immediate impacts was on transportation—or the lack of
                        it. The Métro closed at 7:30pm to comply with the 8pm curfew. Taxis, much in
                        demand, became scarce and prohibitively expensive while private automobiles
                        were requisitioned by the French military. Those working at the Embassy thus
                        grew creative in how they traveled around the city.</p>
                    <p>Herrick asked U.S. automobile owners in Paris to donate their cars for
                        official Embassy service. Instead of being enfolded into the French
                        military, these vehicles were pressed into diplomatic duty and enabled U.S.
                        diplomats and volunteers to be an effective force from the first days of
                        crisis, an accomplishment of which Herrick was very proud.</p>
                    <p>Other solutions were also employed. Wood hired a fiacre to get around the
                        city. His driver, Paul, and an old horse, Grisette, supplied Wood with a
                        one-horsepower transportation option. Wood wrote that Paul,</p>
                    <p>Considers it a great honor to drive for a member of an Embassy and always
                        sits up very straight on his box, for to come and go on missions concerning
                        “les affaires des États-Unis” has imbued him with a great sense of dignity
                        and importance. When waiting in front of the Embassy among the limousines he
                        maintains a rigid and dignified position and insists that Grisette, for her
                        part, shall hold up her head and stand on all four feet. Each noon Paul
                        drives [Herbert] Hazeltine and myself down the nearly deserted
                        Champs-Elysées for lunch at the Café Royal. We must make an absurd spectacle
                        with so much dignity on the box and a total lack of it behind, for Hazeltine
                        and I, relaxing from the strenuous work of the morning, lounge in the seat
                        with our feet far out in front, as we discuss with great vehemence affairs
                        connected with our Embassy work.<note n="45" xml:id="fn45">Wood,
                        33.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="retention-of-herrick">
                    <head>Retention of Herrick</head>
                    <p>The rapid escalation of events created an unusual situation of U.S.
                        diplomatic representation in France, one in which the outgoing Ambassador
                        was retained at the same time that the incoming Ambassador arrived. On
                        August 25, Bryan notified Herrick that Sharp would sail for France the
                        following day. Bryan confided that Wilson wished for Herrick to remain in
                        charge in Paris for the time being, given the extraordinary circumstances,
                        and that Sharp not assume charge until the strain of the German threat to
                        Paris passed.<note n="46" xml:id="fn46">Telegram from Bryan (Washington DC)
                            to Herrick (Paris), August 25, 1914. (National Archives, RG 59, Central
                            Decimal File 1910–29, File 123 H 43)</note>Herrick acquiesced but
                        received permission to make public the Department’s instructions to minimize
                        any misunderstandings of his role—or that of Sharp—in France.<note n="47"
                            xml:id="fn47">Telegram from Secretary of State (Washington DC) to
                            Herrick (Paris), August 28, 1914. Copy from file 123 H 43, 1910–29
                            Central Decimal File, Record Group 59: General Records of the Department
                            of State, National Archives.</note></p>
                    <p>The French were equally as interested in whether Herrick would remain at the
                        helm of U.S. operations in France. On August 25, Jusserand cabled Foreign
                        Minister Théophile Delcassé that “M. Robert Bacon, former Ambassador at
                        Paris, without knowing in what way he can aid us but passionately desiring
                        to be there, will embark tomorrow on <hi rend="italic">La France</hi>. It is
                        possible but not certain that M. Sharp, the new American ambassador, takes
                        the same ship.”<note n="48" xml:id="fn48">Telegram from Jusserand to
                            Delcassé, August 25, 1914. (Ministry of Foreign Affairs Archives, Guerre
                            1914–1918 États-Unis, Vol. 489 Dossier Generale: Août–Octobre
                            1914)</note> The <hi rend="italic">La France</hi> set sail on August 26.
                        Since Sharp’s wife remained too sick to travel, his eldest son George made
                        the trip to keep his father company (and would be smitten enough by Paris to
                        spend most of the war years there). Aboard the ship, Bacon wrote to his
                        wife, “I seem to be conscious of a sort of feverish desire to do something
                        for somebody, with not enough aggressiveness or ability to make it
                            worthwhile.”<note n="49">James Brown Scott, <hi rend="italic">Robert
                                Bacon: Life and Letters</hi> (New York:Arno Press, 1975),
                            203.</note> He was indeed anxious to aid France.</p>
                    <p>For the French, the return of Bacon, a much-beloved former Ambassador, was a
                        boost to morale. Moreover, the symbolism of three U.S. Ambassadors on the
                        ground was perceived within French circles as an indication of the United
                        States’ high regard for its sister republic. The triumvirate of U.S.
                        Ambassadors bolstered French mettle in the dark days of September.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part" xml:id="everyones-embassy">
                <head>September 1914: Everyone’s Embassy</head>
                <p>The Germans neared Paris by early September and the sense of crisis grew. Wood
                    wrote that by September 1, “panic conditions of the most pronounced order exist
                    today,” as many sought to escape Paris ahead of a possible German invasion.<note
                        n="50" xml:id="fn50">Wood, 37.</note> There was a run on the banks, the
                    railway stations and streets overflowed as people tried to flee, and it was
                    impossible to hail a taxicab.<note n="51" xml:id="fn51">Ibid.</note> Much of the
                    Parisian working class remained in the city, but as they worked during the day,
                    the city seemed deserted. <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> of London reported
                    that “the boulevards in the middle of the morning came to be more like the
                    streets of a country town than those of the capital of France.”<note n="52"
                        xml:id="fn52">“Paris Under the German Menace,” <hi rend="italic">The Times
                            History of the War</hi>, Volume II (London: 1915), 461.</note> Yet, some
                    areas remained hotbeds of activity.</p>
                <p>Herrick visited Poincaré at the Elysée Palace on September 2, as the Government
                    of France prepared to remove its seat to Bordeaux. Poincaré recalled that
                    Herrick “arrived strongly moved, the face decomposed under his jolly crown of
                    curly hair.”<note n="53" xml:id="fn53">Raymond Poincaré, preface. T. Betley
                        Mott, <hi rend="italic">Souvenirs de Myron T. Herrick</hi> (Paris: Plon,
                        1930), vii–viii.</note> Herrick informed the French President of his intent
                    to remain in Paris—pending, of course, the government’s approval. Herrick,
                    Poincaré noted, resolved to do anything he could to guard Parisians from the
                    possible pillages and problems in the event the Germans captured the city. “He
                    had tears in his eyes when he spoke to me,” Poincaré wrote.<note n="54"
                        xml:id="fn54">Ibid.</note></p>
                <p>At 10:50pm that evening, the diplomatic corps departed for Bordeaux. The Herricks
                    went to the Gare d’Orsay to see the 11-carriage-long diplomatic train off.<note
                        n="55" xml:id="fn55">Myron T. Herrick. Chapter Two of Myron T. Herrick
                        Remembrances, 1920s but undated, unpublished, 21. (Western Reserve
                        Historical Society, Cleveland, Ohio, Myron T. Herrick Papers, MS 2925,
                        Container 3, Folder 3).</note> Herrick wrote to his son Parmley that many of
                    his diplomat colleagues “seemed cheerful at the thought of leaving Paris; others
                    were crestfallen, as though they were running away from something—as though they
                    were going to ‘miss’ something.”<note n="56" xml:id="fn56">Letter from Herrick
                        (Paris) to Parmeley Herrick, September 4, 1914. (Western Reserve Historical
                        Society, Cleveland, Ohio, Myron T. Herrick Papers, MS 2925).</note> The
                    train did not reach Bordeaux until after lunchtime on September 3. The trip,
                    normally a 10–11 hour jaunt, was a slow slog, according to British Ambassador to
                    France Sir Francis Bertie, who was on the train in one of the three first-class
                    compartments reserved for the British Diplomatic Service. Bertie wrote Herrick
                    that though the trip had “many long stops,” it was “not uncomfortable.”<note
                        n="57" xml:id="fn57">Letter from Sir Francis Bertie (Bordeaux) to Herrick
                        (Paris), September 4, 1914. (Western Reserve Historical Society, Cleveland,
                        Ohio, Myron T. Herrick Papers, MS 2925).</note> One man’s assessment of “not
                    uncomfortable” was another man’s terror. Long after the diplomatic train arrived
                    in Bordeaux, <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> reported, “terrible stories were
                    told of Excellencies sitting five a-side, and fighting with third secretaries at
                    wayside refreshment rooms for a scrap of something to eat.”<note n="58"
                        xml:id="fn58">“Paris Under the German Menace,” <hi rend="italic">The Times
                            History of the War</hi>, Volume II (London: 1915), 469.</note> Herrick
                    dispatched Garrett to Bordeaux to represent U.S., German, and Austro-Hungarian
                    interests to the Government of France. Garrett took Sussdorff and Captain F. H.
                    Pope, one of the Embassy’s military attachés, with him. It is unclear whether
                    the U.S. diplomatic party traveled to Bordeaux on this train or whether they
                    motored down from Paris in Embassy cars.</p>
                <p>The United States was now caretaking interests for eight nations in Paris (the
                    United States, Germany, Austria-Hungary, Great Britain, Japan, Serbia,
                    Guatemala, and Nicaragua). Parisians warmly embraced the U.S. diplomatic corps
                    for its decision to remain behind when most other diplomats fled to Bordeaux.
                    Herrick maintained an aura of calm that blanketed the capital’s population. Wood
                    wrote that Herrick’s picture “is in all the newspapers and shop windows, and
                    even the most humble member of the Embassy shines by reflected glory.”<note
                        n="59" xml:id="fn59">Wood, 47.</note> The Government of France was also a
                    huge supporter of Herrick. In a September 2 telegram, Delcassé asked
                    Jusserand,</p>
                <p>In your opinion, in these conditions is it possible to have President Wilson
                    understand that the Government of France would like to see Mr. Herrick
                    maintained in his functions in Paris until the end of the conflict that France
                    and her allies fight with the German powers?<note n="60" xml:id="fn60">Telegram
                        from Delcassé to Jusserand, September 2, 1914. (Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                        Archives, Guerre 1914–1918 Etats-Unis, Vol. 489 Dossier Generale:
                        Août–Octobre 1914).</note></p>
                <p>On September 3, martial law was declared in Paris, the city in a state of siege.
                    Curfews were imposed. There was no exit or entry of the city gates between the
                    hours of 8pm and 5am without military passes. Cars were only allowed to exit the
                    city with special permits, although they were freely able to enter the city.
                    Those who brought fresh fruits and vegetables into the city were some of the
                    only people allowed regular and frequent access into the city throughout the
                    evening hours.<note n="61" xml:id="fn61">“Prepare Paris to Oppose Siege,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Chicago Daily Tribune</hi>, September 4, 1914, p.
                        1.</note> Those who brought U.S. Ambassadors into the city were also allowed
                    to pass.</p>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="discord-and-amite">
                    <head>The Three Amigos? Discord and Amité</head>
                    <p>The transfer of the government to Bordeaux coincided with the September 3
                        arrival of the Sharps and Bacon in the quickly emptying capital. Bacon,
                        never idle, spent his time at sea reading about pan-Germanism and the
                        Balkans to better understand the events and region that launched Europe into
                        total war within a matter of days.<note n="62" xml:id="fn62">Scott,
                            205.</note> The <hi rend="italic">La France</hi> docked at Le Havre in
                        the early morning hours of September 2, where U.S. Consul John Ball Osborne
                        met the two Ambassadors. In midafternoon, Bacon and the Sharps set out for
                        Paris via automobile, accompanied by Louis Jaray, Secretary of the Comité
                        France-Amérique. The trip was a long and dusty one that passed via Rouen,
                        Pacy-sur-Eure (where they stopped for dinner around 10pm), and
                            Versailles.<note n="63" xml:id="fn63">Warrington Dawson (ed.), <hi
                                rend="italic">The War Memoirs of William Graves Sharp</hi> (London:
                            Constable &amp; Co. Ltd., 1931), 7.</note> Sharp wrote that the walls of
                        the Palace of Versailles that night had, “the impressive, almost unearthly
                        appearance … as we passed it in the lengthening shadows of the waning
                            moonlight.”<note n="64" xml:id="fn64">Dawson, 13.</note></p>
                    <p>Around 4am on September 3, the party pulled in front of the Hôtel de Crillon
                        on the Place de la Concorde. George Sharp wrote his mother that upon arrival
                        “my hair was matted with dirt and both of us were covered from head to foot”
                        in dust from the roads.<note n="65" xml:id="fn65">Lilla Pennant, <hi
                                rend="italic">Wartime Embassy: The Life of William Graves Sharp,
                                U.S. Ambassador to France, and his Son George Clough Sharp During
                                the First World War</hi> (Sommerville, Mass.: Firefly Press, 1989),
                            16.</note> The Sharps took a suite of rooms that overlooked the Place de
                        la Concorde—their residence for the next several months—while Bacon checked
                        into the apartment he kept at the hotel.</p>
                    <p>Sharp did not immediately assume his role as Ambassador, an arrangement
                        agreed upon prior to Sharp’s departure by Bryan, Wilson, and Sharp himself.
                        Herrick continued to serve in an official capacity, freeing Sharp to immerse
                        himself in his new environment as a private U.S. citizen. Sharp visited the
                        battlefields to better acquaint himself with the war’s realities and learned
                        about the people of France. He also searched for a new Ambassador’s
                        residence, as the lease on the mansion occupied by Herrick was costly and
                        not to be renewed. Ellie Thackara, wife of Consul Thackara, helped Sharp
                        secure a house at 14, avenue d’Eylau, which served as the Sharp family
                        residence from Spring 1915 until April 1919.</p>
                    <p>The presence of the three U.S. Ambassadors was immediately reported in the
                        press. Reporter Charles Inman Barnard noted, “The Paris newspapers seem
                        highly pleased at this ‘strong diplomatic manifestation’…constituting a
                        delegation from the United States to see that the rights of universal
                        humanity are respected.”<note n="66" xml:id="fn66">Charles Inman Barnard,
                                <hi rend="italic">Paris War Days</hi>, Sept 4.</note> Yet, the
                        unusual situation bred tensions. On September 5, Bryan cabled Herrick,</p>
                    <p>President fears from a private telegram received there may be
                        misunderstanding in regard to Sharp’s position there. He will be engaged in
                        personal matters such as renting and furnishing house, et cetera, until time
                        arrives to transfer Embassy. If he assists you it will be in the capacity of
                        a private citizen and not officially. The President will desire to consult
                        both of you in regard to the proper time to transfer Embassy.<note n="67"
                            xml:id="fn67">Telegram from Bryan to Herrick, September 5, 1914.
                            (National Archives, RG 59 123 Sh21)</note></p>
                    <p>Herrick later confided to his personal secretary Col. Bentley Mott that “I
                        was much relieved by these instructions,” for he felt that such arrangements
                        “never work satisfactorily, whether in business, war, or diplomacy. Under
                        the conditions then confronting me…I knew that any divided responsibility
                        would be fatal.”<note n="68" xml:id="fn68">Col. Bentley Mott, <hi
                                rend="italic">Herrick Book</hi>, 214.</note></p>
                    <p>From the earliest days, Herrick clearly stated his willingness to step aside
                        and hand the reins of the Embassy over to Sharp as soon as the new
                        Ambassador arrived and settled in enough to do so in the midst of crisis.
                        Sharp himself knew,</p>
                    <p>I was not to assume immediate charge of the mission, as the exigencies of the
                        unusual situation seemed to dictate a deviation from the custom of the
                        outgoing representative leaving either before or upon the arrival of his
                            successor.<note n="69" xml:id="fn69">Dawson, 57.</note></p>
                    <p>Despite such public and professional sentiments, there was little love lost
                        between Herrick and Sharp. Perhaps the seed was sown in those early
                        September days when an incident surrounding publication of Sharp’s interview
                        with the <hi rend="italic">New York Herald</hi> bred suspicion between the
                        two gentlemen.<note n="70" xml:id="fn70">Sharp was interviewed about his
                            arrival, his civilian status until the time arrived for him to take over
                            the Embassy, praise for the French people and institutions (and
                            Herrick), and how he hoped Wilson’s plea for peace would be adopted and
                            a lasting peace and disarmament ensue. A false report circulated within
                            the French press that the resultant article was barred from transmission
                            by the censor’s office for fear it might betray French morale. Sharp
                            wrote home of his suspicions that Herrick used his power and influence
                            to block the article’s publication—and also paid for the anonymous
                            dispatch that claimed (falsely) that the French Government censored the
                            piece. Pennant, 24.</note> The fact that Sharp corresponded with Wilson
                        and others via letters posted privately by his son, George, to avoid Embassy
                        or Department officials reading their contents perhaps did not aid matters.
                        Nor did the fact that as early as mid-September Sharp lobbied Herrick to
                        take control of Embassy operations on October 1.<note n="71" xml:id="fn71"
                            >Mott, 215.</note> Sharp maintained that the period he was in Paris
                        waiting for Herrick to depart “became one of increased embarrassment to
                            me.”<note n="72" xml:id="fn72">Beckles Willson, <hi rend="italic"
                                >America’s Ambassadors to France, 1777–1927</hi> (London: John
                            Murray, 1928), 401.</note></p>
                    <p>While Sharp suffered from perceived embarrassment over his circumstances,
                        Herrick was personally embarrassed for what he considered his successor’s
                        lack of qualifications. In a draft of a September 15 letter to his friend
                        James Parmelee, Herrick noted,</p>
                    <p>Mr. Sharp has arrived and of him I will say very little… he seems to me to be
                        unaware of the responsibilities and utterly lacking in qualifications of the
                        post: one which requires some sort of tact in ordinary times, but in such a
                        time as this, if one were not well acquainted with the condition of things
                        it would be seriously handicapped.<note n="73" xml:id="fn73">Letter from
                            Herrick (Paris) to James Parmelee, September 15, 1914. Myron T. Herrick
                            Scrapbook, Vol. I: 1902–1929. Manuscript Division. Library of Congress,
                            Washington, D.C.</note></p>
                    <p>Relations between Herrick and Bacon were much warmer. The Herricks often had
                        Bacon to lunch or dinner. “Mr. Bacon is such a help,” Carolyn wrote her son
                        and daughter-in-law. “We have asked him to come here and stay with us but he
                        is afraid he will make us trouble.”<note n="74" xml:id="fn74">Letter from
                            Carolyn Herrick to Agnes &amp; Parmely Herrick, September 14, 1914.
                            (Western Reserve Historical Society, Cleveland, Ohio, Myron T. Herrick
                            Papers, MS 2925,Container 15, Folder 234).</note> Myron Herrick
                        considered “Bob” to be “a fine fellow, and deeply impressed over all the
                        things he sees and hears.”<note n="75" xml:id="fn75">Letter from Herrick
                            (Paris) to Parmely Herrick, September 4, 1914. (Western Reserve
                            Historical Society, Cleveland, Ohio, Myron T. Herrick Papers, MS
                            2925).</note> Bacon likewise had high regard for Herrick. “The French
                        people and government are all crazy about him,” Bacon wrote.<note n="76"
                            xml:id="fn76">Scott, 206.</note></p>
                    <p>Assistant Secretary of the War Department Henry Breckinridge was also a
                        Herrick enthusiast. Sent to Europe to assess the war situation on August 6,
                        Breckinridge arrived in Paris close on the heels of the Sharps and Bacon,
                        and also checked into the Crillon. Immediately Breckinridge picked up on the
                        “very anomalous situation” between Herrick and Sharp.<note n="77"
                            xml:id="fn77">Henry Breckinridge, “Robert Bacon: Work in France in the
                            Early Days of the War,” <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, June
                            5, 1919, p. 12.</note> Yet, he found that Bacon’s presence was more than
                        welcome. “In those critical days,” he wrote, Bacon,</p>
                    <p>Was a real, though unofficial, Ambassador of the spirit of America to the
                        French nation. He was everywhere. One day he was consulting with allied
                        officials in Paris. The next day he was racing to various points of the
                        front, following the operations and encouraging his many friends in the
                        French and British armies. His very presence radiated encouragement and
                        spoke to the French and English the moral support of America which had not
                        as yet been translated into official expression.<note n="78" xml:id="fn78"
                            >Ibid.</note></p>
                    <p>Such encouragement as derived from Bacon arrived just in time, for the
                        Germans were at the gates of Paris. Since late August, German proximity to
                        the capital was announced via airplanes that dropped bombs on the city.
                        Poole noted that the first such attacks were met with general panic, death,
                        and excitement, but quickly bred opportunism. “On the second day,” Wood
                        wrote of the bombings, “there were even enterprising vendors in the Place de
                        la Concorde who would rent you opera glasses with which to look at the
                        Boches more closely.”<note n="79" xml:id="fn79">Poole, 65.</note> The German
                        planes—Taubes—flew and dropped their bombs over Paris regularly at sunset in
                        those first weeks. Wood recalled the throngs of people who gathered outside
                        to watch the regular displays. The planes “looked very like a bug crawling
                        across the sky. With our glasses we could see the German aviator looking
                        down at us, and could distinguish on the under side of each wing the black
                        Maltese cross which all German aeroplanes carry as ‘uniform.’”<note n="80"
                            xml:id="fn80">Wood, 39.</note> While “the French already take their
                        daily Taube as much as a matter of course as their daily café,” he observed
                        that the frequent bombings had an immense psychological effect upon the
                            population.<note n="81" xml:id="fn81">Wood, 41.</note> The battle to
                        save Paris had an equally strong impact on Parisians.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="battle-of-the-marne">
                    <head>Battle of the Marne</head>
                    <p>In early September the German Army threatened Paris. In an extraordinary
                        move, military governor of Paris General Joseph Gallieni (a personal friend
                        of U.S. Consul William H. Hunt) orchestrated one of the most famous
                        maneuvers of the war—the taxicab brigades. General Gallieni enlisted
                        Parisian taxicabs and busses to ferry troops to the battlefront lines just
                        outside of the city, which left Paris “denuded of transportation.”<note
                            n="82" xml:id="fn82">Poole, 65.</note> The evening of the first taxicab
                        brigades, the noise awoke Sharp, who rose and watched the odd procession
                        from his hotel window. He did not learn until much later that the
                        progression of automobiles, carriages, and other miscellaneous types of
                        vehicles ferried troops to the front.<note n="83" xml:id="fn83">Dawson,
                            19.</note></p>
                    <p>It was par for the course that U.S. diplomats—and Parisians in general—had
                        little information as the Germans threatened Paris, since French authorities
                        and the press limited news that might have agitated the population into a
                        panic. In order to glean first-hand news, several members of the Embassy
                        staff, such as Wood, toured the frontlines of the battle. “I was not so
                        horrified in viewing these ghastly sights as I had expected,” he wrote,
                        “because I could not pull from me a sense of their unreality.”<note n="84"
                            xml:id="fn84">Wood, 75.</note> On September 13, Second Secretary Frazier
                        was dispatched to the frontlines at Meaux to report on conditions. Frazier
                        “reported that French troops showed respect to German dead by covering their
                        faces with straw while awaiting burying squad.”<note n="85" xml:id="fn85"
                            >Herrick (Paris) to Secretary of State (Washington DC), September 14,
                            1914, rec’d 8:22pm. (National Archives, RG 59 763.72/859)</note></p>
                    <p>Once it was clear that the German offensive was stalled and Paris beyond
                        immediate danger, U.S. diplomats and consular officials refocused their
                        efforts on taking care of German and Austro-Hungarian prisoners-of-war and
                        interned civilians. Herrick visited the internment camp for German and
                        Austro-Hungarian subjects in Flers, but the bulk of this responsibility fell
                        to Garrett as many of the camps were within the Bordeaux vicinity. In
                        September, Garrett visited the three sites closest to him. The camp at Blaye
                        contained roughly 1,200 prisoners of war, nearly half of whom were
                            wounded.<note n="86" xml:id="fn86">Garrett (Bordeaux) to Herrick
                            (Paris), October 5, 1914. (National Archives, RG 59 763.72
                            115/172)</note> Garrett noted that, “my impression of the care given
                        them, the medical treatment, food, etc., was excellent.”<note n="87"
                            xml:id="fn87">Ibid.</note> The male refugee camp at Bazas was located on
                        a race track with temporary wooden buildings to serve the camp’s internees.
                        Garrett reported,</p>
                    <p>The refugees said the food was good. There was a lack of blankets and the
                        holes in the grand stand cover and in the other buildings will certainly let
                        in a lot of cold air when the weather changes. Not half of these refugees
                        had blankets a deficiency which I am trying to supply.<note n="88"
                            xml:id="fn88">Ibid.</note></p>
                    <p>Their chief complaints were “that they had no money to buy extras with.” To
                        remedy the situation, Garrett provided 3,000 francs to the Préfet of the
                        Gironde (2,000 for Austro-Hungarians, 1,000 for Germans) that could be used
                        by the refugees to purchase such extra comforts.<note n="89" xml:id="fn89"
                            >Ibid.</note></p>
                    <p>On September 29, Garrett, Captain Pope, and their wives visited two camps in
                        Libourne for women and children.<note n="90" xml:id="fn90">They reported
                            only 8–10 men present. Garrett was struck by an odd fact of many of the
                            Libourne internees: roughly half of them were French women, wives of
                            Austrian and German subjects, who spoke little or no German.
                            Ibid.</note> While conditions were satisfactory and clean, a blanket
                        shortage was again noted. Upon return from this visit, Garrett sent 1,000
                        blankets to the Sous-Préfet of Libourne to provide for those in need.<note
                            n="91" xml:id="fn91">Ibid.</note> Some camp conditions deteriorated as
                        the autumn progressed. Herrick reported on visits to several camps, two of
                        which had conditions “not altogether satisfactory.” He believed difficulties
                        were partly unavoidable given the circumstances. “I am convinced,” he
                        reported to Bryan, “that the French Government desires that all such
                        establishments shall be properly arranged and maintained.”<note n="92"
                            xml:id="fn92">Herrick (Paris) to Secretary of State (Washington, DC),
                            November 12, 1914. (National Archives, RG 59 763.72115/224)</note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="american-ambulance-hospital">
                    <head>American Ambulance Hospital</head>
                    <p>In addition to these many official duties, the U.S. expatriate community in
                        France pulled together to provide unofficial assistance in the form of war
                        relief societies and medical aid. First and foremost of these initiatives
                        was the American Ambulance Hospital in Neuilly. Established on August 9, the
                        American Ambulance Hospital was a private hospital funded and staffed by
                        U.S. volunteers to treat wounded soldiers from both sides of the conflict.
                        Championed by Herrick, the American Ambulance Hospital was quickly accepted
                        by the Government of France as a military hospital, though it retained its
                        independence.</p>
                    <p>The institution was not without precedent. In 1870, a private ambulance was
                        established by George B. McFarland, a U.S. citizen, and his wife to convey
                        battlefield wounded to Parisian-area hospitals during the Franco-Prussian
                        War. At the time, U.S. Minister to France Elihu Washburne helped solicit
                        funds and support for this ambulance, which was credited with saving
                        hundreds of lives, French and German.</p>
                    <p>Carolyn Herrick was an equally prominent, supportive proponent of the
                        fledgling American Ambulance Hospital in August 1914. As President of
                        American Ambulance’s Women’s Committee, she smoothed over differences of
                        opinion among committee members, kept the group on-track, and ensured the
                        organization’s potency. Carolyn utilized her friendships with French and
                        American women to raise funds and secure volunteers. Her work was
                        facilitated by Mrs. Hermann Harjes (Treasurer), Mrs. Laurence Benet
                        (Secretary), Ellie Sherman Thackara, Mildred Barnes Bliss, members of the
                        American Chamber of Commerce in Paris, and others.</p>
                    <p>The American Ambulance Hospital was given the Lycée Pasteur in Neuilly, a
                        building so new that it lacked doors and windows. Several U.S. architects
                        from the École des Beaux Arts volunteered their time and expertise to
                        convert the unfinished Lycée Pasteur into a first-rate modern hospital. By
                        September 1, the American Ambulance Hospital was ready for service, and
                        received its first patients within a few days. On September 14, Carolyn
                        informed her son and daughter-in-law that, “the Ambulance has many wounded
                        and doing such work.” However, she stressed, “we shall need more money if we
                        have more beds.”<note n="93" xml:id="fn93">Letter from Carolyn Herrick to
                            Agnes &amp; Parmely Herrick, September 14, 1914. (Western Reserve
                            Historical Society, Cleveland, Ohio, Myron T. Herrick Papers, MS 2925,
                            Container 15, Folder 234).</note> Her husband, Ambassador Herrick,
                        quickly recognized the hospital’s utility. He speculated—perhaps
                        correctly—that the American Ambulance Hospital did more than anyone could
                        fathom to strengthen Franco-American relations.</p>
                    <p>Another key volunteer from the U.S. expatriate community in Paris was Anne
                        Harriman Vanderbilt. The daughter of Edward Harriman and the wife of W.K.
                        Vanderbilt, Anne immersed herself in war relief work. She took direct
                        management of the nascent nursing corps in Paris, and used her personal
                        fortune to purchase the first 10 automobiles for the American Ambulance
                        Hospital. Later, she purchased the first Nieuport planes for the Escadrille
                        Lafayette.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="diplomats-under-fire">
                    <head>Diplomats Under Fire</head>
                    <p>On Sunday, September 27, the Germans nearly killed Herrick. That afternoon,
                        Herrick and Frazier hopped into an Embassy car outside 5, rue de Chaillot,
                        to inspect the German Embassy buildings in the rue de Lille. They passed
                        Wood at the Pont d’Alma and a minute later, a German bomb fell on the Avenue
                        du Trocadéro around the corner from the Embassy. It killed an old man and
                        severely maimed a little girl, who lost her leg, but just missed the
                        Ambassador. The following day, Wood overheard a Frenchman at the Café Royal
                        tell his lunch companion that despite the man’s great regard for Herrick,
                        “it would nevertheless have been an excellent service against the enemy had
                        he [Herrick] tactfully allowed himself to be annihilated by the German
                        bomb.” Upon learning of this remark, Herrick “was much amused.”<note n="94"
                            xml:id="fn94">Wood, 110.</note></p>
                    <p>While he took the incident in stride, not all diplomats could handle the
                        stress of war and being under fire with as much grace or aplomb. Reims was
                        in a state of siege by early August, and things quickly grew worse as the
                        German Army bombarded the city in September. U.S. Consul at Reims William
                        Bardel, a naturalized U.S. citizen originally from Germany, was known among
                        the Champagne producers of Epernay as capable and efficient. Yet, even the
                        staunchest of officials broke under the stress. The strain of constantly
                        being under fire grew onerous.</p>
                    <p>In his October 10 dispatch, Bardel informed the Department that, “since my
                        last dispatch (no. 151) of September 4, 1914, I have had to undergo the most
                        terrible experience of all my life.” He described the city’s destruction and
                        scarcity of food. The Bardel family—and likely, much of the Reims
                        population—went without milk, butter, eggs, and even for a time, bread.<note
                            n="95" xml:id="fn95">Letter from Bardel (Troyes) to Secretary of State
                            (Washington DC), October 10, 1914. (National Archives, RG 59 123 B
                            23)</note> The electricity and gas lines were cut, and kerosene lamps
                        and candles were the main sources of light.<note n="96" xml:id="fn96"
                            >Ibid.</note></p>
                    <p>The Bardels regularly sought safety in a wine cellar down the street from
                        their house, which lay in a heavily-damaged area.<note n="97" xml:id="fn97"
                            >“William Bardel, 80, Dies.” <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>,
                            January 1, 1927, p. 13.</note> “Finally,” the Consul noted, “we all
                        became so exhausted from the hardships we had to undergo, and from the
                        horrors we experienced on our runs for safety, that we could stand it in the
                        cellars no longer.” Despite his strong sense of duty, Bardel took his family
                        to Troyes as his wife and daughter showed signs of severe anxiety and trauma
                        from the stress.<note n="98" xml:id="fn98">Letter from Bardel (Troyes) to
                            Secretary of State (Washington DC), October 10, 1914. (National
                            Archives, RG 59 123 B 23)</note></p>
                    <p>Bardel left Vice Consul William Stanford in temporary charge of the U.S.
                        Consulate, and asked the Department for permission to remain at Troyes. The
                        Department acquiesced after receiving a report from Stanford a few days
                        later. The continued, intermittent bombardment of the city was, Stanford
                        wrote, “even more trying than in the early days, when it was done
                            systematically.”<note n="99" xml:id="fn99">Ibid.</note> He found it to
                        be “a nerve-racking life.”<note n="100" xml:id="fn100">Ibid.</note> Yet
                        Stanford remained in Reims until the closure of that Consulate in early 1915
                        to field inquiries from German, British, and French subjects about missing
                            relatives.<note n="101" xml:id="fn101">Ibid.</note> Bardel proceeded to
                        Épernay on November 4, and performed his consular functions at a temporary
                        Consulate established at 20, rue du Commerce until his reassignment to St.
                        Michael’s (the Azores) in October 1915.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part" xml:id="past-the-danger">
                <head>Past the Danger: October-November 1914</head>
                <p>The immediate threat posed to Paris by the German Army passed after
                    mid-September. The Allied armies held the Germans to a standstill and the war
                    along the Western Front transformed into a standoff in the trenches—one that
                    lasted until the German offensive in the spring of 1918. In the meantime, in
                    October 1914, the Government of France settled into life in Bordeaux, as did the
                    members of the diplomatic corps who followed them to that city.</p>
                <p>Garrett, Sussdorff, and Captain Pope were overwhelmed with representational
                    duties. The U.S. diplomats’ primary French contact was Under Secretary Pierre de
                    Margerie, although Garrett dealt directly with Delcassé for important
                        matters.<note n="102" xml:id="fn102">Nicholas Roosevelt, <hi rend="italic">A
                            Front Row Seat</hi>, (Norman, Okla.: University of Oklahoma Press,
                        1953), 70.</note> Garrett’s office was also inundated by requests asking for
                    help ascertaining information about missing French citizens in Germany and
                    Austria-Hungary, in addition to prisoner of war and internment camp visits.
                    Fortunately, help was on the way.</p>
                <p>Garrett’s brother Robert, a Baltimore-based businessman, searched for a young man
                    willing to go to Bordeaux and serve as John’s personal secretary. In October,
                    Robert selected a young man working towards his master’s degree in History at
                    Harvard who volunteered for the position and passed muster. The recruit,
                    Nicholas Roosevelt, cousin of Theodore Roosevelt, sailed on October 21 aboard
                    the <hi rend="italic">Mauretania</hi> for Liverpool and London, where he dined
                    with his fellow <hi rend="italic">Mauretania</hi> passenger Kathryn Page and her
                    father, U.S. Ambassador to the United Kingdom Walter Hines Page.<note n="103"
                        xml:id="fn103">According to Roosevelt, Page was “a large, gangling man with
                        a big nose, a pleasant voice, a simple and amiable manner, and an obviously
                        first-rate intelligence.” Ibid, 68.</note> Roosevelt then proceeded to
                    France and Bordeaux where he assumed his new position.</p>
                <p>Much of the French press also relocated to Bordeaux at the same time as the
                    Government of France and the diplomatic corps. Georges Clemenceau moved the
                    office of his newspaper <hi rend="italic">L’Homme Libre</hi> to the temporary
                    seat of government. The formidable editor and politician known as “The Tiger”
                    lived on the second floor of a small house in the Cours St. Jean, and gained
                    intelligence from U.S. diplomats as to what U.S. citizens said and thought about
                    the war.<note n="104" xml:id="fn104">Ibid, 70.</note> This was a topic that also
                    greatly interested the Government of France. Jusserand filed regular reports
                    from Washington as to the nature of U.S. public opinion of the war and, in
                    particular, its outlook on French and German participation. Roosevelt often saw
                    Clemenceau and observed that the elder man had vigor “such that it was hard to
                    believe that he was 73-years old.” The Tiger, Roosevelt noted, “poured his own
                    overflowing faith into his people.”<note n="105" xml:id="fn105">Ibid,
                    72.</note></p>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="writing-home">
                    <head>Writing Home</head>
                    <p>Despite the continuous press of work, U.S. diplomats and consuls in France
                        found time to write home and share eyewitness accounts once the immediate
                        danger and chaos subsided. From Bordeaux, Garrett wrote his brother Robert
                        in November about the difficulties of remaining in contact with loved ones
                        back home. “I am going to begin a letter to you,” he wrote, “but I have no
                        idea whether I shall be able to finish it or not, there are so many
                        interruptions every minute that I find it practically impossible to get time
                        enough for anything outside of the absolutely necessary.”<note n="106"
                            xml:id="fn106">Letter from John Work Garrett to Robert Garrett, November
                            21, 1914. (The Sheridan Libraries, The Johns Hopkins University, John
                            Work Garrett Papers GAR 19 Box 2.2, Folder 19 Robert Garrett).</note>
                        The diplomat asked his brother to send magazines, noting that “we are
                        entirely without them here and I long for them,” and also asked about the
                        score of that year’s Princeton-Harvard football game. “I hope we won,”
                        Garrett wrote, “if for no other reason than because all three of my
                        secretaries are Harvard men and I don’t want them to have an opportunity to
                        gloat over me.”<note n="107" xml:id="fn107">Ibid.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="war-work">
                    <head>War Work</head>
                    <p>Others began to settle into the new status quo that fall. The U.S. expatriate
                        community that remained in France expanded significantly upon initial
                        efforts such as the American Ambulance Hospital, to establish many war
                        relief charities and medical aid organizations to benefit the French (and
                        belligerent wounded in France). At the forefront were the female members of
                        the U.S. diplomatic community, whose sacrifices were at times enormous.</p>
                    <p>Carolyn Herrick led by example in her role as wife of the U.S. Ambassador.
                        She chaired the American Ambulance’s Women’s Committee, and raised
                        significant funds for it as well as for the American Relief Clearing House
                        after its November 1914 establishment. She died in 1918, and her husband
                        attributed her death to lingering effects of illness contracted during her
                        war relief work in France in 1914. In 1919 the French government decorated
                        Carolyn posthumously for her war relief efforts.</p>
                    <p>Mildred Barnes Bliss founded and served as Vice President of Enfants de la
                        Frontière, a French-American child welfare organization. She toured
                        battlefields and visited sanatoriums and refugee centers throughout France.
                        From her personal fortune, Bliss funded private hospitals and charities. She
                        received numerous decorations from the French government for her war relief
                        efforts. (See Appendix VI for a more detailed account)</p>
                    <p>Ellie Sherman Thackara founded the Servian (Serbian) Ambulance, run through
                        her residence in the Hôtel Belmont, and in October 1914 established the
                        Urgent Fund for Servian Wounded. Thackara was also active with the Red
                        Cross. Her July 1915 death was attributed by many to over-exertion from her
                        war work in Paris.</p>
                    <p>Eleanor Thackara, daughter of Ellie and Consul-General Alexander Thackara,
                        arrived in Paris in early December 1914 to volunteer her services for war
                        relief efforts. She took over some of her mother’s work with the Servian
                        Ambulance, and worked to raise funds for war widows, orphans, and injured as
                        well as for hospitals and ambulance services.</p>
                    <p>There were also the many contributions of Robert Bacon, who actively immersed
                        himself in war relief work from the moment he stepped foot on French soil in
                        early September 1914 until the conflict’s end in November 1918. Bacon’s
                        primary efforts were concentrated upon the American Ambulance Hospital, its
                        organization, fundraising efforts, and recruitment of U.S. doctors,
                        surgeons, and nurses for its staff. He funded other medical enterprises as
                        well, such as a hospital train to ferry wounded soldiers. Martha Bacon, his
                        wife, was deeply involved in raising funds for the American Ambulance from
                        the United States and called the couple’s personal networks into action on
                        behalf of this military hospital.</p>
                    <p>Bacon also helped found the fledging American Ambulance Field Service, the
                        predecessor of the American Field Service (AFS). Composed predominantly of
                        male university student volunteers from the United States, the American
                        Ambulance Field Service drove ambulances for the American Ambulance
                        Hospital. The young men paid their own way so as to not add further burden
                        to already strained French resources. Bacon vouched for his young
                        volunteers; a recommendation from Bacon quashed any French military
                        suspicions that the ambulance drivers who entered France on U.S. passports
                        were German spies.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="new-arrivals-new-obligations">
                    <head>New Arrivals, New Obligations…</head>
                    <p>While war relief efforts occupied the U.S. volunteer community in France,
                        U.S. diplomats found their already significant duties augmented with the
                        November 1914 entry of the Ottoman Empire into the war on the side of the
                        Central Powers. The Embassy took over representational duties for the
                        Turkish Ambassador as well as the responsibility to care for Ottoman
                        subjects in France. Fortunately for the United States, Ottoman subjects in
                        France were not as heavy a burden as Germans or Austro-Hungarians: the
                        Ottomans in France were typically hostile to the Sultan’s regime in
                        Constantinople and not interned by French authorities.</p>
                    <p>To help ease the continued need for Embassy staffing, the Department of State
                        appointed John Gardner Coolidge as Special Agent to U.S. Embassy Paris on
                        November 24. The nephew of Isabella Stewart Gardner, Coolidge, a veteran of
                        the Diplomatic Service who spoke French, sailed for France aboard the <hi
                            rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> on December 4.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="and-departures">
                    <head>…And Departures</head>
                    <p>By mid-November it was clear that the crisis of the war’s early weeks was
                        past and Sharp again agitated to take over control of the Embassy. On
                        November 17, he cabled the Department that, “If agreeable would very much
                        like to have change made here at an early date…Continuance of present
                        conditions only increases embarrassment of my position.”<note n="108"
                            xml:id="fn108">Telegram from Sharp (Paris) to Bryan (Washington DC),
                            November 17, 1914. (National Archives, RG 59 123 Sh21)</note></p>
                    <p>Not everyone agreed with Sharp. According to Coolidge, “it would have been
                        better, from every point of view, to have Mr. Herrick retained at his post
                        in this crisis.”<note n="109" xml:id="fn109">John Gardner Coolidge, <hi
                                rend="italic">A War Diary in Paris: 1914–1917</hi>, (Cambridge,
                            Mass.: Riverside Press, 1931), 7.</note> Herrick, however, acquiesced
                        and on November 28, nearly four months after their originally planned
                        departure, Myron and Carolyn Herrick left Paris for the United States. The
                        Herricks were fêted at the Gare des Invalides by a crowd of French officials
                        and U.S. expatriates as they waved farewell. Not everyone who wanted to
                        attend could make the send-off ceremony. Poincaré, for example, remained
                        with the Government of France in Bordeaux. Herrick, sad to not see the
                        French President again to personally say goodbye, wrote his friend, “be
                        certain that nothing between us will be forgotten.”<note n="110"
                            xml:id="fn110">Letter from Herrick to Poincaré, November 25, 1914.
                            (Ministry of Foreign Affairs Archives, Guerre 1914–1918 Etats-Unis, Vol.
                            490 Dossier Generale: Novembre-Decembre 1914)</note></p>
                    <p>Garrett was also unable to leave Bordeaux. Instead, he telegrammed Herrick
                        aboard the <hi rend="italic">Rochambeau,</hi> “good luck and bon
                            voyage.”<note n="111" xml:id="fn111">Telegram from John Work Garrett to
                            Myron T. Herrick, via the <hi rend="italic">Rochambeau</hi>, undated.
                            (The Sheridan Libraries, The Johns Hopkins University, John Work Garrett
                            Papers, GAR 19, Box 2.3, Folder Myron T. Herrick).</note> The friendship
                        between the two men continued throughout the war and beyond. Garrett later
                        wrote Herrick that “my wife and I often recur to your kindness to us during
                        the early days of the war, and we look forward to a time when it is over and
                        we shall be able to come home again and see you and Mrs. Herrick.”<note
                            n="112" xml:id="fn112">Letter from John Work Garrett to Myron T.
                            Herrick, May 24, 1917. (The Sheridan Libraries, The Johns Hopkins
                            University, John Work Garrett Papers, GAR 19 Box 2.3, Folder 34
                            Correspondence with Myron T. Herrick).</note> Herrick reciprocated the
                        sentiment. In February 1917, he wrote Garrett,</p>
                    <p>My mind goes back to those early days of the war, when you became my
                        ambassador to Bordeaux and thus gave the United States in effect two
                        ambassadors in France. I can now see from this side what you perhaps cannot
                        see there, that our group in Paris, composed of men like yourself, Bliss,
                        and Frazier, contributed something of great value in that difficult
                            time.<note n="113" xml:id="fn113">Letter from Myron T. Herrick to John
                            Work Garrett, February 21, 1917. The Sheridan Libraries, The Johns
                            Hopkins University, John Work Garrett Papers, GAR 19, Box 2.3, Folder
                            34, Correspondence with Myron T. Herrick).</note></p>
                    <p>There was a special bond formed by those at the Embassy in the first months
                        of the war that bound them together in subsequent years. Such ties did not
                        form between Sharp and the Embassy family, perhaps due to differences in
                        personal or professional conduct or perhaps because the conditions that
                        forged the closeness of this group that fall did not exist in the same way
                        afterward.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part" xml:id="new-normal">
                <head>December: Returning to the ‘New Normal’</head>
                <p>Sharp finally assumed control of the Embassy at 5, rue de Chaillot on November
                    28. On December 1, he and his son George boarded the night train to Bordeaux.
                    The Sharps arrived the following day and lodged with the Garretts. On December
                    3, Sharp met with Delcassé at the Foreign Office at 12:30pm, then lunched with
                    Delcassé and the British, Japanese, and Russian Ambassadors. The next day at
                    9am, Sharp, accompanied by Garrett, Sussdorff, Roosevelt, and Capt. Pope,
                    presented his credentials to Poincaré—and also Herrick’s letter of recall. The
                    newly accredited U.S. Ambassador to France then paid personal calls upon other
                    ambassador colleagues in Bordeaux (Britain, Russia, Japan), and left calling
                    cards for French officials and the Ministers of other countries present in the
                    makeshift seat of government.</p>
                <p>The brief time spent in Bordeaux with Poincaré and Delcassé, the first time that
                    Sharp met either statesman in person, deeply marked the new U.S. Ambassador.
                    “Your President impresses me as a strong and well-poised man, full of reserved
                    strength,” Sharp wrote Jusserand on December 12. “Monsieur Delcassé is not only
                    a statesman for whom I have the highest opinion, but, best of all, a man of
                        heart.”<note n="114" xml:id="fn114">Letter from William Graves Sharp to J.J.
                        Jusserand, December 12, 1914. (Ministry of Foreign Affairs Archives, Guerre
                        1914–1918 États-Unis, Novembre–Decembre, Vol. 490)</note></p>
                <p>A few days later, the Government of France returned to Paris. On December 9,
                    Garrett closed the U.S. diplomatic outpost in Bordeaux and on December 10,
                    relocated to Paris, where he continued as Special Agent attached to the Embassy
                    until his appointment as U.S. Minister to the Netherlands and Luxembourg in
                        1917.<note n="115" xml:id="fn115">The cost for the U.S. Mission at Bordeaux
                        from September 2 to December 9, 1914 was 9,554.61 francs, roughly $1,844.04
                        (or $43,951.04 in 2014 values). The largest expense was for rent (3,333.33
                        francs/$643.33) followed by costs for local transportation (3,080.25
                        francs/$594.49) and telegrams and cablegrams (994.75 francs/$191.99).
                        Contingent Expenses, Foreign Missions, Embassy Paris January 14, 1915. (The
                        Sheridan Libraries, The Johns Hopkins University, John Work Garrett Papers,
                        GAR 19 Box 3.5). Conversion rates obtained on August 13, 2014 via <ref
                            target="http://www.usinflationcalculator.com"
                            >www.usinflationcalculator.com</ref>.</note> Once in Paris, Garrett was
                    tasked with running the Embassy’s German and Austro-Hungarian affairs division.
                    This was no small matter; by mid-December it was estimated that roughly 15,000
                    German and Austro-Hungarian subjects remained interned within French
                        borders.<note n="116" xml:id="fn116">Bliss/Sharp (Paris) to Secretary of
                        State (Washington DC), December 17, 1914. (National Archives, RG 59
                        763.72115/330)</note> The Department thus assigned Percival Dodge to the
                    U.S. Embassy in Paris to share the burden with Garrett.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part" xml:id="neutrality-and-war">
                <head>Neutrality and War, 1915–1918</head>
                <p>The return of the government and the diplomatic corps to Paris conferred some
                    degree of normalcy—the ‘new normal’ in what increasingly looked like a prolonged
                    war. Rationing and food restrictions were more noticeable. There were fewer
                    numbers of courses served in hotel restaurants, and meatless days were added to
                    citizens’ food restrictions by the end of 1915.<note n="117" xml:id="fn117"
                        >Coolidge, 16.</note> The U.S. diplomatic community was not immune from the
                    privations of war. By May 1918, the Blisses relied upon sugar rations purchased
                    by their parents in the United States and shipped to them in France.<note
                        n="118" xml:id="fn118">The Bliss parents purchased four pounds of sugar, the
                        maximum they were able to purchase (the limit was two pounds per person),
                        and shipped the sweet treat to Robert and Mildred Bliss in Paris via
                        diplomatic pouch. Letter from William Henry Bliss to Robert Woods Bliss, May
                        29, 1918. (Harvard University Archives, Cambridge, Massachusetts, Papers of
                        Robert Woods Bliss and Mildred Barnes Bliss, HUGFP 76.8 Box 5 MBB
                        Correspondence with ABB and WHB, 1916–1919; 1927).</note> The increased
                    pressure on foodstuffs and basic resources such as fuel translated into tighter
                    border restrictions for goods—and people. Foreign women as of 1915 were only
                    welcome in France if they did nursing or charity work. Otherwise their presence
                    was viewed as a burden on already strained resources.</p>
                <p>Further aspects of daily life changed. Prices increased. By December 1915, the
                    U.S. Consul at St. Étienne asked the Department for an increase in salary as,
                    “it has been found simply impossible to live on the salaries at present
                    allowed…because of the tremendous increase in the cost of all staple
                    commodities, fuel, and clothing.”<note n="119" xml:id="fn119">Letter from
                        William H. Hunt to Secretary of State William Jennings Bryan, December 1915.
                        (National Archives, RG 59 123 H 911)</note> Clothing became more expensive
                    at the same time that dress regulations and ‘norms’ also transformed to better
                    conform to the new realities of life during war. Men’s evening dress, for
                    example, was replaced with dinner coats or uniforms.</p>
                <p>Still, some ‘normal’ traditions continued, such as the French President’s
                    customary New Year’s Day reception for the diplomatic corps. On the afternoon of
                    January 1, 1915, Poincaré hosted approximately 200 diplomats at the Elysée
                        Palace.<note n="120" xml:id="fn120">Coolidge, 21.</note> Roosevelt, freshly
                    back from Bordeaux, attended and observed not only the full dress uniforms of
                    diplomatic representatives but the appearance of various French officials.
                    According to Roosevelt, Delcassé looked “as beaver-like as ever,” Renée Viviani
                    was “tall and unpleasant-looking,” while Aristide Briand appeared “partly fierce
                    and partly bored.”<note n="121" xml:id="fn121">Roosevelt, 73.</note></p>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="embassy-work-continues">
                    <head>Embassy Work Continues</head>
                    <p>As representatives of a neutral power, U.S. diplomats and consuls in France
                        continued to promote U.S. interests. They protected the rights of U.S.
                        business, transportation, and telecommunications entities. There were also
                        other issues that the Embassy contended with, such as restrictions on
                        exportation of rice from French Indochina to the U.S.-held Philippines.</p>
                    <p>There also remained, until 1917, the U.S. responsibility to represent
                        Austro-Hungarian and German interests to the Government of France. Numerous
                        complaints of abuse against German and Austro-Hungarian prisoners of war
                        that required investigation remained one of the Embassy’s more difficult
                        jobs. Originally, the Department forbade Sharp from visiting the POW or
                        civilian internment camps, but in early 1915 Sharp protested his orders as
                        they hindered his ability to fully perform his duties. The Department
                        acquiesced, and Sharp organized teams from the Embassy to visit camps
                        throughout France. He often took George with him on such visits. That April,
                        they toured camps at Chartres, Le Mans, Tours, Poitiers, Chateauroux,
                        Issoudun, Orléans, and Paris.<note n="122" xml:id="fn122">Pennant,
                            32.</note> When Garrett or Dodge visited the camps, often accompanied by
                        Roosevelt, they invited the local French officials for a meal or drink.<note
                            n="123" xml:id="fn123">Roosevelt, 76.</note> In an unusual twist, U.S.
                        diplomats were occasionally in a position to aid old friends. In one such
                        instance in August 1916, Garrett and Bliss argued that Embassy personnel in
                        Germany visit the son of Delcassé, a prisoner of war in Germany, as a nice
                        gesture to the former Foreign Minister.<note n="124" xml:id="fn124">Letter
                            from Robert Woods Bliss to John Work Garrett, August 11, 1916. (The
                            Sheridan Libraries, The Johns Hopkins University, John Work Garrett
                            Papers, GAR 19 Box 2.1 Folder Robert Woods Bliss).</note></p>
                    <p>In general, relations between U.S. diplomats and their French interlocutors
                        ranged from close to friendly to, in the rare instance, disdain. Jusserand,
                        for example, the great statesman who prided himself on his close
                        relationship with U.S. citizens and understanding of the United States,
                        never fully warmed up to Sharp. Following Wilson’s November 1916 reelection,
                        Jusserand reminded the Ministry of Foreign Affairs that U.S. tradition was
                        to replace Ambassadors following each presidential election. Surely, the
                        replacement of Jusserand’s friend Herrick by Sharp in 1914 and the
                        controversy that surrounded it was at the forefront of the French diplomat’s
                        mind. “Many diplomats named to South America by Mr. Bryan will be replaced,”
                        Jusserand reminded his colleagues in 1916. “Only one Ambassador in Europe
                        has the chance to be replaced, Mr. Sharp, who is judged soft and not
                            active.”<note n="125" xml:id="fn125">Letter from Jusserand to Ministry
                            of Foreign Affairs, November 19, 1916. (Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                            Archives, Etats-Unis 1914–1918, Vol. 503 Octobre–Novembre 1916)</note>
                        If Sharp was not as highly regarded as his predecessors, perhaps because he
                        observed U.S. neutrality more strictly, other U.S. officials in France
                        helped to compensate.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="in-st-etienne">
                    <head>In St. Étienne</head>
                    <p>The German Army’s occupation of northern France, the heart of French industry
                        and mining, forced the migration of these industries to the Department of
                        the Loire by 1915. For Hunt, in the Loire’s major city of St. Étienne, this
                        translated into a significantly increased workload as well as more attention
                        from authorities in Paris, New York, Washington, and beyond. While not the
                        first African-American consul to serve in France, at the time of the war’s
                        outbreak in August 1914, Hunt was the only one in France and likely all of
                        Europe. Yet, there is little reference to his skin color in French
                        government archives from this period; U.S. Department of State records
                        include a small “colored” designation next to Hunt’s name on the official
                        Consular Service card for St. Étienne.</p>
                    <p>One of Hunt’s good friends was General Joseph Gallieni, a relationship first
                        formed in the early 1900s when both men were stationed in Madagascar.
                        Throughout the first months of war in 1914, Hunt traveled frequently to
                        Paris to confer with Herrick and, as Hunt’s biographer Adele Logan Alexander
                        alludes, to visit Gallieni.<note n="126" xml:id="fn126">Adele Logan
                            Alexander, <hi rend="italic">Parallel Worlds: The Remarkable Gibbs-Hunts
                                and the Enduring (In)Significance of Melanin</hi>, (Charlottesville:
                            University of Virginia Press, 2010), 159.</note> It is unknown whether
                        Hunt frequented Paris as often once the Embassy was under the control of
                        Sharp and Gallieni departed for the front.</p>
                    <p>Throughout the Loire, Hunt replicated the work of his colleagues at U.S.
                        Embassy Paris in caretaking of German and Austro-Hungarian subjects. Yet,
                        the Consul began to bypass the Department before taking action, and
                        increasingly served the French citizens in his consular district in
                        obtaining information about their captured loved ones in Germany and
                        Austria-Hungary. Hunt believed that “my name was familiar in all the German
                        prison camps where French soldiers were interned.”<note n="127"
                            xml:id="fn127">Alexander, 166.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="life-in-wartime-paris">
                    <head>Life In Wartime Paris</head>
                    <p>In the smaller city of St. Étienne, Hunt was active in the local community.
                        He was the long-serving president of the rugby club, and presided over
                        events that raised funds for French war relief efforts. Hunt was perhaps
                        more deeply embedded into local French society in St. Étienne than his
                        counterparts in Paris. There, in the capital, the U.S. diplomatic community
                        was much larger and created networks, friendships, and social activities
                        that bound its members together. It also included the sizable U.S.
                        expatriate community.</p>
                    <p>Senior diplomats, such as the Garretts, Blisses, and Sharps, regularly
                        included junior Embassy officials in their social plans and often invited
                        them to meals and cocktail parties, as the Herricks did during their
                            tenure.<note n="128" xml:id="fn128">Roosevelt, 73.</note> Alice Garrett,
                        an expert of the arts, offered entrée to young Embassy attachés into the
                        rarified Parisian world of artists, writers, and musicians. She invited
                        Roosevelt and the Embassy’s other young secretaries to the Garrett residence
                        at the Hôtel Ritz for salons as well as for her weekly Sunday morning
                        gymnastics classes, taught by a “middle-aged ex-dancer.”<note n="129"
                            xml:id="fn129">Roosevelt, 79.</note></p>
                    <p>The personal life of others associated with the U.S. diplomatic community
                        continued to develop despite the war. Sharp’s family sailed aboard the <hi
                            rend="italic">Patria</hi> on March 25, 1915, and docked at Marseille in
                        early April.<note n="130" xml:id="fn130">Telegram from Sharp (Paris) to
                            Bryan (Washington DC), April 13, 1915. (National Archives, RG 59 123
                            Sh21)</note> George Sharp, who originally accompanied his father to
                        France with plans to return after a year to the United States for
                        university, pursued a different path once in Europe. In the fall of 1914,
                        the younger Sharp joined a local pension in Paris as a daytime guest so that
                        he could work on his French language skills.<note n="131" xml:id="fn131"
                            >Pennant, 33.</note> By Spring 1915, his language abilities were much
                        improved, and he started to serve as his father’s private secretary. That
                        fall, George deferred entrance to Oberlin College and instead enrolled in
                        classes at the Sorbonne, which he attended twice a week from 8:30am until
                            5pm.<note n="132" xml:id="fn132">Pennant, 19, 34.</note> Sharp
                        eventually graduated from the École des Sciences Politiqueswith high
                        honors.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="embassy-at-war">
                    <head>Embassy At War</head>
                    <p>The work of the Embassy increased with the U.S. entry into the conflict in
                        April 1917. Bliss wrote his father on June 15, 1917, that despite the
                        augmented workload, “I revel in it all and am keeping remarkably fit.”<note
                            n="133" xml:id="fn133">Letter from Robert Woods Bliss to William Henry
                            Bliss, June 15, 1917. (Harvard University Archives, Cambridge,
                            Massachusetts, Papers of Robert Woods Bliss and Mildred Barnes Bliss,
                            HUGFP 76.8 Box 5. WHB to MBB and RWB, 1913; 1917).</note> The diplomat
                        noted that due to the valuable experience he gained and professional
                        development on offer, “I would not exchange any other post for Paris.”<note
                            n="134" xml:id="fn134">Letter from Robert Woods Bliss to William Henry
                            Bliss, June 15, 1917. (Harvard University Archives, Cambridge,
                            Massachusetts, Papers of Robert Woods Bliss and Mildred Barnes Bliss,
                            HUGFP 76.8 Box 5. WHB to MBB and RWB, 1913; 1917).</note> As U.S.
                        involvement in the war grew, the Department sent an influx of diplomats to
                        the Embassy to help out. The convergence of the peace-makers upon Paris
                        beginning in December 1918 and lasting into 1920 continued this trend.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part" xml:id="conclusions">
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>The activities of U.S. Embassy personnel in 1914 signaled the arrival of the
                    United States as a major player in the diplomatic and humanitarian realms as
                    American officials and private citizens assumed an impressive array of duties at
                    a time of unprecedented distress. Thus throughout autumn 1914, while other
                    Embassies and Legations were dark, the U.S. Embassy was a beehive of activity on
                    multiple fronts. In addition to diplomatic duties, the unofficial roles of U.S.
                    diplomats expanded exponentially as the war continued. The Embassy was a nucleus
                    of partnerships that provided for financial relief and medical aid to those in
                    France impacted by the war. Assisted by a corps of U.S. citizens who volunteered
                    their time, energy, and funds, U.S. diplomats and Consuls developed new
                    relationships with each other, the Government of France, and the French public.
                    Their actions shaped public memory of the Franco-American partnership in 1914, a
                    solid foundation that helped further form the sense of a special French-American
                        <hi rend="italic">amité</hi>, onethat endured despite the trials of
                    subsequent decades.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">Dr. Lindsay Sarah Krasnoff</hi>
                        <lb/>Office of the Historian <lb/>U.S. Department of State <lb/>September
                        15, 2014 </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="part" xml:id="appendix-1">
                <head>Appendix I: Biographies</head>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="robert-bacon">
                    <head>Robert Bacon (1860–1919)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Former U.S. Ambassador to France, 1909–1912; Former U.S.
                            Secretary of State, 1909</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p><ref target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/bacon-robert"
                            >Robert Bacon</ref> was born in Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts, in 1860 to
                        a prominent merchant family. He attended Harvard, where he befriended future
                        President Theodore Roosevelt, and graduated in 1880. Bacon spent a year
                        travelling the world and then returned to Boston to begin a successful
                        career in business. In 1905, he became Assistant Secretary of State at the
                        behest of his friend President Roosevelt. In 1909, he was asked to serve as
                        Secretary of State for the duration of the Roosevelt administration after
                        Secretary of State Elihu Root resigned. Bacon served 37 days as Secretary of
                        State until March 5, 1909, when President Theodore Roosevelt left office.
                        From December 1909 until April 1912, Bacon served as U.S. Ambassador to
                        France, winning great fame and endearment from Parisians for his assistance
                        during the 1910 flood of the Seine.</p>
                    <p>After war broke out in August 1914, Bacon was eager to provide assistance. He
                        sailed for France on August 26 aboard the <hi rend="italic">La France</hi>,
                        and arrived in Paris during the early hours of September 3 where he
                        proceeded to his apartment at the Hôtel de Crillon, his base of French
                        operations intermittently for the next several years. As one of Bacon’s
                        first acts, he located un-requisitioned automobiles to serve as makeshift
                        ambulances. He worked in close conjunction with French military authorities
                        to ferry wounded soldiers from the front to the hospitals in Paris, and
                        occasionally served as driver.</p>
                    <p>Bacon greatly augmented his legacy—and that of the United States—in French
                        memory during the war years. He dedicated himself to raising money for the
                        American Ambulance Hospital of Paris, his pet project, and recruited the
                        first group of U.S. doctors (from Harvard) to serve in the hospital. At
                        several points during the war, Bacon traveled between France and the United
                        States, and following the U.S. entry into war in April 1917, joined the U.S.
                        Army. He returned to France under General Pershing’s command, and received
                        several medals from the French government after the war for his endeavors,
                        such as the Croix de Guerre. In March 1919, Bacon left Paris for New York in
                        order to undergo surgery on his neck for mastoiditis, contracted while ill
                        with influenza. Unfortunately, Bacon developed blood poisoning as a result
                        of the operation, and died that May.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter" xml:id="william-bardel">
                    <head>William Bardel (1846–1926)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Consul at Reims (Rheims).</hi></p>
                    <p>William Bardel was born in Germany on September 20, 1846. Little is known
                        about his early years, but he attended State Commercial College in
                        Nuremberg, Germany. Bardel moved to the United States, settled in New York,
                        and worked in the jewelry wholesale business. On October 22, 1872, Bardel
                        became a naturalized U.S. citizen. In December 1900, he passed the Consular
                        Service examination and was appointed Commercial Agent at Bamberg, Bavaria
                        (Germany). On December 16, 1902, Bardel was elevated to Consul, and was
                        assigned to Reims, France, in 1908. Bardel asked the Department of State for
                        a transfer to a station in Germany in April 1914, but was still in France
                        when war broke out that August.</p>
                    <p>Reims lay in the path of the German Army, which entered the city September 4
                        and occupied it until September 17. Once the French Army re-took Reims, the
                        Germans began to bombard the city, including its famed cathedral. Bardel,
                        his wife, and two of their children took shelter in a wine cellar a half
                        block away from their house, and the Bardel residence took a direct hit from
                        a shell, which destroyed half of the building. Ambassador Myron T. Herrick
                        and the Department of State were deeply concerned for the welfare of Bardel.
                        U.S. war correspondent Richard Harding Davis was in Reims on September 19 to
                        cover the story and failed to locate Bardel. Finally, a few days later, the
                        Bardels were reported safe, though alarmingly low on funds. In October
                        Bardel was reposted to the relative safety of Épernay and then to
                        Troyes.</p>
                    <p>Bardel was posted to St. Michael’s on October 7, 1915, where he remained
                        until his next consular posting, to Nueva Gerona, Cuba, on June 15, 1918.
                        Bardel retired in 1920 and returned to the United States. He died at his
                        home in Brooklyn, New York, on December 31, 1926.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>Mildred Barnes Bliss (1880–1969)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wife of Robert Woods Bliss.</hi></p>
                    <p>Mildred Barnes was born in 1880 in New York, the daughter of Demas Barnes and
                        Anna Dorinda Blaksley, and heiress to the Castoria patent medicine fortune.
                        As a young woman, Barnes attended Miss Porter’s School then continued her
                        education at private schools in Paris. In 1908, she married Robert Woods
                        Bliss, thus embarking upon the life of a diplomat’s wife. At the time, this
                        consisted of frequent moves from one posting to another around the world.
                        The couple was sent to Latin America in 1909, and in 1912 to Paris, where
                        they remained for the next eight years.</p>
                    <p>During the Great War, Bliss was known for her fundraising efforts and medical
                        aid in France. She donated enormous sums of money to the American Ambulance
                        Hospital in Neuilly, helped maintain the American Distributing Service,
                        which delivered medical supplies to French hospitals, and funded other
                        programs to provide medical relief, such as hospitals and ambulances. Bliss
                        founded and served as the Vice President of Enfants de la Frontière, a
                        French-American child welfare organization, in addition to participating in
                        many other war relief efforts. Strikingly, she was not a passive supporter;
                        Bliss was highly active. She toured battlefields and visited sanatoriums and
                        refugee centers throughout France, despite the at-times dangerous
                        conditions. The French government conferred several awards upon Bliss in
                        recognition of her work.</p>
                    <p>The Blisses returned to Washington, D.C., in 1920, and purchased a house at R
                        Street and 32nd Street NW, which came to be known as Dumbarton Oaks. In
                        1940, the couple donated it to serve as a specialized research and art
                        center for Byzantine and Medieval learning. Dumbarton Oaks hosted the 1944
                        international conference which discussed creation of an international
                        organization that would replace the League of Nations.</p>
                    <p>Bliss was known for her decades-long philanthropy. She died in her home in
                        January 1969 at age 89.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head> Robert Woods Bliss (1875–1962)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">First Secretary, U.S. Embassy Paris, 1912–1916; Embassy
                            Counselor, 1916–1920.</hi></p>
                    <p><ref
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/bliss-robert-woods"
                            >Robert Woods Bliss</ref> was born on August 5, 1875, in St. Louis,
                        Missouri. He graduated from Harvard University in 1900 and then spent
                        several years working in Puerto Rico. In June 1903, Bliss passed the
                        Department of State qualifying examination, and entered the Diplomatic
                        Service. He was appointed Consul at Venice on June 18, 1903, then held
                        several posts throughout Europe. In April 1908, he married Mildred Barnes,
                        his close companion for the next several decades. They did not have
                        children. On August 4, 1909, Bliss received his first assignment in Latin
                        America as Secretary of the Legation at Buenos Aires. While in Argentina,
                        the Blisses met and developed a close personal friendship and professional
                        relationship with U.S. Minister John Work Garret and his wife, Alice. In
                        February 1912, Bliss was appointed Secretary of the Embassy at Paris, a post
                        he held for the next several years.</p>
                    <p>Bliss was at the Quai d’Orsay on the afternoon of July 28, 1914, and thus
                        learned first-hand that Austria-Hungary declared war on Serbia that day. He
                        quickly returned to the Embassy and conveyed the news to Ambassador Myron T.
                        Herrick and his guests (U.S. businessmen and French officials). From that
                        point through November, Bliss helped Herrick navigate the Embassy from one
                        war crisis to another; fed, lodged, and evacuated U.S. citizens from France;
                        served as protective power for many nations; and protected U.S. interests as
                        a neutral nation. Bliss continued these duties after Ambassador William
                        Graves Sharp assumed control of the Embassy that December.</p>
                    <p>From 1916 until 1920, Bliss served as Counselor of the Embassy, though he was
                        temporarily assigned to the U.S. Legation at The Hague in 1918 to serve as
                        chargé d’affaires. In 1920 Bliss returned to Washington and served in a
                        succession of increasingly senior positions within the Department of State.
                        He was appointed U.S. Minister to Sweden in 1923, and U.S. Ambassador to
                        Argentina in 1927 before retiring from diplomatic service in July 1933.
                        Bliss returned to duty as a special assistant to Secretary of State Cordell
                        Hull during World War II, but retired again in November 1945. Both Blisses
                        were known for their philanthropic efforts. Robert Bliss died in 1962 at age
                        87.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>Spencer Cosby (1867–1962)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Military Attaché, U.S. Embassy Paris.</hi></p>
                    <p>Spencer Cosby was born on October 2, 1867, in Maryland. He was appointed a
                        cadet in the U.S. Military Academy in June 1887, and received several
                        promotions through the service while honing his engineering skills. Cosby
                        was honorably discharged on December 31, 1898, at the rank of major. In
                        March 1909, President William Howard Taft appointed him, at the rank of
                        colonel, in charge of public buildings and grounds in the District of
                        Columbia. That September, he married Yvonne Shepard in Southampton, Long
                        Island. As part of his new responsibilities, Cosby managed the design and
                        construction of new White House executive offices, including what ultimately
                        became the Oval Office. In 1912, he supervised the planting of Japanese
                        cherry trees in the U.S. capital, and on August 7, 1913, Cosby was assigned
                        duty as the Military Attaché at U.S. Embassy Paris.</p>
                    <p>After war broke out in August 1914, Cosby visited battlefields, wrote
                        reports, and transmitted his observations to the War Department in
                        Washington, D.C. In addition to his engineering background, Cosby was an
                        aeronautics expert, and thus closely observed the nascent French air corps.
                        Another of Cosby’s responsibilities that August was to help guard and
                        distribute the gold sent by the U.S. Government to help U.S. citizens
                        stranded in France. In late September, Cosby risked the trip from Paris to
                        Reims in order to bring money—desperately needed—to U.S. Consul William
                        Bardel, a survivor of the German bombardment of that city.</p>
                    <p>Cosby remained at his post in Paris until the United States entered the war
                        in April 1917, at which time he returned to the United States to help train
                        engineer regiments for wartime service. Once the war ended, Cosby held a
                        series of diplomatic and military positions prior to retiring in 1928. He
                        died in his Washington, D.C. house on March 26, 1962, at age 94, and is
                        buried in Arlington National Cemetery.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>Arthur Hugh Frazier (1888–1963)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Second Secretary, U.S. Embassy Paris.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p><ref
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/frazier-arthur-hugh"
                            >Arthur Hugh Frazier</ref> was born on August 12, 1868, in Heidelberg,
                        Germany, to U.S. citizens. Educated by private tutors, he graduated from
                        Lehigh University in 1889. From 1889 until 1891, Frazer studied at the
                        University of Halle, at the Royal College of Viticulture, Geisenheim, and at
                        Fresimus Chemical Laboratory. He put some of this learning into practice
                        with his 1892 purchase of a California vineyard, later sold in 1898. Frazier
                        was a volunteer in the U.S. Army Signal Corps in 1898, then worked for
                        several years in Puerto Rico. In May 1907, Frazier passed the Department of
                        State qualifying exam, and received his first appointment as Secretary of
                        the Legation and Consul-General at San Salvador on August 5, 1908. After
                        postings in Bogotá, Vienna, and Rome, Frazier was appointed as Second
                        Secretary at U.S. Embassy Paris on February 11, 1914.</p>
                    <p>That August, Frazier was one of Ambassador Myron T. Herrick’s “first
                        responders” in Paris. He sprung to action as the Embassy’s workload quickly
                        multiplied and they became responsible for maintaining the German Embassy.
                        Frazier remained attached to the Embassy in Paris through most of the war,
                        rising to First Secretary and then Embassy Counselor by June 1918.</p>
                    <p>In January 1918, Frazier was designated by the Department of State to attend
                        the supreme war council as a diplomatic representative of the United States
                        and report on its proceedings until the permanent U.S. delegates could
                        arrive. After the war, Frazier continued his career in the Diplomatic
                        Service. In 1921, he served as chargé d’affaires pro tempore in Vienna, the
                        first U.S. diplomatic representative there since the December 1917 severance
                        of relations between the two countries. Frazier later settled in Westport,
                        Connecticut, and passed away in 1963.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>John Work Garrett (1872–1942)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Special Agent of the Department of State to Assist the
                            American Ambassador at Paris, 1914–1917.</hi></p>
                    <p><ref
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/garrett-john-work"
                            >John Work Garrett</ref> was born in Baltimore, Maryland, on May 19,
                        1872. He graduated from Princeton University in 1895 and worked in banking
                        before embarking upon a career as a diplomat. Garrett was appointed
                        Secretary of the Legation at The Hague on April 26, 1901 and served at
                        various European posts over the following decade. In 1905, Garrett met Alice
                        Warder, a noted authority on modern painting, while posted to Embassy Berlin
                        as Second Secretary. The couple married in 1908 and maintained a vigorous
                        correspondence for the next several decades. On December 15, 1910, Garrett
                        was appointed U.S. Minister to Venezuela, and on December 14, 1911, U.S.
                        Minister to Argentina.</p>
                    <p>When war broke out in August 1914, Alice was in Switzerland while John
                        remained in the United States. On August 6, Garrett was named Special Agent
                        of the Department of State to Assist the American Ambassador at Paris, and
                        on August 7 he sailed for Europe aboard the North Carolina. Upon arrival in
                        France, Garrett was promptly dispatched to Switzerland to evacuate U.S.
                        citizens from a continent that quickly descended into war. Subsequently,
                        Ambassador Myron T. Herrick sent Garrett to Bordeaux on September 2 as the
                        official U.S. Representative to the Government of France in that city. For
                        the next three months Garrett represented U.S. concerns as well as those of
                        other belligerent countries the United States agreed to act for. This
                        included Germany, Austria-Hungary, and the Ottoman Empire. He visited
                        detention camps, and maintained constant communication with the U.S. Embassy
                        in Paris. Garrett returned to the capital that December along with the
                        Government of France. For the next several years his portfolio consisted of
                        German and Austro-Hungarian issues, notably the care and treatment of enemy
                        nationals in POW and internee camps.</p>
                    <p>In August 1917, Garrett was appointed U.S. Minister to the Netherlands and
                        Luxembourg, resident at The Hague, returning to the post where he began his
                        diplomatic career in 1901. During the post-war years, Garrett remained
                        active in the diplomatic community and returned to Europe yet again as U.S.
                        Ambassador to Italy from 1929 until 1933. He maintained a warm friendship
                        with the Blisses, who he and Alice first served with in Latin America during
                        the pre-war years, as well as with Herrick. Garrett died at his home in
                        Baltimore on June 26, 1942, at age 70.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>Carolyn “Kitty” Parmely Herrick (1858–1918)</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Wife of Myron T. Herrick.</hi></p>
                    <p>Carolyn “Kitty” Melville Parmely was born in 1858 and grew up in Dayton,
                        Ohio. Little is known about her earliest years. On June 30, 1880, she
                        married Myron T. Herrick, a banker, businessman, and lawyer in Cleveland,
                        Ohio, and gave birth to their only son, Parmely Webb Herrick in 1881.</p>
                    <p>Kitty accompanied her husband to France in 1912, and became a regular fixture
                        within the U.S. expatriate community in Paris, known for her Thursday
                        afternoon tea receptions. By the summer of 1914, she, Myron, and their dog
                        Billy looked forward to sailing for home on August 8. Kitty oversaw the
                        packing of the Herrick belongings and dismantling of the Ambassador’s
                        residence at 5, rue François Ièr (the mansion’s lease was expensive and not
                        set to be renewed by in-coming Ambassador <ref
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/sharp-william-graves"
                            >William Graves Sharp</ref>). And then war broke out.</p>
                    <p>In early August, Kitty quickly inserted herself in efforts to fund the newly
                        established American Ambulance Hospital in Paris and the American Relief
                        Clearing House. Her labors were reportedly tireless, and both she and Myron
                        fell ill from overwork. Parisians called her “The American Angel” for her
                        war relief and Red Cross work. Upon her return to the United States that
                        December, Kitty continued fundraising for the two organizations in Paris,
                        and also served in several other prominent women’s clubs, including the
                        YWCA.</p>
                    <p>In August 1918, Kitty and Myron vacationed at the Tallyrand Cottage in Bar
                        Harbor, Maine, where she died on September 15. Myron attributed her death to
                        the lingering impact of her wartime illness, derived from the strains of her
                        many duties and activities in Paris 1914. The Government of France awarded
                        Kitty a posthumous “medal of French gratitude” in August 1919 for her work
                        with the American Ambulance Hospital in Paris and contributions throughout
                        the war.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>Myron T. Herrick (1854–1929)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Ambassador to France, 1912–1914.</hi></p>
                    <p><ref
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/herrick-myron-timothy"
                            >Myron T. Herrick</ref> was born in Huntington, Ohio, on October 9,
                        1854, to Timothy R. and Mary Herrick. Raised in humble circumstances,
                        Herrick attended Oberlin College and Ohio Wesleyan University and also
                        served as a school teacher and journalist before enrolling in law school.
                        After being admitted to the Ohio bar in 1878, Herrick established a law firm
                        in Cleveland and eventually expanded his interests to business and banking.
                        Herrick ran for and served as Republican Governor of Ohio from 1904 until
                        1906. By the time President William Howard Taft nominated him as U.S.
                        Ambassador to France in February 1912, Herrick had amassed a personal
                        fortune and was prominent in the national Republican Party.</p>
                    <p>Herrick and his wife, Carolyn (nicknamed “Kitty”), arrived in Paris that
                        April, and settled into a mansion at 5, rue François Ier, which served as
                        their residence. He charmed the French and forged strong personal
                        friendships with many during his years in Paris, such as with President
                        Raymond Poincaré., These ties grew in intensity and importance when war
                        broke out in 1914.</p>
                    <p>On June 2, 1914, Herrick learned that he would finally be relieved by his
                        successor, <ref
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/sharp-william-graves"
                            >William Graves Sharp</ref>, later that summer. As was (and remains)
                        custom, sitting U.S. ambassadors submit their letters of resignation when
                        new Presidents are elected. When Woodrow Wilson took office in 1913, Herrick
                        submitted his letter of resignation; however, Sharp was not nominated until
                        June 1914 and did not immediately sail for France. That summer, Herrick
                        began his farewell rounds in Paris. On August 1, however, Secretary of State
                            <ref
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/bryan-william-jennings"
                            >William Jennings Bryan</ref> cabled Herrick, and asked that he remain
                        in place for the time being because of the increasingly critical situation
                        in Europe. Tensions mounted over the next several days as France went to war
                        against Germany and Austria-Hungary.</p>
                    <p>Herrick’s tasks—and those of the U.S. Embassy in Paris—multiplied
                        exponentially as they provided for and evacuated stranded U.S. citizens from
                        France and Switzerland. The Herricks opened their home and fed those who had
                        nothing, funded in those early days from their own fortune. Both became ill
                        from overwork, but soon returned to putting in twelve- and fourteen-hour
                        days alongside Embassy employees and volunteers to contend with the crowds.
                        Herrick also assumed diplomatic custodianship of German and Austro-Hungarian
                        interests in August 1914, and, following the departure of the Government of
                        France for Bordeaux on September 2, responsibility for other belligerent
                        interests, including those of the United Kingdom, Japan, and Serbia.</p>
                    <p>By November the height of the crisis passed, and arrangements were made for
                        Sharp to assume control of U.S. diplomatic interests and responsibilities in
                        France in early December. Thus, on November 28, Herrick and Kitty left
                        France and sailed aboard the Rochambeau for New York harbor. Back in the
                        United States, both Herricks worked tirelessly to raise money for the
                        American Ambulance Hospital in Paris and the American Relief Clearing House
                        so that these organizations could continue to provide financial and medical
                        relief.</p>
                    <p>Herrick’s efforts and actions in the war’s first months endeared him further
                        to France and reinforced his love for the country. Appointed to serve as
                        U.S. Ambassador to France a second time in 1921, Herrick reveled in his
                        return to France. In late March 1929, he caught a cold while walking in the
                        funeral procession of his friend, Maréchal Ferdinand Foch. A few days later
                        on March 31, the cold proved fatal and Myron T. Herrick, “Friend of France,”
                        died at No. 2, avenue d’Iéna.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>William Henry Hunt (1863–1951)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Consul at St. Étienne, 1906–1927.</hi></p>
                    <p>William H. Hunt was born on June 29, 1863, in Hunt’s Station, Tennessee. He
                        was raised by his mother, an African American; his father remained unknown,
                        but as Hunt had such a light complexion, it was assumed his father was
                        Caucasian. Hunt attended Lawrence Academy on a scholarship, the only African
                        American student enrolled at the prestigious preparatory school at that time
                        (though not the first to attend). He then enrolled at Williams College,
                        where he also received a scholarship. Hunt was introduced to Ida Gibbs,
                        daughter of Mifflin Wistar Gibbs, in 1889. When in 1897 Mifflin Gibbs was
                        appointed by President William McKinley to serve as Consul at Madagascar,
                        part of the French Empire, Hunt was selected to serve as the Consul’s clerk.
                        He worked his way up the consular hierarchy at Tamatave, assigned as Vice
                        Consul in May 1899, and named Consul on August 23, 1901, after Gibbs
                        returned to the United States for health reasons. In 1904, Hunt married Ida,
                        who divided her time between Madagascar and the United States. Hunt learned
                        as much as he could about the exotic locale. Between 1901 and 1904, he
                        authored several articles about life in Madagascar for the American
                        Geographical Society. Hunt also developed a close friendship with the
                        island’s governor, General Joseph Gallieni. In November 1906, Hunt was
                        reassigned to St. Étienne, France, and arrived at the Consulate at 5, Place
                        de l’Hotel de Ville in January 1907.</p>
                    <p>St. Étienne, located in the Loire valley, became a main hub of French
                        industrial production after the northern part of the country—traditionally
                        the heart of mining and manufacturing—was occupied by the German Army in
                        Fall 1914. Hunt’s duties quickly increased. He frequently traveled to Paris
                        to consult with Ambassador Myron T. Herrick. Hunt visited and inspected
                        internment camps and prisoner of war camps located within his consular
                        region, represented the interests of Germans and Austro-Hungarians interned
                        in his district, and protected and helped evacuate U.S. citizens. His wife,
                        Ida, traveled between France and the United States throughout the war years,
                        volunteering her time and services to the Croix Rouge.</p>
                    <p>Throughout the 1920s, Hunt was an active member of the St. Étienne community,
                        and served as president of the local rugby club. In 1927 he was reassigned
                        to Guadeloupe. He died in 1951.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>DeWitt Clinton Poole Jr. (1885–1952).</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Vice Consul at Paris, 1914–1915.</hi></p>
                    <p>DeWitt Clinton Poole Jr. was born in Vancouver Barracks, Washington, in 1885,
                        and grew up in what he later termed “genteel poverty.” His father was in the
                        military, so the Pooles moved often during DeWitt’s childhood. As a young
                        child, he was sent to France for a year to attend school. In 1906 Poole
                        received his bachelor’s degree from the University of Wisconsin, and in 1910
                        his Master of Diplomacy degree from The George Washington University. Poole
                        entered the Consular Service in 1910 and was sent to Berlin for his first
                        posting from 1911 until 1914. There he met and developed a close friendship
                        with the Consul General, Alexander Montgomery Thackara, and his family.
                        Poole was transferred to Paris to serve as Vice Consul under Thackara and
                        arrived in the French capital in mid-June 1914.</p>
                    <p>Poole was on home leave in the United States to visit his father when war
                        broke out in early August. He rushed to Washington D.C., where he was
                        instructed to sail for France by way of Boston aboard the USS North Carolina
                        on August 5. Once in Paris, Poole jumped into the fray. He assisted stranded
                        U.S. citizens, drew up new identity documents, helped look after the German
                        and Austro-Hungarian citizens under care of the U.S. Government, and
                        distributed money to those in need.</p>
                    <p>Poole was transferred back to service at the Department of State in
                        Washington, D.C., in 1915, and was later assigned to Russia in 1917 where he
                        served as a first-hand witness to the Russian Revolution. Poole’s career in
                        the U.S. Government spanned the next several decades. Upon his retirement,
                        he remained active in international affairs through writing. He died in 1952
                        just after recording his oral history with Columbia University’s Oral
                        History project.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>George Sharp (1898?–1973)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Son, U.S. Ambassador to France William Graves
                        Sharp.</hi></p>
                    <p>George Clough Sharp was born around 1898, the second of William Graves and
                        Hallie Clough Sharp’s five children. Sharp sailed with his father for France
                        on August 26, 1914, aboard the <hi rend="italic">La France</hi> in the
                        absence of his mother (who was too ill to travel). When he arrived several
                        days later, the younger Sharp was just shy of his seventeenth birthday.</p>
                    <p>Sharp accompanied his father on visits to battlefields that fall, delivered
                        his father’s letters to ships departing for the United States, and learned
                        more about France. While he reportedly admired Paris, neither George nor his
                        father spoke much French upon their arrival. The younger Sharp immersed
                        himself in the language, and quickly became fluent.</p>
                    <p>After his father assumed diplomatic responsibilities in December 1914, Sharp
                        continued as the elder Sharp’s companion on official duties. The pair
                        visited prisoner of war camps and internment camps. In Spring 1915, Sharp
                        began to serve as his father’s personal secretary in the Embassy. He also
                        realized that his tenure in France, originally intended to be a gap year
                        prior to returning to the United States for college, would not be as short
                        as originally intended. Sharp enrolled in classes at the Sorbonne and then
                        the École des Sciences Politiques, from which he graduated with honors.</p>
                    <p>After the war, Sharp returned to the United States, where he attended and
                        graduated from Columbia University Law School. In 1936 he married Ruth
                        Baldwin in New York, and practiced law with the New York firm Sullivan &amp;
                        Cromwell. He died at age 75 in 1973.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605434">
                            <hi rend="bold">William Graves Sharp</hi></hi> (<hi rend="bold"
                            >1859–1922).</hi>
                        <ptr
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/sharp-william-graves"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Ambassador to France, 1914–1919.</hi> William Graves
                        Sharp and his twin brother George W. were born in Mt. Gilead, Ohio, on March
                        14, 1859. William was raised in Ohio and received his law degree from the
                        University of Michigan in 1881. He then moved to Elyria, Ohio, where he
                        practiced law. In 1895 he married Hallie Clough with whom he had five
                        children. Sharp entered national politics, and served three terms in the
                        U.S. House of Representatives as Congressman for Ohio’s Fourteenth District
                        from 1909 until 1915, although he resigned in 1914. He was deeply interested
                        in the sciences, was known as the “astronomer of Congress,” and loved
                        aviation. In June 1914, Sharp was confirmed as U.S. Ambassador to
                        France.</p>
                    <p>Hallie was too ill to travel the summer of 1914, so Sharp did not proceed
                        directly to Paris. When war broke out in August, Sharp made plans to sail as
                        soon as possible for France—without his wife. Instead he took his eldest
                        son, George, and the two Sharp gentlemen boarded the <hi rend="italic">La
                            France</hi> on August 26. Halfway through the voyage, Sharp learned that
                        former U.S. Ambassador to France Robert Bacon was on board, also headed for
                        Paris. The Sharps arrived in the city on September 3 and checked into the
                        Hôtel de Crillon on the Place de la Concorde. The famed hotel served as
                        their residence for the next several months until the rest of the family
                        joined them in the spring of 1915.</p>
                    <p>Sharp did not immediately assume his role as ambassador due to the crisis of
                        war and the direct German threat to Paris. Instead, Ambassador Myron T.
                        Herrick continued to serve in an official capacity, freeing Sharp to immerse
                        himself in his new environment. He had the unique opportunity to learn
                        first-hand as a private U.S. citizen about the people of Paris and the
                        country, as well as their wartime hardships. Sharp visited the battlefields
                        to better acquaint himself with the war’s realities. He also searched for a
                        new ambassador’s residence, as the lease on the mansion occupied by Herrick
                        was not to be renewed. Ellie Thackara, the wife of U.S. Consul in Paris
                        Alexander Thackara, helped Sharp secure a house at 14, avenue d’Eylau, which
                        became the Sharp family residence from Spring 1915 through April 1919.</p>
                    <p>On December 1, 1914, Sharp left Paris for Bordeaux where the Government of
                        France was temporarily located. He presented his credentials as U.S.
                        Ambassador to France on December 4, the only U.S. Representative to do so
                        outside of Paris, and returned to the capital that evening. For the next
                        several years, among his many duties, Sharp protected U.S. interests as a
                        neutral power, represented German, Austro-Hungarian, and Ottoman affairs in
                        France, and visited internment camps and prisoner of war camps.</p>
                    <p>Sharp hosted the U.S. delegation to the Paris Peace Conference in 1919, but
                        presented his letter of recall on April 4, 1919. A few years after his
                        return to the United States, Sharp grew ill and died in Elyria, Ohio, on
                        November 17, 1922, at age 63.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605435">
                            <hi rend="bold">Ann Singleton</hi></hi>
                        <hi rend="bold"> (1877–1976).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Clerk, U.S. Embassy Paris.</hi> Ann Singleton was born in
                        Avoyelles Parish, Louisiana, in 1877, and attended H. Sophie Newcomb College
                        in New Orleans for three years prior to attending Mary Baldwin Seminary in
                        Staunton, Virginia, for a year. Singleton dreamed of seeing the world, and
                        took up secretarial work as a means of doing so. From 1899 until 1901,
                        Singleton worked as a stenographer and typewriter for the U.S. Census Office
                        in Washington, D.C., before serving as a stenographer for the Spanish Treaty
                        Claims Commission in Havana, Cuba, from 1902 until 1907 and the Department
                        of State and Justice in Havana, Cuba, from 1908 until 1909. From 1909 until
                        1912, Singleton was engaged as a secretary in Paris and then appointed as a
                        clerk in the Diplomatic Service at U.S. Embassy Paris on September 1, 1912.
                        In 1914, there were five female clerks appointed to serve the Diplomatic
                        Service in overseas posts out of 55 clerks stationed abroad (9%).<note
                            n="135" xml:id="fn135"><hi rend="italic">Register of the Department of
                                State</hi>, November 13, 1913.</note></p>
                    <p>Singleton saved up $600 from her work at the Embassy, a sum she planned to
                        use to tour the world. Singleton was on the verge of departing Paris for the
                        United States to start her journey when war broke out in August 1914. She
                        amended her travel arrangements and remained in France for several more
                        months, providing crucial assistance as Embassy staff responsibilities
                        quickly multiplied. In 1917, Singleton returned to France to serve as
                        private secretary for General John J. Pershing, Chief of the American
                        Expeditionary Forces (AEF). When Pershing arrived in Paris on June 13, 1917,
                        “she was one of two women waiting at the Paris train station for Pershing to
                        arrive. The other woman was a newspaper reporter.”<note n="136"
                            xml:id="fn136">John Malloy, “Daytona Woman Was Pershing Aide,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Daytona Beach Morning Journal</hi>, November 23, 1968,
                            p. 47.</note> Singleton served as Pershing’s private secretary for the
                        remainder of the war.</p>
                    <p>After the war ended in November 1918, she again departed France for the
                        United States to work and save money. Singleton finally began her
                        much-delayed trip around the world in September 1921, departing Seattle for
                        Honolulu and then Japan. For the next decade, Singleton traveled (and
                        worked) throughout the world, and gave lectures on “Circling the Globe on
                        One’s Own.” In 1931, she returned to Washington, and took a job with the War
                        Department, where she worked until her retirement many years later.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605436">
                            <hi rend="bold">Louis Albert Sussdorff Jr.</hi></hi> (<hi rend="bold"
                            >1888–1940).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Third Secretary, U.S. Embassy Paris, 1914–1915.</hi> Louis
                        Albert Sussdorff Jr. was born in Elmhurst, Long Island, on January 7, 1888.
                        He received his bachelor’s cum laude in political science (1910) and law
                        degree (1914) from Harvard University, and from 1910 until 1913 served at
                        the university as an assistant in History and Government. On November 17,
                        1913, he passed the Department of State qualifying exam and entered the
                        Diplomatic Service. Sussdorff was appointed Third Secretary of U.S. Embassy
                        Paris on May 22, 1914.</p>
                    <p>As France descended into a state of war in August 1914, Sussdorff helped
                        maintain the Embassy’s beehive of activity. Ambassador Myron T. Herrick sent
                        him with John Work Garrett, his Special Agent, to follow the Government of
                        France to Bordeaux on September 2. Susdorff helped Garrett manage U.S.
                        diplomatic affairs and maintain communications and correspondence between
                        the U.S. outpost in Bordeaux and the Embassy in Paris, sometimes serving as
                        a courier. He also visited battlefields, prisoner of war camps, and
                        internment camps where he observed and wrote reports on conditions and
                        treatment of detained German and Austro-Hungarian soldiers and civilians.
                        When the Government of France returned to Paris that December, Sussdorff
                        followed.</p>
                    <p>In March 1915, he was assigned to Rio de Janerio and continued his career in
                        the Diplomatic Service serving mostly in Europe. Sussdorff was named Consul
                        General at Antwerp on June 1, 1937, and survived the German aerial
                        bombardment of the city in the spring of 1940. Unfortunately, his luck ran
                        out a few months later when he was killed in August in a car crash outside
                        Cologne, Germany. He was 52 years old.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605437">
                            <hi rend="bold">Alexander Montgomery “Mont” Thackara</hi></hi> (<hi
                            rend="bold">1848–1937).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Consul General at Paris, 1913–1924.</hi> Alexander
                        Montgomery Thackara was born in Philadelphia in 1848 to Benjamin and Mary
                        Thackara, and often went by the nickname “Mont.” He graduated in 1869 from
                        the U.S. Naval Academy and traveled the world with the U.S. Navy. Thackara
                        met Eleanor “Ellie” Sherman in 1879, and the following year they wed at the
                        Washington, D.C. home of her father, General William T. Sherman. Thackara
                        retired from the Navy in 1882 and began work in his family’s business,
                        Thackara, Sons &amp; Co., which manufactured and sold gas fixtures. On April
                        1, 1897, Thackara was appointed by President William McKinley to the U.S.
                        Consular Service. At the time, Thackara’s uncle-in-law, <ptr
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/sherman-john"
                        />John Sherman, served as Secretary of State. Thackara’s first consular
                        posting was to Le Havre, France, that year. He remained there until his
                        March 13, 1905, assignment to Berlin as Consul General. On September 18,
                        1913, Thackara was sent to Paris as Consul General.</p>
                    <p>When war descended on France in August 1914, the work of the U.S. Embassy and
                        U.S. Consulate instantly multiplied as thousands of U.S. citizens fled the
                        Continent. New regulations issued by the Government of France necessitated
                        that all U.S. citizens obtain new identity cards or official documentation
                        attesting to their citizenship. Thackara plunged into wartime work. He
                        assisted fellow citizens as well as the interests of those that the United
                        States agreed to represent (Germany, Austria-Hungary, etc.). As Consul
                        General, Thackara also served as Consulting Director to the American Chamber
                        of Commerce in Paris, an organization that raised funds for war relief
                        efforts and consulted on wartime issues.</p>
                    <p>In 1920, Thackara was awarded the Croix de Guerre by the Government of France
                        as a measure of appreciation for his wartime work. He was unable to accept
                        the award, however, because he was still a U.S. Government employee.
                        Thackara retired in 1924 and remained in Paris. In 1934 the U.S. House of
                        Representatives passed a joint resolution that enabled Thackara to finally
                        accept the Croix de Guerre. Thackara died on January 19, 1937, at the
                        American Hospital in Neuilly from bronchial pneumonia.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605438">
                            <hi rend="bold">Ellie Sherman Thackara</hi></hi> (<hi rend="bold"
                            >1859–1915).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Wife of Alexander Thackara, U.S. Consul General in
                            Paris.</hi> Eleanor “Ellie” Sherman Thackara was born in 1859, the
                        daughter of General William T. Sherman. In 1879 she met Alexander Montgomery
                        “Mont” Thackara, and they wed on May 5, 1880, at her father’s Washington
                        D.C. home. The couple had four children over the next several years: Mary
                        Elizabeth, Eleanor Sherman, William T. Sherman, and Alexander Montgomery Jr.
                        The Thackaras moved to Le Havre, France, in 1897 after Mont was appointed
                        there as Consul. Ellie moved twice more in the next twenty years, dictated
                        by her husband’s career in the Consular Service, to Berlin in 1905 and to
                        Paris in 1913.</p>
                    <p>Once war broke out in August 1914, Thackara immersed herself in volunteer
                        work, raising funds for war relief and medical aid efforts. That month she
                        founded the Servian (Serbian) Ambulance, run through her residence in the
                        Hotel Belmont. For the next several months, the focus of Thackara’s relief
                        work was provision of medical aid to Serbia. In October 1914, Thackara
                        founded the Urgent Fund for Serbian Wounded. She was also very active with
                        the Red Cross.</p>
                    <p>In April 1915, Thackara fell ill. During her convalescence, the King of
                        Serbia sent her a letter of gratitude for all of her efforts on behalf of
                        his people. Unfortunately, Thackara did not fully recover from her illness,
                        which many attributed to over-exertion from her war with war relief efforts.
                        That July, Thackara died in Paris, with her husband and two daughters by her
                        side.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605439">
                            <hi rend="bold">Eleanor Sherman Thackara [Cauldwell]</hi></hi>
                        <hi rend="bold"> (c. 1880s–?).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Daughter, U.S. Consul Alexander Montgomery Thackara.</hi>
                        Eleanor Sherman Thackara was born between 1882 and 1886, likely in the
                        Philadelphia area, to Alexander Montgomery Thackara and Eleanor “Ellie”
                        Sherman Thackara. Little is known about Eleanor’s childhood, or whether she
                        moved to Le Havre, France, with her parents when her father was first posted
                        there as Consul in 1897; she may have attended school in the United States
                        during this period. Eleanor and her sister, Mary Elizabeth, lived with their
                        parents during her father’s tenure as Consul General in Berlin from 1905
                        until 1913. Eleanor specialized in languages, with a reported expertise in
                        French and German. She helped her mother with social functions and worked at
                        the American Women’s Club of Berlin. In the German capital, Eleanor met her
                        future husband, Frederick Cauldwell, who worked in the U.S. Consulate. Their
                        engagement was announced in 1910, but proved to be a long-term one. Thackara
                        moved with her parents to Paris in 1913 when her father was assigned there
                        as Consul General.</p>
                    <p>Thackara was in the United States in August 1914, and by late November booked
                        passage back to France to volunteer her services for war relief efforts.
                        Upon her arrival in Paris in early December, Thackara took over some of her
                        mother’s work with the Serbian Ambulance. During the war, Thackara worked as
                        so many other U.S. women in France did, to raise funds for widows, orphans,
                        the injured, as well as hospitals and ambulance services.</p>
                    <p>Thackara finally married Cauldwell on January 31, 1917, in Rosemont,
                        Pennsylvania and eventually settled in Paris in the 1920s, where they
                        remained until the death of Thackara’s father in 1937. While it is unclear
                        when Eleanor passed away, newspaper accounts report that she was alive in
                        1952 when her daughter, Eleanor Thackara Cauldwell, married.</p>
                </div>
                <!--<p><hi rend="italic">Other U.S. Civilians</hi></p>-->
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605440">
                            <hi rend="bold">Richard Harding Davis</hi></hi> (<hi rend="bold"
                            >1864–1916).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Journalist.</hi> Born in 1864 to Lemuel Clarke Davis, an
                        editorial writer for <hi rend="italic">The Philadelphia Inquirer</hi>, and
                        Rebecca Harding, a writer who published her first piece, “Life in the Iron
                        Mills,” in <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>, Richard Harding Davis
                        was perhaps destined for the world of bon mots. At school, Davis’s strengths
                        were writing and sports, passions he translated into a career as a war
                        reporter. Davis covered several conflicts in the Belle Époque era, but was
                        perhaps known best for his work during the Spanish-American War.</p>
                    <p>Following the Austro-Hungarian declaration of war on July 28, 1914, Davis
                        booked passage aboard an emergency sailing of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Lusitania</hi>, which departed for Europe on August 4. His mission to
                        obtain credentials to cover the British and French armies at the front was
                        hindered by that fact that the U.S. Department of State only accredited one
                        U.S. newsman to Field Marshal Horatio Herbert Kitchener’s army.<note n="137"
                            xml:id="fn137">Fairfax Downey, <hi rend="italic">Richard Harding Davis:
                                His Day,</hi> (New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1933), 248.</note>
                        Instead, Davis journeyed to the Continent without credentials—as did many
                        other U.S. reporters—and witnessed the war’s first wave of destruction in
                        Belgium. In early September, Davis made his way to France, where his reports
                        of the German bombardment of Reims gained wide acclaim. Davis’s accounts of
                        U.S. Consul in Reims William Bardel were some of the only information the
                        outside world had as to the Consul’s fate.</p>
                    <p>Davis returned to the United States, but continued to argue for U.S.
                        preparedness, if not intervention, in the catastrophe. He died of a heart
                        attack in his home in 1916.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605441">
                            <hi rend="bold">H. Hermann Harjes</hi></hi>
                        <hi rend="bold"> (1875–1926).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Banker, Morgan &amp; Harjes</hi>. H. Hermann Harjes, son
                        of a Swiss immigrant to the United States, was born in Paris in 1875.
                        Educated in the United States and Great Britain, he worked for J.P. Morgan
                        in New York for several years before returning to Paris. Over the years,
                        Harjes rose to become senior partner at Morgan, Harjes &amp; Co. In 1897, he
                        married Marie Rovertine Graves, and was reportedly very much in love with
                        her. Widowed by Marie’s death in 1905, Harjes remarried in 1911 to
                        Fredericka Berwind Gilpin, daughter of a wealthy coal mining family from
                        Pennsylvania.</p>
                    <p>Soon after war broke out in 1914, Ambassador Myron T. Herrick called upon
                        Harjes to help solve the problem of how to enable U.S. citizens to draw
                        funds from French banks. Harjes was a valuable member of the U.S. expatriate
                        community in Paris, and donated much more than merely his time and expertise
                        to war relief efforts. He purchased a fleet of ambulances in October,
                        operated by the American Red Cross, and also established a field hospital in
                        France. Harjes was a member of the American Relief Clearing House,
                        established by Herrick to distribute funds and medical supplies in France.
                        Upon Herrick’s departure in November 1914, Harjes took over as President of
                        this organization. He also served as High Commissioner of the American Red
                        Cross Society for France and Belgium, a post he resigned in 1917 to join the
                        U.S. armed forces. Harjes was awarded the Croix de Guerre and the Legion of
                        Honor for his wartime relief work.</p>
                    <p>Harjes remained in Paris after the war and during the 1920s and was a
                        well-known sportsman and polo player. During polo practice in August 1926,
                        Harjes was thrown from his horse and kicked in the head. He was rushed to
                        the hospital, but died.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605442">
                            <hi rend="bold">Nicholas Roosevelt</hi></hi> (<hi rend="bold"
                            >1893–1982</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Private Secretary of John Work
                            Garrett, Special Agent to the U.S. Ambassador to France</hi>
                        <hi rend="bold">.</hi> Nicholas Roosevelt, cousin of U.S. President Theodore
                        Roosevelt, was born in New York City on June 12, 1893. He graduated from
                        Harvard University in 1914, where he served as an assistant to Edward
                        Channing, a professor of U.S. history.</p>
                    <p>After war broke out, Roosevelt wished to be of assistance. That October, a
                        fellow classmate asked Roosevelt if he wished to go to France and serve as
                        the secretary for the U.S. representative to the Government of France at
                        Bordeaux, John Work Garrett. Roosevelt seized the opportunity and sailed
                        that month aboard the <hi rend="italic">Mauretania</hi> for Liverpool and
                        then Bordeaux. One of his fellow passengers for the first leg of that
                        transatlantic journey was Katherine Page, daughter of <ptr
                            target="https://historyatstate.tumblr.com/post/89128785134/u-s-ambassador-walter-hines-page-1855-1918"
                        />U.S. Ambassador to the United Kingdom Walter Hines Page.</p>
                    <p>In Bordeaux, Roosevelt helped Garrett manage the onslaught of work entailed
                        in representing the United States Government as well as German and
                        Austro-Hungarian interests to the Government of France. When the French
                        government returned to Paris in December 1914, Roosevelt followed and served
                        as an attaché at the U.S. Embassy for the next two years. Roosevelt left
                        Paris in 1916 to serve as a secretary to the U.S. Mission to Spain.</p>
                    <p>After the war, Roosevelt continued his work in the diplomatic realm, and
                        served as U.S. Minister to Hungary from 1930 until 1933. He wrote for
                        newspapers and magazines, and authored several books. During the Second
                        World War he served as Chief of the Office of War Information from 1942
                        until 1945. Roosevelt died in 1982.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p><hi xml:id="_Toc397605443">
                            <hi rend="bold">Eric Fisher Wood</hi></hi>
                        <hi rend="bold"> (1889–1962).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Civilian Attaché, U.S. Embassy Paris, Fall 1914</hi>. Eric
                        Fisher Wood was born in New York City in 1889. Educated in private schools,
                        he graduated from Yale University in 1910. He went to Paris in 1914 to
                        pursue his post-graduate work at the École des Beaux Arts, and was a student
                        there when war broke out that summer.</p>
                    <p>In early August, Wood went to the U.S. Embassy and volunteered his services
                        to Ambassador Myron T. Herrick. Desperately short of hands to confront the
                        crisis, Herrick immediately put Wood to work. For the next two months Wood
                        assisted in the Embassy’s German and Austro-Hungarian Affairs Office, which
                        oversaw the rights and conditions of German and Austro-Hungarian subjects
                        interned in France as prisoners of war or civilian detainees. On several
                        occasions, Wood also traveled to the battlefields to observe conditions with
                        other U.S. officials. In October 1914, Wood ceased his volunteer work with
                        the Embassy, and instead donated his services to the fledging Motor
                        Ambulance Corps of the American Hospital in Neuilly. In February 1915, he
                        returned to the United States and published his account of the war’s first
                        few months.</p>
                    <p>Over the next several years, Wood returned to Europe where he served in the
                        British and French armies prior to enlisting as a private in the U.S. Army
                        in 1917. After the war ended, Wood remained in Europe for a time. He was one
                        of the founders of the American Legion in 1919. Wood returned to the United
                        States and settled in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, where he became a well-known
                        architect. He died in 1962.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="appendix-2">
                <head>Appendix II: Jusserand’s Long Voyage<note n="138" xml:id="fn138">Letter from
                        J.J. Jusserand (Washington) to Théophile Delcassé (Paris), August 30, 1914.
                        (Ministry of Foreign Affairs Archives, Guerre 1914–1918 Etats-Unis,
                        Août–Octobre 1914, Vol. 489).</note></head>
                <p><graphic url="clip_image007_967146276.jpg" height="857px" width="624px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image009_1237494039.jpg" height="906px" width="556px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image011_1707673253.jpg" height="904px" width="586px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image013_-43396467.jpg" height="899px" width="583px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image015_584187436.jpg" height="558px" width="615px"/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="appendix-3">
                <head>Appendix III: Diplomatic Protocol in France, Circa 1908<note n="139"
                        xml:id="fn139">Copy from Foreign Service General: (Harvard University
                        Archives, Cambridge, Massachusetts, Papers of Robert Woods Bliss and Mildred
                        Barnes Bliss, HUGFP 76.14 Box 1. Original in U.S. National Archives RG 59
                        143 19/12-28. Enclosure #8 to Despatch #439, dated August 10,
                    1908).</note></head>
                <p><graphic url="clip_image017_-1003648563.jpg" height="829px" width="618px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image019_194371143.jpg" height="901px" width="573px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image021_-420085990.jpg" height="908px" width="555px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image023_-1228434010.jpg" height="912px" width="546px"/>
                    <graphic url="clip_image025_2047379067.jpg" height="901px" width="518px"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="appendix-4">
                <head>Appendix IV: Selected U.S. War Relief &amp; Aid Projects in France,
                        1914–1915<note n="140" xml:id="fn140">William G. Sharp &amp; Gabriel
                        Hanotaux, <hi rend="italic">Le Secours americain en France</hi> (Paris;
                        Librairie Felix, 1915).</note></head>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item>American Ambulance in Neuilly</item>
                    <item>Juilly Hospital (founded by Mrs. Whitney)</item>
                    <item>Tuck Hospital at Rueil (founded my Mr. Tuck)</item>
                    <item>Stillman Hospital at Rue Rembrandt</item>
                    <item>Malmaison Convalescent Home at the chateau of Mr. Tuck</item>
                    <item>Wanamaker Hospital on Champs Elysées</item>
                    <item>Cooper-Hewitt Hospital on Avenue du Bois</item>
                    <item>Harjes Mobile Ambulance</item>
                    <item>Hospital at the American Artist’s Club (founded by Mrs. Whitlaw Reid on
                        rue Chevreuse)</item>
                    <item>Hospital organized by James H. Hyde in rue Adolphe Yvon</item>
                    <item>American Church Relief run by Mr. Watson</item>
                    <item>Camp for French Soldiers fitted up by <ptr
                            target="https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/knight-ridgway-brewster"
                        />Ridgway Knight at Poissy [he later served as US Amb to Syria, Belgium, and
                        Portugal)</item>
                    <item>Convalescent Home instituted by Mrs. Robert Woods Bliss at Mormant</item>
                    <item>Hospital of American Red Cross at Pan</item>
                    <item>Hospital of Mrs. Depew</item>
                    <item>L’ouvroir of Mme. Thackara</item>
                    <item>Herrick organized the American Relief Clearing House to serve as the
                        central POC for U.S. aid to French civilians (was located on rue Francois
                        Ier)</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="italic">At the end is a full list of all U.S. aid and hospitals in
                        France and fundraising aids in the United States.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <p rend="sectiontitlebold">Primary Sources</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Archives</p>
                <list>
                    <item>American Chamber of Commerce in France</item>
                    <item>American Hospital in Paris</item>
                    <item>Bibliothèque National de France</item>
                    <item>French Ministry of Foreign Affairs Archives</item>
                    <item>French <hi rend="italic">Service Historique de la Défense</hi></item>
                    <item>U.S. Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                            United States 1914 World War I Supplement</hi></item>
                    <item>U.S. Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Register of the Department of
                            State</hi></item>
                    <item>U.S. Library of Congress</item>
                    <item>U.S. National Archives</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Personal Paper Collections</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Papers of Robert Woods Bliss and Mildred Barnes Bliss, Harvard University
                        Archives, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</item>
                    <item>Papers of John Work Garrett, The Sheridan Library, Johns Hopkins
                        University, Baltimore, Maryland.</item>
                    <item>Myron T. Herrick Papers, Western Reserve Historical Society, Cleveland,
                        Ohio.</item>
                    <item>William H. Hunt Papers, Moorland-Springarn Research Center, Howard
                        University, Washington, D.C.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Newspapers</p>
                <list>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">Chicago Daily Tribune</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">New York Herald, Paris Edition</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">Le Figaro</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">Le Temps</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">Le Matin</hi></item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Personal Memoirs and Autobiographies</p>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Barnard, Charles Inman. <hi rend="italic">Paris War Days.</hi> Boston:
                        Little, Brown &amp; Co., 1914.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coolidge, John Gardner. <hi rend="italic">A War Diary in Paris:
                            1914–1917</hi>. Cambridge, Mass.: Riverside Press, 1931.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dryden, Elizabeth. <hi rend="italic">Paris in Herrick Days</hi>. Paris:
                        Dorbon-Ainé, 1915.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Guard, William J. <hi rend="italic">Soul of Paris: Two Months in the
                            French Capital During the War of 1914</hi>. The Sun Printing &amp;
                        Publishing Co., 1914.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Poincaré, Raymond. <hi rend="italic">The Memoirs of Raymond Poincaré
                            (1913–1914)</hi>, translated by Sir George Arthur. London: William
                        Heinemann Ltd., 1938.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Poincaré, Raymond. Preface in Bentley Mott, <hi rend="italic">Souvenirs de
                            Myron T. Herrick</hi>. Paris: Plon, 1930.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Poole Jr., DeWitt Clinton. “The Reminiscences of DeWitt Clinton Poole Jr.”
                        Columbia Center for Oral History Collection. January–March 1952.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roosevelt, Nicholas. <hi rend="italic">A Front Row Seat</hi>. Norman,
                        Okla.: University of Oklahoma Press, 1953.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sharp, William Graves and Gabriel Hanotaux. <hi rend="italic">Le Secours
                            americain en France</hi>. Paris: Librairie Felix, 1915.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sharp, William Graves and Warrington Dawson (ed.). <hi rend="italic">The
                            War Memoirs of William Graves Sharp</hi>. London: Constable &amp; Co.
                        Ltd., 1931.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wood, Eric Fisher. <hi rend="italic">The Note-Book of an Attaché: Seven
                            Months in the War Zone</hi> New York: The Century Co., 1915.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <p rend="sectiontitlebold">Secondary Literature</p>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Alexander, Adele Logan. <hi rend="italic">Parallel Worlds: The Remarkable
                            Gibbs-Hunts and the Enduring (In)Significance of Melanin</hi>.
                        Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Green, Nancy. <hi rend="italic">The Other Americans in Paris: Businessmen,
                            Countesses, Wayward Youth, 1880–1941.</hi> Chicago: University of
                        Chicago Press, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Downey, Fairfax. <hi rend="italic">Richard Harding Davis: His Day.</hi>
                        New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1933.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horn, Martin. “A Private Bank at War: J.P. Morgan &amp; Co. and France,
                        1914–1918.” <hi rend="italic">The Business History Review</hi>, Vol. 74, No.
                        2 (Spring, 2000), 85–112.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mott, Bentley. “Myron Herrick, Friend of France,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >World’s Work</hi>, November 1929.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mott, Bentley. <hi rend="italic">Myron T. Herrick: Friend of France</hi>,
                        (Garden City, NY: Doubleday, Doran &amp; Co., Inc., 1929.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nouailhat, Yves-Henri. <hi rend="italic">La France et Les États-Unis Août
                            1914-Avril 1917</hi>. Paris: Publications de la Sorbonne, 1979.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pennant, Lilla. <hi rend="italic">Wartime Embassy: The Life of William
                            Graves Sharp, U.S. Ambassador to France, and his Son George Clough Sharp
                            During the First World War.</hi> Sommerville, Mass.: Firefly Press,
                        1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scott, James Brown. <hi rend="italic">Robert Bacon: Life and Letters</hi>.
                        New York: Arno Press, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stapleton, Craig Roberts with Louise French McCready. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Where Liberty Dwells, There Is My Country: The Story of
                            Twentieth-Century American Ambassadors to France.</hi> Lanham, MD:
                        Hamilton Books, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Willson, Beckles. <hi rend="italic">America’s Ambassadors to France,
                            1777–1927</hi>. London: John Murray, 1928.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
