<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> Guide to
                    Sources on Vietnam, 1969-1975</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> Guide to Sources
                    on Vietnam, 1969-1975</head>
                <div xml:id="content">
                    <p>Prepared by Edward C. Keefer, John M. Carland, and Bradley L. Coleman<lb/>
                        Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State<lb/> Released February 1,
                        2012</p>
                    <p>The Vietnam war is one of the best documented events in U.S. history. 
                        Federal agencies generated a large and unique variety of archival material
                        during the conflict, from traditional memoranda and telegrams, to
                        backchannel messages and White House tape recordings.  This guide to
                        archival resources, based on the work of the Office of the Historian, U.S.
                        Department of State, describes the sources used to compile the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> (FRUS)
                        documentary series on the Vietnam war during the Richard M. Nixon and Gerald
                        R. Ford Administrations, from January 1969 to May 1975.  Despite the
                        expansive coverage dedicated to the Vietnam war in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> series, space constraints forced Department of
                        State historians to choose carefully among the thousands of documents
                        produced during the conflict.  This guide aims to provide a road map for
                        researchers seeking to go beyond documents included in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> to archival resources housed both in Washington
                        and in various locations around the country.  </p>
                    <p>In compiling the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, Department
                        of State historians had a very specific mission to capture: the documentary
                        record of high-level policy decisions and civilian direction and management
                        of the war; U.S. political and military strategy; peace negotiations with
                        the Democratic Republic of Vietnam (North Vietnam) and the National
                        Liberation Front (NLF); U.S. support for the armed forces of the Republic of
                        Vietnam (South Vietnam); and diplomatic, political, and economic relations
                        with South Vietnam.  The five <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        volumes covering the Nixon and Ford administrations contain notes on
                        sources, annotated source lists, and copious footnotes.  Readers should use
                        this guide in conjunction with the published volumes.  Before undertaking
                        archival research, researches should study carefully the documentation
                        contained in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes on Vietnam
                        from 1969 to 1975.  Researchers can purchase the volumes through the U.S.
                        Government Printing Office or view them free of charge on the Office of the
                        Historian, U.S. Department of State website (<ref
                            target="http://history.state.gov">http://history.state.gov</ref>).  In
                        keeping with prevailing scholarly practices, documents researchers initially
                        encounter in the series should be cited to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi>.</p>
                    <p>During the Lyndon B. Johnson administration, the President directed that the
                        U.S. military limit operations to South Vietnam, with the exception of the
                        U.S. air campaign against the Ho Chi Minh Trail and the intermittent bombing
                        of the North during Rolling Thunder.  Department of State historians
                        covering this period determined it desirable to segregate the conflicts in
                        Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia into separate <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volumes.  When Richard Nixon entered office in January
                        1969, however, the President and Special Assistant for National Security
                        Henry Kissinger expanded the war beyond South Vietnam into enemy sanctuaries
                        in Laos, Cambodia, and North Vietnam.  For this reason, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes covering Vietnam during this phase of
                        the war document events across Southeast Asia, including activities such as
                        the invasions of Cambodia (1970) and Laos (1971); the widespread bombing of
                        North Vietnam (1972); and the SS <hi rend="italic">Mayaguez</hi> incident
                        (1975).</p>
                    <p>After a careful reading of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        volumes, researchers should consult the extensive Presidential papers and
                        other White House records at the Nixon Presidential Materials Project.  In
                        2010 the Nixon records were transferred from the National Archives in
                        College Park, Maryland to the Nixon Presidential Library in Yorba Linda,
                        California.  Within this collection, the most valuable information bearing
                        on the administration’s management of the Vietnam War and its search for a
                        negotiated peace in Southeast Asia are the National Security Council (NSC)
                        Files.</p>
                    <p>Two sub-files within the NSC materials provide the best documentation: the
                        Vietnam Subject Files and the Country Files for Vietnam.  These files hold
                        the working records of the NSC staff members responsible for analyzing
                        information on Vietnam for Kissinger, who in turn would use their analyses
                        in his communications with President Nixon.  The Vietnam Subject Files is a
                        topical collection that deals not only with Vietnam but also with Laos,
                        Cambodia, Thailand, and Southeast Asia as a whole.  For example, material on
                        the 1971 U.S.-supported South Vietnamese cross-border operation, Lam Son
                        719, is in the Vietnam Subject Files under the sub-file Special Operations
                        File.  Although the Vietnam Subject Files collection is weighed towards
                        military issues, it also contains abundant records on the attempt to manage
                        the peace process in Vietnam after January 1973.  Like other Nixon records,
                        the archivists have prepared finding aids with folder titles.  The Vietnam
                        Country Files collection, consisting of 29 Hollinger boxes, holds diplomatic
                        and political material primarily about Vietnam and U.S. relations with the
                        Republic of Vietnam.  The boxes, folders, and items within are organized
                        chronologically.  In some cases there are sub-chronologies in each folder of
                        Department of State cables, intelligence cables, and memoranda.  The Vietnam
                        Country Files is the single most cited collection in the five <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes on Vietnam from 1969 to
                        1975.</p>
                    <p>The Far East Country Files, 31 Hollinger boxes, contain folders on Cambodia,
                        Laos, Southeast Asia, Indochina, and Thailand.  Although similar in
                        organization to the Vietnam Country Files, it lacks specific subject
                        folders, but does include topical and issue-specific folders.  Additionally,
                        there is a Cambodian Operations File, consisting of 21 Hollinger boxes, that
                        contains a combination of chronological and topical records covering the
                        U.S.-South Vietnamese movement into Cambodia from April to July 1970.  The
                        files consist mostly of daily situation and action reports, including many
                        to the President, as well as longer reports and briefings to Congress and
                        others on the Cambodian operation.  The Nodis/Khmer section of this file
                        focuses on efforts by various nations to support the Cambodian effort.</p>
                    <p>The search for a negotiated peace is a principal theme of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> coverage of the Vietnam war. 
                        Official peace negotiations were held in Paris at the International
                        Conference Center on Avenue Kléber.  Documentation on these talks,
                        consisting of some 28 Hollinger boxes, is located in the Paris/Talks Meeting
                        Files.  This file begins during the Johnson administration and contains the
                        records—mostly cables to and from the delegation in Paris—of the W. Averell
                        Harriman and Cyrus Vance Mission (HARVAN), from May 1968 to January 1969. 
                        During the Nixon administration, the file covers cable traffic between the
                        Department of State and the delegation in Paris, and to and from the Embassy
                        in Saigon.  There are a few topical folders in the collection with
                        non-telegraphic material, but it is essentially a cables file with the bulk
                        of the material dated between 1969 and 1970.</p>
                    <p>The Nixon administration preferred to use private talks in Paris, as opposed
                        to the official public sessions at Avenue Kléber, as the primary venue for
                        serious negotiations. In August 1969, Washington and Hanoi opened a secret
                        negotiations channel.  At these discussions, Kissinger represented the
                        United States and Hanoi’s Chief Delegate at Paris Xuan Thuy, later joined by
                        Special Adviser Le Duc Tho, represented North Vietnam.  Le Duc Tho was a
                        member of the Politburo in Hanoi and the real chief of the delegation.  The
                        records of the Kissinger and Xuan Thuy-Le Duc Tho negotiations were
                        maintained by NSC staff member Winston Lord, the principal note taker for
                        these secret meetings, and are located in the NSC Files, For the
                        President’s—China/Vietnam Negotiations, C.D. [Camp David].  This file
                        includes virtually all verbatim memoranda of the secret talks, as well as
                        summary memoranda prepared by Kissinger and his staff for the President. 
                        This collection also reveals how Ambassador Ellsworth Bunker and South
                        Vietnamese President Thieu kept abreast of the negotiations.  In all, the
                        Vietnam negotiations portion of the file maintained by Winston Lord fills 24
                        Hollinger boxes.  A second file by the same name exists in the NSC Files,
                        and consists of 3 Hollinger boxes containing mostly copies of Kissinger’s
                        secret talks with Le Duc Tho, original letters from Thieu to Nixon from late
                        1972 to early 1973, and memoranda of conversations for Kissinger’s trip to
                        South Vietnam in October 1972 and Haig’s trip in November 1972.</p>
                    <p>As for U.S.-Soviet relations, the Nixon administration wanted Moscow to
                        pressure North Vietnam into a political settlement.  To this end, Nixon and
                        Kissinger engaged in private talks with Soviet Ambassador Anatoly Fedorovich
                        Dobrynin.  Nine Hollinger boxes of records related to those meeting are in
                        the NSC Files, President’s Trip File, Dobrynin/Kissinger.</p>
                    <p>Following the aforementioned collections, next in importance are several
                        other collections within the NSC Files.  The first is the Backchannel Files
                        which contain secret communications between the White House (essentially the
                        President or Kissinger) and U.S. ambassadors, conducted without the
                        knowledge of the official Department of State bureaucracy. Although the
                        collection includes all backchannel messages, a good portion relate to
                        backchannel messages between the White House and Ambassadors Bunker and
                        Graham A. Martin in Saigon, and to and from other ambassadors in Southeast
                        Asia.  For 1969, however, backchannel communications between the White House
                        and Ambassador Bunker are filed in the Vietnam Subject File.  On almost all
                        occasions, these backchannel messages were more important to the policy
                        process than the regular Department of State telegrams.  Backchannel
                        messages to and from U.S. negotiators in Paris are also in this
                        collection.</p>
                    <p>The Kissinger Office Files—the records of the Special Assistant to the
                        President for National Security Affairs maintained by his immediate
                        staff—are also in the NSC Files.  A key source for documents on U.S. policy
                        toward Vietnam, this collection contains Kissinger’s trip files, items such
                        as briefing books, memoranda, and memoranda of conversations relating to his
                        travels.  These records cover his visit to Saigon in October 1972 to confer
                        with President Nguyen Van Thieu; his negotiating sessions in Paris with Le
                        Duc Tho; his February 1973 Hanoi visit; and activities related to the June
                        1973 Joint Communiqué.  The Kissinger Office Files also have separate
                        Country Files, Far East, sub-section that contains records on Cambodia,
                        especially relating to the efforts of Colonel Jonathan “Fred” Ladd, sent to
                        Phnom Penh by the President, to bolster the fighting ability of Lon Nol’s
                        armed forces.  A Vietnam-South Vietnam Country File, which covers 1971–1972
                        and contains a sub-section on Vietnam-Vietnam Negotiations, are also in the
                        Office Files but, it should be emphasized, the most important material on
                        this issue is in the For the President’s Files.</p>
                    <p>Valuable documents relating to Vietnam are in other collections in the NSC
                        Files.  The Haig Chronological Files includes memoranda, correspondence, and
                        message traffic to and from Haig, much of it relating to Vietnam.  It also
                        contains one box of transcripts of a number of telephone conversations among
                        Haig, Nixon, Kissinger, and other NSC staff members.  These transcripts do
                        not seem to appear elsewhere and often contain significant policy
                        discussions.  The Haig Special File has material arranged topically, much of
                        which relates to Haig’s trips to South Vietnam (aimed at informing President
                        Thieu about the state of the negotiations and, more importantly, at
                        persuading him to accept the American proposals and approach).  This file
                        also includes documents on Haig’s trips to other Southeast Asian nations. 
                        The Agency File, Department of Defense, contains considerable documentation
                        on Vietnam, while the Subject Files (as opposed to the Vietnam Subject
                        Files) hold only occasional Vietnam-related items, some of which is useful,
                        such as Items to Discuss with the President.  A chronological collection of
                        documents within the NSC Files, the President’s Daily Briefing Files often
                        include reports on Vietnam with handwritten comments by President Nixon. 
                        Finally, the Unfiled Material contains documentation on Vietnam.  Made up of
                        material not filed after the President resigned, the collection has no
                        finding aid or organizational logic except that it is organized by
                        date—earliest to latest.  There is no easy way to review it except document
                        by document.</p>
                    <p>The NSC Files in the Nixon Presidential Materials also contain the National
                        Security Council Institutional Files (H-Files), which should not to be
                        confused with the NSC Institutional Matters File (a sub-file of the NSC
                        Files comprising 19 boxes).  The H-Files, consisting of 315 boxes, until
                        recently were under the control of the NSC but have now been transferred to
                        the Nixon Presidential Library.  These files contain the minutes of National
                        Security Council Meetings and NSC subgroups such as the Review Group/Senior
                        Review Group and the Washington Special Actions Group (WSAG), chaired by
                        Kissinger and attended by deputy heads of the federal agencies and the
                        Director of Central Intelligence.  Furthermore, for each set of minutes
                        there are corresponding folders containing papers Kissinger used to prepare
                        for the meetings.  For Vietnam and Southeast Asia, the WSAG functioned as
                        the key policy and crisis management entity.  It dealt, sometimes on a daily
                        basis during critical periods, with events in Vietnam and Southeast Asia,
                        making policy decisions, or asking the President to make the decisions, and
                        following up on Presidential directives.  In addition, this file hold
                        records of the Vietnam Special Study Group (VSSG), a White House dominated
                        organization established to provide the President and Kissinger with
                        independent analysis and advice. Also of value in the Institutional
                        (H-Files) are the National Security Study Memoranda/National Security
                        Decision Memoranda (NSSM/NSDM) Files, containing requests for studies, the
                        studies themselves, and resulting decision memoranda.</p>
                    <p>While the NSC Files and the NSC Institutional Files are the premier
                        collections for Vietnam and Southeast Asia, additional useful collections
                        exist in the Nixon Presidential Materials.  For example, in the White House
                        Special Files one finds the H. R. Haldeman Files, which holds Haldeman’s
                        handwritten accounts of his daily activities.  During his time at the White
                        House, Haldeman at first wrote and later dictated a daily diary.  Although
                        not a foreign policy expert, he was a close confidant of the President and,
                        as Chief of Staff, very close to, and observant of, the decision making
                        process.  His diary is a treasure trove of great historical significance.
                        Available on compact disk (<hi rend="italic">The Haldeman Diaries, the
                            Multi-Media Edition)</hi>, a selection of key entries have been
                        published in book form by G. Putnam and Sons as <hi rend="italic">The
                            Haldeman Diaries: Inside the Nixon White House</hi>.  Additionally, the
                        Nixon Presidential Diary, an appointments diary indicating where the
                        President was and with whom he met or spoke on a given day, is an essential
                        tool for researchers and is found in the White House Central Files, Staff
                        Member and Office Files.</p>
                    <p>The archival sources at the Ford Presidential Library in Ann Arbor, Michigan,
                        offer the best coverage of the final months of the Vietnam war, including
                        domestic political activities, the evacuation of Phnom Penh and Saigon, and
                        the SS <hi rend="italic">Mayaguez</hi> affair.  The Presidential Country
                        Files for East Asia and the Pacific contain invaluable documents, including
                        memoranda, correspondence, telegrams, and reports.  Organized by country
                        name, there are 10 Hollinger boxes with materials exclusively related to
                        U.S. involvement in Southeast Asia.  The NSC East Asia and Pacific Affairs
                        Staff Files offer additional documentation, including a chronological file,
                        SS <hi rend="italic">Mayaguez</hi> papers, and items generated for WSAG and
                        NSC meetings.  Valuable backchannel communications with Ambassador Martin
                        and other Southeast Asian ambassadors fill 2 Hollinger boxes.  Additionally,
                        the library houses Ford administration H-Files, which include briefing
                        books, memoranda, and WSAG meetings minutes produced during the U.S.
                        evacuation of Cambodia and South Vietnam.  A small collection of National
                        Security Agency material at the Ford Library includes the text of helicopter
                        radio communications during the April 1975 emergency.  Researchers should
                        also consult the Agency Files, NSC Vietnam Information Group Files, NSC
                        Congressional Relations Files, NSC Meeting files, Kissinger and Scowcroft
                        West Wing Files, Brent Scowcroft Daily Work Files, White House Central
                        Files, Legislative Inter-Departmental Working Group Files, and Wolfgang
                        Lehmann Papers.  The library maintains detailed findings aids (available
                        online) for each collection.  There are also 10 Hollinger boxes of documents
                        removed from the Embassy by Ambassador Martin during the evacuation, a
                        unique collection considering the embassy staff destroyed or scattered most
                        records covering the period from 1974 to 1975 during the final days in
                        Saigon.  Combined with the Martin backchannel messages, these records offer
                        a detailed account of the Embassy’s experience, important considering the
                        Ambassador’s great personal influence on the handling of the evacuation.</p>
                    <p>The Henry Kissinger Papers at the Library of Congress are likewise valuable. 
                        Although the collection is not open to the public, Kissinger permitted
                        Department of State historians access to these records for use in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.  Material in the papers
                        often replicate documents found in other collections; it nonetheless holds
                        some unique material.  Foremost in this category are the transcripts of
                        Kissinger telephone conversations based on notes taken by a secretary
                        listening in on the phone at Kissinger’s office at the White House or
                        transcribed from tapes recordings from his home telephone.  Needless to say,
                        the Kissinger telephone conversations are a key source for Vietnam War
                        policy.  While general researchers cannot use the transcripts at the Library
                        of Congress, Kissinger has allowed copies to be transferred to the National
                        Archives, where most are open to the public.</p>
                    <p>Other than the transcripts of telephone conversations, Kissinger’s speeches
                        and writings, and his Record of Schedule (appointment diary), the Kissinger
                        Papers are segregated into a classified file (secret and below), a
                        top-secret file, and a section containing a limited amount of restricted
                        data and special compartmentalized information.  In this material, the best
                        collection for Vietnam and Southeast Asia is the Geopolitical File, which
                        contains a wide-ranging section on Vietnam and smaller files on Cambodia and
                        Laos.  Also of value within the Kissinger Papers are the Memoranda to the
                        President File, the Memoranda of Conversations File, and the Presidential
                        File.  However, none of these deal exclusively with Vietnam and Southeast
                        Asia.</p>
                    <p>The Department of State, Department of Defense, and to a lesser extent the
                        Central Intelligence Agency, although strong bureaucratic players in the
                        Johnson Administration’s policymaking, played a reduced role under President
                        Nixon and Henry Kissinger, who concentrated policymaking in the White
                        House.  The files of the Department of State, especially the Central Files
                        and certain Lot Files, are valuable for tracking events in Vietnam, Laos,
                        and Cambodia, and at the Paris Talks.  Before Kissinger became Secretary of
                        State in September 1973, Department of State records offer poor coverage of
                        U.S. policy toward Southeast Asia, because Nixon and Kissinger intentionally
                        excluded the Secretary of State and the Department from the Vietnam
                        decision-making process.  Still, some of the Central Files are useful for
                        political, economic, and military developments in Southeast Asia from 1969
                        to 1974, including POL 27 CAMB/KHMER, POL 27 LAOS, and POL 27 VIET S.  While
                        ostensibly the designation for military operations in Vietnam, and to a
                        lesser extent Laos and Cambodia, POL 27 became a catchall file. 
                        Consequently, it is a good source of material for those interested in
                        political developments in Saigon, Vientiane, or Phnom Penh.  In the Lot
                        Files one finds Ambassador Ellsworth Bunker’s weekly and later monthly
                        summaries of events in South Vietnam to President Nixon.  They covered in
                        detail the government, politics, the economy, and the war.  Although the
                        President rarely read the reports, they nonetheless provide a useful account
                        of important events in South Vietnam; they have been collected and published
                        as <hi rend="italic">The Bunker Papers</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Reports to
                            the President from Vietnam, 1967–1973</hi> (Berkeley, 1990).  The
                        Central Files offer Vietnam-related documents through mid-1973, after which
                        the Department captured memoranda, telegrams, and other records
                        electronically.  Researchers can search and retrieve these later items
                        through a National Archives archival database.</p>
                    <p>Beginning in September 1973, when Kissinger became the Secretary of State,
                        the Department again played an active role in the policymaking process.  The
                        Records of Henry Kissinger (26 Hollinger boxes), 1973–1977, Entry 5403,
                        Record Group 59, at the National Archives contain documents related to
                        Vietnam.  The Transcripts of Secretary of State Kissinger’s Staff Meetings
                        (11 Hollinger boxes), Entry 5117, Record Group 59, are also useful. 
                        Researchers may likewise consult the U.S. Foreign Service post records. 
                        Although they offer little on high policy, the post files are filled with
                        reports and communications on local conditions and activities.  In the
                        absence of U.S. initiative after mid-1973, moreover, the story of U.S.
                        involvement in South East Asia often centers on embassy activity.  The post
                        files, however, provide inconsistent coverage of U.S. activities abroad
                        because many records did not survive the fall of Saigon.  The best
                        preserved, the Phnom Penh Embassy Files, Record Group 84, offer detailed
                        coverage of U.S. activities in Cambodia.  Large portions of the Saigon
                        Embassy collection, on the other hand, were lost in 1975.  The most complete
                        collection of Saigon Embassy documents for the period from 1974 to 1975 is
                        located at the Ford Library, not the National Archives.  Also, while they
                        offer thin coverage of the years between 1969 and 1974, the Lot Files of the
                        Bureau of East Asian Affairs Files, Record Group 59, can be useful for
                        researchers interested in the ending of the Vietnam War.</p>
                    <p>The Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) records are essential for documenting
                        the role of intelligence in the war in Southeast Asia.  Even so, the most
                        important finished intelligence can be found in the Nixon Presidential
                        Materials, NSC Files.  The CIA prepared a daily briefing for the President
                        on Vietnam that is in the National Security Council Files, President’s Daily
                        Briefings.  Additionally, useful collections under CIA’s physical custody
                        are the National Intelligence Center (NIC) Files, which contain many
                        intelligence estimates and memoranda.  Of particular significance are the
                        records of George Carver, Special Assistant for the Director of Central
                        Intelligence (DCI), for Vietnam Affairs.  As the CIA’s foremost Washington
                        expert on Vietnam and Southeast Asia, his files are central to understanding
                        the interplay between intelligence and foreign policy.  The same is true for
                        the DCI (Helms) Files and DCI Executive Registry Files, although these files
                        also include material on non-Vietnam issues that engaged the DCI.  The
                        National Intelligence Council’s <hi rend="italic">Estimative Products on
                            Vietnam, 1948–1975</hi>, published in 2005, contains a good selection of
                        intelligence estimates on Vietnam.  In most cases, <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volumes print only the summaries of the National
                        Intelligence and Special Intelligence estimates while the full texts are
                        published in the in the NIC publication.  Intelligence Files for the Nixon
                        and Ford Administrations, including the records of the 303 Committee/40
                        Committee and related subject files for Vietnam and Southeast Asia were
                        particularly valuable for documenting covert operations and unconventional
                        warfare.  They are currently in the custody of the National Security
                        Council, but are destined for the Nixon and Ford Presidential Libraries.  A
                        Department of State Lot file, the INR/IL Historical Files, holds valuable
                        material for these topics and is similar to the Nixon Intelligence Files. 
                        These files remain in the control of the Department of State.</p>
                    <p>The Department of Defense and Secretary of Defense Melvin Laird were key
                        players in the formation of policy towards Vietnam.  Department of State
                        historians conducted extensive research in the Department of Defense records
                        now housed at the Washington National Records Center in Suitland, Maryland. 
                        Still classified, these files include secret and top-secret documents,
                        organized by office, year, and subject.  These files will likely move to the
                        National Archives in College Park upon declassification.  The Defense
                        Secretary’s key memoranda are almost always in the NSC Files in the Nixon
                        and Ford collections.</p>
                    <p>At the Ford Library, a collection of documents covers Laird’s tenure as
                        Secretary of Defense.  His staff chose these Laird Papers at the end of his
                        term as Secretary of Defense with a view to documenting his major decisions
                        and accomplishments.  The Papers of James R. Schlesinger, Secretary of
                        Defense from 1973 to 1975, are located at the Library of Congress. 
                        Schlessinger’s collection holds memoranda, reports, and communications
                        related to his government service, but is not yet open to the public.  Major
                        portions of the Laird and Schlesinger collections concern Vietnam, Cambodia,
                        and POW/MIA affairs.  In addition, the official files of the Secretary of
                        Defense, Under Secretary of Defense, and their Assistants, plus the records
                        of the Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs,
                        have large sections devoted to Vietnam and Southeast Asia.</p>
                    <p>Defense related records that were not available when the first volumes were
                        being researched, but are worthy of mention as sources, are the records of
                        the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs in Record Group 218 at the National
                        Archives—specifically those of General Earle G. Wheeler, Chairman,
                        1964–1970; Admiral Thomas H. Moorer, 1970–1974; and General George S. Brown,
                        1974–1978—in the National Archives.  The most useful sections of these
                        records are the Chairman’s correspondence to and from the Commander,
                        Military Assistance Command, Vietnam, correspondence to and from the
                        Commander in Chief, Pacific Command, and additional miscellaneous Vietnam
                        related documents in various country folders.</p>
                    <p>Another JCS collection, Admiral Moorer’s Diary, reveals significant
                        information about the policymaking process.  Only made available when the
                        final <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in the Vietnam series
                        were being researched, the Diary contains entries for practically every day
                        during his tour of duty as Chairman.  Each day’s entry contains a series of
                        sub-entries about meetings (in his office, in Secretary Laird’s, at the
                        White House, or elsewhere), telephone conversations, or reflections on
                        policy matters and other topics.  Appended to most daily entries are one or
                        more documents.  Especially useful to the researcher are memoranda for the
                        record Moorer drafted after meetings with President Nixon or with Kissinger,
                        internal memoranda from one of his own subordinates or external ones from
                        Kissinger or Kissinger’s Deputy, Alexander M. Haig, or from other members of
                        the Nixon Administration.  What gives special value to the already immensely
                        valuable diary and its attached documents is that Moorer taped and
                        transcribed many of his telephone conversations and attached the transcripts
                        to the Diary.  These transcripts of conversation—a few with Nixon but more
                        often with Kissinger; Haig; Laird; Admiral John S. McCain (Commander in
                        Chief, Pacific); Generals Creighton W. Abrams and Fred C. Weyand (theater
                        commanders in Saigon); and the Admiral’s own senior subordinate at the
                        Pentagon—reveal the extraordinary and substantial role Moorer played in the
                        formation and implementation of U.S. national security policy in Southeast
                        Asia.</p>
                    <p>After February 1971, the White House Presidential Recordings are a critical
                        source for understanding Vietnam policy developments and to a lesser extent
                        for policy in Cambodia and Laos.  The recordings that are transcribed and
                        cited in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes comprise only
                        a small portion of the recordings available.  Using the tape log, and
                        comparing entries with the meetings and conversations for which there are
                        written records, the editors and the Nixon Tape team at the Office of the
                        Historian have selected policy-significant recordings of meetings and
                        telephone conversations. While tape conversations are difficult to
                        transcribe and do not always lend themselves easily to insertion in
                        documentary publication, the selection presented in these volumes is a
                        representative of the larger body of conversations. Nixon and his close
                        confidants spent hours talking in the President’s Oval and Executive Office
                        Building office. Their conversations were often unstructured and repetitive,
                        their language frank, raw, and often uncomplimentary to individuals and
                        institutions.  While it is the immediacy and apparent unguarded natured of
                        recorded conversations, whether of individuals talking on a telephone or in
                        an office, that give such conversations the reputation for truthfulness they
                        enjoy among historians and others, it should be emphasized that it is just
                        as possible to shade the truth, or lie, in conversations as it is in the
                        more calculated act of writing.  At the same time, when recordings exist, as
                        the Nixon White House tapes do, they become an integral part of the
                        historical record and impose on historians the obligation to exploit them as
                        best they can.  These tapes are an almost breathtaking resource but must be
                        used with caution and viewed within the broader context.  Volumes in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series provide just such a
                        context.</p>
                    <p>What makes the Nixon administration’s records on Vietnam especially revealing
                        is the existence of these unique sources.  The presidential tapes
                        recordings, the Kissinger telephone conversations, the Haldeman Diaries, and
                        the Moorer Diary and telephone conversations provide an added dimension of
                        documentary material.  Taken in conjunction with the more traditional
                        records, these special sources deepen one’s understanding of the characters
                        involved and how they interacted with others and with the circumstances they
                        encountered.  By extension, they also provide a great understanding of the
                        policymaking process.</p>
                    <p>In sum, the records of the Nixon and Ford administrations on Vietnam are a
                        rich and abundant resource but pose some substantial challenges to
                        researchers.  Even with five volumes covering the conflict from 1969 to
                        1975, only a small fraction of the total documentation will be printed in
                        the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.  The editors of these
                        volumes believe, however, that they have selected the most significant
                        documents available for understanding the policy process.  Furthermore, they
                        have added value to their selections through annotation and editorial
                        notes.  While Department of State historians have had to make difficult
                        choices, they believe that the resulting documentary collections provide a
                        solid account of policy decisions by the Nixon and Ford Administrations on
                        the Vietnam War and will stimulate additional research on U.S. involvement
                        in the still-controversial war.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
