<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Short History of the Department of State</title>
                <title type="short">Short History</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>Short History of the Department of State</title>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="foundations">
                <head>Foundations of Foreign Affairs, <date when="1775">1775-1823</date>
                </head>
                <div type="subchapter">
                    <head>Foundations of Foreign Affairs, 1775-1823</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-jmonroe.jpg"/>
                            <head>James Monroe, Early American Diplomat</head>
                        </figure> American diplomats played a key role in the struggle for
                        independence and in winning respect for the new nation during the early
                        years of the new Republic. Those who served included some of the most
                        brilliant and gifted diplomats ever to represent the United States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="origins">
                    <head>Origins of a Diplomatic Tradition</head>
                    <p>Despite their status as colonial subjects of the King, some 18th century
                        Americans already had a great deal of experience negotiating with ministers
                        at the highest levels of the British Government. <figure
                            rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-bfranklin.jpg"/>
                            <head>Benjamin Franklin</head>
                        </figure> In 1757, <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/b-franklin">Benjamin
                            Franklin</ref> began his first term as Pennsylvania’s colonial agent in
                        London. By the end of his second term (1765-75), Franklin also represented
                        Massachusetts, Georgia, and New Jersey. Other distinguished Americans, such
                        as <persName>Arthur Lee</persName>, served in a similar capacity.</p>
                    <p>Franklin secretly negotiated with the British in 1774 to prevent the outbreak
                        of war. Although he was unsuccessful, he gained valuable diplomatic skills.
                        When war became inevitable, a nucleus of Americans, including Franklin, was
                        ready to assume the tremendously important task of representing the
                        breakaway nation in the courts of Europe. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="diplomacy">
                    <head>Diplomacy: A Key Component of the Revolution</head>
                    <p>Given the overwhelming strategic and military advantages of Great Britain,
                        the United States could gain independence only if it attracted the support
                        of Britain’s enemies, France and Spain. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-dean-silas.jpg"/>
                            <head>Silas Deane</head>
                        </figure> In November 1775, Congress established the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1776-1783/secret-committee">Committee of Secret
                            Correspondence</ref> to “correspond with friends” and prospective
                        supporters abroad and to send commissioners to other key countries.
                            <persName>Silas Deane</persName> was sent to France in March 1776, and
                            <persName>Arthur Lee</persName> became a “confidential correspondent” in
                        London.</p>
                    <p>American commissioners during the Revolutionary period were authorized to
                        appoint commercial agents to supply the American war effort, but the
                        committees of the Continental Congress also appointed some commercial agents
                        directly. The resulting confusion caused Franklin to complain,
                            <quote>“Commercial agents . . . and the captains are continually writing
                            for my opinion or orders or leave to do this or that, by which much time
                            is lost to them and much of mine is taken up to little purpose from my
                            ignorance.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-continental-congress.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Continental Congress</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In October 1776, Franklin sailed to France to lead the diplomatic effort. His
                        patient diplomacy combined with the American victory at the
                            <placeName>Battle of Saratoga</placeName> resulted in a Treaty of
                        Alliance with France in February 1778. <persName>Benjamin
                            Franklin</persName> officially became the first American Minister to
                        serve overseas when, on March 23, 1779, he presented his credentials to King
                        Louis XVI of France.</p>
                    <p>In June 1781, Congress named a Peace Commission, including Franklin, John
                        Adams, and John Jay to negotiate an end to the war. The commissioners
                        reached agreement with the British on November 30, 1782. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="articles">
                    <head>Diplomacy under the Articles of Confederation</head>
                    <p>While negotiations in Paris were underway, legislators in the United States
                        created a new government—the <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/articles"
                            >Articles of Confederation</ref>. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-livingston-robert.jpg"/>
                            <head>Robert R. Livingston, First Secretary for Foreign Affairs </head>
                        </figure> Today’s Department of State began on <date when="1781-01-10"
                            >January 10, 1781</date>, as the "Department of Foreign Affairs.”
                        Shortly after approval of the resolution, Congress selected <ref
                            target="/milestones/1776-1783/secret-committee">Robert R.
                            Livingston</ref> of New York as the first Secretary for Foreign Affairs.
                        Many of America’s leading public figures served as envoys under the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1776-1783/articles">Articles of Confederation</ref>,
                        among them <persName>John Adams</persName> in the Netherlands,
                            <persName>John Jay</persName> in Spain, and <persName>Thomas
                            Jefferson</persName> in France.</p>
                    <p>Robert Livingston’s 19 months in office were filled with frustration since
                        the weak and inefficient Articles of Confederation diffused foreign policy
                        making authority. After Livingston complained, Congress further restricted
                        his authority to act. Livingston’s successor, John Jay, another New Yorker,
                        was appointed Secretary for Foreign Affairs on <date when="1784-05-07">May
                            7, 1784</date>, and found the job equally frustrating. During the
                        national debate on whether to adopt the new constitution drafted in 1787,
                        Jay summarized his critique of congressional foreign policy under the
                        Articles of Confederation: <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-jjay.jpg"/>
                            <head>John Jay, Envoy to Spain and Second Secretary for Foreign Affairs
                                under the Articles of Confederation</head>
                        </figure>
                        <quote>“They may make war, but are not empowered to raise men or money to
                            carry it on. They may make peace, but are without power to see the terms
                            of it imposed. . . . They may make alliances, but [are] without ability
                            to comply with the stipulations on their part. They may enter into
                            treaties of commerce, but [are] without power to enforce them at home or
                            abroad.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>While “ministers” handled the country’s official business, other officials,
                        known as “consuls” handled business matters for Americans overseas. Although
                        a 1778 treaty with France provided for the appointment of consular
                        officials, no American consuls began their service until 1781.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Thomas Barclay</persName> of Pennsylvania was appointed consul in
                        France on <date when="1781-10-02">October 2, 1781</date>, replacing
                            <persName>William Palfrey</persName>, who was lost at sea on his way to
                        post. In early 1786, Congress appointed <persName>Samuel Shaw</persName>, a
                        Yankee merchant whose ship <hi rend="italic">Empress of China</hi> had just
                        returned from a successful trading voyage to the Far East, as consul at the
                            <ref target="/countries/china">China</ref>’s western trading port,
                        Canton.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="framework">
                    <head>A New Framework for Foreign Affairs</head>
                    <p>The new <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/convention-and-ratification"
                            >Constitution of 1789</ref> was designed to redress the shortcomings of
                        the Articles of Confederation, and it allotted significantly more
                        responsibility for foreign affairs to the Federal Government. Article II,
                        Section 2 of the Constitution gave the President the power to make treaties
                        with the “advice and consent” of the Senate. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-constitution.jpg"/>
                            <head>The Constitution of the United States</head>
                        </figure>Practically, the clause stipulated that two-thirds of the Senators
                        would have to approve any treaty negotiated by the Executive Branch. The
                        President also was given the power to appoint ambassadors, ministers, and
                        consuls, with Senate approval. But the Legislative Branch retained the power
                        to declare war and, equally important, the power to appropriate money.</p>
                    <p>The Constitution did not give predominance in foreign affairs to the
                        Executive Branch, although early Presidents worked to establish the
                        precedent. <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName> insisted, <quote>“…the
                            President is the only channel of communication between this country and
                            foreign nations, and it is from him alone that foreign nations or their
                            agents are to learn what is or has been the will of the nation.”</quote>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-tjefferson.jpg"/>
                            <head>First Secretary of State under the Constitution, Thomas
                                Jefferson</head>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>But the President could not manage foreign policy alone. On <date
                            when="1788-05-19">May 19, 1789</date>, <persName>James
                            Madison</persName> proposed the creation of a Department of Foreign
                        Affairs under the leadership of a Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.
                        But, since there wasn’t thought to be enough work for a Department of “Home
                        Affairs,” Congress also assigned domestic duties to the new Department of
                        State. <persName>John Jay,</persName> originally appointed as Secretary of
                        Foreign Affairs under the Articles of Confederation, continued at this post
                        until 1790. As President, <persName>George Washington</persName> immediately
                        appointed <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas
                            Jefferson</ref>, then Minister to France, to be the first Secretary of
                        State. Jefferson began work on <date when="1790-03-22">March 22,
                        1790</date>. </p>
                    <p>Despite significant constraints on the Department of State in terms of budget
                        and manpower, the United States achieved a remarkable number of triumphs in
                        foreign affairs during the early years of the republic. During the 1790s,
                        the <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/jay-treaty">Jay Treaty (1794)</ref>
                        and the <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/pickney-treaty">Pinckney Treaty
                            (1795)</ref> regularized relations with England and Spain.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="diplomatictradition">
                    <head>A Diplomatic Tradition</head>
                    <p>As Secretary of State, Jefferson abhorred the intrigues and ostentation of
                        European courts, but as an experienced American diplomat, he realized that
                        if the United States was to be taken seriously, the United States had to
                        adopt some European diplomatic practices. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-gwashington.jpg"/>
                            <head>President George Washington</head>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Washington</persName> and <placeName>Jefferson</placeName> lobbied
                        Congress for a large enough appropriation to support a limited number of
                        overseas missions, in a style comparable to those of other nations.
                        Jefferson drew a distinction between a diplomatic service, conducting
                        political relations with foreign countries, and a consular service, dealing
                        with commercial matters and the needs of American citizens abroad. By 1791,
                        diplomatic missions had been established in five European countries:
                            <placeName>England</placeName>, <placeName>Spain</placeName>,
                            <placeName>France</placeName>, <placeName>Holland</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>Portugal</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Ministers concentrated on two important responsibilities: reporting on
                        significant activities in their countries of residence and executing formal
                        diplomatic instructions transmitted to them from the Department of
                        State.</p>
                    <p>By 1792, 16 consulates had been created, most of them in Europe. Jefferson
                        saw the consulates as a valuable source of intelligence, and he sent a
                        circular letter to consuls asking them to report to him regularly
                            <quote>“such political and commercial intelligence as you may think
                            interesting to the United States.”</quote> He mentioned particularly
                        news of American ships and also <quote> “information of all military
                            preparations and other indications of war, which may take place in your
                            ports.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Consuls did not receive salaries or allowances for expenses, and they lived
                        off the fees they charged for their services. Because their income was so
                        uncertain, consuls often served for many years in the same location and paid
                        little attention to their official duties. One consul in <placeName>La
                            Guaira, Venezuela</placeName>, was dismissed because <quote>“not a
                            single communication”</quote> had been received from him in seven
                        years.</p>
                    <p>The precarious nature of U.S. consuls overseas was a concern to Jefferson. He
                        feared that the few Americans overseas who were eligible to serve as consuls
                        might be in debt or <quote>“…young, ephemeral characters in commerce without
                            substance or conduct.”</quote> Even worse, if appointed, they
                            <quote>“…might disgrace the consular office, without protecting our
                            commerce.”</quote> Congress amended the law requiring consuls and
                        vice-consuls to be American citizens and, when necessary, reputable foreign
                        citizens were appointed as vice-consuls.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="style">
                    <head>American Diplomatic Style</head>
                    <p>Following the early practice of <ref
                            target="/milestones/1776-1783/b-franklin">Benjamin Franklin</ref>,
                        representatives of the United States traditionally wore unpretentious
                        clothing and adopted simple manners, a departure from the ostentatious
                        practice at European courts. Americans considered this policy appropriate
                        for emissaries of a young republic that had repudiated monarchy. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas
                            Jefferson</ref> particularly was opposed to undue ceremony and rigid
                        protocol. Later, he refused to recognize formal social distinctions at
                        dinners held in the <placeName>White House</placeName> during his
                        presidency, especially the order of precedence—i.e., seating by rank—a
                        practice that greatly annoyed the foreign diplomatic corps.</p>
                    <p>Even if the new nation’s democratic ideology had not mandated republican
                        simplicity, the meager salaries paid to American ministers would have
                        produced the same effect. In 1817, President <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James Monroe</ref>, a
                        former Minister to France and a former Secretary of State, complained to a
                        congressional committee about the nation's failure to provide sufficient
                        salaries and allowances for members of the Diplomatic Service. Monroe
                        insisted that American diplomats had to gain access to the most important
                        social circles before they could do their jobs. <quote>“By taking the proper
                            [social] ground,” Monroe wrote, “He will become acquainted with all that
                            passes and from the highest and most authentic sources... Deprive him of
                            the necessary means to sustain this ground, separate him from the circle
                            to which he belongs and he is reduced to a cipher.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Congress turned a deaf ear to these arguments, and ministers at important
                        posts such as London or Paris were forced to spend their own private
                        fortunes. As a result, only those with wealth could aspire to a diplomatic
                        career. Lack of adequate funding also meant that little or no interchange
                        took place between those serving in Washington and those overseas. The
                        diplomatic service and the consular service remained strictly separate.
                        Ultimately, these circumstances limited flexibility and interfered with the
                        development of professionalism.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="staffing">
                    <head>Staffing and Administration</head>
                    <p>Jefferson's initial staff consisted of: <list>
                            <item>a chief clerk—who physically wrote all diplomatic
                                correspondence—,</item>
                            <item>three other clerks,</item>
                            <item>one translator, and</item>
                            <item> a messenger</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Department's domestic budget for 1790, not counting the expenses of
                        employees overseas, was $7,961; a figure which included firewood and
                        stationery. <persName>Jefferson</persName> himself was paid $3,500. Total
                        expenditures in 1791, both domestic and foreign, were $56,600.</p>
                    <p>In 1807 the Department's staff included only a chief clerk, five other
                        clerks, and some part-time help, along with a few retainers. The Secretary
                        of State's salary had been raised to $5,000 per year. In 1818 a Presidential
                        order authorized a staff that included a chief clerk, seven other clerks,
                        and a few other minor employees. In 1820, expenditures for domestic
                        operations reached $87,300; the cost of overseas operations totaled
                        $253,400.</p>
                    <p>Despite the increase in expenditures, the Department of State and its foreign
                        missions were chronically overworked—and so was the Secretary of State.
                            <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-jqadams.jpg"/>
                            <head>Secretary of State John Quincy Adams</head>
                        </figure> In 1817, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy"
                            >John Quincy Adams</ref> complained of excessive responsibilities
                        shortly after assuming his duties. <quote>“Business crowds upon me from day
                            to day requiring instantaneous attention,” he wrote to his wife Louisa.
                            “Unless everything is disposed of just as it occurs, it escapes from the
                            memory and runs into the account of arrears.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Adams found that the Department’s record keeping—already somewhat
                        disorganized because of persistent staff shortages—became even more confused
                        as a result of the burning of <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>,
                        during the War of 1812 and the Department’s expanded domestic
                        responsibilities. In an attempt to straighten out the mess, Secretary Adams
                        carried out the first reorganization of the Department in 1818. An executive
                        order finally spelled out clearly the responsibilities and salaries of the
                        Department’s officers. In particular, it made the Chief Clerk the
                        highest-ranking Department officer below the Secretary and, in addition to
                        making him responsible for carrying out the Secretary’s instructions and
                        assisting him with diplomatic correspondence, the Executive Order gave him
                        oversight over all functions of the Department.</p>
                    <p>To streamline the bureaucratic process, as many as ten clerks, each of whom
                        worked in a specific subject area, reported to the Chief Clerk. Their duties
                        included writing consular and non-diplomatic correspondence, forwarding
                        commissions and other documents to American or foreign ministers, preserving
                        books and papers of the Congress, translating documents, and preparing
                        passports, certificates, and exequaturs for foreign consuls. Other clerks
                        copied and filed documents.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="development">
                    <head>The Development of Foreign Policy</head>
                    <p>During the first 50 years of the nation, diplomats were guided by the idea
                        that the United States should observe political isolation from European
                        powers during peacetime and maintain strict neutrality during periods of
                        war. Years before, <persName>Benjamin Franklin</persName> had summed up this
                        point when he wrote: <quote> “A virgin state should preserve its virgin
                            character and not go suitoring for alliances, but wait with decent
                            dignity for the application of others.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-farewell-address.jpg"/>
                        <head>Selection from Rough Draft of President George Washington's 1796
                            Farewell Address</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In his <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/washington-farewell">1796 Farewell
                            Address</ref>, President <persName>Washington</persName> argued:
                            <quote>“The great rule of conduct for us in regard to foreign nations is
                            to have with them as little political [as distinct from commercial]
                            connection as possible.”</quote> Europe, he continued, had its own set
                        of interests, and those interests were very different from those of the
                        United States. Fortunately, the state of international relations tended to
                        confer freedom of action upon the nation. <quote>“Why forego the advantages
                            of so peculiar a situation? Why, by interweaving our destiny with that
                            of any part of Europe, entangle our peace and prosperity in the toils of
                            European ambition, rival-ship, interest, humor, or caprice?” Therefore,
                            concluded Washington, "it is our true policy to steer clear of permanent
                            alliances with any portion of the foreign world, so far, I mean, as we
                            are now at liberty to do it.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although the political views of <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName> were
                        very different from those of Washington, Jefferson agreed that isolation and
                        neutrality were the most beneficial course for the United States. In his
                        First Inaugural Address <date when="1801">(1801)</date>, Jefferson spoke of
                            <quote>“Peace, commerce and honest friendship with all nations,
                            entangling alliances with none.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="gains">
                    <head>Diplomatic Gains in the Early 19th Century</head>
                    <p>The Department of State played a key role in America’s westward expansion. In
                        1803, the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/louisiana-purchase">
                            <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> Purchase</ref> brought a vast chunk of
                        the continent between Canada and Mexico under United States control.
                        President <persName>James Monroe</persName>'s Administration arranged the
                            <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/rush-bagot">Rush-Bagot Agreement of
                            1817</ref> and the Convention of 1818, which settled disputes with Great
                        Britain over the Great Lakes and the border with Canada westward along the
                        49th parallel to the Rocky Mountains, and the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1801-1829/florida">Adams-Onis (or Transcontinental)
                            Treaty</ref> with Spain (1819), which added Florida to the national
                        domain and settled the boundary with Mexico on advantageous terms. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-louisiana-purchase.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Treaty of the Louisiana Purchase</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>As the United States spread across the continent, and American prestige and
                        influence grew, diplomats worked hard to keep the European nations out of
                        the rest of the Western Hemisphere. Secretary of State <persName>John Quincy
                            Adam</persName>s succinctly summed American thought in the Monroe
                        Doctrine of 1823.</p>
                    <p>The <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref> “closed”
                        the Western Hemisphere to further colonization, announced that the United
                        States would refrain from interference in European affairs, and warned the
                        Europeans to stay out of the domestic affairs of any of the new American
                        Republics. As President Monroe’s message stated: <quote>“We could not view
                            any interposition for the purpose of oppressing [the nations of Latin
                            America], or controlling in any other manner their destiny, by any
                            European power in any other light than as the manifestation of an
                            unfriendly disposition toward the United States.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although the young United States was still too weak to enforce the Monroe
                        Doctrine, its presentation in 1823 was a clear indication that the United
                        States saw itself as the most senior of the republics and the leader of the
                        free nations of the Western Hemisphere.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="conc1">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>Foreign affairs declined in importance toward the end of this period and
                        throughout the 19th century while the nation focused on domestic expansion
                        and internal trade. Despite the great prestige of the Secretary of State in
                        the early days of the nation, Congress remained tight-fisted throughout the
                        19th century when allocating money for foreign affairs.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="expansion">
                <head>The Expansionist Years, <date when="1823">1823-1867</date>
                </head>
                <div type="subchapter">
                    <head>The Expansionist Years, 1823-1867</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-map.jpg"/>
                            <head>Early Map of U.S.</head>
                        </figure> From the birth of the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1899-1913/roosevelt-and-monroe-doctrine">Monroe
                            Doctrine</ref> in 1823 to the purchase of <ref
                            target="/milestones/1866-1898/alaska-purchase">Alaska</ref> in 1867,
                        Americans devoted their national energies to extending their borders from
                        Atlantic to Pacific and to building a diversified economy. American
                        diplomats played an integral part in that process despite a lack of funding,
                        an absence of respect, and numerous hardships abroad.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="world">
                    <head>The World in the Early-19th Century</head>
                    <p>A rare set of international circumstances gave the <placeName>United
                            States</placeName> the luxury to concentrate on domestic expansion
                        during the middle of the 19th century, because the country faced no serious
                        external threats until the <ref target="/milestones/1861-1865">Civil War
                            (1861-1865)</ref>. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-surrender-napoleon.jpg"/>
                            <head>Napoleon surrenders his sword.</head>
                        </figure> After the defeat of <persName>Napoleon</persName> in 1812, a
                        stable and complex balance of power evolved in Europe. Maintaining that
                        delicate balance deterred possible aggressors from intervention in the New
                        World, because any nation tempted to interfere in the affairs of the Western
                        Hemisphere would have would have found itself in considerable difficulty
                        from its neighbors at home. The result was that the United States enjoyed an
                        extended period of tranquility—a very different atmosphere from the days of
                        the early republic.</p>
                    <p>The United States was free to practice a liberal form of nationalism, one
                        that stressed a vague good will toward other nations rather than the pursuit
                        of an active foreign policy. <quote>“Wherever the standard of freedom has
                            been or shall be unfurled, there will her heart, her benedictions, and
                            her prayers be. But she does not go abroad in search of monsters to
                            destroy,” wrote <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName> in 1821.</quote>
                        The republic would influence the world by offering an example rather than by
                        exercising force. That sentiment would govern American foreign policy for
                        nearly 100 years, until the outbreak of World War I.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-mfillmore.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Millard Fillmore</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>For example, in response to the liberal revolutions of 1848 in Europe,
                        President <persName>Millard Fillmore</persName> insisted that the United
                        States must grant to others what it wanted for itself: the right to
                        establish <quote>“that form of government which it may deem most conducive
                            to the happiness and prosperity of its own citizens.”</quote> It became
                        an imperative for the United States not to interfere in the government or
                        internal policy of other nations. Although Americans might
                            <quote>“sympathize with the unfortunate or the oppressed everywhere in
                            their fight for freedom, our principles forbid us from taking any part
                            in such foreign contests,”</quote> Fillmore explained. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="inaction">
                    <head>A Foreign Policy of Inaction</head>
                    <p>The shift toward domestic concerns and the practice of liberal nationalism
                        slowed the growth of the Department of State throughout the 19th century.
                        Secretaries of State after 1823 fought to preserve, not expand, the
                        influence of the Department. In foreign affairs, Presidents sought the
                        counsel of the Secretary of the Treasury or the Secretary of War rather than
                        that of the Secretary of State.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-elivingston.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Edward Livingston</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The low priority attached to foreign relations resulted in the open
                        denigration of diplomacy and its practitioners. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/livingston-edward">Edward
                            Livingston</ref> himself summarized this widespread attitude, when he
                        wrote that Americans thought of their ministers as privileged characters
                            <quote>“selected to enjoy the pleasures of foreign travel at the expense
                            of the people; their places as sinecures; and their residence abroad as
                            a continued scene of luxurious enjoyment.”</quote> Congress often
                        reflected a similar view of diplomats as lazy and under-employed. For
                        example, in 1844 the House Committee on Foreign Affairs proposed to make
                        diplomats work harder by assigning ministers to serve more than one country,
                        so that only one minister would be needed to serve Bolivia, Chile, and Peru.
                        In 1859 Representative <persName>Benjamin W. Stanton</persName> of Ohio said
                        that he knew of <quote>“no area of the public service that is more
                            emphatically useless than the diplomatic service—none in the
                            world.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The practice of the “spoils system,” the award of government appointments in
                        return for political support, reinforced the idea that the Department of
                        State and the Diplomatic and Consular Services were filled with unqualified
                        loafers. President <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName> believed that
                            <quote>“the duties of public officers are . . . so plain and simple that
                            men of intelligence may readily qualify themselves for their performance
                            . . . More is lost by the long continuance of men in office than is
                            generally to be gained by their experience.”</quote> Attitudes like this
                        perpetuated both amateurism in government and a disdain for public service.
                        The egalitarian celebration of the common man worked against efforts to
                        improve the quality and status of those who conducted foreign relations.</p>
                    <p>Some ministers still gained appointment because of their experience and
                        talent. For example, two distinguished historians headed diplomatic
                        missions: <persName>George Bancroft</persName> (<placeName>United
                            Kingdom</placeName>, 1846-49) and <persName>John Lothrop
                            Motley</persName> (Austria, 1861-67). More often, however, personal
                        wealth, political services, or social position, were the only requirements.
                        Many lacked qualifications—even the most elementary knowledge of diplomatic
                        etiquette. A tale is often told, most likely apocryphal, that in 1830
                            <persName>John Randolph</persName> of Virginia actually addressed the
                        Russian Tsar, <quote>“Howya, Emperor? And how’s the madam?”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-bancroft.jpg"/>
                        <head>Distinguished historian and statesmen, George Bancroft</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>One of the few talented diplomats of the era who made a career in the
                        Diplomatic Service, Henry Wheaton, argued in vain for a professional service
                        that recognized merit and granted tenure to the deserving. Those with
                        necessary qualifications, linguistic skill, awareness of diplomatic forms,
                        and with appropriate experience, should, he thought, <quote>“be employed
                            where they can do most service, while incapable men should be turned out
                            without fear or partiality. Those who have served the country faithfully
                            and well ought to be encouraged and transferred from one court to
                            another, which is the only advancement that our system permits
                            of.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The strains of office, including domestic political criticism, imposed great
                        burdens on most Secretaries of State. One of them, <persName>John
                            Clayton</persName> of Delaware who served President <persName>Zachary
                            Taylor</persName> in <date when="1849">1849-1850</date>, noted the
                        consequences: <quote>“The situation I have filled,” he wrote, “was . . .
                            more difficult, more thorny and more liable to misrepresentation and
                            calumny than any other in the world, as I verily believe.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="reorganized">
                    <head>The Department Reorganized—Again</head>
                    <p>The difficulties of those who conducted the nation’s foreign relations led
                        two of President Jackson's Secretaries of State, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/mclane-louis">Louis McLane</ref> and
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/forsyth-john">John Forsyth</ref>,
                        to undertake another full-scale reorganization of the Department from 1833
                        to 1836. They instituted a bureau system, under the direct supervision of
                        the Chief Clerk, to permit the orderly conduct of business. The Diplomatic
                        Bureau and the Consular Bureau were the most important of the six new
                        bureaus.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-mclane.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Louis McLane</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Both bureaus were structured in the same way. In each, three clerks managed
                        overseas correspondence. One clerk was responsible for England, France,
                        Russia, and the Netherlands. Another dealt with the rest of Europe, the
                        Mediterranean, Asia, and Africa. A third communicated with the Americas. A
                        third bureau, for translating and miscellaneous other duties, supported
                        their work. Three other bureaus handled: a) domestic and administrative
                        matters, including archives, laws, and commissions; b) domestic
                        correspondence, Presidential pardons, remissions, and copyrights; and c)
                        disbursing and superintending. </p>
                    <p>As early as 1846, Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/buchanan-james">James Buchanan</ref>
                        saw a flaw in the new system and asked Congress to create the position of
                        Assistant Secretary of State, to be filled by an eminent individual with
                        diplomatic expertise. Unfortunately, Congress chose not to authorize the new
                        position until 1853. A second Assistant Secretary position was permitted in
                        1866. <persName>William Hunter</persName>, who began his service in the
                        Department in 1829, served as Chief Clerk from 1852 to 1866, when he became
                        the second assistant secretary of state. Hunter held the position until his
                        death in 1886.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-jbuchanan.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State James Buchanan</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The number of overseas missions increased from 15 in 1830 to 33 in 1860. Most
                        posts were located in Europe or Latin America, with only modest
                        representation in East Asia and the Pacific. Ministers were sent to China in
                        1843 and Japan in 1859, and a resident commission was established in the
                        Hawaiian Islands in 1843.</p>
                    <p>By 1860, 45 people held appointments in the Diplomatic Service, a remarkably
                        small staff for 33 separate missions. Some ministers were forced to
                        supplement their staffs by appointing “unpaid attachés,” usually young men
                        of private means who performed some duties in return for an introduction
                        into local society and opportunities for personal study and travel. Total
                        overseas diplomatic expenditures rose from $294,000 in 1830 to $1.1 million
                        in 1860.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="consularservices">
                    <head>Consular Services Expands; Many Hardships</head>
                    <p>Similar growth occurred in the Consular Service. The number of consulates
                        exactly doubled from 141 in 1830 to 282 in 1860, and the number of consular
                        agencies increased even more dramatically from 14 to 198 in the same period.
                        Consular Service increases reflected the growing importance and volume of
                        foreign trade. </p>
                    <p>While most diplomats were stationed in urban areas, consuls followed trade to
                        some of the roughest and most remote spots on earth. Their lives—however
                        short—were characterized by numerous hardships. The American consul at Genoa
                        during the 1840s, <persName>C. Edwards Lester</persName>, summarized the
                        situation: <quote>“An American consul is often a foreigner, almost always a
                            merchant, can’t live on his fees, nor even pay the necessary expenses of
                            his office; [he] is scolded or cursed by everybody that has anything to
                            do with him, and is expected to entertain his countrymen, not only with
                            hospitality but with a considerable degree of luxury.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Despite its difficulties, Genoa was clearly a more desirable post than the
                        Brazilian port of Pernambuco (now called Recife). In 1858, Consul Walter
                        Stapp reported from Pernambuco that one of his predecessors had resigned
                        before taking up his office because he had received <quote>“such mournful
                            accounts of this place as to disgust him in advance of his arrival.”
                            Moreover, he continued, “four others have left their bones to bake in
                            these fearfully hot sands, without a slab of stone or a stick of wood to
                            point the stranger to their graves.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Beset by difficult climates and low salaries, consuls rarely received much
                        assistance from the Government of the United States. In 1833, Secretary of
                        State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/livingston-edward">Edward
                            Livingston</ref> noted that officials in the domestic service of the
                        nation were <quote>“surrounded with the means of obtaining information and
                            advice” but that “abroad, an officer is entrusted with the most
                            important function, out of the reach of control or advice, and is left
                            with, comparatively speaking, no written rules for his
                            guidance.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="congress">
                    <head>Congress Takes a Hand in Reform</head>
                    <p>Congress took no action to improve the lives of American representatives
                        abroad until 1856, when it enacted legislation to reform the Diplomatic and
                        Consular Services. The law concentrated on the most publicized
                        problem—inadequate compensation. It prescribed salaries for ministers that
                        ranged from $10,000 per year for most locations to $17,500 per year for
                        London and Paris. While this was an adequate salary for the mid-19th
                        century, that $17,500 salary cap for heads of mission remained in effect for
                        the next 90 years. Consuls, too, were given regular salaries and the fees
                        that they collected were sent to the Treasury. Written regulations were
                        developed to improve the performance of the foreign services.</p>
                    <p>The Act of 1856 was a step forward, but it fell short of providing for truly
                        professional foreign services. For some in the Consular Service, the
                        transition was painful since consuls now had to rely solely on their
                        salaries, which were often insufficient for a comfortable lifestyle. The
                        novelist <persName>Nathaniel Hawthorne</persName>, who experienced both the
                        fee-based and salary systems as U.S. consul in Liverpool, disliked the new
                        salary arrangement. Upon leaving Liverpool in 1857, he commented that his
                        successor, to be successful, would have to be either “a rich man or a
                        rogue.” His remark was prescient. An auditor reported in 1861 that one of
                        Hawthorne’s successors as consul in Liverpool had not reported expenditures
                        of public money for three years, <quote>“contracting public and private
                            debts, which . . . probably exceed $200,000. It is perhaps some
                            consolation to know that this plunderer no longer graces the Government
                            abroad.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="achievements">
                    <head>Diplomatic Achievements</head>
                    <p>Despite the ramshackle nature of the foreign affairs establishment, the
                        Department of State was still able to make significant contributions to the
                        nation during this period. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-treaty-gh.jpg"/>
                            <head>Image of a page from the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo (1848)</head>
                        </figure> Perhaps the most striking achievement was the successful
                        resolution of many outstanding difficulties with Great Britain, the one
                        nation able to threaten the security of the United States. After the
                        unfortunate <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of
                            1812</ref>, Anglo-American controversies were all peacefully resolved:
                        the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/webster-treaty">Webster-Ashburton
                            treaty of 1842</ref> settled the boundary between northeastern Maine and
                        Canada, the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/oregon-territory">Oregon
                            treaty of 1846</ref> extended the U.S.-Canadian border to the West
                        coast, and the Clayton-Bulwer treaty of 1850 provided an understanding on
                        the construction of any future canal across Central America. </p>
                    <p>Of equal importance were successful negotiations that furthered American
                        domination of the continent. The <ref
                            target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">Treaty of Guadalupe
                            Hidalgo (1848)</ref> was of key importance because it ended the Mexican
                        War and annexed a tremendous amount of territory north and west of the Rio
                        Grande to California. The <ref
                            target="/milestones/1866-1898/alaska-purchase">purchase of Alaska</ref>
                        from Russia in 1867 was also a significant triumph for diplomacy. Despite
                        the generally amateurish nature of diplomacy at this time, no serious
                        setbacks marred the nation's foreign affairs between 1823 and 1867.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="seward">
                    <head>Secretary of State William Seward</head>
                    <p>One outstanding diplomat did serve the United States under <persName>Abraham
                            Lincoln</persName> during the most serious 19th century challenge to the
                        nation’s security—Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William Henry
                            Seward</ref>.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-wseward.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State William Seward</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The American Civil War created excellent opportunities for European nations
                        to meddle in the Western Hemisphere, either by violating the Monroe Doctrine
                        or by extending aid to the rebellious South. In the initial stages of the
                        war, Secretary of State <persName>Seward</persName>, ambitious and powerful,
                        tried to gain control of President <persName>Lincoln</persName>’s Cabinet
                        and implement policies on his own authority. Fearing that Lincoln was
                        inadequate to the task, Seward complained that the administration had no
                        policy in dealing with the seceding Southern states and he offered to take
                        over the policy functions of the Government. </p>
                    <p>Lincoln outmaneuvered Seward, but in the process gained his respect. In time,
                        the two developed a remarkably effective collaboration. Working through
                            <persName>Charles Francis Adams</persName>, the U.S. Minister in London,
                        Seward was able to prevent British recognition of the Confederate States and
                        preserve British neutrality, a move that severely handicapped the southern
                        quest for independence. The Secretary's success in fending off serious
                        trouble during the Civil War demonstrated that great achievements in foreign
                        relations almost always depended on close relations between the President
                        and the Department of State. </p>
                    <p>Perhaps in part because of his successful leadership of the Department and
                        his strong pro-Union stance, Seward was also a target of the plot that led
                        to Lincoln’s assassination in April 1865. Recuperating at home from a recent
                        carriage accident, Seward was helpless when a conspirator entered his home
                        just as Lincoln was being murdered. Seward managed to fend off the full
                        force of his attacker until his son Frederick, who was Assistant Secretary
                        of State at the time, rushed into the room to try to protect his father.
                        Secretary Seward was stabbed in the face and throat, and his son was wounded
                        more seriously. Both recovered, however, and continued to serve another four
                        years under Lincoln’s successor, President <persName>Andrew
                            Johnson</persName>. Seward is the only U.S. Secretary of State in
                        history to be the target of a would-be assassin. </p>
                    <p>Seward had two major postwar diplomatic achievements: the removal of French
                        troops from Mexico and the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1866-1898/alaska-purchase">purchase of Alaska</ref>
                        from Russia. During the Civil War, French troops had moved into Mexico,
                        ostensibly to collect debts from the bankrupt Mexican Government. Supported
                        by these troops—and in violation of the Monroe
                            Doctrine—<persName>Napoleon</persName> III of France installed the
                        Archduke <persName>Maximilian of Austria</persName> as Emperor of Mexico in
                        1864. As long as the Civil War continued, Seward could only protest. After
                        the war, Seward skillfully escalated his diplomatic protests, while
                        resisting American domestic pressures for a military expedition into Mexico.
                        In 1867, Napoleon finally acquiesced to Seward’s careful diplomacy and
                        withdrew the French troops.</p>
                    <p>Seward’s interest in buying Alaska derived from his geopolitical vision. Like
                        many 19th century American political figures, he envisioned an expanding
                        American empire increasingly involved in foreign commerce, including the
                        China trade. Although some of his expansionist initiatives were
                        unsuccessful, Seward appropriated the Midway Islands and, most important, in
                        early 1867 negotiated with the Russian minister in Washington for the
                        purchase of Alaska for $7.2 million. Although the purchase was widely
                        satirized as “Seward’s folly” or “Seward’s icebox,” the Secretary correctly
                        gauged the widespread popular support for the treaty, which the Senate
                        overwhelmingly approved.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="conc2">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The triumph of Union forces in 1865 finally ended the dispute over the
                        relative merits of national authority and states’ rights. The nation emerged
                        from the Civil War more powerful and secure than at any time in its history.
                        Because of the balance of power in Europe, the United States would remain
                        largely immune from international dangers for the next 50 years.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="worldpower">
                <head>Rise to World Power, <date when="1876">1867-1913</date>
                </head>
                <div type="subchapter">
                    <head>Rise to World Power, 1867-1913</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-tr-promises.jpg"/>
                            <head>1900 U.S. Campaign Poster </head>
                        </figure> Historians have characterized the 31 years after the Civil War as
                        the least active period in American foreign relations, but it was to be the
                        last such period in U.S. history. The <ref
                            target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">Spanish-American War
                            of 1898</ref> brought enormous change in its wake, and American
                        diplomats were forced to adapt an antiquated foreign affairs establishment
                        to the exercise of world leadership.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="worlds">
                    <head>The World in the mid-19th Century</head>
                    <p>After the Civil War, Americans took advantage of the stable international
                        balance of power to continue the dynamic process of westward expansion and
                        building a strong and powerful economy. There were few changes in nation’s
                        basic foreign policies; the overarching principles of isolation and
                        neutrality generally remained firmly entrenched. <figure
                            rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-wgresham.jpg"/>
                            <head>Secretary of State Walter Gresham </head>
                        </figure> In 1894, Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/gresham-walter-quinton">
                            <persName>Walter Q. Gresham</persName>
                        </ref> of Illinois reaffirmed Washington’s “great rule of conduct” in
                        commenting on what he deemed a questionable departure from the policy of “no
                        entangling alliances”—an agreement with Germany and Great Britain to share
                        control of the Samoan Islands. <quote>“Every nation, and especially every
                            strong nation, must sometimes be conscious of an impulse to rush into
                            difficulties that do not concern it, except in a highly imaginary way,”
                            he noted.</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The continuing national focus on domestic issues does much to explain why,
                        despite its numerous flaws, the conduct of foreign relations continued
                        unchanged. As late as 1894, an observer noted that the public was
                            <quote>“less familiar with the duties of our diplomatic and consular
                            agents than any other branch of the public service.”</quote> In a sense,
                        this was logical, because diplomatic work was carried out overseas, where it
                        could not be observed.</p>
                    <p>For most of the period, diplomacy remained mired in the past. The biographer
                        of Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John Hay</ref> later
                        described the Department in 1898 when Hay became Secretary as <quote>“an
                            antiquated feeble organization, enslaved by precedents and routine
                            inherited from another century, remote from the public gaze and
                            indifferent to it. The typewriter was viewed as a necessary evil and the
                            telephone was an instrument of last resort.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="interference">
                    <head>Political Interference and Corruption</head>
                    <p>Xenophobic Americans regularly condemned their representatives abroad as
                        subversive, and some cast doubt upon the need for any contact whatsoever
                        with the Old World and its representatives. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-ugrant.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Ulysses S. Grant</head>
                        </figure> In 1885, for example, Senator <persName>William E.
                            Robinson</persName> of New York insisted <quote>“…this diplomatic
                            service is working our ruin by creating a desire for foreign customs and
                            foreign follies. The disease is imported by our returning diplomats and
                            by the foreign ambassadors sent here by monarchs and despots to corrupt
                            and destroy our American ideals.”</quote> The Senator's solution was to
                        quarantine entering diplomats “as we quarantine foreign rags through fear of
                        cholera.” </p>
                    <p>Another familiar pattern transcended the Civil War—meddlesome political
                        interference with the Department of State and a tendency to see its overseas
                        posts as rewards for loyalty not talent. In 1869, for example, President
                            <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> made <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/washburne-elihu-benjamin">Elihu B.
                            Washburne</ref>, a friend from Galena, Illinois, the Secretary of State
                        for 12 days so that he could enjoy the prestige of the position when he took
                        up his responsibilities as Minister to France. Washburne's successor, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton Fish</ref> of
                        New York, found that he could not resist political pressure and administer
                        the Department efficiently without strong presidential support. When General
                            <persName>Orville Babcock</persName>, another of Grant's friends, tried
                        to interfere, Fish bluntly informed the President that he could not tolerate
                        such activities. If the President showed lack of confidence in him, he
                        wrote, <quote>“or when the influence of the head of the Department in the
                            administration of its affairs, or the formation of its policy, is
                            overshadowed by others, a sensible or sensitive man will appreciate that
                            the time for his retirement has arrived.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="problems">
                    <head>Problems in the Consular Service</head>
                    <p>Because the consular service expanded so rapidly during this period, incoming
                        presidential administrations found ample overseas rewards for their friends
                        and supporters. Even artists and writers, such as <persName>James Fennimore
                            Cooper</persName>, <persName>Nathaniel Hawthorne</persName>,
                            <persName>William Dean Howells</persName>, <persName>Bret
                            Harte</persName>, and <persName>Thomas Nast</persName> used their
                        political connections to secure lucrative overseas posts. Some hoped for an
                        improvement in their finances, while others were attracted by free time to
                        pursue their writing or a desire for adventure.</p>
                    <p>Despite strenuous efforts to correct them, abuses in the Consular Service
                        persisted into the late 19th century. In 1872, <persName>DeB. Randolph
                            Keim</persName>, a representative of the Department of the Treasury,
                        headed an extensive investigation of the Consular Service. He uncovered many
                        irregularities, among them collection of illegal fees, improper exercise of
                        judicial powers, fraudulent accounting, faulty administration of estates
                        left by Americans who died abroad, and issuance of illegal passports. Keim
                        thought that the most important feature of his investigation was the
                            <quote>“ingenuity displayed by consular officers, since the Act of 1856
                            particularly, in defrauding the Government and grasping gains from
                            various outside sources besides.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="accomplishments">
                    <head>Some Diplomatic Accomplishments</head>
                    <p>Despite the atmosphere of corruption surrounding diplomacy, some members of
                        the foreign services developed special competence and achieved distinguished
                        careers. Prominent among them was <persName>Eugene Schuyler</persName>, who
                        first served as consul in Moscow in 1867 and later held other posts in
                        Europe, before ending his service as the American representative in Cairo in
                        1890. Another was <persName>William Lindsay Scruggs</persName>, who served
                        as Minister to Colombia in 1873 and Minister to Venezuela in 1889.
                            <persName>George P. Marsh</persName> served the United States for 33
                        years as Minister to Turkey (1849-53), special emissary in Athens and Tehran
                        (1850s), and Minister to Italy (1861). He died in Rome in 1882. Two
                        diplomats who developed impressive reputations as regional
                            specialists—<persName>Henry White</persName> in Europe and
                            <persName>William W. Rockhill</persName> in East Asia—began careers that
                        extended well into the 20th century.</p>
                    <p>Despite the general lethargy characterizing foreign policy during this
                        period, several Secretaries of State were proactive. <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">James G.
                            Blaine</ref> of Maine, for example, had long been interested in the
                        development of more cordial relations and the expansion of trade with the
                        American republics. In 1889, he inaugurated the modern Pan American movement
                        with the convocation of an inter-American conference in Washington.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps the most notable development was the elevation of the Monroe Doctrine
                        into an unquestioned article of faith in American foreign policy. In 1895,
                        Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/olney-richard"
                            >Richard Olney</ref> asserted that as a result of the Monroe Doctrine,
                            <quote>“To-day the United States is practically sovereign on this
                            continent, and its fiat is law upon the subjects to which it confines
                            its interposition.” Why was this so? Because, Olney stated, in addition
                            to all other grounds, “its infinite resources combined with its isolated
                            position render it master of the situation and practically invulnerable
                            as against any or all other powers.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="Departmental-reorg">
                    <head>Departmental Organization—and Reorganization</head>
                    <p>The limited importance assigned to foreign relations after the Civil War was
                        reflected in the modest growth of the Department of State and the foreign
                        services. In 1880, the Department had only 80 employees compared with 42 in
                        1860, and the total actually dropped to 76 in 1890. In the period 1860-1890,
                        the number of diplomatic missions increased by only eight to 41, while the
                        number of consulates grew from 282 to 323. Diplomats numbered 45 in 1860 and
                        63 in 1890. The Consular Service expanded much more rapidly, employing 1,042
                        people in 1890 compared with 236 in 1860. Expenditures on domestic and
                        foreign operations rose from $1.3 million in 1860 to only $1.8 million in
                        1890. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-hfish.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Hamilton Fish</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In the early 1870s, Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton Fish</ref>
                        reorganized the Department, expanding the existing “bureau” system, in place
                        since the 1830s. To cope with the growth in overseas missions and
                        consulates, Fish established two diplomatic bureaus and two consular bureaus
                        with geographic responsibilities. The First Diplomatic Bureau and the First
                        Consular Bureau, dealt with the major European nations, China, and Japan.
                        The second pair of bureaus managed communications with the rest of the
                        world—Latin America, the Mediterranean region, Russia, Hawaii, Japan, and
                        Liberia. Several other bureaus were created or underwent name changes—the
                        Law Bureau, Bureaus of Accounts, Bureau of Indexes and Archives, the
                        Statistical Bureau, Bureau of Pardons and Commissions, the Passport Bureau,
                        and the Domestic Records Bureau. Congress also passed legislation in 1874
                        that authorized a Third Assistant Secretary as well as a private secretary
                        to the Secretary of State. There would be no further reorganization until
                        1909.</p>
                    <p>In 1875 the Department of State moved into an imposing new home—the <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/buildings/section27">State, War, and Navy
                            Building</ref> located at 17th Street and Pennsylvania Avenue, N.W.,
                        adjacent to the White House.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="practice">
                    <head>The Practice of Diplomacy</head>
                    <p>From the earliest days of the Republic, a U.S. envoy overseas was known as
                        “minister” since an “ambassador” traditionally was the representative of a
                        king. But in 1893, the United States bowed to the now-common diplomatic
                        practice and upgraded its envoys to the most important foreign nations to
                        the rank of ambassador. Embassies were established in Great Britain, France,
                        Germany, and Italy after those nations conferred ambassadorial rank on their
                        representatives in Washington. The elevation of ministers to ambassadors and
                        legations to embassies was a gradual process and continued until the late
                        1960s when all U.S. chiefs of mission finally held the rank of
                        ambassador.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="superpower">
                    <head>
                        <date when="1898">1898: </date>The Birth of a Superpower</head>
                    <p>The global equilibrium, which had allowed the United States to grow and
                        prosper in virtual isolation since 1815 was gone forever as the result of a
                        short but shattering war. In 1898, U.S. domestic support for the
                        independence of <placeName>Cuba</placeName> enmeshed the United States in a
                        struggle with Spain over the fate of the island nation. The decision to aid
                        the Cuban resistance was a major departure from the traditional American
                        practice of liberal nationalism, and the results of that decision had
                        far-reaching consequences. The 1898 Treaty of Paris ending the war gave Cuba
                        its independence and also ceded important Spanish possessions to the United
                        States—notably Puerto Rico, the Philippines, and the small island of Guam.
                        The United States was suddenly a colonial power with overseas
                        dependencies.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-puerto-rico.jpg"/>
                        <head>Photograph of American Soliders in Puerto Rico during the
                            Spanish-American War</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>This assumption of colonial responsibilities reflected not only the temporary
                        enthusiasms of 1898 but also marked a profound change in the diplomatic
                        posture of the United States. The foreign policies of the early 19th century
                        had less relevance at the dawn of the 20th century because the nation had
                        changed. The United States had almost all the attributes of a great power—it
                        stood ahead or nearly ahead of almost all other countries in terms of
                        population, geographic size and location on two oceans, economic resources,
                        and military potential.</p>
                    <p>Foreign policy had to change to meet these new circumstances. President
                            <persName>William McKinley</persName> drew attention to the new
                        situation in the instructions he gave to the delegation of American
                        statesmen who negotiated the Treaty of Paris. “We cannot be unmindful that
                        without any desire or design on our part the war has brought us new duties
                        and responsibilities which we must meet and discharge as becomes a great
                        nation on whose growth and career from the beginning the Ruler of Nations
                        has plainly written the high command and pledge of civilization.” </p>
                    <p>Another contemporary observer, <persName>George L. Rives</persName>, extended
                        this interpretation. <quote>“Whether we like it or not,” he wrote, “it is
                            plain that the country is now entering into a period in its history in
                            which it will necessarily be brought into far closer and more complex
                            relations with all the other great Powers of the world,” an outcome that
                            would leave established foreign policy outmoded. “We shall now and
                            henceforth be looked upon as having cast aside our traditional attitude
                            of isolation.”</quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="newpolicies">
                    <head>New Policies for Latin America, Asia</head>
                    <p>U.S. policy toward Latin American policy involved a significant revision of
                        the Monroe Doctrine. Throughout the 19th century, American diplomats used
                        the Monroe Doctrine to warn the European powers against further colonization
                        in the Western Hemisphere. It did not imply the right of the United States
                        to intervene in the internal affairs of the other American republics.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-troosevelt.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Theodore Roosevelt</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In 1904, President <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName>changed the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref> through his
                            <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/roosevelt-and-monroe-doctrine"
                            >“Roosevelt Corollary.”</ref> Roosevelt and other prominent Americans
                        were concerned that European creditor nations would use the unpaid debt of
                        the Latin American states to gain political control over them. Roosevelt
                        said that no Latin American nation adhering to “acceptable international
                        standards of behavior” had to fear intervention by the United States. But:
                            <quote>“Chronic wrongdoing, or an impotence which results in a general
                            loosening of the ties of civilized society, may in America, as
                            elsewhere, require intervention by some civilized nation.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Moreover, he continued, <quote>“in the western hemisphere the adherence of
                            the United States to the Monroe Doctrine may force the United States,
                            however reluctantly, in flagrant cases of such wrongdoing or impotence,
                            to the exercise of an international police power.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the same time, the acquisition of the Philippines triggered the
                        development of a new American policy for East Asia. As American businessmen
                        eyed the vast potential of the Chinese market, European incursions in
                            <placeName>China</placeName> threatened to cut off American access. In
                        1899, Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John Hay</ref>
                        proposed that nations interested in China should “enjoy perfect equality of
                        treatment for navigation,” that is, maintain the principle of free trade, or
                        the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/hay-and-china">“open door.”</ref> In
                        1900, Hay extended the open-door policy to include respect for the
                        territorial and administrative integrity of China.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="prestige">
                    <head>New Prestige, New Growth</head>
                    <p>These major changes in policy and the subsequent increase in U.S.
                        international political commitments resulted in a newly invigorated
                        Department of State. The Department was thoroughly reorganized to meet its
                        new responsibilities and important steps were taken toward the development
                        of professional, democratic foreign services.</p>
                    <p>In 1898, the Department employed 82 people; by 1910 the number had risen to
                        234. The Diplomatic Service grew modestly from 93 people in 1900 to 121 in
                        1910. But expansion required a considerable increase in the annual budget.
                        The expenditures of the Department at home and overseas increased from $3.4
                        million in 1900 to $4.9 million in 1910. The Consular Service also
                        experienced a significant addition to its workload. Reflecting the boom in
                        overseas trade from $1.8 billion to $3 billion, annual fees collected almost
                        tripled in less than 20 years. </p>
                    <p>Increased responsibility necessitated a thorough reorganization of the
                        Department in 1909. One reformer, Assistant Secretary of State
                            <persName>Francis M. Huntington Wilson</persName>, succeeded in
                        increasing the number of leadership positions, so that the Department now
                        had three Assistant Secretaries of State, a Counselor to undertake a
                        Counselor to undertake special assignments, and a Director to administer the
                        Consular Service.</p>
                    <p>The bureau system was expanded to organize diplomacy by distinct geographic
                        region—Western Europe, the Near East, the Far East, and Latin America—a move
                        that fostered improved overseas communication. Several other bureaus and
                        divisions were created to handle other new areas of responsibility, notably
                        a Bureau of Trade Relations and a Division of Information. Talented
                        diplomats were brought back to Washington to staff the new geographic
                        bureaus, adding much-needed field experience.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="professionalism">
                    <head>A New Professionalism</head>
                    <p>Although the expansion and reorganization of the Department were significant
                        factors, the most distinctive feature of the early 20th century was a strong
                        movement toward fully professionalized and democratic foreign services.
                        America’s new position in the world forced the nation to recognize that
                        amateurism in the conduct of foreign policy could be costly. One critic
                        wrote, <quote>“As we would not put a ship into the hands of a commander
                            ignorant of navigation, an army under the control of a general without
                            military training, a suit at law into the hands of a counsel who never
                            opened a law book . . . so we should not put the foreign affairs of our
                            government into the hands of men without knowledge of the various
                            subjects which go to make up the diplomatic science.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-troosevelt.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Theodore Roosevelt</head>
                        </figure> President <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName> agreed and
                        emphasized the need to upgrade diplomatic performance: <quote>“The trouble
                            with our ambassadors in stations of real importance,” he told a friend,
                            "is that they totally fail to give us real help and real information,
                            and seem to think that the life work of an ambassador is a kind of
                            glorified pink tea party.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The domestic spirit of “progressivism” and an emphasis on good government
                        fueled the demand for change in the Diplomatic and Consular Services. A
                        truly professional foreign service meant that the practices of the past
                        would have to end. The spoils system would have to be replaced by
                        competitive examination and guaranteed tenure; the merit system would have
                        to be adopted as the basis for award of pay increases and promotions, and
                        pay and allowances would have to be adequate to the job. As President
                        Roosevelt told a friend in 1908, <quote>“I am anxious to have it understood
                            that it is not necessary to be a multimillionaire in order to reach the
                            highest positions in the American diplomatic services.” Or, as
                            Representative Frank O. Lowden of Illinois expressed it, “It ought to be
                            possible for the lowest man in the foreign service to feel that it is
                            within his power, if his service justifies it, to reach the highest
                            post.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-gcleveland.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Grover Cleveland</head>
                        </figure>President <persName>Grover Cleveland</persName> anticipated the
                        reform movement in 1895, when he issued an executive order that made
                        appointment to most positions in the Consular Service contingent upon
                        passing written and oral examinations. Unfortunately, the reform was short
                        lived because the President himself selected the individuals who would take
                        the examinations. When President <persName>McKinley</persName> took office
                        and was determined to appoint his own consular officers, Cleveland’s
                        executive order was ignored. Only one person out of 112 applicants failed
                        the tests. When <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/root-elihu">Elihu
                            Root</ref> became Secretary of State, he noted, “It has evidently come
                        to be regarded as cruel and inhuman treatment not to pass a man. In view of
                        the character of the examination, a rejection would practically be an
                        imputation of idiocy.”</p>
                    <p>Presidents Theodore Roosevelt and <persName>William Howard Taft</persName>
                        took the most serious steps toward reform. In November 1905, President
                        Roosevelt established competitive entrance examinations and the merit
                        promotion system for all diplomatic and consular positions except those of
                        minister and ambassador. His Secretary of State, Elihu Root, shepherded a
                        law through Congress that created a grade classification system for consular
                        positions and also provided for the inspection of consular establishments
                        every two years. However, this statute did not mention President Roosevelt’s
                        reforms; Roosevelt remedied this omission by means of another executive
                        order issued in June 1906.</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-wtaft.jpg"/>
                            <head>President William Howard Taft</head>
                        </figure>During his Administration, President Taft set up a board of
                        examiners to administer both oral and written examinations to prospective
                        diplomats. He also ordered that vacancies in the higher ranks of secretaries
                        of legations and embassies be filled only from within the career service and
                        that for the purposes of retention and promotion, the efficiency records be
                        maintained for every diplomatic officer and clerk in the Department. While
                        these measures did not include ministers or ambassadors, both Roosevelt and
                        Taft rewarded several secretaries with appointments as chiefs of mission.
                        Taft, for instance, promoted 18 from the diplomatic service to ministerships
                        or ambassadorships.</p>
                    <p>American missions overseas were also subject to reform. It became clear that
                        there was a need to establish and maintain embassy and legation buildings
                        appropriate to the nation’s new status in international affairs and
                        business. As one reformer argued, <quote>“All men, rich and poor, cultivated
                            or uncultivated, are impressed by appearances. Foreigners necessarily
                            judge us by what they see of us in their own country. We pride ourselves
                            on being the richest people on earth and declare loudly that nothing is
                            too good for us. And yet we are content to cheapen ourselves among the
                            nations of the earth by the shabby showing we make among them in respect
                            to our embassies. We feel ashamed at appearing poverty-stricken in the
                            eyes of the inhabitants of other countries and of placing ourselves
                            commercially below third or even fourth rate powers.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Similarly, a former attaché promoted the enhancement of U.S. facilities
                        abroad so that <quote>“traveling Americans will no longer be mortified at
                            the sight of the United States embassy or legation being located on a
                            single floor in an apartment house or office building with a tin shield
                            over the door far inferior in appearance to that of many a butcher or
                            baker in the vicinity.”</quote> In response to the rising complaints,
                        Congress took a step forward when it passed the Lowden Act (1911), the first
                        legislation to provide for the purchase of buildings to house overseas
                        missions. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="conc3">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The Spanish-American War of 1898 revealed the first cracks in the
                        international balance of power that had governed global relations since
                        1815. The United States entered the 20th century as an emerging
                        superpower—and adopted new foreign policies and professional diplomatic
                        practices to suit its role. The revitalized Department of State had little
                        time to prepare for the unprecedented challenges that the United States
                        would face during the first European war in 100 years.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="globalconflict">
                <head>The Challenge of Global Conflict, <date when="1913">1913-1945</date>
                </head>
                <div type="subchapter">
                    <head>The Challenge of Global Conflict, 1913-1945</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-wilson-wwi.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Woodrow Wilson announcing the U.S. Declaration of War
                                against Germany before Congress</head>
                        </figure> The First World War was one of the great turning points in modern
                        history. The 1914-1918 conflict triggered a period of international
                        disequilibrium that would characterize most of the 20th century, generating
                        political turbulence and organized violence on a hitherto unimaginable
                        scale. The Department of State would struggle to meet the new
                        challenges.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="worldin1914">
                    <head>The World in 1914</head>
                    <p>The First World War greatly affected the international position of the United
                        States because it shattered the general global stability that had cocooned
                        the nation for almost 100 years. Political isolation, however appropriate
                        during the 19th century, no longer served the national interest, and the
                        country was pulled into foreign entanglements unthinkable just a few years
                        earlier.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-wwi.jpg"/>
                        <head>Soldier during World War One</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>When war broke out in <date when="1914">1914</date> between the Allied Powers
                        (Great Britain, France, Russia, Japan, and later Italy) and the Central
                        Powers (Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Turkey), the United States announced a
                        policy of strict neutrality in keeping with tradition. This position was
                        untenable when American shipping came under repeated attack from German
                        U-boats.</p>
                    <p>During the period of American neutrality (1914-1917), attitudes toward
                        international affairs born in the wake of the Spanish-American War
                        blossomed. As its global interests expanded, United States found itself in
                        conflict with another rising power—Germany. Ironically, American interests
                        were frequently aligned with those of an old enemy, Great Britain. The war
                        exacerbated the trend, and a tense diplomatic conflict with Germany over the
                        legality of unrestricted submarine warfare against neutral shipping simply
                        accelerated a political process that had begun some years earlier.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="war">
                    <head>America Enters the War; Wilson's Plan for Peace</head>
                    <p>The entry of the United States into the First World War in April 1917 as an
                        “associate”—not ally—of the Allies, was more than just a response to
                        submarine warfare; it also reflected the vision of President Woodrow Wilson.
                            <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-wwilson.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Woodrow Wilson</head>
                        </figure> By 1917, the war had grown into a quasi-global conflict, verging
                        on total war and completely unlike any conflict before it. Wilson thought
                        that the United States alone could shape an effective peace settlement
                        because he believed that the combatants were politically and morally
                        bankrupt. Wilson felt that American intervention in 1917 would ensure that
                        the United States would play a decisive role and dominate the postwar peace
                        conference.</p>
                    <p>The President's plan for the future, outlined in the “Fourteen Points”
                        (January 1918) and augmented by later pronouncements, envisioned restoration
                        of a stable, equitable, and enduring international balance through a new
                        collective security organization, the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1914-1920/league">League of Nations</ref>, based on
                        a consensus of the great powers. Due in large part to Wilson's vision, the
                        United States had changed course from isolation toward engagement.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="newchallenges">
                    <head>New Challenges for the Department</head>
                    <p>The fundamental shift in foreign policy that accompanied World War I posed
                        great challenges for the Department of State as it assumed duties never
                        anticipated in earlier years. Both the Diplomatic and Consular Services
                        expanded their reporting functions to provide much needed information and
                        augmented their diplomatic and consular efforts. During the years of
                        neutrality, American missions located in belligerent countries often acted
                        as caretakers for the interests of countries on the other side of the
                        conflict. The U.S. Embassy in Berlin, for example, represented British,
                        Japanese, and Italian interests in Germany until the United States abandoned
                        neutrality.</p>
                    <p>The burgeoning responsibilities of the foreign services led to an increase in
                        personnel and expenditures. Many temporary employees were assigned to duties
                        at home and overseas, and resignations and retirements were minimized in an
                        attempt to retain experienced officers. Congress authorized a significant
                        number of new permanent positions, including 27 in the Diplomatic Service,
                        for a total of 97. The domestic complement grew from 234 employees in 1910
                        to 708 one decade later. Expenditures jumped from $4.9 million in 1910 to
                        $13.6 million in 1920.</p>
                    <p>For the first time since the very earliest years of the nation, the American
                        people were interested in foreign affairs. As a result, the Department
                        attracted considerable attention and even praise, a welcome change from the
                        general apathy or distrust that characterized the heyday of isolation. The
                        rise of the “new diplomacy,” a term used to describe statecraft responsive
                        to the desires of popular majorities, brought international politics and its
                        practitioners fully into the consciousness of people who had never before
                        been concerned with foreign relations.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="advisors">
                    <head>Other Foreign Policy Advisors</head>
                    <p>Despite its expanded operational responsibilities and its increased
                        respectability, the Department of State lost much of its influence on the
                        formulation of major foreign policy decisions. Almost all the significant
                        decisions of the conflict—to pursue strict neutrality in 1914, to intervene
                        on behalf of the Allies in 1917, to champion the League of Nations in 1918,
                        and to negotiate a peace treaty on American terms in 1919—emanated from the
                        White House without decisive contributions from the Secretary of State and
                        his subordinates.</p>
                    <p>Several factors contributed to the displacement of the Department of State as
                        the principal source of advice about the most crucial questions of war and
                        peace. One key factor was that none of President Wilson’s Secretaries of
                        State had a close and confidential relationship with him. Wilson relied
                        primarily on others for advice, notably an intimate friend, Edward M. House
                        of Texas. A less obvious but equally significant factor was that the
                        Department was poorly organized to meet the requirements of wartime. It
                        tended to act slowly, and it lacked expertise in dealing with military
                        issues. Moreover, the exigencies of the national emergency dictated the
                        participation of many agencies in decisions about foreign relations, notably
                        the War Department, the Navy Department, and the Treasury, as well as
                        temporary organizations such as the War Industries Board. The Department of
                        State was not prepared to take a leading role in coordinating these
                        activities. Finally, modern communications rendered the President less
                        dependent on the Department for accurate information than past presidents
                        had been.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="modernization">
                    <head>Modernization of the Department</head>
                    <p>The experience of modern warfare demonstrated that the Department of State
                        would have to undergo major changes. As early as 1915, in response to the
                        wartime pressures on the Diplomatic and Consular Services, Congress passed
                        the Stone-Flood Act, which permitted the appointment of certain diplomatic
                        and consular officers to functional positions rather than to specific posts
                        in the field. Prior to this, consular officers who wanted to transfer to the
                        Diplomatic Service had to take the examinations, and oral examiners who
                        might want to keep diplomacy the preserve of men from the “right schools” or
                        “right families” could reject the candidates, despite their experience. In
                        addition to assignment after examination or presidential appointment, the
                        1915 law permitted reassignment by administrative transfer.</p>
                    <p>But even after the war, the public believed that the modernization of
                        American diplomatic practice was still far from complete. In January 1920,
                        Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert"
                            >Robert Lansing</ref>, writing to a sympathetic Congressman, John Jacob
                        Rogers of Massachusetts, described the problem: <quote>“The machinery of
                            government provided for dealing with our foreign relations is in need of
                            complete repair and reorganization. As adequate as it may have been when
                            the old order prevailed and the affairs of the world were free from the
                            present perplexities it has ceased to be responsive to present
                            needs.”</quote> Three categories of reform were required to enable the
                        Department to function effectively under the changed conditions of the
                        postwar period: <list>
                            <item>(I) The foreign services had to be fully professionalized and
                                democratized;</item>
                            <item>(II) The structure of the Department had to be modernized to deal
                                effectively with a whole range of new policy initiatives; and</item>
                            <item>(III) Relations between the Department and other participants in
                                the foreign policy process had to be clarified and conducted in a
                                new institutional context.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="rogers">
                    <head>The Rogers Act</head>
                    <p>After the war ended, Congress completed the pre-war movement toward a fully
                        professional and democratic Foreign Service. Representative Rogers, who led
                        the congressional campaign, stated his objective in 1923: “Let us strive for
                        a foreign service which will be flexible and democratic; which will attract
                        and retain the best men we have; which will offer reasonable pay, reasonable
                        prospects for promotion, [and] reasonable provision against want when old
                        age comes to a faithful servant.” Hugh Gibson, a respected diplomat
                        interested in reform, supported Rogers, arguing that improvements in the
                        Diplomatic and Consular Services would attract the most qualified candidates
                        so that “we can choose our men by the only good method—that is, by keen
                        competition.” He hoped for creation of “a real diplomatic career, which is
                        open to any American citizen who has the necessary qualifications.” </p>
                    <p>In 1924, the Rogers Act fundamentally reformed the foreign services by
                        establishing a career organization based on competitive examination and
                        merit promotion. The Diplomatic and Consular Services were unified into one
                        organization performing both functions. Members of the new “Foreign Service
                        of the United States of America” would be commissioned in a given class at a
                        set salary rather than commissioned for service at a specific overseas
                        mission or post. Salaries would range from $3,000 for the lowest level
                        (Class 9) to $9,000 for Class 1 officers. Officers would be placed in
                        positions for three years with the presumption of regular rotation to other
                        assignments. The Rogers Act granted regular home leave and set up a
                        retirement system. It also allowed for representational expenses, although
                        these allowances were not authorized until 1931. A special reinstatement
                        provision permitted career officers who became chiefs of mission to remain
                        in the Foreign Service after completing their tours of duty. Earlier they
                        had been required to resign without assurance of a future presidential
                        appointment to other responsible duties, which led at times to the
                        discarding of the most experienced and competent officers at the height of
                        their abilities.</p>
                    <p>Several other measures also furthered reform. In 1925, the Foreign Service
                        School was founded to provide specialized training in languages and other
                        necessary skills. The following year, Congress passed the Foreign Service
                        Buildings Act; among other things, it established a fund of $2-million per
                        year—gradually increasing in later years—for the construction, purchase, and
                        maintenance of missions and consulates overseas. The U.S. Government also
                        took responsibility for the purchase or rental of office space and living
                        quarters, further reducing a need for private wealth as a prerequisite to a
                        diplomatic career. </p>
                    <p>Despite these improvements, certain flaws in the Rogers Act became apparent,
                        especially inequities in the promotion of those serving in consular
                        assignments. Congress moved to correct the problems in the Moses-Linthicum
                        Act (1931), which reorganized the Board of Foreign Service Personnel to
                        ensure impartial promotion practices. Other sections of the law improved
                        salaries, authorized representation and post allowances and paid annual
                        leave and sick leave, set up an improved retirement system, and conferred
                        career status on clerks in the Foreign Service. Reflecting on these reforms,
                        Assistant Secretary of State <persName>Wilbur J. Carr</persName> noted that
                        “the Foreign Service had finally attained the goal for which Presidents,
                        Secretaries of State, and businessmen of the country had striven for years,
                        namely, a reasonable, adequate provision in the way of pay and allowances
                        for the men who served the United States in a diplomatic or consular
                        capacity in foreign countries.”</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately many of these gains proved temporary. During the <ref
                            target="/milestones/great-depression">Great Depression</ref>, economies
                        in government led to the suspension of promotions, a 15 per cent reduction
                        in salaries, abolition of representational and living allowances,
                        elimination of paid home leaves, and suspension of recruiting for four
                        years. The result was a 10 percent reduction in the size of the Foreign
                        Service between July 1932 and December 1934.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="incremental">
                    <head>Incremental Reorganization</head>
                    <p>In 1924, the Secretary of State—who had final responsibility for policy and
                        administration—had relatively few senior officials to help him. The Under
                        Secretary provided support on policies of special importance. Three
                        Assistant Secretaries handled economic and financial questions,
                        international law, and general administration. The Chief Clerk supervised
                        both the Department's clerks and its physical property, while the Director
                        of the Consular Service also served as budget officer. The Solicitor handled
                        legal business, and the Economic Adviser made recommendations concerning
                        international trade and finance. Various other bureaucratic entities, such
                        as the Division of Passport Control and the Bureau of Accounts, provided
                        additional support. Five geographic bureaus maintained communications
                        between Washington and missions abroad.</p>
                    <p>When problems grew acute or new responsibilities arose, limited modifications
                        were made to the 1909 bureaucratic structure. For example, a Division of
                        Publications was established in 1921 to centralize work on informational
                        projects such as the documentary series Foreign Relations of the United
                        States. In 1929, a Division of International Conferences and Protocol was
                        formed to cope with the very substantial increase in multilateral
                        negotiations. Two new divisions were created in 1938—a Division of
                        International Communications and a Division of Cultural Relations.</p>
                    <p>But in real terms, growth in the Department of State stagnated. Between 1920
                        and 1930, the domestic work force increased by only six to 714, the Foreign
                        Service grew from 514 to 633, and annual expenditures rose from $13.6
                        million to $14 million.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="return">
                    <head>A Return to Isolationism</head>
                    <p>But the changes weren’t enough. The failure to fully modernize the Department
                        of State reflected the country’s lack of commitment to an energetic foreign
                        policy after the Senate repudiated the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Treaty of Versailles</ref>.
                            <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-hughes.jpg"/>
                            <head>Secretary of State Charles Evans Hughes</head>
                        </figure> Woodrow Wilson was the first American president to envision the
                        United States as a global leader, but the nation was not yet ready to accept
                        responsibilities commensurate with its power.</p>
                    <p>During the 1920s, the United States strongly resisted binding international
                        commitments and focused instead on preventing the outbreak of war. Secretary
                        of State Charles Evans Hughes played a key role in the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1921-1936/naval-conference">Washington Naval
                            Disarmament Conference (1921-22)</ref>, and Secretary of State Frank
                        Kellogg was instrumental in the creation of the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1921-1936/kellogg">Paris Peace Pact (1928)</ref>, a
                        multilateral agreement outlawing offensive warfare. <figure
                            rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-kellogg.jpg"/>
                            <head>Secretary of State Frank Kellogg</head>
                        </figure> Although clear dangers emerged during the Great Depression of the
                        1930s, the massive economic shocks reinforced the country's isolationist
                        inclinations during the rise of totalitarianism.</p>
                    <p>As a result, the Department of State returned to the passivity of the 19th
                        century, and accepted a secondary role from 1919-1939. One historian has
                        described the generally backward state of the organization when Secretary
                            <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Cordell Hull</ref>
                        assumed control. He wrote: “In 1933 the Department was small, placid,
                        comfortably adjusted to the lethargic diplomacy of the preceding decade, and
                        suffused with habits of thought that reached back to a still earlier day.”
                        Overseas missions were in a comparable state, he noted. “The Foreign
                        Service—genteel, slow-moving, and complacent—also cherished its ties with
                        the past.”</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="nuetrality">
                    <head>“Interventionist” Neutrality</head>
                    <p>But the neglectful attitude toward foreign relations characteristic of the
                        interwar years, changed rapidly after the start of the Second World War. The
                        undeniable menace of the Axis—Nazi Germany and its partners Italy and
                        Japan—forced the United States to pursue an interventionist policy. Despite
                        an official stance of neutrality, President Franklin D. Roosevelt authorized
                        the sale of destroyers to Great Britain in return for leases on some Western
                        Atlantic bases and eventually provided wholesale economic assistance to the
                        United Kingdom and the Soviet Union through the Lend-Lease Act of 1941.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-fdr-lend.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Franklin D. Roosevelt signing the Lend-Lease Act of
                            1941</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>As the Nazis began the systematic persecution of Jews first in Germany and
                        then later in occupied Europe, the United States faced a major crisis in
                        refugee policy. Even though the nation admitted more refugees from Nazi
                        tyranny than any other country, the United States had the capacity to admit
                        many more. But the American public was still isolationist and
                        anti-Semitic—and preoccupied with domestic economic problems. Since
                        Americans were apathetic toward the plight of the refugees, there was little
                        chance of persuading Congress to increase the existing national origins
                        quotas. Although President Roosevelt was sympathetic, he did not use his
                        office to implement changes in U.S. refugee policy.</p>
                    <p>The Department of State, mirroring the public mood, also failed to lead on
                        the issue, and anti-Semitism influenced policy at a key level. An historian
                        of the refugee crisis has concluded, “The Department of State compiled a
                        dismal record. It discouraged or actively opposed virtually all efforts for
                        a more generous American policy . . . It obstructed the emergency visa
                        program for political refugees. And it tolerated consuls whose anti-alien,
                        anti-Semitic, and politically conservative attitudes influenced their
                        decisions in visa cases.” </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="wartime">
                    <head>Wartime Diplomacy</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="../secretaries/hull-cordell.jpg"/>
                            <head>Secretary of State Cordell Hull</head>
                        </figure> The United States entered the war when the Japanese attacked <ref
                            target="/milestones/1937-1945/PearlHarbor">Pearl Harbor</ref> on
                        December 7, 1941. The Department faced immediate new burdens and
                        responsibilities from evacuating Americans from combat zones, representing
                        the interests of belligerents in enemy countries, and assisting
                        prisoner-of-war exchanges, to maintaining liaison with the International Red
                        Cross and dealing with refugees. During the war, Department officials also
                        helped coordinate the activities of various agencies created to mobilize the
                        nation for total war and to assist in the reconstruction of liberated
                        territories. The Department of State also created a complex system of
                        efficient international communication.</p>
                    <p>The Department’s staff grew at an unprecedented rate. In 1940, the Department
                        had 1,128 domestic employees, with total expenditures of $24 million. By
                        1945, the staff had more than tripled (3,767 employees) with a budget of
                        about $50 million. Recruiting for the career Foreign Service was suspended
                        during the war, but a Foreign Service Auxiliary was created to provide
                        additional manpower. By January 1946, the Auxiliary included 976 people.</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-hawallace.jpg"/>
                            <head>Vice President Henry A. Wallace</head>
                        </figure> However, like Wilson during WWI, President Roosevelt relied on
                        other advisers—such as Harry Hopkins, Vice President Henry A. Wallace,
                        General George C. Marshall, Under Secretary of State Sumner Welles, and
                        Secretary of the Treasury Henry Morgenthau, Jr.—and largely ignored the
                        advice of the Secretary of State.</p>
                    <p>Although Secretary <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell"
                            >Cordell Hull</ref> was usually informed of important decisions, he
                        rarely participated in the major wartime conferences at which the leaders of
                        the alliance forged the victory of 1945. His inability to gain the
                        President's full confidence kept the Department from a paramount role in
                        many major decisions. It is not surprising that Secretary Hull commented
                        bitterly toward the end of his service: <quote>“When I accepted this office,
                            I knew that I would be misrepresented, lied about, let down, and that
                            there would be humiliations that no man in private life could accept and
                            keep his self-respect. But I made up my mind in advance that I would
                            accept all these things and just do my job.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Secretary Hull proved influential only in one area—preparation of plans for a
                        postwar international organization. In 1942, Hull established an Advisory
                        Committee on Postwar Foreign Policy to avoid the partisan fighting that
                        characterized the period after World War I. In 1944, representatives of 44
                        nations met at <ref target="/milestones/bretton-woods">Bretton Woods</ref>
                        to agree on plans for post-war economic policy, to stabilize currency, and
                        to establish a World Bank. Later that year at the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1937-1945/war-time-conferences">Dumbarton Oaks
                            conference</ref>, world leaders hammered out a draft charter for a new
                        international organization—the United Nations. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="embarrasment">
                    <head>Embarrassment Brings Change</head>
                    <p>In 1943, Under Secretary of State Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. immediately began
                        a major reorganization of the Department of State because of the
                        embarrassments that stemmed directly from wartime experience. As one
                        journalist summarized the situation: “Notwithstanding the personal prestige
                        of the Secretary of State Hull, the organization he heads has only to be
                        mentioned in almost any circle, American or foreign, to arouse either doubt,
                        despair, or derision.” Stettinius’ reorganization marked the birth of the
                        modern Department of State. His reforms ensured that the Department would
                        participate effectively in shaping the nation’s foreign relations in the
                        postwar period.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/stettinius-edward-reilly.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Stettinius concentrated on key deficiencies of the Department, particularly
                        the poor division of responsibility for important functions, inadequate
                        means of obtaining and disseminating information, and ineffective long-range
                        planning. In December 1944, shortly after Stettinius succeeded Hull as
                        Secretary of State, he issued Department Order 1301, which concentrated
                        similar functions in the same office and related offices under a senior
                        official, either the Under Secretary or one of six Assistant
                        Secretaries.</p>
                    <p>To coordinate the work of the Department, ensure follow-through, and conduct
                        long-range planning, Order 1301 created several new entities. A Staff
                        Committee including the Secretary and his principal subordinates became the
                        chief managerial group in the Department. A Coordinating Committee was
                        formed to investigate policy options and control inter-office projects. A
                        Joint Secretariat monitored Department activity to ensure that decisions
                        were handled efficiently. Finally a Policy Committee and a Committee on
                        Postwar Problems were created to focus on long-range planning.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Stettinius also streamlined functions overlapping the jurisdictions
                        of the traditional geographic bureaus. New bureaus were set up to deal with
                        trade relations, cultural diplomacy, and public information. Another
                        important functional organization came into being in September 1945—the
                        Interim Research and Intelligence Service, which is the forerunner of the
                        present-day Bureau of Intelligence and Research. These innovations minimized
                        fragmentation of jurisdiction that so frequently immobilized the Department
                        in a crisis when quick decisions were required.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="conc4">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The Department of State that emerged from World War II better prepared to
                        play a leading role in the foreign policy process and to participate fully
                        in the difficult tasks ahead. In July 1945, Secretary James F. Byrnes
                        recognized the extent of the postwar challenge. “The supreme task of
                        statesmanship in the world over is to help them understand that they can
                        have peace and freedom only if they tolerate and respect the rights of
                        others to opinions, feelings, and way of life which they do not and cannot
                        share.” </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="containmentandcoldwar">
                <head>Containment and Cold War, 1945-1961</head>
                <div type="subchapter">
                    <head>Containment and Cold War, 1945-1961</head>
                    <p>The Department of State reached the zenith of its power and influence in the
                        period immediately after World War II under the guidance of three strong and
                        influential Secretaries of State: George Marshall, Dean Acheson, and John
                        Foster Dulles. The “Cold War” brought major changes to U.S. policy abroad,
                        while McCarthyism targeted the Department at home. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="worldin1945">
                    <head>The World in 1945</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-hstruman.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Harry S. Truman</head>
                        </figure> When Harry S Truman became President in April 1945, much of Europe
                        and Asia lay in ruins. Although the Axis powers had been defeated, an
                        ominous new threat appeared on the horizon. The United States and the Soviet
                        Union, who were allies during World War II, emerged from the war as global
                        powers, increasingly in conflict with each other. By 1947, efforts to
                        maintain cooperation between Washington and Moscow had broken down
                        completely. President Truman, working closely with two assertive Secretaries
                        of State—<ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-george-catlett"
                            >George C. Marshall</ref> (1947-1949) and <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/acheson-dean-gooderham">Dean G.
                            Acheson</ref> (1949-1953)—took decisive steps to contain Soviet
                        expansion in regions in which the United States had vital interests. The
                        United States was about to enter a new kind of war: the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1945-1952/foreword">“Cold War.”</ref>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="kennan">
                    <head>George Kennan and Containment</head>
                    <p>At the end of the war, the Soviet Union was a closed society under the iron
                        grip of Joseph Stalin.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-gkennan.jpg"/>
                        <head>George Kennan</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Few in the West had experience with the communist state and even fewer
                        understood what motivated the Soviets. One man who had first hand knowledge
                        was a Foreign Service officer, George F. Kennan. In 1946, while he was
                        Chargé d’Affaires in Moscow, Kennan sent an 8,000-word telegram to the
                        Department—the now-famous “long telegram”—on the aggressive nature of
                        Stalin’s foreign policy. Kennan, writing as “Mr. X,” published an outline of
                        his philosophy in the prestigious journal <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> in 1947. His conclusion was that “the main element of any
                        United States policy toward the Soviet Union must be that of a long-term
                        patient but firm and vigilant containment of Russian expansive tendencies.”
                            <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/kennan">Containment </ref>provided a
                        conceptual framework for a series of successful initiatives undertaken from
                        1947 to 1950 to blunt Soviet expansion.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="truman">
                    <head>The Truman Doctrine and the Marshall Plan</head>
                    <p>The first step was the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/truman-doctrine"
                            >“Truman Doctrine”</ref> of March 1947, which reflected the
                        combativeness of President Harry Truman. Truman wanted to “scare the hell”
                        out of Congress. Arguing that Greece and Turkey could fall victim to
                        subversion without support from friendly nations, Truman asked Congress to
                        authorize $400-million in emergency assistance. To justify this course, he
                        said: “I believe we must assist free peoples to work out their destinies in
                        their own way.” The key to preventing the overthrow of free nations was to
                        attack the conditions of “misery and want” that nurtured
                        totalitarianism.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-truman.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Harry S. Truman</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Soon this general principle was applied to Western Europe as a whole. In June
                        1947, Secretary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-george-catlett">George C.
                            Marshall</ref> proposed the extension of massive economic assistance to
                        the devastated nations of Europe, saying that the policy of the United
                        States was not directed “against any country or doctrine but against hunger,
                        poverty, desperation, and chaos. Its purpose should be the revival of a
                        working economy in the world so as to permit the existence of political and
                        social conditions in which free institutions can exist.”</p>
                    <p>What the Secretary of State left unsaid was that while the U.S. plan would be
                        open to the Soviet Union and its satellites in Eastern Europe, it emphasized
                        the free market economy as the best path to economic reconstruction—and the
                        best defense against communism in Western Europe. Congress responded to
                        Marshall’s proposal by authorizing the European Recovery Program, better
                        known as the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/marshall-plan">Marshall
                            Plan</ref>. An investment of about $13 billion in Europe during the next
                        few years resulted in the extraordinarily rapid and durable reconstruction
                        of a democratic Western Europe.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="containment">
                    <head>Containment and Collective Defense</head>
                    <p>It was also inevitable that the policy of containment would develop a
                        political-military dimension. In June 1948, Senator <persName>Arthur H.
                            Vandenberg</persName> of Michigan sponsored a resolution in the Senate
                        that called for the <quote>“progressive development of regional and other
                            collective arrangements for individual and collective self-defense in
                            accordance with the purposes, principles, and provisions of the [United
                            Nations] Charter.”</quote>
                    </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-vandenberg.jpg"/>
                        <head>Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>President Truman had already applied the principles of containment to Latin
                        America. The Rio Pact, signed in September 1947, provided that “an armed
                        attack by any State shall be considered as an attack against all the
                        American States and, consequently, each one of the said Contracting Parties
                        undertakes to assist in meeting the attack.” Collective security was invoked
                        again in the North Atlantic Treaty. Signed in Washington in April 1949, it
                        created the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic Treaty
                            Organization (NATO)</ref>. The Rio Pact and the NATO Alliance formally
                        marked the end of George Washington’s policy of no entangling alliances.
                        Economic assistance and collective defense agreements became the bulwark of
                        Western containment policy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="secretary">
                    <head>A Changing Role for the Secretary</head>
                    <p>After 1945, most Secretaries of State were chosen because they possessed
                        broad foreign policy experience and the management skills deemed essential
                        to effective performance. Secretaries traveled extensively to negotiate and
                        coordinate with their foreign counterparts and chiefs of state, but they
                        also had to spend a large amount of time on administration. Although the
                        burdens of office increased exponentially, Secretaries also gained prestige,
                        as a consequence of the high priority now accorded to foreign relations.</p>
                    <p>During this period, the Department absorbed several wartime organizations
                        dealing with international economic affairs into its permanent bureaucratic
                        structure. In August 1946, the Department created a new Under Secretary for
                        Economic Affairs to manage the complex economic component of U.S. foreign
                        policy. Working with the existing Assistant Secretary for Economic Affairs,
                        the Under Secretary supervised international economic activities and
                        established effective relations with the International Bank for
                        Reconstruction and Development (IBRD), the International Monetary Fund
                        (IMF), and the UN’s Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). </p>
                    <p>A change in foreign policy required a change in the Foreign Service as well.
                        Congress passed the Foreign Service Act of 1946, which was intended to
                        “improve, strengthen, and expand the Foreign Service . . . and to
                        consolidate and revise the laws relating to its administration.” A new
                        Director General and a Foreign Service Board were created to improve
                        administration, while a new Board of Examiners maintained the principle of
                        competitive entrance. The law also provided for improvements in assignments
                        policy, promotion procedures, allowances and benefits, home leave, and the
                        retirement system. In recognition of the growing importance of specialized
                        experience, the act also created the Foreign Service Reserve for lawyers,
                        doctors, economists, and intelligence analysts. Finally, the Foreign Service
                        School became the Foreign Service Institute and offered advanced training
                        for Department personnel in subjects of critical importance in the rapidly
                        changing world.</p>
                    <p>In April 1947, the Department of State moved to new quarters, the wartime
                        home of the War Department, now available after the completion of the
                        Pentagon. The new headquarters of the Department of State was located in
                        northwest Washington, D.C., in an area known as Foggy Bottom. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="security">
                    <head>A New National Security Structure</head>
                    <p>The new challenges and responsibilities of the Cold War convinced many in
                        Congress that Truman’s foreign policy establishment needed reform because it
                        relied heavily on a few key White House aides. In July 1947, Congress passed
                        the National Security Act, which would have a profound effect on the
                        Department of State. Proponents of reform wanted to coordinate foreign,
                        defense, and domestic policy by establishing the National Security Council
                        (NSC) under the chairmanship of the President and composed of only six
                        permanent members: the Secretaries of State, Defense, Army, Navy, and Air
                        Force, and the Chairman of the National Resources Board. The President could
                        designate the heads of other executive departments, such as the Director of
                        the new Central Intelligence Agency, to attend if needed.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-nsa.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Truman signing the National Security Act into Law</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Under the terms of the legislation, the NSC would consist of a small staff
                        headed by an Executive Secretary appointed by the President. There was no
                        legislative provision for the post of “national security adviser,” and the
                        small NSC staff had no role in the formulation or implementation of
                        policy.</p>
                    <p>Truman did not take well to the idea that his foreign policy advisers would
                        be mandated by Congressional legislation, and he rarely attended the initial
                        meetings of the National Security Council. The Secretary of State was named
                        as the ranking member in his absence, and the Department of State controlled
                        the NSC and its operations. The State Department’s Policy Planning Staff
                        wrote most of the NSC’s papers, which after discussion by the Council and
                        approval by Truman, were then disseminated to the bureaucracy in summary
                        form as NSC actions.</p>
                    <p>Under Truman, the NSC did not displace the Secretary of State as the
                        President's senior adviser on international questions; it simply required
                        all agencies to contribute to the decision-making process. With the
                        proliferation of new issues and new U.S. agencies active overseas, the State
                        Department could not on its own control everything. The NSC was the
                        mechanism through which the Department of State could exert consistent
                        influence on national security policy. Used properly, it had the potential
                        to deploy the vast array of American power—diplomatic, political, economic,
                        psychological, and military—to reach common goals. This was an objective
                        that the Department had failed to achieve during the troubled years between
                        1914 and 1945.</p>
                    <p>But the Department of State could only realize its full potential in the new
                        institutional context if the Secretary of State gained the confidence of the
                        President. Both Secretary Marshall and Secretary Acheson did, and Truman
                        tended to bypass the slower-moving National Security Council. Truman was
                        always anxious to complete action on important questions, and he wanted to
                        make his decision as soon as he had a sound basis to do so. Secretary
                        Acheson, noted one biographer, “could always provide an adequate basis, or
                        its appearance, before any rival body . . . In the race with time, which was
                        the key to influence over the President, Acheson was unbeatable.” </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="koreanwar">
                    <head>NSC-68 and the Korean War </head>
                    <p>The events of 1949 made foreign policy the nation’s top priority. NATO became
                        a working alliance, the United States provided military assistance to
                        Europe, the Soviet Union detonated an atomic bomb, and the Mao Zedong’s
                        communist party took control of mainland China. The Department of State
                        ordered a complete review of American strategic and military policy, and, in
                        April 1950, the Department sent a paper calling for a broad-based and
                        reinvigorated containment policy toward the Soviet Union, directly to the
                        President. The paper later became known as <ref
                            target="/milestones/1945-1952/NSC68">NSC-68</ref>. After the outbreak of
                        fighting on the Korean peninsula, NSC-68 was accepted throughout the
                        government as the foundation of American foreign policy.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-koreanwar.jpg"/>
                        <head>U.S. Soldiers during the Korean War</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>When North Korea invaded South Korea in June 1950, the United States
                        sponsored a "police action"—a war in all but name—under the auspices of the
                        United Nations. The Department of State coordinated U.S. strategic decisions
                        with the other 16 countries contributing troops to the fighting. In
                        addition, the Department worked closely with the government of Syngman Rhee,
                        encouraging him to implement reform so that the UN claim of defending
                        democracy in Korea would be accurate. </p>
                    <p>The Korean War was difficult to fight and unpopular domestically. In late
                        1951, the two sides bogged down on the 38th parallel, and the conflict
                        seemed reminiscent of trench warfare in World War I. The American public
                        tired of a war without victory, especially when negotiation stalled as well.
                        The stalemate eroded Truman’s public support and helped to elect the
                        Republican presidential candidate, popular military hero General Dwight D.
                        Eisenhower, as the next President.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="eisenhower">
                    <head>Foreign Policy under President Eisenhower </head>
                    <p>As Supreme Allied Commander in Europe during the war, President Eisenhower
                        had a well-earned reputation for staff work and organization. He was
                        determined to make the Department of State a part of the NSC’s structured
                        system of integrated policy review, and the NSC enjoyed a renaissance during
                        his Administration. Discussion papers were prepared by the NSC’s own
                        Planning Board—not the Department of State, and the Planning Board ironed
                        out interdepartmental differences before a policy paper went to the NSC. The
                        full Council, with Eisenhower almost always in attendance, debated the
                        policy options and made decisions, which were then sent as recommendations
                        to the President in the form of NSC actions. Another subcommittee, the
                        Operations Coordinating Board, made sure that the bureaucracy carried out
                        the recommendations approved by the President. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-dulles-eisenhower.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Dulles with President Eisenhower</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Dulles drew a sharp line between the policy review process and day-to-day
                        operations, which he felt were the exclusive province of the Department of
                        State. Dulles also believed that some issues, such as covert operations,
                        were too sensitive to be discussed by the full NSC. Because of his close
                        ties to the President and his even closer relationship with his brother, CIA
                        Director Allen Dulles, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster">John Foster
                            Dulles</ref> was second in importance only to the President at any NSC
                        meeting. President Eisenhower often dominated the discussions, but Dulles
                        remained his most influential foreign policy adviser. </p>
                    <p>Dulles was a staunch anti-communist. For this Secretary of State there was no
                        grey area—nations were either part of the “Free World” or part of the Soviet
                        bloc; he had little time for neutralism or non-alignment. Secretary Dulles
                        also had a tendency to speak dramatically. In a 1954 speech, he said that
                        the United States would meet Soviet provocations not necessarily where they
                        occurred but where the United States chose, based on its “deterrent of
                        massive retaliatory power.” In a 1956 <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> magazine
                        interview, Dulles described how he had passed the word to the Chinese and
                        the North Koreans that unless the communist powers signed the Korean
                        armistice, the United States would unleash its atomic arsenal. Dulles
                        claimed that by moving to the brink of atomic war, he ended the Korean War
                        and avoided a larger conflict. From that point on, Dulles was associated
                        with the concepts of <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/foreword">“massive
                            retaliation”</ref> and “brinksmanship,” a supposedly reckless
                        combination of atomic saber rattling and eyeball-to-eyeball standoffs. In
                        reality, the so-called atomic threat to China was less definitive than
                        Dulles had claimed, and the Eisenhower Administration policy of “massive
                        retaliation” was far more cautiously based on mutual atomic deterrence. </p>
                    <p>During the Eisenhower years, the United States consolidated the policy of
                        containment, although some critics have argued that the administration
                        extended it too far. The United States ratified a series of bilateral and
                        multilateral treaties designed to encircle the Soviet Union and its allies,
                        including the People’s Republic of China (PRC). Among these arrangements
                        were the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/cento">Central Treaty
                            Organization (CENTO)</ref>; the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1953-1960/seato">Southeast Asia Treaty Organization
                            (SEATO)</ref>; and bilateral defense or security treaties with Japan,
                            <placeName>South Korea</placeName>, the <placeName>Republic of
                            China</placeName>, and the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>. Secretary
                        Dulles was the most prominent advocate of global containment and he traveled
                        the world tirelessly to ensure its success. In 1954, the United States took
                        a strong stand in favor of the Chinese Nationalists when the PRC bombarded
                        Taiwan’s island strongholds. In 1955, assistance began to flow to the new
                        nation of South Vietnam, created after the withdrawal of France from
                        Indochina. In 1958, the United States again rattled the saber to protect the
                        Chinese Nationalists’ offshore islands.</p>
                </div>
                <!-- TAKEN DOWN PER STEVE'S REQUEST  <div type="subchapter" xml:id="mccarthy">
                    <head>McCarthyism Hits the Department</head>
                    <p>The Cold War years were troubling ones for the Foreign Service, after it
                        became the prime target of Senator <persName>Joseph McCarthy</persName>'s
                        search for pro-Communist subversives in the U.S. Government. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-mccarthy.jpg"/>
                        <head>Senator Joseph McCarthy</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In February 1950, shortly after the Soviet Union developed its own nuclear
                        weapons and Mao Zedong’s communist forces seized power in China, the
                        Wisconsin Senator launched his anti-communist crusade with a speech in
                        Wheeling, West Virginia. Describing the international position of the United
                        States in the most dire terms, he insisted: “How can we account for our
                        present situation unless we believe that men high in the government are
                        concerting to deliver us to disaster? This must be the product of a great
                        conspiracy on a scale so immense as to dwarf any previous venture in the
                        history of man.”</p>
                    <p>He announced that he had a list of 205 subversives—<quote>“a list of names
                            that were made known to the Secretary of State as being members of the
                            Communist Party and who nevertheless are still working and shaping
                            policy in the State Department.”</quote> Senator McCarthy never made
                        that list public or proved any of his allegations. A number of the most
                        experienced Foreign Service officers—notably the Department’s corps of Far
                        Eastern experts, the so-called “China hands,” including Oliver Edmund Clubb,
                        John Patton Davies, John Stewart Service, and John Carter Vincent—were
                        forced out of the Department or suffered serious damage to their
                        reputations. </p>
                    <p>McCarthy's allegations had a lasting effect on those who remained in the
                        Department. John W. Ford, a security officer at the time, has since noted,
                        “few people who lived through the McCarthy era in the Department of State
                        can ever forget the fear, intimidation, and sense of outrage which permeated
                        Foggy Bottom.” In 1978, the Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs,
                            <persName>David D. Newsom</persName>, said: “I can recall the shock of
                        the taunts and suspicions leveled at the State Department and those who
                        served in it. It must be satisfying, but not full recompense, for those who
                        suffered in that period to have our nation now realize that they were
                        substantially right.” </p>
                    <p>The mistaken notion that the Department of State somehow served the nation’s
                        enemies lingered on for some years. One former Department of State employee,
                        Epers , was found guilty of passing secrets to the Soviets in the late
                        1930s, but this exception did not detract from the fact that the criticism
                        by McCarthy and others of like mind was unjustified.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-algerhiss.jpg"/>
                        <head>Alger Hiss</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The Foreign Service and Department of State were convenient targets for “Red
                        baiting” because they were without a domestic constituency. The absence of
                        powerful and assertive support from organized interest groups, especially in
                        comparison with most other major agencies, made the Department vulnerable to
                        McCarthy’s irresponsible charges and allowed him to attack it without fear
                        of serious retaliation. Personally, Secretary Dulles and President
                        Eisenhower may have deplored McCarthy’s attacks, but they did little to
                        combat McCarthy. Only when the Senator took on the U.S. Army did he meet
                        real resistance and lose his influence and power.</p>
                </div> -->
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="wristonization">
                    <head>"Wristonization"</head>
                    <p>While the Department struggled with McCarthyism, it also sought to modernize
                        its personnel practices. Postwar growth produced what one historian
                        described as <quote>“inertia, inflexibility, and loss of efficiency in the
                            use of personnel.”</quote> Stanton Griffis, a businessman who served as
                        ambassador to several countries, later satirized the confused situation.
                        Overseas missions, he noted, constituted <quote>"a fantastic network of men,
                            women, and typewriters, who report [on] political, economic, labor, and
                            agricultural conditions.”</quote> These reports then went to Washington,
                        where they were immediately filed away. Then “the home team, having properly
                        disposed of the information from the field, proceeds to write its own
                        endless reports to go forward to the same ultimate fate in the embassies
                        throughout the world.” </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-wriston.jpg"/>
                        <head>Henry M. Wriston</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The post-1945 personnel problems of the Department of State attracted the
                        attention of a commission created to investigate all aspects of government
                        organization after World War II, which was headed by former President
                        Herbert Hoover. In 1949, the commission called for reforms to eliminate one
                        important source of difficulty—the negative distinctions between Foreign
                        Service officers and Civil Service employees who staffed the Department's
                        headquarters in Washington. In 1954, Secretary of State Dulles asked Henry
                        M. Wriston, the president of Brown University, to undertake a study of the
                        Department's personnel practices. Dulles drew attention to a number of
                        concerns, among them poor morale because of managerial shortcomings, low
                        intake into the Foreign Service, and inequities that stemmed from variations
                        in the treatment of different categories of employees. After examining these
                        matters, Wriston called for the integration of many Civil Service employees
                        into the Foreign Service, a process that took several years and was known as
                        “Wristonization.” By the end of 1957, the Foreign Service had more than
                        doubled in size to 3,436 officers. By August 1959, 1,523 Foreign Service
                        officers were assigned to positions in the Department in an effort to
                        improve communications between Washington and the overseas missions and to
                        fulfill the legal requirement that Foreign Service officers spend a portion
                        of their careers in the United States.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="quarters">
                    <head>New Secretary; New Quarters</head>
                    <p>John Foster Dulles resigned in April 1959 because of ill health and died of
                        cancer soon afterward. Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/herter-christian-archibald">Christian
                            A. Herter</ref>, who served mostly from a wheelchair because of his
                        severe arthritis, replaced him. With the death of Dulles and the approaching
                        end of Eisenhower’s second term, U.S. foreign policy initiatives became less
                        significant. The Department more often found itself responding to crises or
                        explaining foreign policy failures. Negotiations with the Soviet Union on a
                        test ban treaty collapsed, the shoot down of a U-2 spy plane over the Soviet
                        Union allowed Soviet leader <persName>Nikita Khrushchev </persName>to cancel
                        a planned 1960 summit, Fidel Castro introduced communism into Cuba, and the
                        U.S. Government began planning for a covert invasion of Cuba. In Southeast
                        Asia, the Eisenhower Administration committed additional U.S. resources and
                        advisers, although not U.S. combat troops.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/herter-christian-archibald.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Christian Herter</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In early January 1961, the Department of State moved into its new <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/buildings/section28">headquarters</ref>,
                        which it continues to occupy today. Secretary Dulles and President
                        Eisenhower had laid the cornerstone of the new building in September 1957;
                        using the same trowel that George Washington had used to lay the cornerstone
                        of the Capitol. The new building was an extension of the Department’s
                        quarters in the old War Department building and was about four times as
                        large. The architects designed the building on a vertical/pyramid plan,
                        placing different offices of bureaus on multiple floors connected by
                        elevators. The higher the job, the higher the floor. Assistant secretaries
                        were on the sixth floor; the Secretary and his immediate staff occupied the
                        seventh floor—the top working level of the building. The eighth floor was
                        reserved for diplomatic reception rooms.</p>
                    <p>The new building was in the stark modern architectural style of the 1950s.
                        What it lacked in aesthetics, it attempted to compensate for in efficiency
                        and use of space. The Department had two large conference rooms and a number
                        of smaller rooms available for meetings. Most of the 7,000 employees of the
                        Department, previously housed in the old State building and 29 separate
                        annexes, moved into new offices. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="conf5">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>When <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> and his “New Frontiersmen” entered
                        office in January 1961, they came with a reputation for being young and
                        dynamic, but they also came with many of the same the preconceptions and
                        assumptions held by <persName>Dwight Eisenhower</persName> and
                            <persName>John Foster Dulles</persName>. A rapid succession of crises
                        would bring the world to the brink of nuclear war and test the mettle of
                        Kennedy and his diplomats. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="superpowers">
                <head>Superpowers Collide, 1961-1981</head>
                <div type="subchapter">
                    <head>Superpowers Collide, 1961-1981</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-coldwar.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Richard Nixon and Soviet Premier L. Brezhnev during a
                                1973 Meeting</head>
                        </figure> During the 1960s and 1970s, American foreign policy was dominated
                        by rivalry with the Soviet Union. Although the two superpowers stepped to
                        the brink of nuclear war, diplomacy prevailed and negotiation continued. In
                        an attempt to break the bipolar dynamic and win advantage for the United
                        States, President Nixon opened contact with the Peoples’ Republic of China.
                        The power and influence of the Department of State fluctuated as it competed
                        with the National Security Council for the ear of the President.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="jfk">
                    <head>The World in 1961</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-jfk.jpg"/>
                            <head>President John F. Kennedy</head>
                        </figure> John F. Kennedy entered office determined to restore the prestige
                        and power of the United States, which he felt had eroded during Eisenhower’s
                        watch and to stop the expansionism of the Soviet Union.</p>
                    <p>Kennedy’s policy led to a concerted diplomatic effort to win new friends
                        among the “non-aligned” nations of the world. But it was a policy that also
                        drew the United States into frequent, intense clashes with the Soviet
                        Union—and brought the world to the brink of nuclear war.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="jfk-foreignpolicy">
                    <head>Kennedy's Foreign Policy</head>
                    <p>Kennedy’s close advisers believed that Eisenhower’s foreign policy
                        establishment was stultified, slow moving, overly reliant on brinksmanship
                        and massive retaliation, and complacent. Their fear was that after eight
                        years, the State Department would be unable to implement their new
                        international vision. The new President was determined to control foreign
                        policy through a young and energetic White House and NSC staffers who would
                        make their own informal contacts within the foreign affairs bureaucracy.
                        Furthermore, Kennedy thought that Eisenhower and Secretaries Dulles and
                        Herter had all but ceded the newly emerging states in Latin America, Asia,
                        and Africa to the communists. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-kennedy.jpg"/>
                        <head>Official White House Portrait of President John Kennedy</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The execution of Kennedy’s foreign policy did not quite live up to the
                        stirring rhetoric of his inaugural speech, in which he said: “Let every
                        nation know, whether it wishes us well or ill, that we shall pay any price,
                        bear any burden, meet any hardship, support any friend, oppose any foe, in
                        order to assure the survival and the success of liberty.” In fact, his
                        foreign policy was marred by a string of failures. </p>
                    <p>First, Kennedy gave the green light to an Eisenhower-initiated invasion of
                        the <ref target="/milestones/1961-1968/cuban-missile-crisis">Bay of
                            Pigs</ref> in Cuba in 1961. Based on faulty intelligence, the military
                        action, which was carried out by Cuban exiles without crucial air support
                        was a fiasco. Then in June 1961 at the Vienna Summit with Soviet Premier
                            <persName>Nikita Khrushchev</persName>, Kennedy was unprepared and
                        seemed to be a lightweight playboy. Next, Kennedy’s tough talk about the
                        Soviet Union in Berlin did not improve the situation—instead, the Soviets
                        built the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/berlin-airlift">Berlin
                            Wall</ref>. Finally, his decision not to draw the line against communism
                        in Laos, as the Eisenhower Administration had urged, left South Vietnam as
                        the place to fight communism in Asia. </p>
                    <p>Kennedy’s overall record was a mixed bag of success and failure. At the
                        President’s urging, Congress established the U.S. Arms Control and
                        Disarmament Agency (ACDA) in 1961 as a separate entity under Department of
                        State auspices. The Administration built on Eisenhower’s extensive
                        negotiations with the Soviet Union, but the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1961-1968/limited-ban">Limited Test Ban Treaty</ref>
                        signed by Kennedy only outlawed atmospheric but not underground nuclear
                        testing. In Vietnam, the Kennedy Administration approved the overthrow of
                        President Diem, believing that any successor government would have to be an
                        improvement over Diem’s. They were wrong. Finally, U.S. initiatives in
                        Western Europe, such as support for British entry into the European Economic
                        Community and European defense integration, also were unsuccessful.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="cubanmissile">
                    <head>The Cuban Missile Crises</head>
                    <p>In October 1962, the Kennedy Administration faced its most serious foreign
                        policy crisis. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-cubancrisis.jpg"/>
                            <head>President Kennedy with his cabinet during the Cuban Missile
                                Crisis</head>
                        </figure> Soviet Premier <persName>Nikita Khrushchev</persName> saw an
                        opportunity to strengthen the relationship between the Soviet Union and
                            <persName>Fidel Castro</persName>’s Cuba and make good its promise to
                        defend Cuba from the United States. In May 1960, Khrushchev began to ship
                        ballistic missiles to Cuba and technicians to operate them. He believed that
                        President Kennedy was weak and would not react to the Soviet move.</p>
                    <p>After extensive consultation with his foreign policy and military advisers,
                        Kennedy blockaded Cuba on October 22, 1962. The two sides stood on the brink
                        of nuclear war, but Khrushchev capitulated six days later and the missiles
                        were dismantled. In return, Kennedy disbanded its own missile sites in
                            <placeName>Turkey</placeName>. The most confrontational period in
                        US-Soviet relations since World War II was at an end.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="jfk-state">
                    <head>Kennedy and the Department of State</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> chose <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/rusk-david-dean">Dean Rusk</ref> to be
                        his Secretary of State, convinced that Rusk would not challenge presidential
                        control of foreign policy. A former Rhodes Scholar, professor of government,
                        college dean, senior Department official under Secretaries Marshall and
                        Acheson, and president of the Rockefeller Foundation, Rusk had impressive
                        qualifications. Quiet, self-effacing, and supremely loyal without being a
                        “yes” man, Rusk never became part of Kennedy’s inner circle and failed to
                        establish a close rapport with the young President. Rusk served for eight
                        years as Secretary of State, but he found fellow southerner and
                        self-proclaimed “self-made man” Lyndon Johnson a more compatible boss than
                        Kennedy. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/rusk-dean-david.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Dean Rusk</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The new administration hoped to infuse a new energy into the Department of
                        State, but Kennedy made some appointments that he came to regret. For
                        example, Under Secretary of State Chester Bowles, an old-line New Deal
                        liberal, was not well suited to run the Department of State, as his job
                        required. Bowles was a thinker and a grand conceptualizer, but he was not an
                        administrator. In late November 1961, Kennedy replaced Bowles with Under
                        Secretary of State for Economic Affairs George Ball, who was the principal
                        Europeanist in the Kennedy team at State. Walt W. Rostow transferred from
                        the White House to be Counselor and head of the Policy Planning Staff, while
                        Rusk’s friend George McGhee replaced Ball, and Ambassador-at-Large W.
                        Averell Harriman became Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                        Affairs. The reshuffle was meant to improve both the Department’s
                        administration and its policy role. </p>
                    <p>The Department did improve its performance somewhat in Kennedy’s eyes over
                        time. Secretary Rusk was a key adviser during the Cuban Missile Crisis of
                        October 1962, and other Department officials, including Llewellyn E.
                        Thompson, played a key role as an adviser on the Soviet Union and as a
                        drafter of letters to Khrushchev. But as a general trend during the Kennedy
                        years, the National Security Council increased in prominence at the expense
                        of the Department of State, and McGeorge Bundy's role as National Security
                        Adviser grew proportionately. Although he sought to be neutral on policy
                        matters, laying out the bureaucratic and policy options for the President,
                        increasingly he and his active NSC staff began to shape the agenda and
                        orchestrate the dialogue of policy debate.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="tradition">
                    <head>Traditional Diplomacy Expanded</head>
                    <p>Early in his administration, Kennedy clarified the role he expected
                        ambassadors to play. In May 1961, Kennedy sent all ambassadors and
                        department heads a letter reminding them that ambassadors were in charge of
                        all U.S. activities in their respective countries and were responsible for
                        all members of the mission, no matter which agency originally sent them.
                        Kennedy was acknowledging a new reality—most major U.S. Government agencies
                        now had overseas staff reporting to someone other than the Department of
                        State. The President expected that those representatives would still report
                        to their home offices in Washington, but he required them to obtain the
                        chief of mission’s concurrence for all important cables and policy
                        recommendations. Kennedy's letter, which also laid out appeal procedures in
                        case of serious disagreement, was an effort to end inter-agency maneuvering
                        and rivalry at U.S. embassies. </p>
                    <p>During these years, the Department shook off the staid pace of the Eisenhower
                        era as its mission expanded beyond the realm of national security policy and
                        the management of Cold War crises. Foreign Service officers performed duties
                        that far transcended the traditional tasks of representation, negotiation,
                        and reporting. Knowledge of scientific, economic, cultural, and social
                        issues became essential, as many more officers were assigned to the newly
                        emerging nations of Africa and Asia.</p>
                    <p>At the Kennedy Administration’s urging, Congress established a separate
                        Agency for International Development (AID) in November 1961 under the
                        ultimate authority of the Secretary of State. Walt Rostow, a former academic
                        economist, was the leading proponent of economic development for the “Third
                        World,” and his take-off theory of development permeated the Department and
                        AID. Many Foreign Service officers and their Civil Service colleagues set
                        out to change the world and bring economic development to Asia, Africa, and
                        Latin America.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="domestic">
                    <head>Domestic Upheaval and a New President</head>
                    <p>Lyndon B. Johnson became President after Kennedy’s assassination in November
                        1963.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-lbj.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Lyndon B. Johnson</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Although his foreign policy team initially remained the same, there were
                        subtle changes. As Vice President, Johnson had been kept out of the foreign
                        policy decision-making process by the Kennedy team. Secretary Rusk and the
                        Department of State had often suffered similar treatment during the Kennedy
                        years. Shared humiliation and a sense of frustration made the new President
                        sympathetic to Rusk and the Department of State. From that point on, Rusk
                        was a strong and influential Secretary of State. He repaid Johnson’s trust
                        and support by loyally defending the President’s increasingly unpopular
                        Vietnam policy to Congressional critics, the American public, and world
                        opinion. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="lbj">
                    <head>Johnson's Foreign Policy</head>
                    <p>Privately, Johnson agonized over the consequences of the U.S. escalation in
                        Vietnam and raged at the incompetence of the succession of military juntas
                        that tried to govern that country and carry on a war against Viet Cong
                        guerrillas and North Vietnamese regulars. Publicly, he was determined not to
                        lose the war. As a result, in 1968 there were 500,000 American troops in
                            <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> and no end in sight to the
                        conflict. After an extensive re-examination, President Johnson decided to
                        disengage from a struggle lacking U.S. domestic support. He desperately
                        tried to initiate formal peace negotiations in Paris before the 1968
                        presidential election, but the peace talks commenced only as he left
                        office.</p>
                    <p>Johnson was also concerned about Latin American policy, which was another of
                        his special interests. He chose Eisenhower official <persName>Thomas C.
                            Mann</persName> to be Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                        Affairs. Mann let it be known that he would judge Western Hemisphere
                        neighbors by their commitment to anti-communism rather than their commitment
                        to democracy. The <ref target="/milestones/1961-1968/alliance-for-progress "
                            >Alliance for Progress</ref>, begun with such fanfare under Kennedy, was
                        allowed to wither as a result of neglect and its own internal problems.
                        Johnson’s policy toward Latin America became increasingly interventionist,
                        culminating with the deployment of U.S. soldiers to Santo Domingo to prevent
                        another communist takeover in the Caribbean.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="management">
                    <head>Management of Foreign Policy</head>
                    <p>During the Johnson years, complaints persisted about the Department’s
                        management of foreign policy. In a 1966 quest for greater efficiency, the
                        Department created “country directors” in the geographic bureaus to support
                        chiefs of mission and their embassies. These directors formulated and
                        communicated policy guidance and mobilized operational and administrative
                        support for an embassy’s “country team.” </p>
                    <p>Also in 1966, Johnson made the Secretary of State formally responsible for
                        overall direction, coordination, and supervision of interdepartmental
                        activities overseas and created the Senior Interdepartmental Group (SIG),
                        chaired by the Under Secretary of State, to do just that. Several
                        Interdepartmental Regional Groups were created to support the work of the
                        SIG, chaired by Assistant Secretaries of State. On paper at least, the
                        Department of State was in charge of the <ref
                            target="/milestones/1945-1952/national-security-act">NSC policy
                            process</ref>. In reality, the system did not work as planned and did
                        not survive beyond the Johnson Administration. At least for Vietnam and a
                        few other high-profile issues, Johnson still relied on Rusk, the Secretary
                        of Defense, and his National Security Adviser, meeting through the mechanism
                        of the “Tuesday lunch,” an extremely restricted version of the National
                        Security Council. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="inequality">
                    <head>The Department addresses Inequality</head>
                    <p>Johnson was also a firm believer in civil rights, and his commitment directly
                        affected the Department of State. Lyndon Johnson pushed the Department of
                        State hard to recruit more African-Americans and women, and he made a
                        conscious effort to increase their presence in the upper levels of the
                        Department and its related foreign policy agencies. The Department,
                        reflecting American racial attitudes, offered no meaningful opportunity to
                        African-Americans for most of its existence.</p>
                    <p>While prominent African-Americans, such as the famous abolitionist, Frederick
                        Douglass, had represented the United States overseas during the 19th
                        century, in reality the only posts open to African-American men were in
                        black nations. Change came no more quickly in the 20th century. The first
                        African-American to enter the Foreign Service was <persName>Clifford R.
                            Wharton</persName> in 1925. Although he later became the first career
                        diplomat of his race to serve as a chief of mission, his early career was
                        spent mostly in posts traditionally reserved for African-Americans. Wharton
                        remembered telling a personnel officer: <quote>“You’re not only
                            discriminating against us in the Service, but you’re exporting
                            discrimination abroad.”</quote> Johnson’s greatest success in this
                        campaign was to convince prominent African-American journalist
                            <persName>Carl T. Rowan</persName> to become Director of the U.S.
                        Information Agency.</p>
                    <p>The President was also concerned about the status of women because their role
                        at the Department of State had been a limited one. The Department did not
                        employ any women in full-time positions until 1874, and for some time
                        thereafter they were deemed qualified only for clerical duties. In 1905, for
                        example, Assistant Secretary <persName>Frederick Van Dyne</persName> said:
                            <quote>“The greatest obstacle to the employment of women as diplomatic
                            agents is their well known inability to keep a secret.”</quote> The
                        first woman to enter the Foreign Service did not do so until 1922, and the
                        first woman ambassador was not appointed until 1933.</p>
                    <p>President Johnson realized that women had not been given a fair chance in the
                        Department of State and the Foreign Service. Although the number of women in
                        senior positions in the Department increased 33 percent in the 1960s, women
                        still held just 2.5 percent of senior slots. It was not until 1971, when
                        Foreign Service officer Alison Palmer won her gender discrimination case,
                        that the Department finally addressed long-standing problems. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="nixon-nsc">
                    <head>President Nixon and the NSC</head>
                    <p>The election of President Richard M. Nixon in 1968 led to important changes
                        for the Department of State. Foreign policy had been Nixon’s specialty in
                        Congress and as Vice President under Eisenhower. As President, he fully
                        intended to control foreign policy and make the major decisions himself. He
                        created an activist <ref
                            target="/milestones/1945-1952/national-security-act">NSC</ref> staff
                        under Harvard Professor <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/kissinger-henry-a">Henry A.
                            Kissinger</ref>, whom he named as his National Security Adviser.
                        Kissinger and the NSC staff acted as a buffer between the President and his
                        cabinet departments and agencies, analyzing their recommendations and making
                        sure that the President’s interests were protected. Kissinger’s NSC staff
                        analyzed all foreign policy memoranda, which were then approved by Kissinger
                        himself before they went to the President.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-nixon.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Richard Nixon</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Not surprisingly, President Nixon chose a Secretary of State whom he thought
                        would not challenge him and his NSC staff. Secretary of State William P.
                        Rogers was a former Attorney General under Eisenhower, a lawyer known for
                        administrative and organizational skills, but not for his breadth of foreign
                        policy expertise. The President and Kissinger reserved for themselves the
                        big policy issues: Vietnam, the Soviet Union, China, and strategic arms
                        limitation. They set up special communications channels on these issues
                        unknown to the rest of the bureaucracy, withheld information, and excluded
                        Rogers and other official NSC members from key meetings. Part of the problem
                        was the President’s aversion to large gatherings and his reclusive
                        personality. Kissinger’s penchant for secrecy and his natural rivalry with
                        Rogers and Secretary of Defense Melvin Laird were other contributing
                        factors.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="nixon-foreignpolicy">
                    <head>Nixon’s Foreign Policy </head>
                    <p>President Nixon pursued two important policies that both culminated in 1972.
                        In February he visited Beijing, setting in motion normalization of relations
                        with the People's Republic of China. In May, he traveled to the Soviet Union
                        and signed agreements that contained the results of the first <ref
                            target="/milestones/1969-1976/salt">Strategic Arms Limitation Treaty
                            talks (SALT I)</ref>, and new negotiations were begun to extend further
                        arms control and disarmament measures.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-nixon-china.jpg"/>
                        <head>Nixon's Visit to China</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>These developments marked the beginning of a period of <ref
                            target="/milestones/1969-1976/detente">“détente”</ref> in line with a
                        general tendency among Americans to favor a lower profile in world affairs
                        after the <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976/foreword">Vietnam War</ref>,
                        which finally ended in 1975 with the last withdrawal of U.S. personnel.
                        While improvements in relations with the Soviet Union and the People’s
                        Republic of China signaled a possible thaw in the Cold War, they did not
                        lead to general improvement in the international climate. The international
                        economy experienced considerable instability, leading to a significant
                        modification of the international financial system in place since the end of
                        World War II. </p>
                    <p>During the Nixon Administration, international scientific, technological, and
                        environmental issues grew in prominence. In October 1973, Congress passed
                        legislation creating the Bureau of Oceans and International Environments and
                        Scientific Affairs (OES), to handle environmental issues, weather, oceans,
                        Antarctic affairs, atmosphere, fisheries, wildlife conservation, health, and
                        population matters. The Department had difficulty filling the new Assistant
                        Secretary position until January 1975, when the former Atomic Energy
                        Commissioner, <persName>Dixie Lee Ray</persName>, took the job. However, she
                        resigned six months later claiming that OES was not playing a significant
                        policy role.</p>
                    <p>Although Secretary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/rogers-william-pierce">Rogers</ref>
                        still had broad responsibility for foreign policy, including Europe, the
                        Middle East, Africa, Latin America, and international organizations, the
                        Department of State resented its exclusion from key policy decisions, and
                        the Secretary continually fought to make his views known. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="kissinger">
                    <head>Kissinger Becomes Secretary of State</head>
                    <p>During 1973, the Watergate scandal proved a major distraction to the nation
                        and overshadowed any achievements President Nixon gained in foreign affairs.
                        When the President focused on foreign policy, he was accused of trying to
                        distract public attention from charges of abuse of power and avoiding the
                        impeachment process. Disappointed by the Watergate scandal and tired of
                        fighting bureaucratic battles, Secretary Rogers resigned on September 3,
                        1973. President Nixon named Kissinger as Secretary of State—in addition to
                        his role as National Security Adviser. With one man doing both jobs, the
                        problems that Rogers faced disappeared, but Kissinger at times found himself
                        in an awkward position when, as National Security Adviser, he had to make
                        judgments on the Department of State’s position.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/kissinger-henry-a.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Henry A. Kissinger</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Many of Kissinger’s NSC staff moved to important positions in the Department,
                        creating an inner circle within the agency. In 1973, Winston Lord became
                        Director of the Policy Planning Staff, and Helmut Sonnenfeldt became
                        Counselor. In 1975, Lawrence Eagleburger was confirmed as Under Secretary of
                        State for Management, and Harold Saunders took over as the Director of
                        Intelligence and Research.</p>
                    <p>Kissinger was a very demanding Secretary of State; he was hard on his staff
                        and hard on himself. He worked a brutal number of hours seven days a week,
                        and he expected his aides to do the same. In the course of his tenure as
                        Secretary of State, he flew 565,000 miles, making 213 visits to foreign
                        countries. He once visited 17 countries in 18 days, and after the October
                        1973 war, Kissinger spent 33 consecutive days in the Middle East negotiating
                        disengagement between Israel and Syria. Despite his self-admitted “merciless
                        driving” of his staff, morale improved at the Department during his tenure
                        as Secretary. Foreign Service officers and Civil Servants appreciated his
                        conceptual abilities as a strategist. They were also relieved that under his
                        stewardship the Department of State was once again at the center of the
                        foreign policy process. As Kissinger tackled all the complexities that faced
                        a Secretary of State, he came to rely more and more upon the Department’s
                        permanent staff. </p>
                    <p>Because of growing Congressional and public disapproval of the fact that
                        Kissinger was wearing two hats, he resigned as National Security Adviser in
                        late 1975. Nixon’s successor, President Gerald R. Ford, named Lieutenant
                        General Brent Scowcroft, Kissinger’s deputy at the NSC, as National Security
                        Adviser.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="carter">
                    <head>Carter's Foreign Policy</head>
                    <p>The election of Democrat Jimmy Carter as President in 1976 brought a new
                        emphasis, based on Carter’s personal ideology, to U.S. foreign policy.
                        Carter believed that the nation’s foreign policy should reflect its highest
                        moral principles—a definite break with the policy and practices of the Nixon
                        Administration. In 1977, Carter said, “For too many years, we’ve been
                        willing to adopt the flawed and erroneous principles and tactics of our
                        adversaries, sometimes abandoning our own values for theirs. We’ve fought
                        fire with fire, never thinking that fire is sometimes best quenched with
                        water. This approach failed, with Vietnam the best example of its
                        intellectual and moral poverty. But through failure we have now found our
                        way back to our own principles and values, and we have regained our lost
                        confidence.”</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-carter.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Jimmy Carter</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Carter refused to continue the past practice of overlooking the human rights
                        abuses of our own allies, and was particularly tough on South Korea, Iran,
                        Argentina, South Africa, and Rhodesia (Zimbabwe). He also ended more than 30
                        years of U.S. political and military support to one of Latin America’s most
                        abusive leaders—President Somoza of Nicaragua.</p>
                    <p>Carter clearly defined the foundation of his foreign policy: “Our policy is
                        based on an historical vision of America’s role. Our policy is derived from
                        a larger view of global change. Our policy is rooted in our moral values,
                        which never change. Our policy is reinforced by our material wealth and by
                        our military power. Our policy is designed to serve mankind.”</p>
                    <p>Initially, the diplomatic initiatives of President Carter and Secretary Vance
                        were quite successful. In 1978, the Administration completed the process
                        begun during the Nixon Administration and normalized relations with mainland
                        China. President Carter himself facilitated the Camp David Peace Accords
                        between Israel and Egypt, which paved the way for new progress in the Middle
                        East and an end to the long-running hostilities between the two sides.
                        Carter and Vance also persuaded the Senate to consent to a treaty promising
                        to return the Panama Canal to Panamanian control by 1999. In 1979, President
                        Carter and Soviet leader Leonid Brezhnev signed a follow-on nuclear arms
                        control agreement, known as SALT II. </p>
                    <p>Carter’s new emphasis on human rights led to a Congressional requirement for
                        the annual submission by the Department of State of “a full and complete
                        report” on human rights practices around the world. The first volume of the
                        Country Reports on Human Rights Practices covered the year 1976 and was
                        released in 1977. In less than 300 pages, the report analyzed the situation
                        in 82 countries. In contrast, 195 individual reports were included in the
                        volume for the year 2000, covering virtually every country in the world, and
                        the overall report was about 6,000 pages long.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="vance">
                    <head>Jimmy Carter and Cyrus Vance</head>
                    <p>President Jimmy Carter’s new emphasis in foreign policy brought a new
                        approach to policymaking to the Department of State. Secretary of State
                        Cyrus Vance was a soft-spoken man with extensive experience in international
                        law and previous service as Deputy Secretary of Defense under President
                        Johnson.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/vance-cyrus-roberts.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Cyrus Vance</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>He believed strongly in teamwork and focused on making the Department
                        function smoothly and efficiently. Initially, Vance was aided by President
                        Carter’s determination to cut down the size and influence of the NSC, which
                        Carter believed had become too powerful under Presidents Nixon and Ford.
                        Under Vance, the organization charts actually followed the lines of
                        authority. A high proportion of Vance’s assistant secretaries, especially
                        those in the geographic bureaus, were Foreign Service officers. Vance
                        believed in delegation, and he encouraged ambassadors to play a role in
                        policy formulation. He promoted affirmative action and during his tenure,
                        minority Foreign Service officers increased from six to 11 percent and women
                        from 10 to 14 percent of the service. African-American Ambassadors were no
                        longer a rarity—President Carter appointed 14 during his four years in
                        office. </p>
                    <p>Under Vance, the Department of State expanded the role of
                        ambassadors-at-large as government-wide coordinators. Ambassador-at-Large
                            <persName>Henry Owen</persName>, for instance, coordinated economic
                        summits. There was an Ambassador at Large for Mexican Affairs and one for
                        Refugee Affairs. At the urging of Congress, the Department of State created
                        a coordinator for human rights issues in April 1975; a position which
                        President Carter and Congress upgraded in August 1977 to Assistant Secretary
                        for Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs. The war on drugs resulted in the
                        1978 creation of a Bureau of Narcotics Matters to coordinate the
                        international narcotics control activities of all U.S. agencies. In 1980, a
                        Bureau of Refugee Programs was split off from the Bureau of Human Rights to
                        deal with the avalanche of refugee problems and issues.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="iraniancrises">
                    <head>The Iranian Hostage Crisis </head>
                    <p>Representing the United States abroad has been a dangerous job since the
                        beginning of the Republic, but that was never truer than during the Carter
                        Administration. In the wake of a successful revolution by Islamic
                        fundamentalists against the pro-American Shah of Iran, the United States
                        became an object of virulent criticism and the U.S. Embassy in Tehran was a
                        visible target. On November 4, 1979, Iranian students seized the embassy and
                        detained more than 50 Americans, ranging from the Chargé d’Affaires to the
                        most junior members of the staff, as hostages. The Iranians held the
                        American diplomats hostage for 444 days. While the courage of the American
                        hostages in <placeName>Tehran</placeName> and of their families at home
                        reflected the best tradition of the Department of State, the Iran hostage
                        crisis undermined Carter’s conduct of foreign policy. The crisis dominated
                        the headlines and news broadcasts and made the Administration look weak and
                        ineffectual. Although patient diplomacy conducted by Deputy Secretary Warren
                        Christopher eventually resolved the crisis, Carter’s foreign policy team
                        often seemed weak and vacillating.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-iraniancrisis.jpg"/>
                        <head>U.S. hostage being paraded in front of the public</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The Administration’s vitality was sapped, and the <placeName>Soviet
                            Union</placeName> took advantage of America’s weakness to win strategic
                        advantage for itself. In 1979, Soviet-supported Marxist rebels made strong
                        gains in <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, <placeName>Angola</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>Mozambique</placeName>. <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> fought
                        a successful border war with <placeName>China</placeName> and took over
                            <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> from the murderous Khmer Rouge. And, in
                        late 1979, the Soviet Union invaded Afghanistan to support its shaky Marxist
                        government. </p>
                    <p>In light of these challenges to global stability, President Carter
                        significantly altered his view of both the Soviet Union and the advice of
                        his own advisers. Carter initially favored Secretary <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/vance-cyrus-roberts">Vance</ref>’s
                        policy of negotiation, but by 1980 was more receptive National Security
                        Adviser <persName>Zbigniew Brzezinski</persName>’s more confrontational
                        stance. Once again the National Security Council and the Department of State
                        were in open conflict. The issue came to a head when Secretary Vance opposed
                        a mission to rescue the hostages in Iran—a move championed by Brzezinski.
                        Vance had been correct—the 1980 mission was a debacle. But Vance was
                        frustrated and he resigned in protest in April 1980. Cyrus Vance was the
                        first Secretary of State clearly and publicly to tie his resignation to a
                        difference of opinion over policy since <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/bryan-william-jennings">William
                            Jennings Bryan</ref> in 1915. Carter chose Senator Edmund Muskie as his
                        new Secretary.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="reforms">
                    <head>Landmark Departmental Reform </head>
                    <p>In 1980, Congress passed the landmark Foreign Service Act, the first new
                        legislation on the service since 1946, designed to address problems both at
                        home and overseas. The act was the culmination of reform initiated by Vance
                        and Deputy Secretary of State <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/christopher-warren-minor">Warren M.
                            Christopher</ref> and implemented by Under Secretary of State for
                        Management Benjamin Read. </p>
                    <p>The act created a Senior Foreign Service (SFS) to address a real
                        problem—there were too many senior officers and not enough senior posts.
                        Now, the number of senior personnel would be related to the number of
                        available jobs. Those who did not pass the close scrutiny and rigorous
                        standards for the SFS would be assured a 20-year career and a pension.
                        Foreign Service pay was raised and overseas allowances and spousal rights
                        were liberalized. The Foreign Service Reserve System ended with the
                        acknowledgement that it that had not worked as planned, and specialists who
                        had been part of the “Wristonization” experiment of the 1950s were
                        transferred back into the Civil Service. The act created a Foreign Service
                        of 6,850 people and a domestic work force of 3,800 Civil Servants, for a
                        total of about 10,650 employees.</p>
                    <p>The Foreign Service Act encouraged qualities in the Foreign Service that were
                        essential to the modern practice of diplomacy. Under Secretary of State for
                        Political Affairs <persName>David D. Newsom</persName> summarized these
                        qualities in 1978: “An understanding of our own nation; a balanced
                        sensitivity to other societies and peoples; a firm grasp of the subject
                        matter of international relations; and the skill to bring this knowledge
                        together in advancing both the interests of our country and the
                        establishment of working understandings with others.”</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="hostageend">
                    <head>An End to the Hostage Crisis </head>
                    <p>Republican Ronald Reagan defeated Carter in the 1980 presidential election.
                        Although Deputy Secretary of State Warren Christopher had completed
                        negotiations under Algerian auspices to free the American hostages in
                        Tehran, President Carter and Secretary of State Edmund S. Muskie, suffered
                        to their last day in office. On January 20, 1981, the hostages were finally
                        freed—but only after Ronald Reagan had been sworn in as president. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="conc6">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The Carter Administration, which had begun with such high hopes, ended its
                        term locked in a cold freeze with the Soviet Union, including escalating
                        confrontations in Africa, South Asia, and Southeast Asia. The good work it
                        had accomplished during its early years faded in popular memory. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="endofcoldwar">
                <head>The End of the Cold War, 1981-1992</head>
                <div type="subchapter">
                    <head>The End of the Cold War, 1981-1992</head>
                    <p>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="sh-berlin-wall.jpg"/>
                            <head>The Fall of the Berlin Wall</head>
                        </figure>
                        <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName> inherited a country demoralized and on
                        the defensive in the face of Soviet expansionism. By the end of the period,
                        the Berlin Wall had fallen, the Soviet satellite states of Eastern Europe
                        were free, and the Soviet Union itself disbanded. But the United States and
                        its diplomats struggled to cope with new threats to global stability—and
                        take advantage of new opportunities.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="worldin1981">
                    <head>The World in 1981</head>
                    <p>President Reagan entered office in January 1981, determined to contain, if
                        not “roll back,” Soviet expansionism in global trouble spots such as
                        Afghanistan and Angola. The United States and its European allies found
                        themselves in frequent disagreement over the western response to Soviet
                        moves against the burgeoning Solidarity movement in Poland and European
                        participation in the Soviet natural gas pipeline from Western Europe to
                        Siberia. The Reagan Administration adopted a two-pronged approach to
                        authoritarian governments in Asia, Africa, and Latin America. The Central
                        Intelligence Agency provided military assistance for “freedom fighters” to
                        combat left-wing regimes, while the Department of State provided diplomatic
                        incentives for right-wing regimes to allow free elections.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="haig">
                    <head>The President and Secretary Haig</head>
                    <p>The new President acknowledged his own lack of experience in international
                        affairs, and nominated a recognized authority in the field, General
                        Alexander M. Haig, Jr., as Secretary of State. Although Haig was a military
                        man, he was politically adept and played a key role in domestic as well as
                        foreign policy under President Nixon. A former Commander-in-Chief of the
                        U.S. European Command, Haig was also well versed in current military
                        strategy on both sides of the Iron Curtain. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/haig-alexander-meigs.jpg"/>
                        <head>General Alexander M. Haig, Jr.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>During the transition, Reagan assured Haig that his administration would
                        speak with one voice on foreign policy—but the reality was sometimes
                        different. Haig described his role as the “vicar” for the “formulation,
                        conduct, and articulation of foreign policy.” But because Haig had no prior
                        personal relationship with the President and White House advisers strictly
                        controlled access to the Oval Office, there was little policy coordination
                        and the government spoke with several voices on foreign policy. Both sides
                        were suspicious of the other and refused to send Reagan a draft directive
                        defining National Security Council responsibilities. As a result, during its
                        first year the Administration lacked the traditional foreign affairs
                        machinery necessary to coordinate long-term planning. Foreign policy
                        decision-making was chaotic.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="haigandstate">
                    <head>Secretary Haig and the Department</head>
                    <p>As Secretary, Haig did exercise control over the decision-making process
                        within the Department of State. Deputy Secretary of State William P. Clark,
                        although lacking deep experience in foreign affairs, was a personal friend
                        of the President whom Haig expected to act as an “interpreter” between the
                        Department of State and the White House. Haig selected Walter J. Stoessel,
                        Jr. as Under Secretary for Political Affairs, the highest post in the
                        Department reserved by tradition for career Foreign Service officers. Within
                        a year, Clark moved to the White House as National Security Adviser and
                        Stoessel was promoted, becoming the first Foreign Service officer to serve
                        as Deputy Secretary of State.</p>
                    <p>Four of the five Assistant Secretaries for the geographic bureaus were also
                        career appointees, including Stoessel’s eventual replacement, Lawrence S.
                        Eagleburger, the Assistant Secretary for European Affairs. But only one of
                        Haig’s five appointees, Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs
                        Herman Cohen, remained on the job for eight years.</p>
                    <p>In addition to Robert C. McFarlane, who became Counselor of the Department,
                        Haig tapped several outside experts in national security affairs, including
                        Paul D. Wolfowitz for Director of the Policy Planning Staff and Richard R.
                        Burt for Director of the Bureau of Politico-Military Affairs. Wolfowitz,
                        Burt, and McFarlane functioned as the Secretary’s “brain trust” to generate
                        ideas outside the normal Foreign Service and Civil Service channels. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="reaganforeignpolicy">
                    <head>Reagan’s Foreign Policy</head>
                    <p>The Reagan Administration also came to Washington determined to combat
                        communism—especially in Latin America. Reagan and his advisers focused in
                        particular on El Salvador, Nicaragua, and Cuba. Haig decided to make El
                        Salvador a "test case" of his foreign policy. Conflicts between the White
                        House and the State Department and with the Congress, however, frustrated
                        the Administration’s bold plans. While Haig sought a significant increase in
                        military assistance to El Salvador, Congress made certification of progress
                        on human rights a quid pro quo. The two branches of government clashed
                        regularly over assistance and certification. </p>
                    <p>Administration officials also disagreed on China policy. For over a decade,
                        the White House had managed most high-level contacts between Washington and
                        Beijing. Under Haig, the Department of State assumed primary responsibility
                        for the formulation and implementation of the Administration's China policy.
                        Haig wanted to transform the informal alliance with China into a “strategic
                        association” to block Soviet “hegemony” in Asia, but the President insisted
                        on loyalty to Taiwan. The Administration debate on Taiwan, especially over
                        the sale of military aircraft, resulted in a crisis in relations with China,
                        which was only alleviated in August 1982, when, after months of arduous
                        negotiations, the United States and China issued a joint communiqué on
                        Taiwan in which the United States agreed to limit arms sales and China
                        agreed to seek a “peaceful solution.”</p>
                    <p>In the critical Middle East region, the White House, preoccupied with its
                        domestic agenda, largely deferred to the Department of State and its Foreign
                        Service experts. The Department continued negotiations to implement the Camp
                        David Peace Accords, a task complicated by the assassination of Egyptian
                        President Anwar al-Sadat in October 1981, and the June 1982 Israeli invasion
                        of Lebanon. Philip C. Habib, the President’s special envoy, conducted
                        Kissinger-like shuttle diplomacy to reach a ceasefire agreement.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="shultz">
                    <head>Secretary Shultz Takes Charge </head>
                    <p>After Secretary Haig resigned in late June 1982, citing a recent shift from
                        the "careful course" of the Administration’s foreign policy, Reagan turned
                        to George P. Shultz, who would serve as Secretary of State for 6-1/2
                        years—the longest tenure since Dean Rusk in the 1960s. An economist by
                        training, Shultz had held three cabinet-level posts during the Nixon
                        Administration and brought to the job of Secretary of State long experience
                        in government and economic diplomacy. Despite his frequent clashes with
                        Secretary of Defense Casper Weinberger over major issues of foreign policy,
                        Shultz forged an effective partnership with President Reagan by the end of
                        the President's first term. Shultz deferred to Reagan on major foreign
                        policy decisions, while Reagan delegated to Shultz the details of
                        diplomacy.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/shultz-george-pratt.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State George Shultz</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Shultz relied primarily on the Foreign Service to formulate and implement the
                        Reagan’s foreign policy. However, he believed that the Deputy Secretary of
                        State should be a political appointee, as familiar with senior officials in
                        the White House as with those in the Department. He first selected Kenneth
                        W. Dam, a law professor, to serve as his alter ego; in June 1985, Shultz
                        recruited John C. Whitehead, an investment banker, to fill the post. Many of
                        the principal officers appointed by Haig remained to serve under the new
                        Secretary. Eagleburger, for example, stayed as Under Secretary for Political
                        Affairs until May 1984, when another career appointee, Michael H. Armacost,
                        replaced him. By the summer of 1985, Shultz had personally selected most of
                        the senior officials in the Department, emphasizing professional over
                        political credentials in the process.</p>
                    <p>In his farewell address to the Department, Shultz commented that the decision
                        to surround himself with Foreign Service officers had been “one of the
                        smartest things I’ve done.” The Foreign Service responded in kind by giving
                        Shultz its “complete support,” making him one of the most popular
                        Secretaries since Dean Acheson. </p>
                    <p> From 1982 to 1989, Shultz was the driving force behind the Administration’s
                        effort to promote peace between Israel and its neighbors. In response to the
                        escalating violence in the region, Reagan sent a Marine contingent to
                        protect the Palestinian refugee camps and support the Lebanese Government.
                        After a year of sustained diplomatic effort, the October 1983 bombing of the
                        Marine barracks in Beirut killed 241 U.S. servicemen, the most serious
                        foreign policy reversal of Reagan’s first term.</p>
                    <p>Reagan’s decision to give the National Security Council staff operational
                        responsibility in the Middle East led to the most serious setback of his
                        second term, the Iran-Contra affair, when Administration officials devised a
                        complicated covert plan to raise money for the anti-government “contra”
                        forces in Nicaragua through the sale of missiles to Iran. The resulting
                        controversy allowed the Department of State to resume control of Middle East
                        policy. By December 1987, Shultz had assembled a strong team of
                        professionals when the Intifada, or Palestinian uprising, challenged Israeli
                        authority in the West Bank and Gaza Strip. After six months of shuttle
                        diplomacy, Shultz had established a diplomatic dialogue with the Palestine
                        Liberation Organization in December 1988, laying the groundwork for further
                        negotiations during the next administration.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="europe">
                    <head>The United States in Europe</head>
                    <p>Shultz believed that the Department’s most important task was the conduct of
                        its Soviet and European diplomacy. By the summer of 1982, relations were
                        strained not only between Washington and Moscow but also between Washington
                        and key capitals in Western Europe. In response to the imposition of martial
                        law in Poland the previous December, the Reagan administration had
                        prohibited U.S. companies as well as their European subsidiaries or
                        licensees from involvement in the construction of a natural gas pipeline
                        from Siberia to West Germany. European leaders vigorously protested
                        sanctions that damaged their interests in the pipeline but not U.S.
                        interests in grain sales to the Soviet Union. Shultz finally resolved this
                        “poisonous problem” in December 1982. The Americans agreed to abandon
                        sanctions against the pipeline, and the Europeans agreed to adopt stricter
                        controls on strategic trade with the Soviets.</p>
                    <p>A more controversial issue was the NATO Ministers’ 1979 “dual track”
                        decision: if the Soviets refused to remove their SS-20 medium range
                        ballistic missiles within four years, then the Allies would deploy a
                        countervailing force of cruise and Pershing II missiles in Western Europe.
                        When negotiations on these intermediate nuclear forces (INF) stalled, 1983
                        became a year of the protest. Shultz and other Western leaders worked hard
                        to maintain allied unity amidst popular anti-nuclear demonstrations in
                        Europe and United States. In spite of Western protests and Soviet
                        propaganda, the allies began deployment of the missiles as scheduled in
                        November 1983.</p>
                    <p>As the missiles were installed, Shultz thought the time was right “to resume
                        a dialogue with the Soviets if we could.” But Secretary Shultz was out of
                        sync with the President and his hard-line advisers. In March 1983, the
                        President announced the Strategic Defense Initiative and called the Soviet
                        Union an “evil empire”—without consulting the Secretary of State beforehand.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="gorbachev">
                    <head>Gorbachev and Perestroika</head>
                    <p>The policy struggle in Washington further intensified when a new Soviet
                        leader, Mikhail Gorbachev, emerged in March 1985. In order to restructure
                        the Soviet economy and reform domestic society, Gorbachev needed to reduce
                        military spending at home and political tensions abroad. His goal was a
                        fundamental change in the relationship between the superpowers and his
                        method was arms control agreements. Shultz encouraged Reagan to develop a
                        personal relationship with Gorbachev. Reagan and Gorbachev held four summit
                        meetings between November 1985 and May 1988 in Geneva, Reykjavik,
                        Washington, and Moscow.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-reagan-gorbachev.jpg"/>
                        <head>President Ronald Reagan and Soviet Leader Mikhail Gorbachev in
                            Russia.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Their personal relationship produced its most practical result in December
                        1987, when the two leaders signed the Intermediate Range Nuclear Forces
                        (INF) Treaty. The treaty, which eliminated an entire class of missiles in
                        Europe, was a milestone in the history of the Cold War. Although Gorbachev
                        took the initiative, Reagan was well prepared to adopt a policy of
                        negotiations. Shultz and the Department of State played a key role in this
                        diplomatic approach.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="managementfails">
                    <head>Management Fails the Department </head>
                    <p>The Department of State has at times been more adept at the formulation of
                        policy than the management of its resources. The Reagan Administration was
                        no exception. The Under Secretary for Management was described at the time
                        as responsible for “keeping the Foggy Bottom bureaucracy in paper clips and
                        the embassies stocked with gin and hors-d'oeuvres.” This attitude was
                        further reflected in the fact that Richard T. Kennedy, who held the position
                        during Haig’s tenure, also served as the U.S. Representative to the
                        International Atomic Energy Agency in Vienna. The American Foreign Service
                        Association complained that Kennedy was therefore unable to devote enough
                        attention to the Department’s budget and personnel. Secretary Shultz
                        assigned a higher priority to management and chose Ronald I. Spiers, the
                        first and only career appointee to serve as Under Secretary for Management.
                        Spiers held the job for five years—longer than anyone else before him.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/shultz-george-pratt.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State George Pratt Shultz</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The Department of State faced additional challenges in managing its budget
                        and personnel. “Reaganomics”—the effort to cut government expenditures and
                        revenues despite a dramatic increase in defense spending—left little money
                        to improve the state of the nation's diplomatic machinery. During the Reagan
                        Administration, the Department of Commerce was the only cabinet-level agency
                        to receive a smaller portion of the budget than the State Department. From
                        1981 to 1988, spending for State Department operations and programs
                        decreased as a percentage not only of the federal budget but also of the
                        gross domestic product. The financial situation deteriorated in particular
                        when Congress passed the so-called Gramm-Rudman-Hollings Act in 1985, which
                        mandated spending cuts to reduce the federal budget deficit. Under
                        Gramm-Rudman, the Department endured what one high-level official called
                        “its worst budget crisis in modern times.” Shultz pleaded for budgetary
                        relief every year and some cuts were restored, but the Department’s
                        infrastructure and employee morale were damaged by the forced economies.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="politicizedappointees">
                    <head> Department Appointments Politicized </head>
                    <p>The process of appointment of principal officers in the Department of State
                        and ambassadors became increasingly politicized during the Reagan
                        Administration, with some appointments causing controversy. Reagan was
                        forced to withdraw the nomination of Ernest Lefever as Assistant Secretary
                        of State for Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs when a majority on the
                        Senate Foreign Relations Committee concluded that he was not an advocate for
                        human rights and rejected his nomination. </p>
                    <p>The Foreign Service Act of 1980 stipulated that the President should
                        “normally” appoint Foreign Service officers, not political supporters, as
                        ambassadors. Nonetheless, during his first term Reagan proposed nearly as
                        many political as Foreign Service ambassadors. The American Foreign Service
                        Association charged in 1981 that this record made “a mockery of the careful
                        selection and long and varied experience which professional career officers
                        bring to senior assignments within the service.” Although Shultz reversed
                        the trend, the number of non-career ambassadors was higher under Reagan than
                        under any President since Herbert Hoover. Although Reagan made some
                        distinguished appointments from outside the Foreign Service—such as Arthur
                        Burns in Bonn—his critics pointed to ambassadors of lesser distinction.
                        Spiers publicly complained in 1987 that such appointments demonstrated “a
                        lack of respect” that would “have a corrosive effect on the career service.”
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="foreignservicechanges">
                    <head>More Change for the Foreign Service</head>
                    <p>The Department also began the implementation of the Foreign Service Act of
                        1980. Although the creation of a Senior Foreign Service was designed to
                        advance some officers to the highest ranks, the “up-or-out” promotion system
                        forced many—including those with valuable language and area expertise—into
                        early retirement. The Department offered “limited career extensions” for
                        those retirees whose experience merited retention but not promotion. The
                        “up-or-out” system, however, left too many officers down and out, resulting
                        in a serious threat to morale. In 1988, Congress temporarily suspended the
                        system pending a thorough review of its impact on the service. </p>
                    <p>Throughout the decade, the Foreign Service also faced the public perception
                        that it had become the last refuge of an elitist group of white men. In
                        accordance with the 1980 act, the Department tried to make the service more
                        “representative of the American people” by recruiting, hiring, and promoting
                        women and minorities. From 1980 to 1990, the percentage of women in the
                        Foreign Service doubled to nearly 25 percent, although the percentage of
                        minorities rose by only one-quarter to 12.5 percent. In spite of
                        “substantial progress,” Spiers conceded in 1985 that the lack of equal
                        opportunity was still a serious problem, as reflected by the low number of
                        women and minorities serving in the Senior Foreign Service. Despite the new
                        emphasis on diversity, allegations of discrimination persisted. The
                        Department continued to fight two lawsuits--one filed by women in 1976 and
                        the other by African-Americans in 1986--that claimed a systematic denial of
                        promotion and career opportunity.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="spying">
                    <head>Embassies Subject to Violence, Spying </head>
                    <p>During the 1980s, the Department of State spent more time and money than ever
                        before on the security of its posts and personnel. From 1980 to 1989, more
                        U.S. civilians died overseas in the line of duty than during the entire 19th
                        century. The Department did not address security matters fully until after
                        two devastating terrorist attacks on U.S. installations: In April 1983, a
                        truck loaded with explosives blew up outside the embassy in Beirut, killing
                        63 employees, including 17 U.S. diplomatic and military personnel; and in
                        September 1985, another explosion at the Embassy killed an additional 12
                        Foreign Service nationals. After a thorough study of the terrorist threat
                        against U.S. diplomatic installations, the Department, with Congressional
                        approval, began a $1-billion program for more than 60 construction projects
                        worldwide. </p>
                    <p>U.S. installations abroad also remained a primary target for espionage,
                        particularly by the Soviet Union. Twice in one year, the Department learned
                        that the Soviet intelligence agency had seriously compromised security at
                        the embassy in Moscow. In January 1985, the U.S. Marine Corps announced that
                        one of its security guards at the Embassy had passed classified information
                        to a Russian woman. In August of the same year, the Department ceased
                        construction on the new embassy building, when an inspection revealed that
                        Soviet intelligence agents had embedded countless listening devices in the
                        concrete. After a comprehensive review of the project and years of debate in
                        Congress, the Clinton Administration finally adopted many of the
                        recommendations of the inspection report. By then, the unfinished embassy
                        had become the most expensive construction project in U.S. diplomatic
                        history. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="baker">
                    <head>President Bush and Secretary Baker</head>
                    <p>During most of the Cold War, the Secretary of State and the National Security
                        Adviser competed for influence over the President’s foreign policy.
                        Presidential candidate <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName> pledged to end
                        the centralization of foreign policy decision-making in the White House,
                        which had reached extremes during the “Iran-Contra affair.” Bush wanted
                        ambassadors to have a larger advisory role, while a reduced NSC staff would
                        be less intrusive. Choosing his cabinet from among people he already knew,
                        Bush selected one of his closest friends, <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/baker-james-addison">James A. Baker
                            III</ref>, as Secretary of State. Baker had served as White House Chief
                        of Staff and Secretary of the Treasury under Reagan. Bush characterized
                        Baker as a “gimmie,” and announced his appointment less than 24 hours after
                        his election. The foreign policy of the Bush presidency benefited greatly
                        from the personal rapport between the two men. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="../secretaries/baker-james-addison.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State James Baker</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Bush brought his own considerable foreign policy experience to the
                        presidency. In addition to his eight years as Vice President, he had served
                        as Ambassador to the United Nations, U.S. envoy to the People’s Republic of
                        China, and as Director of the CIA. Bush was at the helm of a
                        smooth-functioning national security team comprised of Secretary Baker,
                        Secretary of Defense Richard Cheney, National Security Adviser Brent
                        Scowcroft, and Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff Colin L. Powell.
                        Although intense policy differences occurred, a collegial approach to
                        foreign policy-making was the norm, especially in the “breakfast group” of
                        Baker, Cheney, and Scowcroft, which met weekly to iron out problems that
                        could not be resolved through the bureaucratic channels of interdepartmental
                        meetings or the deputies committee system.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="bushi">
                    <head>Bush’s Foreign Policy</head>
                    <p>With the end of the Cold War, the Bush foreign policy team faced such radical
                        and rapid global changes that the Department of State seemed capable only of
                        reacting to events. The collapse of first the Soviet bloc in Eastern Europe
                        and then the Soviet Union itself, the reunification of Germany, the end of
                        apartheid in South Africa, pro-democracy demonstrations in China’s Tiananmen
                        Square, the international coalition formed to combat Iraq’s Saddam Hussein
                        in the Middle East stretched the ability of the U.S. foreign policy
                        establishment—from the President to the Department of State—to stay in front
                        of events and formulate policy. </p>
                    <p>Despite Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev’s perestroika and glasnost, the fate
                        of Soviet reforms remained unknown. During his first summit meeting, when
                        Bush asked what the Soviet Union would look like in several years, Gorbachev
                        quipped, “Even Jesus Christ couldn’t answer that question!” Lacking both
                        clairvoyance and an internal Soviet monitoring system, the Department of
                        State struggled to keep abreast of the rapid changes within the
                        disintegrating Soviet empire. Initially, the Department lagged behind the
                        NSC in pushing the President to move U.S.-Soviet relations beyond
                        confrontation to a period of engagement. Secretary of State Baker argued
                        that until the division of Europe ended, the Administration had to be
                        cautious about prematurely declaring an end to the Cold War. </p>
                    <p>Secretary Baker relied heavily on a trio of close advisers. He named Dennis
                        Ross, a specialist on Soviet and Middle Eastern affairs, as Director of the
                        Policy Planning staff. Ross operated as virtually a one-man command staff,
                        proposing positions on critical issues that Baker often adopted wholesale.
                        Equally influential was Robert Zoellick, dubbed the Secretary’s “second
                        brain” by journalists. Appointed Counselor of the Department, Zoellick
                        served as Baker’s “gatekeeper” for policy papers and personnel access. He
                        also became the chief sub cabinet official on German reunification. To
                        ensure that the Department’s views were presented to the public as Baker
                        wanted, he appointed former Treasury staff aide Margaret deB. Tutwiler as
                        Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs and Department Spokesman. Baker’s key
                        aides built a valuable working partnership with their counterparts at the
                        NSC, forging an alliance that oversaw German reunification and provided
                        critical support for democratic change in the former Soviet republics and
                        Eastern Europe.</p>
                    <p>Bush’s own active involvement and direct communications with foreign leaders
                        surprised many career officers at the Department, and not everyone was
                        comfortable with informal lines of communication. Vernon Walters, the U.S.
                        Ambassador to the Federal Republic of Germany, reportedly resigned in part
                        due to frustration after continuously hearing second-hand reports from the
                        West German Foreign Ministry of agreements reached independently by Bush and
                        Chancellor Helmut Kohl.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="berlinwall">
                    <head>The Berlin Wall Falls and USSR Dissolves</head>
                    <p>Initially, Department of State officials and Bush’s foreign policy team were
                        reluctant to speak publicly about German “reunification” due to fear that
                        hard-liners in both the German Democratic Republic (GDR) and the Soviet
                        Union would stymie reform. Although changes in the GDR leadership and
                        encouraging speeches by Gorbachev about nonintervention in Eastern Europe
                        boded well for reunification, the world was taken by surprise when, during
                        the night of November 9, 1989, crowds of Germans began dismantling the
                        Berlin Wall—a barrier that for almost 30 years had symbolized the Cold War
                        division of Europe. By October 1990, Germany was reunified, triggering the
                        swift collapse of the other East European regimes.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-berlinwall2.jpg"/>
                        <head>People celebrating the fall of the Berlin Wall.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Thirteen months later, on December 25, 1991, Gorbachev resigned and the Union
                        of Soviet Socialist Republics dissolved. President Bush and his chief foreign
                        policy advisers were more pro-active toward Russia and the former Soviet
                        republics after the collapse of the Communist monolith than while it was
                        teetering. In a series of summits during the next year with the new Russian
                        President Boris Yeltsin, Bush pledged $4.5-billion to support economic
                        reform in Russia, as well as additional credit guarantees and technical
                        assistance.</p>
                    <p>The two former Cold War adversaries lifted restrictions on the numbers and
                        movement of diplomatic, consular, and official personnel. They also agreed
                        to continue the <ref target="/milestones/1989-1992/strategic-arms-reduction"
                            >Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty negotiations (START)</ref>, begun
                        before the collapse of the Soviet Union, which set a goal of reducing their
                        strategic nuclear arsenals from approximately 12,000 warheads to 3,000-3,500
                        warheads by 2003. In January 1993, three weeks before leaving office, Bush
                        traveled to Moscow to sign the START II Treaty that codified those nuclear
                        reductions.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="globaleproblems">
                    <head>New Global Problems Emerge</head>
                    <p>Rapid change in Europe was mirrored by equally complex problems in China,
                        South Asia, and the Korean peninsula. In the <placeName>People’s Republic of
                            China</placeName>, tanks and troops attacked pro-democracy demonstrators
                        in Tiananmen Square in June 1989, effectively suppressing the movement.
                        Media coverage of the suppression made a powerful impression, as nations
                        around the world realized that China was not prepared to follow the
                            <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName> and <placeName>Eastern
                            Europe</placeName> and allow its people more freedom. The United States
                        joined the protest of many other nations by imposing economic sanctions and
                        condemning the suppression and killing of the pro-democracy demonstrators. </p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-tsquare.jpg"/>
                        <head>"The Goddess of Democracy" erected in Tiananmen Square during the
                            protest.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In an effort to improve U.S. relations with China, Bush sent Deputy Secretary
                        of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/eagleburger-lawrence-sidney"
                            >Lawrence Eagleburger</ref> and National Security Adviser Brent
                        Scowcroft on a secret trip to China in July 1989. When word of their visit
                        became public several months later, the President was criticized for
                        pursuing “constructive engagement” with the Chinese Communist government so
                        soon after the Tiananmen Square killings and his announcement of a U.S. ban
                        on all high-level talks between the two countries. </p>
                    <p>Unlike the serious human rights abuses in China, the changes taking place in
                        South Africa signaled a peaceful end to the practice of apartheid. Secretary
                        Baker described U.S. policy as a “classic carrot-and-stick strategy,” in
                        which the Department of State issued threats of continued sanctions as well
                        as invitations to the United States to both black and white South African
                        leaders as incentives to end apartheid. The Department’s African Bureau took
                        the lead. Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs Herman Cohen met
                        privately with South African President F.W. de Klerk to inquire whether he
                        was prepared to end apartheid.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-de-klerk.jpg"/>
                        <head>South African President, F.W. de Klerk</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>By late 1989, de Klerk had desegregated many public places, released numerous
                        African National Congress (ANC) and other anti-apartheid political
                        prisoners, and discussed black-white power sharing. A few months later, de
                        Klerk released Nelson Mandela from prison after 27 years of incarceration.
                        Mandela proved to be a potent symbol of national healing, respected by most
                        blacks and whites in South Africa. Recognizing that the government was on a
                        course toward a nonracial, multiparty democracy, the ANC soon ended its
                        policy of armed struggle against the South African Government.</p>
                    <p>The Department of State’s African Bureau also played a critical role in
                        bringing about the end of the proxy war in Angola between the pro-Soviet and
                        pro-U.S. factions. In the spring of 1991, Cohen conducted negotiations with
                        the Soviets that ended more than 20 years of support for guerrilla warfare
                        between contending groups, although peace remained elusive in that
                        war-ravaged country.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="firstgulf">
                    <head>The First Gulf War</head>
                    <p>Of all the policy successes during this era, the Department of State and
                        President Bush are most clearly associated with the successful effort to
                        roll back the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-gulf-war.jpg"/>
                        <head>President G. H.W. Bush visiting the Troops during the First Gulf
                            War</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>When Saddam Hussein invaded his small, oil-rich neighbor in the summer of
                        1990, the Department faced its first full-scale post-Cold War international
                        crisis. Bush’s foreign policy team forged an unprecedented international
                        coalition consisting of the NATO allies and the Middle Eastern countries of
                            <placeName>Saudi Arabia</placeName>, <placeName>Syria</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to oppose Iraqi aggression. Although
                            <placeName>Russia</placeName> did not commit troops, it joined the
                        United States in condemning Iraq, its long-time client state. The Department
                        of State orchestrated the diplomacy for this grand coalition’s effective air
                        campaign in January 1991, which was followed by “Operation Desert Storm,” a
                        100-hour land war, which expelled Iraqi forces from Kuwait. </p>
                    <p>During the Gulf crisis, Secretary of State Baker relied heavily on two
                        men—John Bolton, Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization
                        Affairs, who played a significant role in coordinating relations with the
                        United Nations, and Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs Robert
                        Kimmitt, who was Baker’s day-to-day crisis manager. One innovation that
                        greatly facilitated decision-making during the Gulf War was the use of
                        teleconferences, which saved many hours of travel time. Instead, Baker and
                        others could communicate and display charts through cameras and television
                        screens.</p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="sh-bolton-john.jpg"/>
                        <head>Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs,
                            John Bolton</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>After the success in Kuwait, President Bush paid special tribute to the
                        Foreign Service officers who labor in relative obscurity until they are
                        caught up in a dangerous conflict or become the victims of international
                        terrorism. President Bush made a special visit to the Department of State to
                        honor 33 employees for their service at our embassies in Baghdad and Kuwait,
                        which included finding food and supplies for trapped Americans in those
                        countries and helping children to safe havens after fighting erupted.
                        Acknowledging the peril most Americans never see, Bush said, “I know that
                        often your jobs are not comfortable or safe.” </p>
                    <p>Iraq was not the only trouble spot in the Middle East during Bush’s four
                        years in office. The perennial tension between Israel and its Arab neighbors
                        continued to test the expertise of the many U.S. ambassadors and area
                        experts. Baker’s personal involvement, reflected in numerous trips to the
                        region, helped bring about the first face-to-face talks between Israel and
                        all of its Arab neighbors in Madrid, beginning in October 1991. Secretary
                        Baker’s <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976/arab-israeli-war-1973">“shuttle
                            diplomacy”</ref> rivaled <ref
                            target="/departmenthistory/people/kissinger-henry-a">Henry
                            Kissinger</ref>’s in 1974. From the beginning of Baker’s tenure until
                        August 23, 1992, when he resigned to become White House Chief of Staff, he
                        made 217 trips abroad.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/eagleburger-lawrence-sidney">Lawrence
                            Eagleburger</ref>, who succeeded Baker, became the first Foreign Service
                        officer to serve as Secretary of State. During a 27-year government career,
                        Eagleburger had been a staffer for Kissinger’s National Security Council,
                        and held numerous senior positions at the Department of State, including
                        Under Secretary for Political Affairs, Deputy Under Secretary for
                        Management, and Assistant Secretary for European Affairs. Eagleburger's
                        appointment reflected Bush’s deep respect for the Foreign Service. Bush
                        compiled an impressive record of nominating career officers to
                        ambassadorships (72 percent), one of the best records for all Presidents in
                        the post-1945 era.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="conc7">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>As the 1990s began, the Cold War was finally over and the United States was
                        the sole remaining superpower. But hopes for a safer, more peaceful world
                        would be dashed as regional conflicts and global problems challenged the
                        American foreign policy establishment to chart a new course for the United
                        States.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
