<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Buildings of the Department of State</title>
                <title type="short">Buildings</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State, 1985</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Printed in 1985, scanned and OCRed and adapted to TEI in 2008 </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Homes of the Department of State, 1774-1976</hi> originally
                    appeared in monthly installments in the Department of State <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi> from October 1975 to July 1976 and was published as a
                    consolidated booklet in 1985. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="1-homes-cover.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>Original Foreword</head>
                <p>The contents of this publication appeared in monthly installments in the
                    Department of State <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi> from October 1975 to July
                    1976. This publication consolidates those articles, which are unaltered except
                    for minor changes and corrections.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi> series derived from a manuscript completed
                    in 1956 by Richard S. Patterson, then a member of the Historical Division,
                    Department of State. This earlier work has been completely revised, and the last
                    chapter, "Extended and Remodeled New State Building," consists almost entirely
                    of new material. Two chapters are completely new—"The Period of the Continental
                    Congress, September 1774—October 1781" and "Nassau Hall, Princeton, N.J., June
                    30, 1783—November 4, 1783." An Appendix, also new, treats various buildings used
                    as annexes.</p>
                <p>Homer L. Calkin, Chief of the Special Studies Branch, Historical Studies
                    Division, directed this revision. Edwin S. Costrell, Chief of the Historical
                    Studies Division, supervised the overall project. Dana J. Johnson, Catherine M.
                    Desseau, and Kathleen Fitzpatrick typed the manuscript. Installments in the <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi> benefited from the editorial assistance of
                    Catherine F. George and the proofreading of Karen J. Corso and Alyce Fay Hawley.
                    Mary Kay Fleck and Phyllis Young of the Offiсе of Media Services, provided
                    helpful technical assistance in adapting the <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi>
                    articles for the format of this publication.</p>
                <signed>Lee H. Burke</signed>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section1">
                <head>The Period of the Continental Congress</head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1774-09">Sept. 1774</date>—<date when="1781-10">Oct. 1781</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>The Department of State came into existence through a process of gradual
                    evolution which began in <date when="1774">1774</date>. Initially, the <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/continental-congress">Continental
                        Congress</ref> exercised control over American foreign relations. Under its
                    auspices committees of Congress managed foreign affairs from November 1775 to
                    October 1781.</p>
                <p>The first such committee was the Committee of Secret Correspondence,<note n="1">By resolution of April 17, 1777, the name of the committee was changed to
                        the "<ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/secret-committee">Committee for
                            Foreign Affairs</ref>," <hi rend="italic">Journals of the Continental
                            Congress, 1774-1789</hi> (Washington, 1904-1937), VII, 274. [Hereafter
                        cited as <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>.]</note> which was appointed
                    pursuant to a resolution of Congress of November 29, 1775, "for the sole purpose
                    of corresponding with our friends in Great Britain, Ireland, and other parts of
                    the world." In the beginning, the Committee consisted of <persName>John
                        Dickinson,</persName>
                    <persName>Benjamin Franklin,</persName>
                    <persName>Benjamin Harrison,</persName>
                    <persName>John Jay,</persName> and <persName>Thomas Johnson.</persName>
                    <note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> III, 392.</note> However, there were frequent
                    changes in the membership. On many occasions Congress in the Committee of the
                    Whole acted on foreign affairs matters thereby limiting the power of the
                    Committee of Secret Correspondence and its successor, the Committee for Foreign
                    Affairs. For instance, the Congress "prepared in the minutest detail the
                    instructions to Franklin when he was elected commissioner on September 27, 1777,
                    to negotiate a treaty with France."<note n="3">Graham H. Stuart, <hi rend="italic">The Department of State</hi> (New York, 1949), p.
                        1.</note> James Lovell, a member of the Committee for Foreign Affairs, wrote
                    on August 6, 1779, that <quote>"there is really no Such Thing as a Comtee of
                        foreign affairs existing, no Secretary or Clerk, further than I persevere to
                        be one and the other. The Books and Papers of that extinguished Body lay yet
                        on the Table of Congress or rather are locked up in the Secretary's private
                        Box."</quote>
                    <note n="4">Francis Wharton, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Revolutionary Diplomatic
                            Correspondence of the United States</hi> (Washington, 1889), III,
                        288.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Thus, from 1774 to 1781, the buildings in which foreign relations were managed
                    were the buildings occupied by the Continental Congress.<note n="5">The twelve
                        buildings in which the Continental Congress met during its lifetime are
                        identified and discussed in a work by Robert Fortenbaugh entitled <hi rend="italic">The Nine Capitols of the United States</hi> (York, Pa.,
                        1948).</note> Congress met in Carpenters' Hall, Philadelphia, for its first
                    session, commencing on September 5, 1774. The subsequent sessions in
                    Philadelphia were held in the Pennsylvania State House, now known as
                    "Independence Hall," except for a short time in 1778, when it met in "College
                    Hall." During the Revolutionary War, the advance of British troops forced
                    Congress to leave Philadelphia on two occasions. From December 20, 1776, to
                    February 27, 1777, Congress met in Baltimore in a house owned by Henry Fite. On
                    September 27, 1777, it met at the Court House at Lancaster, Pennsylvania, and on
                    September 30 moved to the York Court House, where it remained until June 27,
                    1778. It was not until 1781, when the Department of Foreign Affairs was
                    established by the Continental Congress, that a building separate from those
                    occupied by the Congress was used for foreign affairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section2">
                <head>Carpenters' Hall, <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1774-09-05">Sept. 5, 1774</date>—<date when="1774-10-26">Oct. 26,
                        1774</date>
                </head>
                <p>The first meeting place of the Continental Congress was Carpenters' Hall in
                        <placeName>Philadelphia.</placeName>
                    <note n="6">Philadelphia was chosen as the meeting place because of its central
                        location and accessibility and also because of its size and importance. In
                        1774, it had an estimated population of approximately 40,000 making it the
                        second largest city in the British Empire. (<hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> p.
                        13.)</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="2-carpenters-hall.jpg"/>
                        <head>Carpenter's Hall</head>
                    </figure> According to John Adams:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"At ten the delegates all met at the City [or Smith's]
                        Tavern, and walked to the Carpenters' Hall, where they took a view of the
                        room, and of the chamber where is an excellent library… The general cry was,
                        that this was a good room, and the question was put, whether we were
                        satisfied with this room? and it passed in the affirmative."<note n="7">Charles Francis Adams, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Works of John
                                Adams</hi> (Boston, 1850), vol. II, 365.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entry briefly records that on Monday, <date when="1774-09-05">September 5, 1774</date>, <q rend="blockquote">"A number
                        of the Delegates chosen and appointed by the Several Colonies and Provinces
                        in North America to meet and hold a Congress at Philadelphia assembled at
                        the Carpenters' Hall...."<note n="8">
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> I, 13.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>Carpenters' Hall was built in <date when="1770">1770</date> for the Carpenters'
                    Company of Philadelphia—a society of master craftsmen patterned after the guilds
                    of England. The two-story structure was located at the end of an alley, south
                    from Chestnut Street, between Third and Fourth Streets. <q rend="blockquote">"The lower floor, consisting of one large room was occupied by the
                        Congress, and the rooms in the second story by committees."<note n="9">Gaillard Hunt, <hi rend="italic">The Department of State of the United
                                States; Its History and Functions</hi> (New Haven, 1914), p.
                            427.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>Congress used Carpenters' Hall as its meeting place only for the first session,
                    from September 5, 1774, to October 26, 1774. It was in Carpenters' Hall that the
                    Congress first decided how the colonies should meet British threats to their
                    freedom. Grievances were openly stated, and a policy of resistance to the
                    British was agreed upon.</p>
                <p>On October 26, 1774, Congress dissolved itself. However, it resolved that a
                    Second Continental Congress should meet in Philadelphia on the "tenth of May
                    next unless the redress of grievances, which we have desired, be obtained before
                    that time."<note n="10">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> I, 102.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Carpenters' Hall was used for various purposes after Congress moved elsewhere.<note n="11">The primary source for this paragraph was a pamphlet by the
                        U.S. Department of the Interior National Park Service, entitled <hi rend="italic">Carpenters' Hall, Independence National Historical
                            Park</hi> (Washington, 1967).</note> During the Revolutionary <pb n="2"/>War, the lower floor was used as a hospital. Arms and equipment were stored in
                    the basement. In 1790 the Secretary of War, <persName>Henry Knox,</persName>
                    rented the ground floor. In 1791 it was used as the first Bank of the United
                    States. Subsequently, it was rented by many organizations until 1856 when the
                    Carpenters' Company decided to renovate the building, <quote>"especial care to
                        be taken to preserve, as much as possible every feature in said Hall as it
                        now exists indicative of its original finish."</quote>
                    <note n="12">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> [р. 10].</note> It exists today as one of the
                    historic sites in <placeName>Independence National Historical Park in
                        Philadelphia.</placeName>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section3">
                <head>Pennsylvania State House (Independence Hall),
                        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/> Intermittingly from <date when="1775-05-10">May 10, 1775</date> to <date when="1781-03-01">March 1, 1781</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Second Continental Congress convened in Philadelphia on May 10, 1775. This
                    time it met in the Pennsylvania State House, or Independence Hall, as it is now
                    called. It was in this building that the Declaration of Independence was signed. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="3-pa-state-house.jpg"/>
                        <head>Pennsylvania State House</head>
                    </figure> The Committee of Secret Correspondence met here from its establishment
                    in 1775 until it was replaced by the Committee for Foreign Affairs on April 17,
                    1777, except for the brief time that Congress was in Baltimore. It was here,
                    too, that the first diplomatic representative to the American Colonies,
                        <persName>Conrad Alexandre Gérard</persName> of France presented his letter
                    of credence to Congress on August 6, 1778. The State House had been built for
                    the provincial government, which for a half century previously had had no
                    official building. Construction on the building began in 1732, and although the
                    Assembly had met in the building as early as 1735, it was not completed until
                    1748. When completed, the building had a facade 107 feet in length connected by
                    closed arcades, or piazzas, to wing buildings some 50 feet long. The following
                    is a description of the building:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The main building had a decked gable roof, balustraded
                        between the chimneys and surmounted by a centrally located cupola.... The
                        first floor contained two chambers about 40 feet square, separated by a
                        spacious center hall about 20 feet wide.... The State House was not
                        elegantly furnished. Chairs, tables, curtains, screens, and other items
                        purchased for the building were never unduly expensive .... The building
                        appears to have been heated originally by open fireplaces for which stoves
                        were later substituted."<note n="13">Edward M. Riley, <hi rend="italic">Independence National Historical Park, Philadelphia, Pa.,</hi>
                            National Park Service Historical Handbook Series No. 17 (Washington,
                            1954, revised 1956), pp. 4-5.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>In 1750 the Assembly directed that a tower be erected to contain a staircase and
                    belfry. By 1753 the tower was completed and the State House bell (now called the
                    Liberty Bell) was hung. This was the bell that was rung to announce the adoption
                    of the <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/declaration">Declaration of
                        Independence</ref> on <date when="1776-07-08">July 8, 1776.</date>
                </p>
                <p>There have been various alterations of the State House through the years. When
                    the British occupied Philadelphia in 1777-1778, they damaged the State House by
                    converting the first floor into a barracks and making the second floor into a
                    hospital for wounded American prisoners. The old steeple had rotted and become
                    so weak that it was taken down in 1781. A new one was built in 1828. Congress
                    Hall was begun in 1787 and finished in 1789. The City Hall building was begun in
                    1789 and finished in 1791. These two halls formed part of the complex of which
                    the State House was a part. From 1802 until 1828 Charles Wilson Peale used the
                    Assembly Room and second floor of the State House for a museum and portrait
                    gallery.</p>
                <p>Beginning in 1828, there have been a series of restorations, continuing even at
                    the present time. Since 1898 the State House has been a public shrine in
                    Independence National Historical Park.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section4">
                <head>
                    <persName>Henry Fite</persName>'s House, <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1776-12-20">Dec. 20, 1776</date>—<date when="1777-02-27">Feb. 27,
                        1777</date>
                </head>
                <p>In mid-December 1776 Congress decided to move to Baltimore to escape capture by
                    the advancing British.<note n="14">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> VI, 1027.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="4-henry-fites-house.jpg"/>
                        <head>Henry Fite's House</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>It first met in Baltimore on December 20, 1776, and remained just over two
                    months, until February 27, 1777.</p>
                <p>The old Court House was offered to the Congress as a meeting place, but according
                    to the diary of John Adams, it chose to meet "in the last house at the west end
                    of Market Street, on the south side of the street; long chamber with two
                    fireplaces, two large closets and two doors."<note n="15">Fortenbaugh, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 22.</note>
                </p>
                <p> The house belonged to <persName>Henry Fite,</persName> who rented it to the
                    Congress for three months for 60 pounds. It was described as follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"'Congress Hall,' as it was afterwards called, was a
                        spacious three-story and dormered attic brick building-10 windows long, with
                        3 doors, and 5 windows deep with a center door on the short side. It stood
                        on the corner of Liberty and Baltimore Street, as Market Street is now
                        named... 'Congress Hall' was destroyed by fire on September 4, 1860, but a
                        bronze tablet marks the approximate site of the building."<note n="16">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 23.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>The time in Baltimore was a trying one for the Congress. There were complaints
                    that "the town was exceedingly expensive, and exceedingly dirty, that at times
                    members could make their way to the assembly hall only on horseback, through
                    deep mud."<note n="17">Edmund Cody Burnett, <hi rend="italic">The Continental
                            Congress</hi> (New York, 1941), p. 233.</note>Throughout the session
                    there was inadequate representation from the various colonies. However, it is
                    worth noting that Samuel Adams had declared in the earlier part of the session,
                    "We have done more important business in three weeks than we had done, and I
                    believe should have done, at Philadelphia, in six months."<note n="18">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 232.</note>The appointment of a committee
                    of five to prepare a plan for obtaining foreign assistance was included in the
                    business of the Congress.</p>
                <p>When conditions made it possible to return to Philadelphia, Congress resolved, on
                    February 27, 1777, "that when Congress adjourns this evening, it be adjourned to
                    meet at <pb n="3"/>
                    <pb n="4"/> Philadelphia, on Wednesday next."<note n="19">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> VII, 168.</note> On March 4, 1777, Congress
                    met again in Philadelphia at the State House.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section5">
                <head>Court House, <placeName>Lancaster</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1777-09-27">Sept. 27, 1777</date>
                </head>
                <p>By September 1777 the British were again approaching
                        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> and threatening the safety, of the
                    Congress. On September 14 the Congress resolved that if it "shall be obliged to
                    remove from Philadelphia, Lancaster shall be the place at which they shall
                    meet."<note n="20">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> VIII, 742.</note> Further pressure by the
                    British finally forced the Congress to leave Philadelphia on September 18.<note n="21">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 754.</note> Tо avoid the enemy, the
                    delegates took a round-about way to Lancaster, generally arriving there
                    September 26.<note n="22">Fortenbaugh, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p.
                        33.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="6-court-house-lancaster.jpg"/>
                        <head>Court House, Lancaster</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Congress held only one session in Lancaster, on September 27, 1777, in the Court
                    House.<note n="23">Most authorities assert that the meeting place was at the
                        Court House; however, the documentary evidence is not conclusive on this
                        point.</note> The record of this session indicates that all of the business
                    conducted on that day in Lancaster related to military matters.<note n="24">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> VIII, 755.</note> At the end of the day,
                    Congress resolved to adjourn to York, across the Susquehanna River, "there to
                    meet on Tuesday next, at 10 o'clock."<note n="25">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>The Lancaster Court House was built in 1739. Perhaps the best description of the
                    building was recorded by William Marshe in 1744:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"It is a pretty large brick building two stories high. The
                        ground room... is very spacious...</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"Fronting the justices' bench, and on each side of it, are
                        several long steps or stairs.... This Court House is capable to contain
                        above 800 persons without incommoding each other.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"When we had surveyed this room we went up stairs into one
                        overhead. This is a good room, and has a large chimney... Adjoining to this
                        room, is a smaller one...</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"On the top of the Court House is a kind of cupola. We
                        ascended a ladder and got into it. From hence we had a complete view of the
                        whole town, and the country several miles round, and likewise of part of the
                        Susquehanna river at twelve miles distance."<note n="26">"Marshe's
                            Journal," in William Henry Egle, ed., <hi rend="italic">Notes and
                                Queries,</hi> 3d series, vol. I (Harrisburg, Pa., 1895), 277.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>The Court House was destroyed by fire in June 1784. A new Court House was
                    subsequently erected on the same site and was completed in 1787.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section6">
                <head>Court House, <placeName>York</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1777-09-30">Sept. 30, 1777</date>-<date when="1778-06-27">June 27,
                        1778</date>
                </head>
                <p>After meeting one day at Lancaster, Congress moved to York so that the
                    Susquehanna River would be between it and the enemy. It was at York from
                    September 30, 1777, until June 27, 1778. While there, Congress met at the York
                    County Court House. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="5-court-house-york.jpg"/>
                        <head>Court House, York</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The Court House was erected in 1754. Its cupola was like that on the Court House
                    in Lancaster.<note n="27">Information for this and the following two paragraphs
                        was provided by Landon Charles Reisinger, Historical Researcher for The
                        Historical Society of York County, in a letter to Lee Burke, July 7,
                        1975.</note> There were subsequent additions to the building after it was
                    first built. In 1790 an adjoining office building was constructed. In 1792 a
                    gallery was built in the court room, and in 1796 the interior was completed as a
                    formal court room. In 1814 two additional gables and a large clock tower were
                    added.</p>
                <p>In 1838 construction on a new and larger Court House on a new site was begun, and
                    the old Court House was demolished in 1841. The York County Bicentennial
                    Commission is presently planning to reconstruct the old Court House in time for
                    the 1977-78 celebration of the 200th Anniversary of the meeting of the Congress
                    in York.</p>
                <p>It was while the Congress was at York that it passed the Articles of
                    Confederation, although they were not to become effective until ratified by the
                    various states. It was also while the Congress was at York that a treaty of
                    Alliance was signed on February 6, 1778, with the French. Three months later a
                    committee of the Congress began to prepare instructions to American
                    commissioners at foreign courts.</p>
                <p>Congress received word that the British army had evacuated Philadelphia on June
                    18, 1778. On June 24 it resolved that Congress adjourn on next Saturday, June
                    27, "from this place to meet at Philadelphia, on Thursday, the 2 day of July
                    next."<note n="28">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XI, 641.</note>
                </p>
                <p>When the members of Congress returned to Philadelphia, they found that the
                    British had left the State House and many other buildings in a disgraceful
                    condition, and there was mention of the Congress "shuffling from Meeting House
                    to College Hall."<note n="29">"Letter from Henry Laurens to the President of
                        South Carolina (Rawlins' Lowndes)," July 15, 1778, in Edmund C. Burnett, <hi rend="italic">Letters of Members of the Continental Congress,</hi> vol.
                        III (Washington, 1926), 333.</note> Josiah Bartlett, a delegate from New
                    Hampshire, in a letter dated July 13, 1778, wrote:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Congress meets in the College Hall, as the State House
                        was left by the enemy in a most filthy and sordid situation, as were many of
                        the public and private Buildings in the City. Some of the genteel Houses
                        were used for Stables and Holes cut in the Parlor floors &amp; their
                        dung shoveled into the Cellars. The country Northward of the City for
                        several Miles is one common waste. The Houses burnt, the Fruit Trees
                        &amp; others cut down and carried off, fences carried away, Gardens and
                        Orchard..."<note n="30">Quoted in Fortenbaugh, op. cit., p. 48. A shortened
                            version of the letter is in Burnett, <hi rend="italic">Letters of
                                Members of the Continental Congress,</hi> op. cit., pp.
                            328-329.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>Because of the conditions at Philadelphia, Congress had some difficulty
                    reassembling. Although some members met on July 2 according to the adjournment,
                    it was not until July 7 that there was a quorum and business could be conducted
                    in a normal manner. On December 1, 1778, the Congress extended its working
                    hours, meeting at least two hours each evening until the present state of
                    foreign affairs had been fully considered.</p>
                <pb n="5"/>
            </div>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section7">
                <head>
                    <placeName>13 South Sixth Street, Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1781-10">October 1781</date>-<date when="1783-06">June 1783</date>
                </head>
                <p>About eight years before the Department of State was set up under the
                    Constitution, the <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/framework">Department of Foreign Affairs</ref>, directed by a Secretary for Foreign
                    Affairs, was established by a resolution passed by the Continental Congress on
                    January 10. 1781.<note n="1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XIX, 43.</note> This new Department was
                    justified by the Congress on the basis that "the extent and rising power of
                    these United States entitles them to a place among the great potentates of
                    Europe while our political and commercial interests point out the propriety of
                    cultivating with them a friendly correspondence and connection."<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Secret Journals of Congress</hi> (Boston, 1821), II,
                        580.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="7-13-south-6th-st-phl.jpg"/>
                        <head>13 South Sixth Street, Philadelphia</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The new Secretary for Foreign Affairs was <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/livingston-robert-r">Robert R.
                        Livingston</ref>,<note n="3">On February 22, 1782, Congress adopted new
                        regulations for the Department of Foreign Affairs, and therein the full
                        title of the Secretary was "Secretary to the United States of America, for
                        the department of foreign affairs." <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXII,
                        87-92.</note> a delegate from New York and a former member of the Foreign
                    Affairs Committee.<note n="4">Livingston was elected by Congress August 10,
                        1781, <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> XXI, 851-852: he took the oath of office
                        on October 20, 1781, and entered upon his duties the same day, MS.
                        Department of State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 59, I, 281, No. 79, I,
                        287, and No. 126, 1: his salary was $4000, Wharton, <hi rend="italic">op.
                            cit.,</hi> V, 199-202; Congress accepted his resignation on June 4,
                        1783, <hi rend="italic">Journals, </hi> XXIV, 382.</note> Soon after taking
                    office, Livingston set up his offices in a small, plain, brick house at 13 South
                    Sixth Street, a short distance north of the northeast corner of Sixth and
                    Chestnut Streets, in Philadelphia.<note n="5">At this time, the seat of
                        government under the Articles of Confederation was at Philadelphia.</note>
                    This building was the first home of an office of foreign affairs as an entity
                    separate from Congress, although the Secretary was still, in reality, an agent
                    of Congress, which continued to involve itself closely in the conduct of foreign
                    relations.</p>
                <p>The building at 13 South Sixth Street had been erected in 1773. Measuring but 12
                    feet across the front by 30 feet in depth, it consisted of three stories and an
                    attic, with two rooms to each story; it had a gable roof which sloped to front
                    and rear.<note n="6">Thompson Westcott, <hi rend="italic">The Historic Mansions
                            and Buildings of Philadelphia</hi> (Philadelphia, 1877), p. 318. Also,
                        see "Sketch from C.A. Poulson by D.J. Kennedy," in the collections of the
                        Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia (reproduced in this
                        article).</note> A room on the second floor overlooking the street served as
                    Livingston's office. Various "great personages" of the time "frequently
                    clambered up the dark and narrow winding stairs" to transact business with the
                    Secretary.<note n="7">This description of the Department is based on an account
                        given by John Fannin Watson, who visited the building in the late 1820's and
                        talked with its then owner, the same Pierre Etienne DuPonceau who had served
                        as Livingston's second Under Secretary nearly fifty years before; John F.
                        Watson, <hi rend="italic">Annals of Philadelphia, Being a Collection of
                            Memoirs, Annecdotes, and Incidents of the City and Its Inhabitants</hi>
                        (Philadelphia and New York, 1830), pp. 365. 366.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The new Department was very small in those early days. Livingston estimated the
                    Department's total contingent expenses for 1783 for messenger, stationery,
                    office hire, wood, and candles to be the relatively modest sum of $1,200.<note n="8">MS. Department of State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 144, p. 49,
                        June 23. 1782.</note> Livingston's staff, when it was fully organized,
                    consisted of two Under Secretaries, Lewis Richard Мorris and Pierre Etienne
                    DuPonceau;<note n="9">For biographical sketches, see <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of American Biography</hi> (New York 1928—), XIII, 215-216;
                        V, 525-526.</note> a clerk and translater of French, the Reverend John P.
                    Tetard; and clerk, Walter Stone.<note n="10">MS. Department of State,
                        Continental Congress Papers, No. 79, III, 113, February 26, 1783.</note> The
                    two Under Secretaries shared the back room of the second floor, and the
                    translator and the clerk occupied the ground <pb n="7"/>floor.<note n="11">Watson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit., </hi> pp. 365-366.</note> This staff
                    dealt with an American diplomatic corps which consisted at the time of
                    Livingston's resignation on June 4, 1783, of five Ministers Plenipotentiary, all
                    of whom, except Jefferson, were engaged in negotiating peace in Paris.
                        <persName>Benjamin Franklin</persName> was the Minister in Paris,
                        <persName>John Adams</persName> had been accredited to the Hague and
                        <persName>John Jay</persName> to Madrid, and <persName>Henry
                        Laurens</persName> and <persName>Thomas Jefferson,</persName> with the same
                    rank as their colleagues, were Commissioners for the negotiation of peace.<note n="12">The peace treaty was signed before Jefferson left for Paris.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The building at 13 South Sixth Street ceased to be the home of the Department of
                    Foreign Affairs after Livingston resigned. A succession of tenants then occupied
                    it, using it at different times as a residence, a shop, and a boarding house.<note n="13">It was valued under the act of Congress approved July 9,
                        1798,"for the valuation of Lands and Dwelling Houses" (I Stat. 580), at the
                        sum of $1,000; MS. National Archives, Record Group 58, Book A, "List of the
                        Taxes Assessed on each dwelling house which with the outhouse Appurtenant
                        thereto and the lot on to which the same are erected not exceeding two Acres
                        in any case in the First Assessment district in the first division of the
                        State of Pennsylvania and exceeding in Value the Sum of One Hundred
                        Dollars." October 1, 1798, p. 153.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In 1844, this and adjoining property extending to the corner of Sixth and
                    Chestnut Streets was purchased by Abraham Hart, member of a firm of booksellers,
                    who tore down the old buildings in March 1846 and erected a five-story building
                    known as "Hart's Buildings." This building, which was occupied by stores and
                    other businesses, was destroyed by fire on December 26, 1851. It was rebuilt by
                    the new owner, A. J. Drexel, in the 1890s.<note n="14">Westcott, op. cit., p.
                        320; John F. Watson, <hi rend="italic">Annals of Philadelphia, and
                            Pennsylvania, in the Olden Time</hi> (Philadelphia, 1898), III, 283. 15
                        MS. Department of State, file 102.5/7- 953. Also, see Martin I. Yoelson,
                        Supervisory Interpretive Specialist, Independence National Historical Park,
                        Philadelphia, to Edwin S. Costrell, Chief, Historical Studies Division,
                        March 27, 1975.</note> The entire city block where the house at 13 South
                    Sixth Street formerly stood now forms part of Independence Mаll.<note n="15">MS. Department of State, file 102.5/7-953. Also, see Martin I. Yoelson,
                        Supervisory Interpretive Specialist, Independence National Historical Park,
                        Philadelphia, to Edwin S. Costrell, Chief, Historical Studies Division,
                        March 27, 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>When Livingston resigned as Secretary of the Department of Foreign Affairs,
                    Congress again assumed direct control of foreign relations until a successor to
                    Livingston could be named. In the resolution accepting Livingston's resignation,
                    Congress directed that the Department's papers should be turned over to the
                    Secretary of Congress, Charles Thomson.<note n="16">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXIV, 382.</note> In a letter to Livingston
                    dated, June 4, 1783, Thomson wrote that, "as the resolve only directs me to
                    receive the papers into my care, and as I am determined to have nothing to do
                    with the business of the office, I must beg the favor of you to order all the
                    papers packed up, sealed with your seal, and then sent to my office, where they
                    shall lie until Congress shall otherwise dispose of them."<note n="17">Wharton, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> VI, 475.</note> The Department's
                    papers were turned over to Thomson, apparently on June 6.<note n="18">"The
                        Papers of Charles Thomson," in <hi rend="italic">Collections оf, the New
                            York Historical Society for the Year 1878 </hi> (New York, 1879), pp.
                        170-171.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section8">
                <head>Nassau Hall, <placeName>Princeton, N.J.</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1783-06-30">June 30, 1783</date>—<date when="1783-11-04">Nov. 4,
                        1783</date>
                </head>
                <p>Following <persName>Robert Livingston's</persName> resignation as Secretary for
                    Foreign Affairs in June 1783, the President of Congress acted as Secretary for
                    Foreign Affairs ad interim until March 1784.<note n="1">Burnett, <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> VII, 192. According to Gaillard Hunt, "Lewis
                        R. Morris, the first Under-Secretary of the Department, had been left by
                        Livingston in charge of the Department's business, but Congress gave him no
                        authority to act, so he soon left the office." (Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op.
                            cit.,</hi> p. 40.)</note> During this time, the papers of the Department
                    of Foreign Affairs remained locked, sealed, and inaccessible, and foreign
                    relations were managed wholly by Congress, upon reports of special committees.<note n="2">Burnett, 
                        <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> pp. 269-270, 461; <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> XXVI, 49-50, 64-65, 104-105.</note> The
                    buildings used by Congress during this period were, therefore, the buildings in
                    which foreign policy was managed. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="8-nassau-hall.jpg"/>
                        <head>A northwest prospect of Nassau Hall, in New Jersey</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>From June 30 to November 4, 1783, Congress met in Nassau Hall in Princeton, New
                    Jersey.<note n="3">There is evidence to suggest that of its first three
                        sessions (June 30, July 1 am 2), Congress met at a house owned by Colonel
                        George Morgan, called "Prospect," See Varnum Lansing Collins, <hi rend="italic">The Continents Congress At Princeton</hi> (Princeton,
                        1908) pp. 43, 57-58.</note> Congress moved there to flee from mutinous
                    troops.<note n="4">Burnett, <hi rend="italic">The Continental Congress</hi> pp.
                        576-580. A primary source for information about the Congress in Princeton
                        was Gary B. Nash, "... <hi rend="italic">and Distinguished Guests"- The
                            Continental Congress at Princeton, 1783</hi> (Princeton, 1962).</note>
                    Since October 1781 when Cornwallis had surrendered his army at Yorktown,
                    Americans had been waiting impatiently for the signing of a peace treaty with
                    Great Britain. As the months passed and the peace negotiations dragged on, the
                    army became increasingly restless, weary of the long war, and impatient with the
                    unfulfillеd promises of Congress for back pаy. On June 20 troops surrounded the
                    Statehouse in Philadelphia, where Congress was meeting in an attempt to satisfy
                    their grievances.</p>
                <p>Although there were no violent incidents, and the mutiny quickly subsided,
                    Congress felt insulted by the event and unsupported by the government of
                    Pennsylvania, which was apparently unwilling or unable to provide protection. A
                    resolution was passed directing Congress "to me (on Thursday next at Trenton
                    Princeton, in New Jersey, in order that further and more effectual measures may
                    be taken for suppressing the present revolt, and maintaining the dignity and
                    authority of the United States."<note n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXIV, 410.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The President of Congress, Elias Boudinot, adjourned the Congress <pb n="9"/> on
                    June 24 and ordered it to reassemble in Princeton on June 26. It actually
                    convened on June 30, 1783.<note n="6">Burnett, <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>
                        VII, 195-6; <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi>, 411.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Princeton may have been chosen by President Boudinot because he was a native of
                    Princeton, his wife was from a prominent Princeton family, Princeton was located
                    approximately midway between New York and Philadelphia, and Boudinot was a
                    Trustee of the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University).<note n="7">Nash, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 7.</note> Princeton may also have
                    been chosen because it had a building large enough in which the Congress could
                    meet.</p>
                <p>Nassau Hall, the principle building of the College, had been erected in 1754-756.
                    It was the largest academic building in the colonies. The following is a
                    description of Nassau Hall based upon the earliest known illustration, which was
                    printed in the <hi rend="italic">New American Magazine</hi> in 1760:<note n="8">Paul Norton and Robert C. Smith, "Nassau Hall—Architecture", in <hi rend="italic">Nassau Hall, 1756-1956---Bicentennial Convocation,
                            September 23, 1956</hi> (condensation of Henry L. Savage, ed., <hi rend="italic">Nassau Halls, 1756-1956,</hi> published by Princeton
                        University, September 22, 1956, and reprinted from <hi rend="italic">The
                            Princeton Alumni Weekly </hi> of September 12, 1956).</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"There are three flat-arched doors on the north side giving
                        access by a flight of steps to the three separate entries (an entry refers
                        here to the hallway on each floor running the full length of the building).
                        At the center is a projecting section of five bays surmounted by a pediment
                        with circular windows, and other decorations. The only ornamental feature
                        above the cornice, is the cupola, standing somewhat higher than the twelve
                        fireplace chimneys. Beyond these there are no features of distinction.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The simple interior design is shown in the plan, where a
                        central corridor provided communication with the students' chambers and
                        recitation rooms, the entrances, and the common prayer hall; and on the
                        second floor, with the library over the central north entrance. The prayer
                        hall was two stories high, measured 32 by 40 feet, and had a balcony at the
                        north end which could be reached from the second-story entry. Partially
                        below ground level, though dimly lighted by windows, was the cellar, which
                        served as kitchen, dining area (beneath the prayer hall), and storeroom. In
                        all there were probably forty rooms for the students, not including those
                        added later in the cellar when a moat was dug to allow additional light and
                        air into that dungeon."</q>
                </p>
                <p>For its regular sessions, Congress met in the college library room, which was
                    over the main entrance. For ceremonial occasions, it adjourned to the prayer
                    hall or chapel on the main floor.</p>
                <p>One such ceremonial event took place on October 31, 1783, when Peter John van
                    Berckel presented his credentials to Congress as the minister representing the
                    Netherlands. Congress was at first embarrassed, as reflected in a letter from
                    Madison, because of having to receive him <quote>"in an obscure village... and
                    without a Minister of F[oreign] A[ffairs]."</quote>
                    <note n="9">Burnett, 
                        <hi rend="italic">The Continental Congress, op. cit.,</hi>
                        p. 587.</note> After extensive preparations, however, the event was a
                    success, facilitated perhaps by information provided just prior to the ceremony
                    that the treaty between the United States and Great Britain had been signed on
                    September 3.</p>
                <p>Congress had been in Princeton for only four months when it adjourned on November
                    4 to meet at Annapolis on November 26. Its stay in Princeton had been brief and
                    very little of great importance had been decided while it was there. Attendance
                    in Congress was often very low, "much of the time no more than six states
                    represented."<note n="10">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid., p. 580.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Nassau Hall remains today as one of the mina buildings on the campus of Princeton
                    University. The interior of the building was destroyed by fire in 1802 and gain
                    in 1855, but in each case the original walls remained. These two restorations,
                    1802 and 1855, as well as subsequent minor alterations changed the building only
                    slightly from its original construction in 1756 to the present-day
                    appearance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section9">
                <head>State House, <placeName>Annapolis</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1783-11-26">Nov. 26, 1783</date>—<date when="1784-08-19">Aug. 19,
                        1784</date>
                </head>
                <p>In 1783 Congress moved the seat of government from Princeton to Annapolis, where
                    it remained until August 19, 1784.<note n="1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXV, 809; XXVII, 632, 636-638, 710.</note>
                    Although the Congress had resolved to meet at Annapolis on November 26, 1783,<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid., XXV, 807.</hi>
                    </note> there was not a sufficient number of members in attendance "to proceed
                    to business" until December 13, 1783.<note n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> XXV, 809.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="9-state-house-annapolis.jpg"/>
                        <head>A front view of the State House at Annapolis</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The papers of the Department of Foreign Affairs remained locked, sealed, and
                    inaccessible,<note n="4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> XXVI, 49-50, 64-65, 104-105; Burnett, <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> VII, 269-70, 461.</note> and the President
                    of Congress acted as Secretary for Foreign Affairs <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>
                    <note n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p.192.</note> until March 2, 1784, when
                    Congress elected Henry Remsen, Jr., "as under secretary in the office for
                    foreign affairs, to take charge of the papers in that office."<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXVI, 122.</note> He served in this
                    capacity, taking charge of the books and papers without other assistance, until
                    Livingston's successor, <persName>John Jay,</persName> entered upon his duties
                    as Secretary for Foreign Affairs in December 1784.<note n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> XXVIII, 150-151.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In Annapolis, Congress met in the Senate chamber of the State Capitol,<note n="8">Fortenbaugh, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 62</note> and while
                    no specific record has been found as to where Remsen had his office in
                    Annapolis, its most probable location was with Congress in the State
                    Capitol.</p>
                <p>Several reasons could be suggested for this conclusion: <list type="simple">
                        <item>1) Remsen was functioning as Under Secretary in Annapolis while the
                            seat of government was there;<note n="9">MS. Department of State,
                                Continental Congress Papers, No. 78, XIX, 463, March 13, 1784; No.
                                181, August 4, 1784.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>(2) the records and papers of his office were there;<note n="10">
                                <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXVII, 632.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>(3) it would have been convenient;</item>
                        <item>(4) the building was spacious, and contained many committee rooms and
                            other office space apart from the Senate chamber where Congress met;<note n="11">William R. Staples, <hi rend="italic">Rhode Island in
                                    the Continental Congress</hi> (Providence, 1870), p. 463, David
                                Howell to William Greene, Governor of Rhode Island; Elihu S. Riley,
                                "The Ancient City." <hi rend="italic">A History of Annapolis, in
                                    Maryland, 1649-1887</hi> (Annapolis, 1887), p. 201.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>(5) when the Maryland General Assembly tendered Congress the use of
                            the State House, it specifically excluded the other public buildings
                            that stood on the public circle, and, in fact, the State Government
                            abandoned the State House altogether during the period that Congress met
                            there;<note n="12">MS. Department of State, file 114.115- 2653, Morris
                                L. Radoff, Archivist, Hall of Records, Annapolis, to G. Bernard
                                Noble, Chief, Division of Historical Policy Research, May 26,
                                1953.</note> and</item>
                        <item>(6) the offer of Annapolis as a temporary seat of government, as
                            conveyed by the Governor of Maryland to Congress in August 1783, stated
                            that the Governor's house and the State House would be made available
                            "for the immediate use of Congress and their officers."<note n="13">MS.
                                Department of State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 46, pp.
                                113-116.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list> Since only the President of Congress would use the Governor's house,
                    occupying it as his residence, Congress and its subordinate officers, of whom
                    Remsen was one, would presumably use the State House-though for business
                    purposes only, finding residences for themselves elsewhere.</p>
                <p>The Maryland State Capitol, or State House, in which the Continental Congress met
                    in 1783-1784, is still standing-although altered and enlarged since that time-on
                    an elevated area called "State Circle" in the center of Annapolis.<note n="14">The following sources were consulted it describing the State Capitol
                        building in Annapolis: <hi rend="italic">The Columbian Magazine</hi>
                        (Philadelphia, 1787-1792), III 80-82, February 1789; David Ridgely, <hi rend="italic">Annals of Annapolis</hi> (Baltimore, 1841), pp. 145-147,
                        208-215, 232-236; Riley, op. cit. , pp. 161-164, 200- 207, 224; and Morris
                        L. Radoff, <hi rend="italic">Buildings of the State of Maryland at
                            Annapolis</hi> (Annapolis 1953, Publications of the Hall of Record,
                        Commission of Maryland No. 9), <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi>
                    </note> Its history extends back to 1769, when the Colonial Assembly
                    appropriated L7,500 sterling toward the erection of a new building on the site
                    of an earlier State House. Although the cornerstone was laid in 1772, the
                    General Assembly did not meet in the building until 1780.</p>
                <p>This building consisted of a basement and two full stories of brick construction
                    surmounted by a wooden superstructure. It measured 120 feet across the front and
                    82 feet in depth exclusive of a semi-octagonal bay which was later removed. A
                    dome, of at least the outside structure of one, in place in 1774, was torn down
                    in 1785 and replaced with another that was begun in 1785 or 1786 and finished on
                    the outside in 1788 and on the inside in 1793.</p>
                <p>The new dome was 40 feet in diameter at its base. Above the dome was cupola, and
                    above it a spire extending 200 feet from the ground.</p>
                <p>The main entrance to the building was through a modest portico facing southeast.
                    This portico opened into a hall that gave a view of the interior of the dome. On
                    the right-hand side of the hall was the Senate chamber and on the left-hand side
                    the chamber of the House of Delegates, each with lobby and a gallery. From the
                    hall two flights of stairs led to offices on the second floor.</p>
                <p>Over the years the interior of the building has been subjected to considerable
                    alteration, and an annex has been added at the rear of the building. Restoration
                    of the old Senate chamber, where the Continental Congress met however, gives to
                    that room today its original appearance.</p>
                <p>Many incidents of historic interest took place in this building. Among them were
                    Washington's resignation as commander in chief of the Continental Army on
                    December 23, 1783, the ratification of the definitive treaty of peace with Great
                    Britain on January 14, 1784, and the meeting of the Annapolis Convention in
                    1786.</p>
                <pb n="11"/>
            </div>
            <pb n="12"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section10">
                <head>French Arms Tavern, <placeName>Trenton</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1784-11-01">Nov. 1</date>—<date when="1784-12-24">Dec. 24,
                        1784</date>
                </head>
                <p>From Annapolis Congress moved to Trenton, New Jersey, where it was in session
                    from November 1 to December 24, 1784. In Trenton Congress met in a building then
                    known as the "French Arms Tavern," which was located on the southwest corner of
                    King (now Warren) and Second (now State) Streets. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="10-french-arms-tavern.jpg"/>
                        <head>The French Arms Tavern, Trenton</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>For nearly the entire time Congress was at Trenton, the papers of the Department
                    of Foreign Affairs were under the control of the Under Secretary, Henry Remsen,
                    Jr.<note n="1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXVI, 122; XXVIII, 150-151.</note> A new
                    Secretary for Foreign Affairs, <persName>John Jay,</persName> had been appointed
                    in May 1784 to succeed <persName>Robert Livingston,</persName> who had resigned
                    11 months before, but he did not enter upon his duties until December 21,
                    1784.</p>
                <p>Although no specific record has been found as to where in Trenton Remsen had his
                    office,<note n="2">No record of where the office was located is known to exist
                        in Trenton; see MS. Department of State, file 102.516-1753, Roger H.
                        McDonough, Director, Division of the State Library, Archives and History,
                        Department of Education, Trenton, New Jersey, to G. Bernard Noble, Chief,
                        Division of Historical Policy Research, June 17, 1953, and
                        enclosures.</note> he was probably with Congress. The French Arms Tavern was
                    a building evidently large enough to have accommodated not only the meetings of
                    Congress and the office of its Secretary, but the Department of Foreign Affairs
                    as well.</p>
                <p>The building known in 1784 as the "French Arms Tavern" had been erected as a
                    residence by <persName>John Dagworthy</persName> in the early 1730's.<note n="3">The description of the French Arms Tavern is based on the following
                        sources: Carlos E. Godfrey, <hi rend="italic">The Mechanics Bank, 1834-1919,
                            Trenton in New Jersey; a History</hi> (Trenton, 1919), pp. 7-53, <hi rend="italic">passim;</hi> Harry J. Podmore, <hi rend="italic">Trenton,
                            Old and New</hi> (Trenton, 1927), pp. 59-64; Trenton Historical Society,
                            <hi rend="italic">A History of Trenton,</hi> 1679-1929 (Princeton,
                        1929), I, 186-187, 191-192, 210, 216, 319, II, 566- 569.</note> In its day
                    it was considered the most beautiful, and was also the largest, house in
                    Trenton. It stood on a lot that had a frontage of 66 feet on King Street and
                    extended back 230 feet on Second Street. Built of stone and stucco, two stories
                    high, with a gabled roof, it consisted of a main structure 45 feet in width and
                    43 feet in depth (inside measurements) plus a narrower extension in the rear on
                    the Second Street side which served as kitchen and servant's quarters. From
                    front to back through the middle of each story of the main structure ran a broad
                    hallway, which contained the staircase; there were four rooms on a floor, each
                    provided with a large fireplace; and there was a spacious room in the attic.
                    Outside the main doorway, on King Street, was a broad landing from which two
                    sets of eight stone steps descended in opposite directions to the sidewalk. To
                    the rear of the house, at the end of the lot, stood a coach house and
                    stables.</p>
                <p>The building was owned by <persName>John Dagworthy</persName> until his death in
                    1756. For two years during this period, from 1740 to 1742, it was the official
                    residence of Governor Lewis Morris. In 1760 it was sold to Samuel Henry, an iron
                    manufacturer, who made it his residence until he leased the property to Jacob G.
                    Bergen in 1780 for use as a tavern.</p>
                <p>Before opening the tavern, which he named "Thirteen Stars," Bergen made extensive
                    changes in the building. He added a third story, with a gabled, dormer-windowed
                    roof; converted two of the first-floor rooms into one room 20 feet in width and
                    43 feet in length, which became known as the "Long Room;" and set up a barroom
                    in the basement. In 1783 the building was described as a "Dwelling-house 45 by
                    43 Feet, <pb n="13"/> 3 Stories, 11 Rooms, 8 with Fire-places—a Kitchen—and
                    Stabling for 12 Horses."</p>
                <p>For a short time, <persName>John Cape</persName> took over the management and
                    changed the name to the French Arms. When Bergen returned to the management in
                    1783, he retained the French Arms name.</p>
                <p>In 1784 a commission appointed by the New Jersey Legislature leased the tavern,
                    which was still the largest building in town, for the use of the Continental
                    Congress. The Long Room was refurnished to serve as the assembly hall; its
                    ceiling was whitewashed, the walls repapered, the floor recarpeted.</p>
                <p>Congress took few actions of any significance during its stay at Trenton. A lot
                    of time was spent in appealing to the states to send delegates, and there was
                    some discussion on establishing a federal city. Congress and its committees
                    continued to direct foreign affairs. Diplomatic relations were established with
                    only two countries by this time;<note n="4">France on August 6, 1778, and the
                        Netherlands on April 19, 1782.</note> however, while at Trenton, the
                    Congress discussed the possibility of appointing ministers to reside at London
                    and at Madrid.<note n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXVII, 675-676, 693-694.</note> On December
                    24, 1784, Congress "adjourned to meet at the city of New York, on the eleventh
                    Day of January following..."<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXVII, 704.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Following the adjournment of Congress on December 24, 1784, Francis Witt ran the
                    tavern under the name of the "Blazing Star" until 1789, when Henry Drake took
                    possession and renamed it the "City Tavern." Drake was followed by a succession
                    of proprietors who continued the tavern under the last-mentioned name until
                    1837. In 1836 the property was sold to the Mechanics &amp; Manufacturers
                    Bank, which razed the old tavern building the following year to make way for a
                    bank building. The site is now occupied by the New Jersey Bank.<note n="7">This
                        bank operates under the original charter granted to the Mechanics &amp;
                        Manufacturers Bank in 1834; telephone conversation with John Cole,
                        Historian, New Jersey National Bank, February 5, 1975.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="14"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section11">
                <head>Fraunces Tavern, <placeName>New York City</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1785-01-11">Jan. 11, 1785</date>—<date when="1788-04-30">Apr. 30,
                        1788</date>
                </head>
                <p>Sometime between December 24, 1784, when Congress adjourned its session in
                    Trenton, and January 11, 1785, the seat of government was moved to New York
                    City. The first meeting place for Congress in New York was the City Hall. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="11-fraunces-tavern-nyc.jpg"/>
                        <head>Fraunces Tavern, New York, restored in 1906-1907</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Although some have stated that the first location of the Department of Foreign
                    Affairs in New York was also in the City Hall in a room above the Council
                    chamber, an item in a Department account book under date of January 19, 1785,
                    seems to contradict this. It indicates "cash paid a cartman for hauling two
                    cases belonging to the Office, from the City Hall, where they had been carried
                    thro' mistake with the Boxes of the Secretary's [Charles Thomson, Secretary of
                    Congress] Office."<note n="1">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Cash
                        Book, 1785-1795, under the date mentioned.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The location of the Department from January 11, 1785, to April 30, 1788, was in a
                    building known as "Fraunces Tavern," which was owned by Samuel Fraunces, a noted
                    innkeeper.<note n="2">For a biographical sketch, see <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of American Biography,</hi> VII, 1.</note> Fraunces Travern
                    was situated on the southeast corner of Great Dock (now Pearl) and Broad
                    Streets.<note n="3">The Department opened for business on January 28, 1785; MS.
                        Department of State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 120, I, 5-6.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of Foreign Affairs shared Fraunces Tavern with the War Office,<note n="4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXVIII, 207-208, March 28, 1785; David C.
                        Franks, <hi rend="italic">The New York Directory </hi> (New York, 1787),
                        under "Knox, Henry" (the only known copy of this New York city directory,
                        the second to be issued, is among the collections of the New York Historical
                        Society).</note> occupying approximately 5 rooms initially, and perhaps for
                    the duration of its stay in Fraunces Tavern. At least one of the rooms was on
                    each of the first two floors.<note n="5">On January 20, 1785, payment was given
                        to laborers for opening boxes belonging to the Department and carrying the
                        cases contained therein "up stairs;" on January 23, 1785, to a woman for
                        sweeping and scrubbing four rooms; and on April 19, 1785, to a laborer for
                        cleaning the street in front of the office (MS. Department of State,
                        Accounts Records, Cash Book, 1785-1795, under the dates mentioned).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Charles Thomson, on behalf of Congress, leased the tavern for two years,
                    commencing May 1, 1785.<note n="6">The indenture was dated April 6, 1785,
                        though endorsed as executed the following day (MS. Department of State,
                        Continental Congress Papers, No. 59, I, 218-220).</note> He was acting under
                    authority of a resolution passed by Congress on April 4, 1785:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">
                        <hi rend="italic">"Resolved,</hi> by nine states, That the Secretary of
                        Congress take a lease from Samuel Frauncis [sic] for his house, now occupied
                        by the public, for the term of two years, at the rate of eight hundred and
                        twelve dollars and one half of a dollar a year:</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"That a warrant be drawn in favour of the said Samuel
                        Frauncis for the sum of sixteen hundred and twenty five dollars, on account
                        of the said rent, and to discharge a mortgage on said house...."<note n="7">
                            <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXVIII, 228.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>In January 1787 Secretary Jay requested that the Department be moved into the
                    City Hall in May when the lease of Fraunces Tavern would expire. He was informed
                    that no rooms could be spared for that purpose.<note n="8">MS. Department of
                        State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 127, II, 46, 47.</note> Accordingly,
                    the Department of Foreign Affairs, and the War Department as well, remained in
                    Fraunces Tavern for another year, from May 1, 1787 to April 30, 1788. (Certain
                    offices of the Treasury Department were also located there during this period.)<note n="9">Rent for the building was paid to George Powers, Fraunces'
                        successor as owner, through Powers' agent, George Stanton (MS. Library of
                        Congress, Statements of the Financial Affairs of the Late Confederated
                        Government of the United States from February 1781 to September 1789, p. 43;
                        MS National Archives, Record Group 53, Waste Book F and Journal D, from the
                        Register's Office in New York, August 31, 1785-July 14, 1789, II. 1506,
                        1609, 1644, 1686. These two records of accounts seem not wholly
                        reconcilable.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The building known as "Fraunces Tavern"<note n="10">Except as otherwise
                        indicated, the description of Fraunces Tavern was taken from Henry R.
                        Drowne, <hi rend="italic">A Sketch of Fraunces Tavern and Those Connected
                            with Its History,</hi> 6th edition (New York, 1966), published at
                        Fraunces Tavern by the Sons of the Revolution in the State of New
                        York.</note> was erected as a residence in 1719 by Stephen de Lancey, a
                    French Huguenot who had come to New York in 1686 and who had subsequently
                    amassed a fortune as a merchant. It was considered one of the finest homes in
                    the city.</p>
                <p>Having a frontage of 55 feet on Pearl Street and extending back 42 feet along
                    Broad Street,<note n="11">MS. Department of State, file 811. 421/1-2953, A.E.
                        Rhinehard, Secretary, Sons of the Revolution in the State of New York, New
                        York City, to G. Bernard Noble, Chief, Division of Historical Policy
                        Research, January 29, 1953.</note> it was built of red English brick in
                    front and of yellow Dutch brick on the Broad Street side. It consisted of three
                    stories plus cellar and attic, with a French roof covered with tile and lead. On
                    the second floor was a room called the "Long Room," which was well adapted to
                    public entertainment. Offering the property for sale in the New York <hi rend="italic">Royal Gazette</hi> of March 17, 1781, Fraunces described it as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"AN elegant Three Story and a Half Brick Dwelling House,
                        situated in Great Dock Street, at the corner of Broad Street, the property
                        of Mr. Samuel Fraunces, and for many Years distinguished as the Queen's Head
                        Tavern; in which are nine spacious Rooms, besides five Bed-chambers, with
                        thirteen Fire places, an excellent Garret in which are three Bed rooms well
                        finished, an exceeding good Kitchen, and a Spring of remarkable fine Water
                        therein; a most excellent Cellar under the whole, divided into three
                        commodious apartments; a convenient Yard with a good Cistern and Pump, and
                        many other conveniences too tedious to mention; the whole in extraordinary
                        good repair,... "</q>
                </p>
                <p>The building had served as de Lanсey's residence from its completion until the
                    early 1730's. It was owned thereafter, but not occupied, by the de Lancey family
                    until 1759, when it was purchased by the firm of de Lancey, Robinson &amp;
                    Company, which used it as an office and warehouse.</p>
                <p>In 1762 the firm sold the property for £2,000 to <persName>Samuel
                        Fraunces,</persName> a West Indian of French extraction, who opened the
                    building to the public as a tavern, and succeeded in making it the <pb n="15"/>
                    most noted hostelry in colonial New York. Prior to the Revolutionary War it was
                    known as the "Queen's Head Tavern."</p>
                <p>From 1765 to 1770 Fraunces leased the building to others. He took possession
                    again in 1770 and conducted the tavern until shortly before the British captured
                    the city in September 1776 and made him a prisoner. According to his own
                    account, he "submitted to serve for some Time in the Menial Office of Cook in
                    the Family of General Robertson [General James Robertson, British Governor of
                    New York City, 1780-1783] without any Pay, or Perquisite whatsoever, Except the
                    Priviledge of disposing of the Remna[n]ts of the Tables which he appropriated
                    towards the Comfort of the American Prisoners within the City."<note n="12">MS.
                        Department of State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 41, III, 292-295,
                        memorial of Fraunces to Congress dated at New York, March 5, 1785.</note>
                    Exactly when Fraunces resumed operation of the tavern is not known, but his
                    offer of sale on March 17, 1781, was unsuccessful, and it is of record that he
                    was running it in 1783 and 1784. On April 23, 1785, shortly after leasing the
                    premises to Congress, he sold the property to George Powers, a Brooklyn butcher,
                    for £1,950.</p>
                <p>Throughout most of its history the tavern has been the scene of banquets and
                    entertainments attended by notables of history. Among incidents of historic
                    interest that took place there were the founding of the New York Chamber of
                    Commerce on April 5, 1768, a public dinner given by Governor Clinton to General
                    Washington on November 25, 1783, and General Washington's farewell to his
                    officers on December 4, 1783.</p>
                <p>By the beginning of the twentieth century, as a result of wear and tear through
                    the years, of damage by fire, and of reconstruction and remodeling, the building
                    had lost all its characteristics of colonial architecture. In 1904 it was
                    purchased by the Sons of the Revolution, who restored it in 1906-1907.<note n="13">On January 24, 1975, a lunch-time bombing of an annex of the Fraunces
                        Tavern by a group calling themselves the Armed Forces of Puerto Rican
                        National Liberation (FALN) killed 4 persons and injured 53. There was only
                        minor damage to the main tavern building. See <hi rend="italic">The New York
                            Times,</hi> January 25, 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName>John Jay</persName> served as Secretary for Foreign Affairs throughout
                    the time the Department was at Fraunces Tavern. When he commenced his tenure of
                    office, <persName>Henry Remsen, Jr.,</persName> the Under Secretary previously
                    elected by Congress, was his only subordinate.<note n="14">MS. Department of
                        State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 127, I, 1.</note> Gradually, Jay
                    increased his staff to consist of Remsen as Under Secretary, two clerks, a
                    salaried part-time translator of French, three men who translated Netherlandish,
                    German, and Spanish respectively on a piecework basis,<note n="15">The four
                        translators did their work outside the office of the Department.</note> and
                    a doorkeeper-messenger.<note n="16">MS. Department of State, Continental
                        Congress Papers, No. 127, I, 4, 8, 23, 28, 53, 74, 77; II, 20, 37; No. 120,
                        IV, 31-32, May 7, 1789.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As Secretary for Foreign Affairs, Jay strengthened the role of the Department in
                    conducting foreign relations by channeling all foreign affairs matters through
                    his office at Fraunces Tavern. Congress affirmed this in a resolution dated
                    February 11, 1785, which required that all communications to and from the United
                    States on the subject of foreign affairs be made through the Secretary, and that
                    all letters, memorials, or other papers on the subject of foreign affairs for
                    the United States be addressed to him. The Secretary was also authorized to
                    appoint an interpreter so that in the future all papers written in a foreign
                    language which might be communicated to Congress from the Department of Foreign
                    Affairs would be accompanied with a translation into English.<note n="17">MS.
                        Continental Congress, 25, II, folio 413; quoted from Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> pp. 44-45</note>
                </p>
                <p>Although Jay's Department remained somewhat dependent on Congress in conducting
                    foreign relations, it was gaining a degree of independence which would serve as
                    the pattern for its successor—the Department of State—under the
                    Constitution.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="16"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section12">
                <head>First Location on Broadway, <placeName>New York City</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1788-05-01">May 1</date>—<date when="1788-10-02">Oct. 2, 1788</date>
                </head>
                <p>On May 1, 1788,<note n="1">May Day was moving day in old New York, according to
                        Sidney I. Pomerantz, <hi rend="italic">New York, an American City,
                            1783-1803</hi> (New York and London, 1938), p. 228.</note> the
                    Department of Foreign Affairs with Jay still as Secretary, along with the War
                    Office under Secretary <persName>Henry Knox,</persName>
                    <note n="2">For a biographical sketch, see <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of
                            American Biography,</hi> X, 475-477.</note> moved from Fraunces Tavern
                    to a house on Broadway.<note n="3">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records,
                        Cash Book, 1785-1795, under date of May 5, 1788; MS. National Archives,
                        Record Group 53, Waste Book F and Journal D, from the Register's Office in
                        New York, August 31, 1785-July 14, 1789, II, 1803, 1832.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="12-first-broadway-nyc.jpg"/>
                        <head>The first location of the Department of Foreign Affairs on Broadway
                            was in the general area shown here.</head>
                    </figure>The exact location of the house is not known. According to Gaillard
                    Hunt, however, it was on the west side of Broadway near the Battery.<note n="4">Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 428.</note> It is clear that
                    Jay's residence was located in this area,<note n="5">In 1786 Jay lived at 8
                        Broadway (Franks, <hi rend="italic">New York Directory,</hi> 1786, p. 55);
                        in 1787 he was at 99 Broadway (<hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1787, under <hi rend="italic">Jay, John</hi>); and in 1789 he was at 133 Broadway (<hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1789, p. 47)</note> which may indicate that
                    his office was nearby. Whatever its exact location may have been, it long ago
                    was destroyed to make way for the commercial development of that street.</p>
                <p>The house was owned by Walter Livingston,<note n="6">See Footnote #3 above.
                            <persName>Gaillard Hunt</persName> (<hi rend="italic">op. crit.,</hi> p.
                        428) stated that the house was owned by one <persName>Philip
                            Livingston.</persName>
                    </note> a first cousin of Jay's wife.<note n="7">Edwin B. Livingston, <hi rend="italic">The Livingstons of Livingston Manor</hi> (New York, 1910),
                        p. 229.</note> Livingston had been a Member of the Continental Congress in
                    1784 and 1785, and he was one of three Commissioners of the United States
                    Treasury from 1785 to 1789.<note n="8">For a biographical sketch, see <hi rend="italic">Biographical Directory of the American Congress,
                            1774-1949</hi> (Washington, 1950), p. 1468. Walter Livington was a son
                        of Robert Livingston (1708-1790), and not a son of Philip Livingston
                        (1716-1778), as therein stated.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department occupied two rooms, "one of which the Secretary reserves for
                    himself and the Reception of such Persons as may have Business with him, and the
                    other for his Deputy and [two] Clerks."<note n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXXIV, 426.</note> Rent for the house was
                    paid by the Government at the rate of $625 (f250) a year, plus taxes of $4485.<note n="10">
                        MS. National Archives, Record Group 53, Waste Book F and
                        Journal D, from the Register's Office in New York, August 31, 1785-July 14,
                        1789, II, 1876.</note>
                </p>
                <p>After occupying this building for only five months, the Department was obliged to
                    move in October 1788 because the Congress had decided to use Jay's office as its
                    own meeting place.<note n="11">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> XXXIV, 577; Burnett, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Continental Congress,</hi> p. 720; Burnett, <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> VIII, 802.</note> The War Office and "other Offices" of
                    the Government remained in the building at least until April 30, 1789.<note n="12">MS. National Archives, Record Group 53, Waste Book F and Journal D,
                        from the Register's Office in New York, August 31, 1785-July 14, 1789, II,
                        1876.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="17"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section13">
                <head>Second Location on Broadway, <placeName>New York City</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1788-10-02">Oct. 2, 1788</date>—<date when="1790-10">Oct.
                        1790</date>
                </head>
                <p>On October 2, 1788, the Department of Foreign Affairs moved to another building
                    on Broadway.<note n="1">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Cash Book,
                        1785-1795, under dates Oсtober 3, 1788, June 18, 1789, and October 5,
                        1790.</note> Again, the exact location is not known for certain. According
                    to Hunt, however, this building was a house located on the east side of the
                    street.<note n="2">Hunt, <hi rend="italic">Department of State,</hi> p.
                        428.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="14-trinity-church-nyc.jpg"/>
                        <head>A view of Broadway showing Trinity Church. When the Department became
                            the Department of State, it occupied a building across Broadway from the
                            Churchyard.</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>There is evidence that corroborates Hunt's statement regarding the location of
                    this building. It is recorded that the Department, while occupying this second
                    house on Broadway, paid office rent to one Elias "Nexen"<note n="3">Elias
                        "Nixsen" was a grocer whose address at the time was Burling Slip (<hi rend="italic">New-York Directory,</hi> 1789, p. 66).</note> (the name is
                    variously spelled) for the period from October 2, 1788, to May 1, 1789, in the
                    sum of L 40 New York currency.<note n="4">MS. Department of State, Accounts
                        Records, Cash Book, 1785-1795, under date June 18, 1789.</note> From
                    February 1, 1787, or earlier, until April 30, 1788, he and Isaac Stoutenburgh,
                    acting as attorneys for John Johnson, had collected rent from the Government for
                    a house which was occupied as an office by the Board of Treasury.<note n="5">MS. National Archives, Record Group 53, Waste Book F and Journal D, from
                        the Register's Office in New York, August 31, 1785-July 14, 1789, 1, 1458;
                        II, 1502, 1703.</note> On May 1, 1788, the Board of Treasury moved to other
                    quarters,<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">lbid.,</hi> p. 1728.</note> and on the same date the New
                    York <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>
                    <note n="7">This newspaper was then titled - "The New-York Journal, and Daily
                        Patriotic Register," except on Thursdays, when it was "The New-York Journal,
                        and Weekly Register." The advertisement was repeated in the issues of May 2,
                        3, 5, 6, and 7, 1788.</note> carried the following advertisement:</p>
                <!--   <p>Image of newspaper (should be image 13)</p> -->
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">TO BE SOLD, That pleasantly situated House and Lot of
                        Ground NEARLY opposite Old Trinity Church-Yard, the corner of French
                        Church-street [then better known as King Street; now Pine Street], and
                        Broad-Way, now in the occupation of the Honorable Board of Treasury, and
                        rents for 120 1. per annum.-For further particulars enquire of Col. Isaac
                        Stoutenburgh, corner of Dye-street, North-River, or Elias Nexson, No. 8,
                        Burling-slip....</q>
                </p>
                <p>Thus the house occupied until April 30, 1788, by the Board of Treasury was
                    located on the corner of Broadway and King Street. Also, it was on the east side
                    of Broadway, because Trinity Church and churchyard were on the west side and
                    King Street began at Broadway and ran eastward. Perhaps Nexson failed to sell
                    this property for the owner, or possibly he was retained as the attorney for the
                    new owner, and perhaps it was this house that the Department of Foreign Affairs
                    moved into in October 1788.<note n="8">In 1786 the Continental Congress had an
                        office of some kind either in this building or in one directly across King
                        Street from it, for the New York directory for that year, after listing the
                        names of the then Delegates to Congress, states that they were "To be heard
                        of at the Congress' Office, 81, Broadway, co[r]ner of King-street;" Franks,
                            <hi rend="italic">New-York Directory, 1786,</hi> p. 54.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was during the period of the Department's occupancy of this second building on
                    Broadway that the change-over took place from government under the Articles of
                    Confederation to government under the Constitution. The new Congress convened on
                    March 4, 1789, although there was no quorum of the House of Representatives
                    until April 1 and no quorum of the Senate until April 6. President Washington
                    took his oath of office on April 30. Until such time as a Department of Foreign
                    Affairs was established under the Constitution, the former Department, with John
                    Jay still as Secretary, continued to function.</p>
                <p>The Department of Foreign Affairs under the Constitution was created by an act of
                    Congress approved on July 27, 1789.<note n="9">1 Stat. 28.</note> Its name was
                    changed less than two months later, on September 15, 1789, to the Department of
                    State, and its functions were augmented to include certain domestic duties as
                    well as those pertaining to foreign affairs already prescribed.<note n="10">1
                        Stat. 68.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The first Secretary of State under the Constitution was <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson.</ref>
                    Although he was commissioned on September 26, 1789, he was still in France at
                    the time, and Jay continued to perform the essential duties of the office until
                    Jefferson entered upon his duties on March 22, 1790.</p>
                <p>The Department of Foreign Affairs under the Articles of Confederation was a
                    time-tested model for the new Department. Its strengths, as well as its defects,
                    would prove invaluable in constructing the new organization.</p>
                <p>Jay had initiated many new procedures that would be adopted by the Department of
                    State. Among these, he had begun carefully to collect and file the Department's
                    papers, including the official correspondence of the diplomatic representatives,
                    both this country's as well as foreign. Jay indicated that "it is to papers in
                    this office that future historians must recur for accurate accounts of many
                    interesting affairs respecting the late Revolution."<note n="11">
                        <hi rend="italic">Correspondence and Public Papers of John Jay,</hi> ed.
                        H.P. Johnston (4 vols., New York, 1890-1893), III, 251.</note>
                </p>
                <pb n="18"/>
                <p>Also during this early period, some of the country's greatest diplomats had
                    served and had achieved notable diplomatic successes. Among these great
                    diplomats were Adams, Franklin, Jay, and Jefferson. The <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">Treaty of 1783</ref> had been
                    negotiated, and the beginnings of relations with other countries were becoming
                    firmly established.</p>
                <p>When Jefferson took over, the Department was still in the building on Broadway.
                    Evidently, however, its quarters in this building were smaller than its needs,
                    because by 1790 a portion of its effects amounting to nine cartloads was stored
                    in rooms in the New York City Нall.<note n="12">MS. Department of State,
                        Accounts Records, Cash Book, 1785-1795, under date Oсtober 5, 1790.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In June 1790 Jefferson's staff consisted of two principal clerks, three clerks,
                    one part-time translator of French, and two office keeper messengers.<note n="13">MS. Department of State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 120, IV,
                        167-168.</note> One of the principal clerks, Roger Alden, resigned on July
                    25, 1790.<note n="14">Stuart, <hi rend="italic">The Department of State,</hi>
                        p. 17.</note>
                </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="15-head-shot.jpg"/>
                    <head>Engraving of Thomas Jefferson, 1770</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Department occupied the second location on Broadway until October 1790 when
                    the seat of the new government was moved to Philadelphia.<note n="15">МS.
                        Department of State, Accounts Records, Cash Book, 1785-1795, under date
                        October 5, 1790.</note> When it moved out of this building, the Department
                    remained responsible for payment of rent, [Image: Rounded head portrait of ?]
                    amounting to about $150, until its year's lease expired, and it sublet the
                    building to two tenants for the unexpired term.<note n="16">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> under date May 1, 1791; MS. Department of
                        State, Continental Congress Papers, No. 120, IV, 191.</note> The house,
                    which was the last home of the Department of Foreign Affairs and the first home
                    of the Department of State, has, like other residences that formerly stood along
                    lower Broadway, long since disappeared from the scene.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="19"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section14">
                <head>
                    <placeName>307 Market Street, Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1790-10">October 1790</date>—<date when="1793-04">April 1793</date>
                </head>
                <p>On July 16, 1790, while still in <placeName>New York,</placeName> an act of
                    Congress was approved to change the seat of government to
                        <placeName>Philadelphia.</placeName>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="16-307-market-street.jpg"/>
                        <head>The buildings occupied by the Deparment of State in Philadelphia were
                            in the general area shown here in a view of Second Street, north from
                            Market Street, drawn and engraved by W. Birch &amp; Son.</head>
                    </figure> The law provided:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"That prior to the first Monday in December next, all
                        offices attached to the seat of the government of the United States, shall
                        be removed to, and until the said first Monday in December, in the year one
                        thousand eight hundred, shall remain at the city of Philadelphia, in the
                        state of Pennsylvania, at which place the session of Congress next ensuing
                        shall be held."<note n="1">Stat. 130.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>Between October 1 and November 10, 1790, pursuant to the foregoing statutory
                    provision, the Department of State was in the process of moving from New York to
                    Philadelphia. A portion of the Department's effects, amounting to twenty-one
                    cartloads, was transported by water. The remainder, amounting to eight or nine
                    cartloads, went by land.<note n="2">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records,
                        Cash Book, 1785-1795, under dates October 1, 2, 5, 9, 13, 15, and November
                        10, 1790.</note>
                </p>
                <p>By October 13, 1790, the Department was beginning to get established in a
                    building at 307 Market Street.<note n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                    </note> The building was on the north side of that street between Eighth and
                    Ninth Streets.<note n="4">MS. Department of State, file 102.5-7-953, Riley to
                        Noble, July 9, 1953; letter from Martin I. Yoelson, Supervisory Interpretive
                        specialist, Independence National Historical Park, Philadelphia, to Edwin S.
                        Costrell, Chief, Historical Studies Division, March 27, 1975. Some
                        historians of Philadelphia have state that it was on the northwest corner of
                        Eighth and Market Streets. For references to the corner location, see J.
                        Thomas Scharf and Thompson Westcott, <hi rend="italic">History of
                            Philadelphia, 1609-1884</hi> (New York, 1895-1898), I, 396; Ellis P.
                        Oberholtzer, <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia, a History of the City and Its
                            People</hi> (Philadelphia, etc., 1912) I, 342; and <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> (Harrisburg, 1931-1933), III, 788.</note> It was
                    "directly opposite" the house Jefferson had chosen for his residence. The
                    building was "three stories high with a garret, kitchen and stable,"<note n="5"> Jefferson Papers (Boyd, ed.), XVII, 596; also see pp. 385-386.</note> and
                    its windows were fitted with venetian blinds.<note n="6">MS. Department of
                        State, Accounts Records, cash Book, 1785-1795, under date May 20,
                        1791.</note> Rent for the the building was $186.67 a year.<note n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> under date April 6, 1793; also see MS.
                        Department of State, 5, Domestic Letters, p. 14.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Department remained in this building until April 1793.<note n="8">Under an act
                        of congress of July 9, 1798, the building was valued at $2,000 (MS. National
                        Archives, Record Group 58, Book A, "List of the Taxes Assessed....," October
                        1, 1798, p. 97). The site of this building is now occupied by a part of the
                        department store of Strawbridge &amp; Clothier (letter from Yoelson to
                        Costrell, March 27, 1975).</note> During this time, Jefferson's staff
                    consisted of the Chief Clerk, three clerks, a clerk for foreign languages, and
                    an officekeeper- messenger.<note n="9">MS. Department of State, 5 Domestic
                        Letters, p. 14.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Expenses for the Department at this time were still relatively low. In 1790,
                    Jefferson estimated that the Department's expenses for one year would be $7,961.
                    Of this amount $7,300 was for the salaries of the Secretary and his staff. The
                    remaining $691 covered office rent, firewood, stationery, newspapers, gazettes,
                    contingencies, etc.<note n="10">Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op. crit.,</hi> p.
                        96.</note> When Jefferson turned his office over to <persName>Edmund
                        Randolph</persName> at the end of 1793, the expenses of the Department had
                    increased to $9,661.67.<note n="11">Stuart, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p.
                        22.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The cost of foreign intercourse was considerably higher inasmuch as a Minister's
                    salary was $9,000 and a Charge d'Affaires' salary was $4,500, compared to the
                    Secretary's salary of $3,500. In the report made in November 1792, Jefferson
                    estimated that the $40,000 appropriated for the Foreign Fund was ample for
                    existing needs of the service abroad.<note n="12">Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op.
                            crit.,</hi> p. 110.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="20"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section15">
                <head>
                    <placeName>287 Market Street, Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1793-04">April 1793</date>—<date when="1794-05">May 1794</date>
                </head>
                <p>On or about April 1, 1793, the Department of State moved from the building at 307
                    Market Street to a building which was apparently larger.<note n="1">MS.
                        Department of State, Accounts Records, Cash Book, 1785-1795, under date
                        April 11, 1793.</note> According to a 1793 Philadelphia city directory, the
                    new home of the Department was located at 287 Market Street<note n="2">James
                        Hardie, <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia Directory,</hi> 1793, p. 72.</note>
                    on the north side of the street between Seventh and Eighth Streets (now 719
                    Market Street).<note n="3">MS. Department of State, file 102.5/7-953, Riley to
                        Noble, July 9, 1953; and Yoelson to Costrell, March 27, 1975.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="17-287-market-street-randolph.jpg"/>
                        <head>Edmund Randolph</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Except for the mention of blinds on the third-story windows, and of walls and
                    ceilings of the rooms that were whitewashed,<note n="4">MS. Department of
                        State, Accounts Records, Cash Book, 1755-1795, under dates March 30 and
                        November 23, 1793.</note> no description or picture of this building has
                    been found. The property was owned by John Dunwoody, an "innkeeper" living next
                    door at 285 Market Street,<note n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> under date July 3, 1793.</note> to whom the
                    Department paid rent at the rate of $266.67 a year from April 1, 1793, to April
                    15, 1794, and at the rate of $400 a year from April 16 to May 15, 1794.<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> under dates July 3 and October 3, 1793, and
                        January 3 and May 15, 1794.</note> Under a July 9, 1798, act of Congress,
                    the property was valued at $2,800.<note n="7">MS. National Archives, Record
                        Group 58, Book A, "List of the Taxes Assessed...," October 1, 1798, p.
                        113.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The entire frontage from Seventh to Eighth Street on the north side of Market
                    Street is now occupied by the Lit Brothers department store, of late
                    nineteenth-century construction.<note n="8">MS. Department of State, file
                        102.5/7-953, Riley to Noble. July 9, 1953; and Yoelson to Costrell, March
                        27, 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department was in this building until May 1794 except for a time in
                    September-October 1973 when it ceased to function because of a severe yellow
                    fever epidemic in Philadelphia. On September 12 Jefferson wrote: <quote>"The
                        fever spreads faster... all my clerks have left me but one: so that I cannot
                        go on with business."</quote>
                    <note n="9">MS. Library of Congress, Thomas Jefferson Papers, No. 93, p. 15965:
                        Nathan Schachner, <hi rend="italic">Thomas Jefferson: a Biography</hi> (New
                        York, 1951), 1, 508, 512.</note> A few days later, he set out for
                    Monticello. Jefferson completed his tenure of office as Secretary of State on
                    December 31, 1793, while the Department was in the building at 287 Market
                    Street. <persName>Edmund Randolph</persName> succeeded to the office on January
                    2, 1794, in the same building.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section16">
                <head>Sixth and Arch Streets, <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1794-05">May 1794</date>—<date when="1796-11">October 1796</date>
                </head>
                <p>In the middle of May 1794, the Department of State moved from the building at 287
                    Market Street to another building in Philadelphia, located on the southeast
                    corner of Sixth and Arch Streets.<note n="1">MS. Department of State, Accounts
                        Records, Cash Book, 1785-1795, under dates August 8 and 15, 1784; <hi rend="italic">Stephen's Philadelphia Directory, for 1796</hi>
                        (Philadelphia, 1796), p. 213; Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p.
                        428.</note> Notices of the move appeared in the Philadelphia newspapers for
                    many days. The Philadelphia Gazette of the United States stated that "THE OFFICE
                    of the Secretary is moved from High [Market] Street, to the New Buildings, the
                    corner of Sixth &amp; Mulberry [Arch] Streets."<note n="2">May 15, 1794,
                        and in each subsequent issue of this newspaper (daily except Sunday) to and
                        including that of May 31, 1794.</note> The Philadelphia <hi rend="italic">General Advertiser </hi> indicated, under the heading "Secretary of State's
                    Office," that "The Office of the Secretary of State is removed to the house next
                    to the corner of Sixth in Arch Street."<note n="3">May 17, 1794, and in each
                        subsequent issue of that newspaper (daily except Sunday) to and including
                        that of June 30, 1794.</note>
                </p>
                <p>No description or picture of this house has been found. The site is now an open
                    area included in the three-block Independence Mall.<note n="4">Yoelson to
                        Costrell, March 27, 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department remained in this building until about October 29, 1796. During
                    this time, it paid a quarterly rent of $108.335 to Nathan Sheppard, a "lumber
                    merchant."<note n="6">Hardie, <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia Directory,</hi>
                        1794, p. 138; <hi rend="italic">Stephen's Philadelphia Directory, for
                            1796</hi> p. 165.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On August 20, 1795, while the Department was at this location, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/pickering-timothy">Timothy Pickering</ref>
                    reluctantly succeeded <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/randolph-edmund-jennings">Edmund
                        Randolph,</ref> who had been forced to resign, as Secretary of State. In a
                    letter to a Mr. Higginson dated September 22, 1795, Pickering declared:
                        <quote>"...you will believe the President not so unwise as to have tendered
                        and me not so imprudent as to have accepted an office to which I am so
                        little competent. The business of the office could not be suspended and from
                        necessity I have by the President's direction undertaken the temporary
                        conduct of it."</quote>
                    <note n="7">Stuart, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 29.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department never had more than eight or nine employees while Pickering was
                    Secretary, and he did much of the clerical work himself.<note n="8">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 33</note> On February 10, 1796, Pickering's
                    staff consisted of the Chief Clerk, three clerks, a translator, and a messenger.<note n="9">MS. Department of State, Miscellaneous Letters, January—April
                        1796.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="22"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section17">
                <head>
                    <placeName>North Street, Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1796-10-29">Oct. 29, 1796</date>—<date when="1797-08-31">Aug. 31,
                        1797</date>
                </head>
                <p>On October 29, 1796, the Department of State moved again in Philadelphia to a
                    building on North Street (known formerly also as "North Allеу" and now a part of
                    Cuthbert Street).<note n="1">This street is the northerly one of two streets,
                        each only a block long, which run east and west from Fifth to Sixth Street
                        between Market and Arch Streets.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="18-north-st-philadelphia.jpg"/>
                        <head>During yellow fever epidemics in Philadelphia, the Department occupied
                            offices in the State Capitol at Trenton.</head>
                    </figure> A notice in the Philadelphia <hi rend="italic">Gazette of the United
                        States</hi> mentioned the move as follows: "THE office of the secretary of
                    state of the United States, is removed to the north side of North alley, between
                    Market and Arch, and between Fifth and Sixth streets, third door above Fifth
                    street."<note n="2"> October 29, 1796; also see October 31, 1796, and November
                        1, 1796.</note>
                </p>
                <p>No description or picture of this building has been found, and it does not seem
                    possible now to determine just where on the north side of North Street in 1796
                    "the third door above Fifth-street" was located. Most likely it was a residence.
                    Perhaps it was also of very modest proportions, for properties in the immediate
                    vicinity ranged in valuation in 1798 between $400 and $1,600.<note n="3">MS.
                        National Archives, Record Group 58, Book A, "List of the Taxes Assessed...,"
                        October 1, 1798, pp. 105, 107, 114, 119, 121, 124.</note> All of the
                    buildings now on the north side of this street are of more recent construction.<note n="4">MS. Department of State, file 102.517-953, Riley to Noble. July
                        9, 1953; Yoelson to Costrell, March 27, 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department remained in this location until <date when="1797-08-31">August 31,
                        1797,</date> when, because of a yellow fever epidemic in Philadelphia, it
                    moved temporarily to Trenton. When the Department returned to Philadelphia, it
                    moved into another building.</p>
                <p>[Image: During yellow fever epidemics in Philadelphia, the Department occupied
                    offices in the State Capitol at Trenton.]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="23"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section18">
                <head>State House, <placeName>Trenton</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1797-08">August</date>—<date when="1799-11">November 1797, 1798,
                        1799</date>
                </head>
                <p>From August to November in 1797, 1798, and 1799, Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/pickering-timothy">Timothy Pickering</ref>
                    moved the Department of State to Trenton, New Jersey, because of recurring
                    epidemics of yellow fever in Philadelphia. In 1797 the Department moved from
                    Philadelphia to Trenton between August 31 and September 5 and returned to
                    Philadelphia between November 2 and 8. In 1798 it moved to Trenton between
                    August 13 and 18 and returned between November 10 and 16. In 1799 it was in
                    Trenton from about August 29 to about November 1. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="19-state-house-trenton-pickering.jpg"/>
                        <head>Timothy Pickering</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>For each move, the Department's furniture, books, and papers were carted to the
                    Philadelphia waterfront, shipped up the Delaware River to Lamberton (then just
                    south of Trenton; now a part of that city), and then carted to Trenton. For the
                    return trip, the process was repeated in reverse, and the Department would
                    resume its functions in Philadelphia. While in Trenton, the Department occupied
                    rooms in the New Jersey State House.<note n="1">MS. Department of State,
                        Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses, Day Book, 1798- 1820, pp. 20, 21, 22,
                        24, 25, 26, 35, 47, 48, 50, 51, 52, 53, 55; MS. Department of State, 10
                        Domestic Letters, pp. 161, 164, 170, 202, 239; <hi rend="italic">11
                            ibid.,</hi> pp. 52, 177, 190.&gt;</note>
                </p>
                <p>This was a new building at the time, having only been completed in 1794 at a cost
                    of 3,000. It was a plain, roughcast structure of a bluish color, measuring 100
                    feet across the front and 60 feet in depth, with a bow at either end. It
                    consisted of two stories and an attic, with a gable roof and a cupola or belfry
                    in the center of the roof. Over the years, extensive additions and improvements
                    have been made until the original building, although embodied in the present
                    structure, is no longer recognizable.<note n="2">Podmore, <hi rend="italic">Trenton, Old and New,</hi> pp. 75-81; Trenton Historical Society, <hi rend="italic">History of Trenton,</hi> I. 206-208; II, 991-992.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="24"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section19">
                <head>
                    <placeName>13 South Fifth Street, Philadelphia</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1797-11">November 1797</date>—<date when="1800-05">May 1800</date>
                </head>
                <p>When the Department of State returned to Philadelphia in November 1797, it moved
                    into a building at 13 South Fifth Street on the east side of the street between
                    Market and Chestnut Streets. A notice of the move, ordered by the Department,<note n="1">MS Department of State, Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses,
                        Day Book, 1798- 1820, p. 72.</note> appeared in the Philadelphia <hi rend="italic">Gazette of the United States</hi> on November 10, 11, 13, 14,
                    and 16, 1797. It stated that "The Office of Secretary of State OF THE UNITED
                    STATES IS removed to No. 13, South Fifth street, near Chestnut street."</p>
                <p>No picture of this building is known to exist, but it is described as a three
                    story brick house measuring 21 by 35 feet on a lot measuring 21 by 56 feet, and
                    its valuation is given as $2,700.<note n="2">MS. National Archives, Record
                        Group 58, Book A, "List of the Taxes Assessed...," October 1, 1798, pp 141,
                        155; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> Book B, No. 4, "Particular List or
                        Description of all Lands, Lots, Buildings, and Wharves, owned, possessed, or
                        occupied, on the 1st Day of October, 1798, in Middle Ward being within the
                        City of Philadelphia in the State of Pennsylvania, excepting only such
                        Dwelling-houses, as, with the Out-houses appurtenant thereto, and the Lots
                        on which they are erect, not exceeding two Acres in any Case, are above the
                        Value of One Hundred Dollars," items 109, 128.</note> In that part of the
                    house which was occupied by the Department of State the chimneys had 16 flues.<note n="3"> MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses,
                        Day Book, 1798- 1820, p. 38.</note> The walls and ceilings of the rooms were
                    whitewashed, and there were venetian blinds at the windows.<note n="4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> pp. 8, 19, 51, 53.</note> The premises
                    included a kitchen with a fireplace, a cellar, and a yard in which there was a
                    pump.<note n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> pp. 24, 39, 46.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department shared this building with the office of the Postmaster General.
                    The rent was $950 a year, payable in advance to the owner, James Simmons. Of
                    that amount, the Department of State paid $600 and the office of the Postmaster
                    General $350.<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> pp. 22, 46, 72, 78; Cornelius W. Stafford, the
                        Philadelphia Directory, for 1797-1801 (Philadelphia, 1797-1801), 1798
                        volume, register section, p. 14; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1799,
                        register section, p. 12; <hi rend="italic">ibid., 1800,</hi> register
                        section, p. 18.</note> When the Department left the building in 1800, it had
                    to pay the owner an extra $100 for damage done to the house during its
                    occupancy, and an additional $25 because the house was left uncleaned.<note n="7">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses, Day
                        book 1798-1820, p. 78.</note> The site of this house is now occupied by the
                    Lafayette Building, a ten-story office building erected in the 1920's.<note n="8">Letter from Yoelson to Costrell, Arch 27, 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State remained in the building at 13 South Fifth Street until
                    May 1800, when it moved with the seat of government to Washington, D.C. In this
                    building, <persName>Timothy Pickering</persName> concluded his period of service
                    as Secretary of State on May 12, 1800. He has the dubious distinction, according
                    to Graham Stuart, writing in 1949, of being the only Secretary of State who was
                    "dismissed from office." After Pickering declined to follow President Adams'
                    suggestion that he resign, Adams wrote to him as follows: "Divers causes and
                    considerations essential to the administration of the government, in my
                    judgment, requiring a change in the Department of State, you are hereby
                    discharged from any further service as Secretary of State."<note n="9">Quoted
                        in Stuart, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 33.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="25"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section20">
                <head>Treasury Department Building, <placeName>Washington</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1800-06">June</date>—<date when="1600-08">August 1800</date>
                </head>
                <p>The same act of Congress of July 16, 1790 which made Philadelphia the interim
                    seat of government from 1790 to 1800 also provided that, beginning on the first
                    Monday in December 1800, the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> would
                    be the permanent seat of government and that suitable buildings should be
                    erected for the accommodation of Congress, the President, and the public offices
                    of the government.<note n="1">1 Stat. 130.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="20-treasury-dept-building.jpg"/>
                        <head>United States Treasury Building 1804</head>
                    </figure> The date for moving was changed by an act of Congress approved on
                    April 24, 1800,<note n="2">2 Stat. 55.</note> which authorized the President to
                    direct the removal of the executive departments to the city of Washington at any
                    time he might judge proper after the adjournment of the current session of
                    Congress and prior to the convening of the next session.<note n="3">"An act
                        approved May 13, 1800, advanced the date of convening of the next session of
                        Congress from the first Monday in December 1800 to the third Monday in
                        November (2 Stat. 85).</note>
                </p>
                <p>On May 15, 1800, just one day after Congress had adjourned in Philadelphia,
                    President <persName>John Adams</persName> directed the department heads to move
                    their offices and staffs to Washington as soon as it was convenient so that the
                    public offices would be opened for business by June 15.<note n="4">George
                        Gibbs, ed., <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Administrations of Washington
                            and John Adams, Edited from the Papers of Oliver Wolcot, Secretary of
                            the Treasury</hi> (New York, 1846), II, 362.</note> All the executive
                    departments made this move between May 15 and June 15 as the President had
                    instructed. "The removal was not a stupendous task; ... the Government personnel
                    consisted of only 126 persons."<note n="5">Federal Writers' Project, Works
                        Progress Administration, <hi rend="italic">Washington, City and
                        Capital</hi>(Washington, 1937), p. 47.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Secretary of the Treasury Wolcott described local conditions as he found them
                    upon his arrival:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"There are few houses in any one place, and most of them
                        small, miserable huts, which present an awful contrast to the public
                        buildings....You may look in almost any direction, over an extent of ground
                        nearly as large as the city of New York, without seeing a fence or any
                        object except brick-kilns and temporary huts for laborers."<note n="6">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>On May 27 <persName>Charles Lee</persName>, Secretary of State <hi rend="italic">ad interim,</hi> wrote from Philadelphia that the books and papers of the
                    Department were packed for removal to Washington and that he would proceed there
                    the following day.<note n="7">MS. Department of State, 5 Instructions, U.S.
                        Ministers, p. 341.</note> Certain Philadelphia newspapers of May 28, 1800,<note n="8">For example, Philadelphia <hi rend="italic">Gazette &amp;
                            Universal Daily Advertiser,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Claypole's
                            American Daily Advertiser.</hi>
                    </note> carried the following notice:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Office of the Department of State, will be removed
                        this day from Philadelphia. All letters and applications are therefore to be
                        addressed to that Department at the <hi rend="italic">City of
                            Washington,</hi> from this date.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <date when="1800-05-28">"28th May, 1800."</date>
                </p>
                <p>Lee left Philadelphia on the morning of May 28<note n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> May 29, 1800.</note> and arrived in Washington
                    by May 31.<note n="10">"Diary of Mrs. William Thornton, 1800- 1863," in <hi rend="italic">Records of the Columbia Historical Society , Washington,
                            D.C.</hi> (Washington, 1895—), X, 149.</note> By June 7 the Department
                    of State was beginning to function in Washington,<note n="11">MS. Department of
                        State, 5 Instructions, U.S. Ministers, p. 342.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The first home of the Department of State in Washington was in the "Treasury
                    Department Building" which was shared with other government offices. It was
                    located to the east of the White House, about where the center wing of the
                    present Treasury Department Building stands.<note n="12">"Diary of Mrs. William
                        Thornton, Capture of Washington by the British," in <hi rend="italic">Records of the Columbia Historical Society', XIX, 176, </hi> footnote
                        6. Contemporary maps of Washington and various other sources verify this
                        statement.</note> It remained in this building only about three months.</p>
                <p>The Department stored some supplies not needed for current use in a building
                    referred to as "Lear's Store"<note n="13">MS. Department of State, Accounts
                        Records, Contingent Expenses, Day Book, 1798- 1820, pp. 81, 82, 83.</note>—a
                    large stone warehouse which had been erected by Colonel Tobias Lear, formerly
                    President Washington's private secretary. Fronting on the Potomac, it was in the
                    square bounded by Twenty-sixth, Twenty-seventh, F, and G Streets Northwest.<note n="14">Wilhelmus B. Bryan and Samuel C. Busey, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Removal of the Seat of Government to the District of Columbia</hi>
                        (Washington, 1900; Senate Document No. 62, 56th Cong., 1st Sess.), p. 14.
                        Christian Hines, <hi rend="italic">Early Recollections of Washington
                            City</hi> (Washington, 1866), p. 23.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Treasury Department Building was one of two structures which were at this
                    time intended to house the executive offices of the government. The other
                    building had a corresponding location to the west of the White House, but was
                    not ready for occupancy by June 1800. President Washington had determined the
                    location for the two buildings in October 1796, and on March 3, 1797 he had
                    approved the architect's plans for the buildings.<note n="15">
                        <hi rend="italic">American State Papers, Miscellaneous</hi> II, 481, 482,
                        483, 484. John C. Fitzpatrick, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Writings of George
                            Washington</hi> (Washington, 1931-1944), XXXV, 248-250, 389, 400,
                        413.</note> George Hadfield was the architect.<note n="16">MS. National
                        Archives, Record Group 42, Letters Received by Commissioners of Public
                        Buildings and Grounds, Washington, D.C., XIII, Nos. 1361, 1364, Hadfield to
                        the Commissioners, May 14 and 16, 1798. Wilhelmus B. Bryan, A History of the
                        National Capital (New York, 1914-1916), 1, 314. For a biographical sketch of
                        George Hadfield, see Dictionary of American Biography, VIII, 76-77.</note>
                </p>
                <pb n="26"/>
                <p>On May 7, 1798, the Commissioners for the District of Columbia had an
                    advertisement inserted in the newspapers of Philadelphia, Baltimore, Georgetown,
                    and Alexandria which read in part as follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Commissioners will receive proposals until the 20th of
                        June next, for building in the City of Washington, one of the Executive
                        Offices for the United States, of the following external dimensions-148 feet
                        in length, and fifty seven feet six inches in breadth—cellar walls, 30-
                        Inches—first story 23 Inches, and second story 18 Inches—partition walls
                        averaging 15 Inches; to contain on the ground floor, 14 Rooms; same number
                        on the second story, and in the Roof 8 Rooms, with a passage.—The whole
                        external of the building to be of stock brick;—the inside walls of hard
                        burnt brick—cellars of best foundation stone, to the height of the
                        girders.—The outside walls as far as they shew above ground, to the plinth,
                        to be of plain ashlar free stone—soles of windows, sills of doors, and
                        string course of free-stone.—The house to be covered with cypress
                        shingles—the rooms in general to be 16 feet by 20—finished in a plain neat
                        manner, of the best materials—six small rooms to be groined.—"<note n="17">MS. National Archives, Record Group 42, Proceedings of the
                            Commissioners of Public Buildings and Grounds of the City of Washington
                            and District of Columbia, IV, 126-127.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>Of the various proposals submitted to the Commissioners in response to this
                    advertisement, that of Leonard Harbaugh of Washington was accepted. On June 23,
                    1798, a contract was signed with Harbaugh for the erection of the building east
                    of the White House at a cost of $39,511 and for its completion by July 1, 1800.<note n="18">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> pp. 158, 162-164.</note>
                </p>
                <p>During the course of the construction, a number of agreed changes were made from
                    the original plans and specifications.<note n="19">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Letters Received by Commissioners, XVI, No.
                        1676, Harbaugh to the Commissioners, July 8, 1799.</note> For example,
                    through an error on the part of the surveyor laying off the ground for the
                    foundation, the length of the building was increased 7 1/2 or 8 feet over that
                    shown on the original plans.<note n="20">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> XX, No. 2066, Harbaugh to the Commissioners,
                        March 19, 1802. <hi rend="italic">lbid.,</hi> Public Buildings and Grounds,
                        Proposals and Estimates, 1795-1816, James Hoban to the Commissioners,
                        December 15, 1800.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The building, completed a few weeks ahead of schedule, was a plain two-story
                    structure of brick on a freestone foundation, with abasement and a
                    dormer-windowed attic. It appears that it was about 149 feet in length, east and
                    west, and 57 1/2 feet wide. There were fourteen rooms on the first floor,
                    fourteen on the second floor, and eight in the attic. Twenty-four of the rooms
                    were 17 by 20 feet, eight were of nearly the same dimensions, and four were
                    fireproof rooms of 10 by 12 feet.<note n="21">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Letters of the Commissioners of Public
                        Buildings and Grounds of the City of Washington and District of Columbia, V,
                        422, the Commissioners to Charles Lee, May 20, 1800. <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Public Buildings and Grounds, Proposals and Estimates, 1795
                        -1816, James Hoban to the Commissioners, December 15, 1800. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-john">John Marshall</ref> was
                    the first Secretary of State to have his office in Washington. He entered upon
                    his duties on June 6, 1800. At the time, his staff consisted of the Chief Clerk,
                    seven clerks, and one messenger.<note n="22">MS. Department of State, 3 Report
                        Book, p. 114.</note>
                </p>
                <pb n="27"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section21">
                <head>One of the "Six Buildings," <placeName>Washington</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1800-09">September 1800</date>-<date when="1801-05">May 1801</date>
                </head>
                <p>After approximately three months in the overcrowded Treasury Department Building,
                    the Department of State moved into one of a block of houses known as the "Six
                    Buildings " located on the north side of Pennsylvania Avenue between
                    Twenty-first and Twenty-second Streets Northwest.<note n="1">Hines, <hi rend="italic">Recollections of Washington,</hi> p. 26. Bryan, <hi rend="italic">National Capital,</hi> p. 233, note.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="21-one-of-six-bldgs-washington.jpg"/>
                        <head>Section of the row of the "Six Buildings" on Pennsylvania
                            Avene.</head>
                    </figure> The exact building is not a matter of record. At the same time the
                    Navy Department occupied another one of the Six Buildings;<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> I, 351. Federal Writers' Project, <hi rend="italic">Washington, City and Capital,</hi> p. 642.</note>
                    according to a biographer of the then Secretary of the Navy, this was building
                    numbered 2107.<note n="3">Harriot Stoddert Turner, "Memoirs of Benjamin
                        Stoddert, First Secretary of the United States Navy," in <hi rend="italic">Records of the Columbia Historical Society,</hi> ХХ , 163.</note> The
                    War Department occupied a three story house on the south side of Pennsylvania
                    Avenue nearly opposite the Six Buildings until November 8, 1800, when the
                    building, together with all the books and papers of the office of the Secretary
                    of War, was destroyed by fire.<note n="4">Bryan and Busey, Removal of the Seat
                        of Government, pp. 13, 14. Bryan National Capital, I, 351. Gibbs, Memoirs,
                        II, 446, 478. American State Papers, Miscellaneous, I, 232.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It has frequently been asserted that the Department of State moved in 1800 into
                    one of the so-called "Seven Buildings" rather than one of the Six Buildings. The
                    Seven Buildings were a block of brick houses on the north side of Pennsylvania
                    Avenue commencing at the corner of Nineteenth Street Northwest and extending
                    westward.<note n="5">Caemmerer, <hi rend="italic">Washington, the National
                            Capital,</hi> pp. 371, 372. Federal Writers' Project, Washington, <hi rend="italic">City and Capital,</hi> p. 641.</note> This assertion is
                    erroneous since contemporary records of the Department of State refer
                    specifically and repeatedly to its occupancy of one of the houses among the Six
                    Buildings.<note n="6">МS. Department of State, Accounts- Records, Contingent
                        Expenses, Day Book, 1798- 1820, pp. 82, 84, 85, 93, 108, 111.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Six Buildings were erected sometime prior to May 15, 1800.<note n="7">American State Papers, Miscellaneous, I, 256 (square 74).</note>
                    Construction was begun by James Greenleaf, a speculator in Washington real
                    estate, and was completed by Isaac Polock, to whom the property had been sold.<note n="8">Bryan, <hi rend="italic">National Capital,</hi> I, 233,
                        note.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Old photographs of the Six Buildings<note n="9">Reproduced, e.g., in Hans P.
                        Caemmerer, <hi rend="italic">Washington, the National Capital</hi>
                        (Washington, 1932; Senate Document No. 332, 71st Cong., 3d Sess.), p. 40; in
                        Chalmers M. Roberts, <hi rend="italic">Washington, Past and Present</hi>
                        Washington, 1949-1950), p. 140; and herein.</note> show a solid row of seven
                    brick houses, each with three stories, a basement, and an attic, and all of
                    similar though not identical architectural style. In front, each of the six
                    houses had two windows to the left and a doorway to the right on the first
                    floor, three windows on the second floor, and three smaller windows on the third
                    floor. Each had a gable roof which sloped to the front and back, and each had a
                    single dormer window in the front roof, except the house on the extreme right,
                    which had two dormer windows. This house was not one of the original Six
                    Buildings, but was erected later.</p>
                <p>The numbers of the seven houses, when street numbers were assigned to <pb n="28"/>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="22-modern-six-pennsylvania-ave.jpg"/>
                        <head>The area of the "Six Buildings" as it was in 1977, showing the only
                            remaining original building at center.</head>
                    </figure>them, were 2105, 2107, 2109, 2111, 2113, 2115 and 2117. The Six
                    Buildings were 2107 to 2117.<note n="10">Federal Writers' Project, <hi rend="italic">Washington, City and Capital,</hi> p. 642.</note> The
                    building numbered 2109 is still standing and is readily recognizable as the
                    house shown in the old photographs of the Six Buildings. This building is now
                    occupied by a "publick house" called Tammany Hall. The site of the houses
                    numbered 2111, 2113, and 2115 is now occupied by the Marquette Apartments
                    building, which perpetuates the number 2115. The site of the houses numbered
                    2105 and 2107 is now occupied by the Circle Theater Building, and the site of
                    the house numbered 2117 is now occupied by a portion of the building which
                    houses the Group Health Association.</p>
                <p>The Department of State moved to one of the Six Buildings sometime between August
                    27 and September 5, 1800. Forty-six cartloads of furniture, books, and other
                    effects of the Department of State, including the models of inventions submitted
                    to the Patent Office, which was then a part of the Department, were removed from
                    the Treasury Department Building and from Lear's Store and taken to one of the
                    Six Buildings. Included also was furniture belonging to the Department's
                    messenger, which was moved from a house in Georgetown that the Department had
                    rented for his use from June 6 to September 6, 1800. The Department purchased a
                    set of bookshelves "for a library in the Secretary's room" and another set for
                    the third story of the house, and had four large iron grates installed,
                    evidently so coal could be burned in the fireplaces. On November 6, 1800, the
                    Department paid the firm of Thompson &amp; Veetch, of Alexandria, Va., $450
                    for nine months' rent for this house which included a kitchen and a coach house
                    on the premises used by the Department as a stable and for coal storage.<note n="11">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses, Day
                        Book, 1798- 1820, pp. 81- 84, 88, 90, 93, 96, 118.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In this house, <persName>John Marshall</persName> completed his service as
                    Secretary of State on March 4, 1801, when the Jefferson administration took
                    charge. Marshall had already been appointed Chief Justice of the United States
                    by President Adams, and for a short time he carried on the duties of both
                    positions.</p>
                <p>Attorney General <persName>Levi Lincoln</persName> then filled in as Secretary
                        <hi rend="italic">ad interim until</hi>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james">James Madison</ref>
                    entered upon his duties as Secretary on May 2, 1801. Madison had been
                    commissioned on March 5, 1801, but his father had died in February and he was
                    needed at home to attend to personal matters.</p>
                <p>The Department was still quite small at this time. When Marshall resigned, there
                    were only ten people on the staff, and the salaries totaled only $11,500<note n="12">Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 191.</note> The office of
                    Chief Clerk had become quite important because he acted for the Secretary in his
                    absence. The other employees recorded and copied the correspondence, collated
                    the laws, recorded land patents, made out exequaturs for consuls, issued
                    passports, issued patents, granted copyrights, and performed any other function
                    given to the Department. The diplomatic service was also very small at this
                    time, there being only five envoys who had the rank of minister.<note n="13">Stuart, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 36.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="29"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section22">
                <head>Public Building West of the <placeName>White House</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1801-05">May 1801</date> - <date when="1814-08">August 1814</date>
                </head>
                <p>Approximately three days after <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james">James Madison</ref> entered
                    upon his duties as Secretary of State, succeeding <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-john">John Marshall</ref> on
                        <date when="1801-05-02">May 2, 1801,</date> the Department of State began to
                    move from one of the Six Buildings on <placeName>Pennsylvania Avenue</placeName>
                    to a newly constructed building west of the White House. The move was completed
                    about the middle of June. Some boxes containing models belonging to the Patent
                    Office had already been moved to the still unfinished new building about the
                    last week in December 1800.<note n="1">MS. Department of State, Accounts
                        Records, Contingent Expenses, Day Book, 1798- 1820, p. 93.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="23-public-bldg-west-white-house.jpg"/>
                        <head>Included in this highly imaginative view of the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">British invasion of
                                Washington</ref>, August 24-25, 1814, is the Public Building West of
                            the White House (marked I).</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>This building was known in its day as "the New Building," "the War Office," and
                    "the public building west of the President's house."<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> page 105. MS. National Archives, Record Group
                        42, Letters of the Commissioners, VI, 74-75.2 Stat. 589, April 28, 1810,
                        sec. 2. At that time the White House was called the President's
                        house.</note> Located where the center wing and west-center entrance of the
                    Old Executive Office Building are now, it was the second of two structures
                    intended to house the executive offices of the government, the other being the
                    already described<note n="3">See preceding chapter.</note> Treasury Department
                    Building on the east side of the White House.</p>
                <p>On <date when="1799-07-23">July 23, 1799,</date> while the Treasury Department
                    Building was still under construction, the Commissioners for the District of
                    Columbia had sought proposals for the erection of a second executive office
                    building, to be located on the west side of the White House. This building was
                    to be like the Treasury Department Building—"of similar Dimensions &amp;
                    form in every respect"—except that "the Foundation will be laid ten feet deeper
                    from the Surface of the Ground."<note n="4">MS. Nation Archives, Record Group
                        42, Letters of the Commissioners, V, 271-272, the Commissioners to Harbaugh
                        and others.</note> It was "sunk to the eaves in a hollow prepared for it, so
                    that it might be on a level with the Treasury,"<note n="5">John B. Osborne,
                        "The Removal of the Government to Washington," in <hi rend="italic">Records
                            of the Columbia Historical Society,</hi> III, 149. Winslow M. Watson,
                        ed., <hi rend="italic">In Memoriam: Benjamin Ogle Tayloe</hi> (Washington
                        and Philadelphia, 1880), p. 150.</note> and from this fact it was commonly
                    said to have been "built in a hole in the ground."<note n="6">Lurton D.
                        Ingersoll, <hi rend="italic">A History of the War Department of the United
                            States</hi> (Washington and Philadelphia, 1880), p. 110.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On August 6, 1799, the Commissioners entered into a contract for the construction
                    of this building with Leonard Harbaugh, the builder of the Treasury Department
                    Building. The price was $39,511, exactly the same amount as for the Treasury
                    Department Building. Construction was to begin within six weeks and was to be
                    finished by November 1, 1800.<note n="7">MS. National Archives, Record Group
                        42, Proceedings of the Commissioners, V. 175-177.</note> The building was
                    not completed, however, until about April 30, 1801.<note n="8">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Letters of the Commissioners, VI, 74-75, the
                        Commissioners to the Secretary of War and to Harbaugh, April 16,
                        1801.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The available records indicate that the size and the style and details of
                    construction of this building were in all respects similar to those of the
                    Treasury Department Building. It was a plain two-story structure of brick on a
                    freestone foundation, with a basement and a dormer-windowed attic. About 149
                    feet in length, east and west, and 57 ½ feet in breadth, it stood with its west
                    end near the east side of Seventeenth Street just above F Street. On each floor
                    a corridor ran the length of the building, with rooms on each side.<note n="9">Edward D. Ingraham, <hi rend="italic">A Sketch of the Events Which Preceded
                            the Capture of Washington by the British, on the Twenty-fourth of
                            August, 1814</hi> (Philadelphia, 1849), p. 48.</note> There were
                    fourteen rooms on the first floor, fourteen on the second floor, and eight in
                    the attic. Twenty-four of the rooms were 17 by 20 feet, eight were of nearly the
                    same dimensions, and four were fireproof rooms of 10 by 12 feet.<note n="10">MS. National Archives, Record Group 42, Letters of the Commissioners, V,
                        422, the Commissioners to Charles Lee, May 20, 1800. <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Public Buildings and Grounds, Proposals and Estimates,
                        1795-1816, James Hoban to the Commissioners, December 15, 1800.</note> The
                    roof was of shingle; the window sills were of stone; there were numerous
                    fireplaces; the rooms and corridors were plastered and whitewashed; and the
                    windows were fitted with venetian blinds.<note n="11">MS. Department of State,
                        Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses, Day Book, 1798- 1820, pp. 118-119,
                        143, 149, 157, 163, 179, 205, 213, 266, 294, 300, 304.</note> A well
                    supplied water for the building.<note n="12">MS. National Archives, Record
                        Group 42, Letters of the Commissioners, V, 280, the Commissioners to
                        Harbaugh, August 8, 1799.</note> Bookshelves from the Six Buildings were set
                    up in the attic of the new building, as well as 675 feet of new shelving. A set
                    of bookcases in six parts was purchased for the Secretary's room, and at least
                    three of the four iron grates that the Department had installed in the house
                    among the Six Buildings were set up in the new building.<note n="13">MS.
                        Department of State, Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses, Day Book, 1798-
                        1820. pp. 105, 108, 111, 118.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A contemporary British diplomat seemed unimpressed with the Department's new
                    home. He wrote that in this building "the Secretary of State received Foreign
                    Ministers in a very indifferent little room into which they were ushered by his
                    clerk."<note n="14">Margaret B. Tinkcom, "Caviar Along the Potomac: Sir
                        Augustus John Foster's 'Notes on the United States,' 1804-1812," in <hi rend="italic">William and Mary Quarterly; a Magazine of Early American
                            History, Institutions and Culture</hi> (Williamsburg, Va., etc., 1892—),
                        3d ser., VIII, January 1951, 74.</note> For a time the new building housed
                    not only the Department of State, in-<pb n="30"/>[Image: Included in this highly
                    imaginative view of the British invasion of Washington, August 24-25, 1814, is
                    the Public Building West of the White House (marked I).] cluding the Patent
                    Office, but also the War Department, the Navy Department, the General Post
                    Office, the City Post Office, and offices of both the Superintendent and the
                    Surveyor of the city of Washington. By March 1810 the Department of State
                    occupied one small fireproof room on the first floor, four rooms on the second
                    floor (including one room, occupied by the Patent Office, which had been created
                    by partitioning off part of the corridor), and four rooms in the attic.
                    Apparently the small fireproof rooms and the attic rooms were used only for the
                    storage of books and records.<note n="15">MS. Department of State, 15 Domestic
                        Letters, pp. 420-422, Secretary of State <persName>Robert Smith</persName>
                        to <persName>Josiah Quincy,</persName> March 13, 1810.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Later in 1810 the City Post Office and the offices of the Superintendent and the
                    Surveyor were removed from the new building to other quarters. In 1812 the
                    General Post Office and the Patent Office moved into the Blodget Hotel Building,
                    subsequently known as the "General and City Post Office Building."</p>
                <p>The Blodget Hotel Building was a three-story brick structure located on the
                    northeast corner of <placeName>Eighth and E Streets Northwest,</placeName>
                    fronting on <placeName>E Street.</placeName> It was erected in 1793-1795 by
                        <persName>Samuel Blodget,</persName> a speculator in Washington real estate,
                    but it had remained unfinished and unoccupied until its purchase by the
                    government under authority of an act of Congress, approved April 28, 1810.<note n="16">2 Stat. 589, 691. <hi rend="italic">American State Papers,
                            Miscellaneous, 11, 188.</hi> George Watterston, <hi rend="italic">New
                            Guide to Washington</hi> (Washington, 1847-1848), pp. 63-64. Bryan, <hi rend="italic">National Capital,</hi> I, 260, 528, 553-554; II, 247. <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Patent Office Society</hi> (Washington,
                        1918—), XVIII, July 1936, 124, 126. For a biographical sketch of Samuel
                        Blodget, see <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of American Biography,</hi> II,
                        380-381.</note> The following description of the building was published in
                    1816:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Patent Office, constructed according to the plan of J.
                        Hoban, esquire, (who gained the prize for that of the President's house,)
                        consists of three stories, and is a hundred and twenty feet long, and sixty
                        feet wide. It is ornamented with a pediment, and six Ionic pilasters. From
                        the eminence on <pb n="31"/> which it stands, the richly-wooded hills rise
                        on every side, and form a scenery of unequalled beauty."<note n="17">David
                            B. Warden, <hi rend="italic">A Chorographical and Statistical
                                Description of the district of Columbia</hi> (Paris, 1816), p.
                            37</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="24-public-bldg-west-white-house.jpg"/>
                        <head>Blodget's Hotel, home of the Patent Office from 1810 to 1836.</head>
                    </figure> The Patent Office originally occupied two large rooms and two small
                    rooms in the west or Eighth Street wing of the second floor. In 1829 it and the
                    City Post Office were moved into a newly constructed addition to the building
                    which faced Seventh Street. The entire building, including everything belonging
                    to the Patent Office, was destroyed by fire on December 15, 1836.<note n="18">
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Patent Office Society,</hi> XV11I, Jul y
                        1936, 126 — 127, 129, 130. This publication deals also with the subsequent
                        homes of the Patent Office, which was transferred from the Department of
                        State to the Department of the Interior in 1849.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Departments of State, War and Navy remained in the building west of the White
                    House until August 1814. It was in this building that <persName>Robert
                        Smith</persName> succeeded Madison as Secretary of State on <date when="1809-03-06">March 6, 1809</date> (Madison had succeeded Jefferson as
                    President on March 4, 1809), and was in turn succeeded by <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James Monroe</ref> on <date when="1811-04-06">April 6, 1811</date>. The Department of State remained
                    virtually unchanged during this period. In a report made on January 1, 1807,
                    Secretary Madison listed the personnel of the Department, gave a brief
                    description of their duties, and listed their salaries. The Secretary's salary
                    was still $5,000 and the total for the other eight employees was $7,812.<note n="19">Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> pp. 191-193.</note>
                </p>
                <p>While the Department of State was in this building, the United States declared
                    war with England on <date when="1812-06-18">June 18, 1812</date>. During the War
                    of 1812, British forces invaded Washington on <date when="1814-08-24">August 24,
                        1814</date>. That night and the following morning they burned the Capitol,
                    the White House, and the two executive office buildings, including that occupied
                    by the Department of State, and destroyed other property both public and
                    private.</p>
                <p>Five days earlier, President Madison had suggested that Secretary of State Monroe
                    leave Washington to investigate the British advance. Sighting the enemy the
                    following day, Monroe at once sent orders directing the officers of the
                    Department of State to save the records. (At that time the records of the
                    Department included, besides those of its own activities since 1789, the
                    Declaration of Independence, the Constitution, the records of the Continental
                    Congress, the original laws and treaties of the United States, and other
                    valuable papers.)</p>
                <p>The clerks of the Department immediately placed the records in linen bags and
                    loaded them into carts. They were taken first to a vacant gristmill on the
                    Virginia side of the Potomac two miles above <placeName>Georgetown,</placeName>
                    and then, because that location seemed unsafe, to <placeName>Leesburg,
                        Va.,</placeName> where they were kept for "some weeks."<note n="20">Ingraham, <hi rend="italic">Capture of Washington,</hi> pp. 35, 47-49.
                        Bryan, <hi rend="italic">National Capital,</hi> I. 626-627.</note> (The
                    records and models of the Patent Office, which were then in the Blodget Hotel
                    Building, were spared by the invaders.)</p>
                <p>In response to a resolution of the House of Representatives of October 24, 1814,
                    requesting information regarding the destruction of official books and papers of
                    the respective Departments in the British invasion of August 1814, the Secretary
                    of State <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> reported on November 14 as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"... when it became apparent from the movements of the
                        enemy, after his debarkation at Benedict, [Maryland,] that his destination
                        was the seat of Government, every exertion was made, and every means
                        employed, for the removal of the books and papers of this office, to a place
                        of safety; and, notwithstanding the extreme difficulty in obtaining the
                        means of conveyance, it is believed that every paper and manuscript book of
                        the office, of any importance, including those of the old Government, and
                        all in relation to accounts, were placed in a state of security.... it was
                        not found practicable however, to preserve, in like manner, the volumes of
                        laws reserved by Congress for future disposition; many of the books
                        belonging to the library of the Department, as well as some letters <pb n="32"/>on file of minor importance from individuals on business mostly
                        disposed of, which were unavoidably left, and shared the fate, it is
                        presumed, of the building in which they were deposited."</q>
                    <note n="21">
                        <hi rend="italic">American State Papers, Miscellaneous,</hi> II, 252.</note>
                    Because of the quick action of Secretary Monroe and his colleagues, many
                    important historical documents had been saved. One historian stated that these
                    men "deserve public gratitude for... indelible shame... would have followed
                    if... [the British] had carried away with them, as trophies of their exploit,
                    the original of the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution of the
                    United States."<note n="22">Hunt, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p.
                        200.</note> The home of the Department of State, however, did not fare as
                    well. All that remained of this building were the stone foundations and the
                    brick outer walls. A report by George Hadfield dated October 13, 1814, on "the
                    present state of the Public Buildings," includes the following paragraph
                    regarding the two executive office buildings:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Public Offices, These two Buildings in consequence of
                        their having been executed entirely of brick, in the upper structure of the
                        outward walls, have sustained, without material injury, the violence of
                        excessive heat; The apparent and actual damage can be easily corrected by
                        the facility with which bricks can be removed, and replaced in a Building;
                        here also an advantage presents itself from calamity, by affording the
                        opportunity of erecting these Buildings in the interior, of solid material,
                        and thereby render them fireproof, an object often wished in their former
                        state, for the certain preservation of the Public Documents from accidental
                        fire;[.]"<note n="23">MS. National Archives, Record Group 42, Letters
                            Received by Commissioners, ХХ I, No. 2162.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <pb n="33"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section23">
                <head>
                    <placeName>G Street Near Eighteenth Street</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1814-09">Sept. 1814</date> - <date when="1816-03">March 1816</date>
                </head>
                <p>The British attack on the Capital city, including the destruction of the public
                    buildings, forced the government offices to locate elsewhere. Ten days after the
                    British invasion, the Washington <hi rend="italic">Daily National
                        Intelligence</hi> announced (September 3, 1814): "The Public Offices will be
                    accomodated in houses which have been tendered by their proprietors for that
                    purpose, and will immediately recommence the usual routine of business. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="25-g-street-near-eighteenth.jpg"/>
                        <head>G Street Near Eighteenth Street</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The issue of that newspaper for September 9, 1814, included this further
                    information:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Public Buildings having been mostly destroyed, the
                        various offices are locating themselves in those private houses which are
                        most commodious and conveniently situated for the purpose. The President
                        will occupy Col. Taylor's large house, which was lately occupied by the
                        French Minister. The Department of State occupies the house lately inhabited
                        by Judge Duvall; the Treasury Department is fixed at the House formerly
                        occupied by the British minister Foster; the War Office is in the building
                        adjoining the Bank of the Metropolis. The Navy Office in Mr. Mechlin's House
                        near the West Market, and the General Post Office in one of Mr. Way's new
                        houses, &amp;c. &amp;c." Therefore, sometime between September 3 and
                        9, 1814, the Department of State moved into "the house lately inhabited by
                        Judge Duvall."<note n="1">The reference is to Gabriel Duvall, of Maryland.
                            who was then an Associate Justice of the United States Supreme Court.
                            see <hi rend="italic">Biographical Directory of the American
                                Congress,</hi> pp. 1111-1112.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>According to Department of State records, this house was located on the South
                    side of G Street, between 17th and 18th Streets, Northwest.<note n="2">MS.
                        Department of State, Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses, Department of
                        state, 1881-1889, p. 188.</note> At least two Washington historians state
                    that this building was located on the site of the present Young Men's Christian
                    Association Building on G Street.<note n="3">Maud Burr Morris, "An Old
                        Washington Mansion (2017 I Street Northwest)," in <hi rend="italic">Records
                            of the Columbia Historical Society,</hi> XXI, 125-126. Bryan, <hi rend="italic">National Capital, </hi> II, 192.</note> District of
                    Columbia land records indicate that in 1814-1816 only one building stood in this
                    approximate location, and this was a house situated on the westerly half of
                    original lot 14 in square 169, astride the line between the former boy's
                    building at 1730- 1732 G Street and the main building of the Young Men's
                    Christian Association at 1736 G Street. A deed of trust made on October 17,
                    1805, names James Calder of Georgetown as the owner of the property and
                    describes the house as a three-story brick house measuring 26 feet 9 inches by
                    36 feet 9 inches, with kitchen, stable, and carriage house, all of brick, on a
                    lot measuring 31 feet along G Street and 113 feet deep."<note n="4">MS.
                        Recorder of Deeds, D.C., Land Records, lib. O No. 14, fols. 303-307.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On September 1, 1815, while the Department of State still occupied the house,
                    Calder sold it, together with additional land extending westward to Eighteenth
                    Street, to Tobias Lear for $8,000.<note n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> lib. AK No. 35, fols. 455-457.</note> On the
                    same date Lear's son, <persName>Benjamin L. Lear,</persName> bought a small lot
                    adjoining the property on the east,<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> fols. 457-458.</note> and on November 17,
                    1815, Lear bought a lot adjoining his son's lot on the east.<note n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> fols. 232-234.</note>These purchases gave the
                    Lears a total frontage on G Street of approximately 240 feet.</p>
                <p>The Department of State continued to occupy this house until about April <pb n="34"/> 1, 1816. During this time, <persName>James Monroe</persName> was
                    Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>On January 21, 1818, Lear's widow and son sold the whole property on G Street to
                    Attorney General <persName>William Wirt</persName>
                    <note n="8">For a biographical sketch, see <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of
                            American Biography,</hi> XX, 418-421.</note> for $12,000.<note n="9">MS. Recorder of Deeds, D.C., Land Records, lib. AP No. 40, fols. 475-476,
                        477-478.</note> Wirt continued as Attorney General until March 3, 1829.
                    During that time he made this house his residence,<note n="10">John P. Kennedy,
                            <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Life of William Wirt, Attorney-General
                            of the United States,</hi> rev. edition (Philadelphia, 1856), II, 67,
                        225.</note> and it came to be known as the "Wirt property"<note n="11">MS.
                        Recorded of Deeds, D.C., Land Records, lib. WB No. 93, fols. 1-10, June 1,
                        1842.</note> or the "Wirt Mansion." The house had evidently been enlarged
                    during Lear's ownership and presumably after the Department of State had vacated
                    it, because, although it measured less than 27 by 37 feet in 1805 and stood
                    until 1815 on a lot only about four feet wider than the house, Wirt, who had a
                    large family, described the house on the day he bought it as "quite
                    comfortable,"<note n="12">Kennedy, <hi rend="italic">op. crit.,</hi> p.
                        67.</note> and there were subsequent references to it as a "mansion."</p>
                <p>The house subsequently changed hands a number of times.<note n="13">For example,
                        see MS. Recorder of Deeds, D.C., Land Records, lib. WB No. 25, fols.
                        351-358; lib. WB No. 54, fols. 158-162; lib. WB No. 69, fols. 319-321; lib.
                        WB No. 67, fols. 48-74; lib. WB No. 93, fols. 1-10; lib. WB No. 116, fols.
                        282-284; lib. JAS No. 5, fols. 493-496; lib. JAS No. 210, fol. 114; lib. JAS
                        No. 52, fols. 51-59; and Writers' Program, <hi rend="italic">Guide to the
                            Nation's Capital,</hi> p. 98.</note> It was probably still standing in
                    1887, because on June 8 of that year the Department of State purchased from
                    Mathew B. Brady six prints of a photograph of it.<note n="14">MS. Department of
                        State, Accounts Records, Contingent Expenses, Department of State,
                        1881-1889, p. 188.</note>(These prints have not been located.)</p>
                <p>On <date when="1889-03-01">March 1, 1889,</date> John R. McLean of Cincinnati,
                    Ohio, and his wife, sold the property, together with another property just south
                    of it on Eighteenth Street, to the Columbia Athletic Club for $45,000.<note n="15">MS. Recorder of Deeds, D.C., Land Records, lib. 1377, fols.
                        279-282.</note> It was presumably shortly after this sale that the old house
                    was razed, for the Columbia Athletic Club proceeded to erect, partly on its
                    site, a five-story brick structure with an ornate brownstone front which later
                    was the boys' building of the Young Men's Christian Association.<note n="16">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> lib. 1381, fols. 152-178.</note>
                </p>
                <p>By 1898 the Columbia Athletic Club was in default on interest payments on its
                    mortgage on the property, and on December 30, 1898, the property was sold at
                    auction to the YMCA.<note n="17">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> lib. 2356, fols. 280-289.</note> The main
                    building of the YMCA, which covers the westerly portion of the site of the old
                    house, was erected in 1904.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="35"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section24">
                <head>
                    <placeName>Rebuilt Public Building West of the White House</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1816-04">April 1816</date> - <date when="1819-08">August 1819</date>
                </head>
                <p>On or shortly before <date when="1816-03-01">April 1, 1816,</date> the Department
                    of State moved from its temporary quarters in the house on G Street to the
                    rebuilt public building west of the White House. As before the British invasion,
                    the Department shared this building with the War and Navy Departments. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="26-rebuilt-public-bldg-west-wh.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Navy Department building in 1884, showing added third
                            story.</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Congress had provided, on <date when="1815-02-13">February 13, 1815,</date> "That
                    the President of the United States cause to be repaired or rebuilt forthwith,
                    the President's House, Capitol and public offices, on their present sites in the
                    city of Washington,"<note n="1">3 Stat. 205.</note> Within fourteen months, the
                    reconstruction of the public building to the west of the White House was
                    completed and ready for occupancy at a cost of not quite $32,000.<note n="2">American State Papers, <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous,</hi> II,
                        438.</note> The <hi rend="italic">Daily National Intelligencer </hi> of
                    April 2, 1816, offered the following comment: <hi rend="italic">"The Public
                        Offices.</hi> —It is very satisfactory to perceive that the Public
                    Buildings, occupied by the different Offices, are already repaired, we might
                    almost say rebuilt, so as to be in a condition much superior to that in which
                    they were before their conflagration by the torch of our late enemy. The
                    Department of State is already moved into the East end of the second story of
                    the building west of the President's house; where it has very capacious and
                    excellent apartments, being very much better accommodated as to room and
                    arrangement than heretofore."</p>
                <p>Work on the building had involved fairly extensive patching of the existing outer
                    brick walls and the rebuilding of the roof and the interior. The architect was
                    James Hoban, who had been awarded first prize for his design of the White House,
                    who had designed and built the Blodget Hotel, and who was currently supervising
                    the rebuilding of the White House.<note n="3">For a biographical sketch of
                        James Hoban, see <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of American Biography,</hi> IX
                        91-92.</note> Josias Thompson was the contractor, and the bricklaying work
                    was contracted by Peter Mortie.<note n="4">MS. National Archives, Record Group
                        42, Letters Received by Commissioners, XXII, Nos. 2202 and 2266, Mortie to
                        the Commissioners, June 10, 1815, and Hoban to the Commissioners, January
                        29, 1816; XXIII, No. 2302, Hoban to the Commissioners, April 16,
                        1816.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The rebuilt building was the same size as the original and evidently very similar
                    to it in design both inside and outside. It was two stories high, with a
                    basement and an attic with entrances on each of its four sides. On both stories
                    a corridor ran the length of the building, with fourteen rooms on each side of
                    each corridor. In the center of the building, on the north side of the corridor,
                    was a wide staircase.<note n="5">Peter Force, <hi rend="italic">A National
                            Calendar, for 1820</hi> (Washington 1820), pp. 177, 180-181. Jonathan
                        Elliot, <hi rend="italic">Historical Sketches of the Ten Miles Square
                            Forming the District of Columbia</hi> (Washington, 1830), p. 164.
                        Watterston, <hi rend="italic">Guide to Washington,</hi> p. 61.</note>
                    Apparently there were twenty-eight fireplaces, the hearths of which, in the
                    rooms for the Secretaries, were of stone, and in the other rooms "of stock Brick
                    neatly laid in mortar."<note n="6">MS. National Archives, Record Group 42,
                        Letters Received by Commissioners, XXII, No. 2250, Hoban to the
                        Commissioners, October 30, 1815.</note> At the time the Department of State
                    occupied the building, the roof was of shingle, which was subsequently replaced
                    with slate,<note n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">American State Papers, Miscellaneous,</hi> II, 578</note>
                    and the rooms were whitewashed.<note n="8">MS. Department of State, Account
                        Records, Contingent Expenses, Day Book, 1798- 1820, p. 334.</note> A new
                    desk and bookcase were purchased for the Secretary's room for $90 on March 19,
                    1817.<note n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 314.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State, by the end of 1817, occupied five rooms on the second
                    floor at the south and east end of the building and four rooms in the attic,
                    while the Patent Office (still a part of the Department) occupied two rooms in
                    the General and City Post Office Building (Blodget Hotel building). According to
                    a report by John Quincy Adams, who had succeeded Monroe as Secretary of State on
                    September 22, 1817,<note n="10">Monroe actually had asked Adams to be Secretary
                        on March 6, 1817, two days after his inauguration as President. Adams was in
                        Great Britain at the time as the U.S. Minister and did not receive Monroe's
                        proposal until April 16, 1817. Adams accepted immediately, although he did
                        not arrive in the United States until August 6, and entered upon his duties
                        September 22, 1817. John Graham, the Chief Clerk, served as <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> Secretary from March 4 to March 9, and the
                        new Attorney General, Richard Rush, carried on in the same capacity until
                        Adams assumed the office.</note> this space was wholly inadequate to the
                    needs of the Department,<note n="11">MS. Department of State, 3 Report Book, p.
                        8. American <hi rend="italic">State Papers, Miscellaneous, II,</hi>
                        470.</note> even though the total personnel, including messengers, and
                    assistants still numbered only about a dozen persons.</p>
                <p>Secretary Adams also complained about the amount of work he had to do in the
                    Department of State. In a letter to a friend dated June 22, 1818, he wrote: "It
                    was considered by Mr. Madison that the public duties of the Department of State
                    were more than sufficient for one man.... For myself I can only assure you that
                    I have found the duties of the Department to be more than I can perform. Some of
                    them therefore are not performed."<note n="12">
                        <hi rend="italic">The Writings of John Quincy Adams,</hi> ed., W.C. Ford
                        (New York 1916), VI, 354.</note> "All is disorder and confusion," he
                    lamented.<note n="13">
                        <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of John Quincy Adams,</hi> ed. Charles F. Adams
                        (Philadelphia, 1875), IV, 100.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Consequently, Adams took steps to <pb n="36"/> improve the work of the
                    Department. By an executive order in 1818, the duties and salaries of a number
                    of the clerks were specifically stated.<note n="14">House Document No. 194,
                        15th Cong., 1st Sess., VII, (serial 11).</note> Among other things, he also
                    set up an improved system for filing and registering diplomatic and consular
                    correspondence put in order<note n="15">
                        <hi rend="italic">Memoirs... op. cit.,</hi> p. 224</note>; the Department's
                    accounts;<note n="16">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 366.</note> and improved the system of
                    recording the laws and resolutions of Congress, which was then a function of the
                    Department of state.<note n="17">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> p. 435.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Although the Department of State moved out of the public building west of the
                    White House in 1819, that building continued to house the Navy Department for
                    nearly sixty-five years thereafter. Pursuant to a joint resolution of Congress
                    approved December 15, 1864,<note n="18">13 Stat. 565.</note> it was enlarged by
                    the addition of a third story and an extension or wing on the south side.<note n="19">A photograph of the old building, which was taken by Third Assistant
                        Secretary of State Alvey A. Adee in 1884, shortly before it was torn down,
                        and which shows in the background portions of the east and south wings of
                        the then unfinished State, War, and Navy Building, is reproduced in this
                        chapter.</note> The building was razed between February 18 and March 31,
                    1884, to make way for the erection of the center and west wings of the State,
                    War, and Navy Building—the present Old Executive Office Building which still
                    stands on that site.<note n="20">House Executive Document No. 337, 50th Cong.,
                        1st Sess. (serial 2561), p. 3.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="37"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section25">
                <head>
                    <placeName>Northeast Executive Building</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1819-08">August, September 1819</date>-<date when="1866-11">November
                        1866</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Department's need for more space, as reported by John Quincy Adams in
                    December 1817 (see previous chapter), was not unique in the administration. In
                    his annual message to the Congress on December 2, 1817, President Monroe
                    indicated that the public buildings in Washington had become "altogether
                    insufficient for the accommodation of the several Executive Departments."<note n="1">James D. Richardson, <hi rend="italic">A Compilation of the Messages
                            and Papers of the Presidents, 1789-1897</hi> (Washington, 1896-1899),
                        II, 19.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="27-northeast-executive-bldg.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Northeast Executive Building in 1830, home of the Department from
                            1819 to 1866</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Congress agreed that there was a need for more space and recommended that two
                    additional public buildings be erected similar in structure to those east and
                    west of the White House.<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">American State Papers, Miscellaneous,</hi> II,
                        470-473.</note> An act was approved April 20, 1818, which provided for the
                    erection of <quote>"two buildings, suitable for offices of the executive
                        departments, to be placed north of the buildings at present occupied by
                        those departments, and in a line parallel therewith; each of said new
                        buildings to contain forty rooms of convenient size." </quote>
                    <note n="3">3 Stat. 441.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Construction of the two buildings was completed in 1819 at a total cost of
                    $191,756.71.<note n="4">
                        <hi rend="italic">American State Papers, Miscellaneous,</hi> II, 578.</note>
                    The designer and contractor was James Hoban.<note n="5">Hoban made two progress
                        reports, which together give a detailed picture of the two buildings. See
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> p. 530; and House Document No. 15, 16th
                        Cong., 1st Sess. (serial 32), pp. 6-7.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The two new buildings were located east and west of the White House and north of
                    the two older executive office buildings. The east building, which became known
                    as the Northeast Executive wing of the Treasury Department Building, stood where
                    the north Building now stands. It became the home of the Department of State.
                    The west building, known as the Northwest Executive Building, was located where
                    the north wing of the Old Executive Office Building (Old State Department
                    Building) is now. It was the home of the War Department.</p>
                <p>The two old buildings continued to be used by the government. The Southeast
                    Executive Building continued to house the Treasury Department until it was
                    destroyed by fire on <date when="1833-03-31">March 31, 1833.</date> The
                    Southwest Executive Building, formerly used by the Department of State, became
                    the home of the Navy Department.</p>
                <p>The new buildings, each 157 by 57 feet, were two stories, plus basement and
                    attic, with dormer windows in the attic. There was an entrance on each of the
                    four sides of the buildings. The floor plans of the two buildings were
                    identical. A corridor ran the length of each floor, with rooms on either side,
                    sixteen on the first floor and fifteen— one of them about triple-sized,
                    however—on the second floor. The triple-sized room, which was designed as a
                    library, was in the center front, extending the length of the portico, and had
                    five windows. In the center of each building, on the south side of the corridor,
                    was a wide staircase.<note n="6">Peter Force, <hi rend="italic">A Directory for
                            the Public Offices</hi> (Washington, 1820), pp. 3-7. Force, <hi rend="italic">National Calendar for 1820,</hi> pp. 177-181. David H.
                        Bates, <hi rend="italic">Lincoln in the Telegraph Office </hi> (New York,
                        1907), p. 146.</note> By the early 1830s, the exteriors of all four
                    executive office buildings were painted a leaden-gray color with white trim.<note n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">Picture of the City of Washington</hi> (Washington, 1836),
                        p. 13. MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Northeast Executive
                        Building, Miscellaneous Accounts, 1843- 1857, p. 10. Also various
                        photographs.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A description of the two buildings as they appeared in 1830 follows (the
                    dimensions here given are not exact):</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"At the distance of about 200 yards, on the east of the
                        President's house, are situated two buildings for the departments of State
                        and of the Treasury; and at the same distance on the West, are two others
                        for the War and Navy departments. These buildings are all of the same
                        dimensions and construction; they are 160 feet long and 55 feet wide, of
                        brick, two stories in height; they are divided in their length by a broad
                        passage, with rooms on each side and a spacious staircase in the centre. The
                        two most northerly buildings are ornamented with an Ionic portico of six
                        columns and pediment; and every observer must be convinced that the two
                        other buildings require some such finish on their south fronts, to make them
                        complete. —The grounds about these offices have been graduated and planted,
                        of late years; and the shrubbery begins to present a pleasing appearance."<note n="8">Elliot, <hi rend="italic">Historical Sketches of the Ten
                                Miles Square Forming the District of Columbia</hi> (Washington,
                            1830), p. 164.</note>
                    </q>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="29-northeast-executive-bldg-p2.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Southwest Executive Building (above), home of the Department from
                            April 1816 to August 1819, stood to the right and rear of the White
                            House. </head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State—not including the Patent Office, which remained in the
                    Post Office Building— moved into the new Northeast Executive Building from the
                    building on Seventeenth Street west of the White House (Southwest Executive
                    Building) sometime between August 21 and September 11, 1819.<note n="9">MS.
                        Department of State, 17 Domestic Letters, pp. 350-351, 356-357, 359, 362.
                        MS. Department of State, Miscellaneous Letters, July-August 1819, Peter
                        Force to the Secretary of State, August 23, 1819.</note> It occupied eleven
                    rooms on the second floor and six on the attic floor.<note n="10">MS.
                        Department of State, Account Records, Requisitions of the Treasury,
                        1818-1825, p. 67, October 13, 1819." Force, <hi rend="italic">National
                            Calendar for 1820,</hi> pp. 178, 182-183. Force, <hi rend="italic">A
                            Directory for the Public Offices,</hi> pp. 4, 8-9.</note> The large
                    library probably counted as two rooms, because, according to a publication of
                    1820, the Department then occupied ten rooms on the second floor, including the
                    library, while the Fifth Auditor of the Treasury and his staff occupied the
                    other five rooms on that floor<note n="11">Force, <hi rend="italic">National
                            Calendar for 1820,</hi> pp. 178, 182-183. Force, <hi rend="italic">A
                            Directory for the Public Offices,</hi> pp. 4, 8-9.</note>
                </p>
                <pb n="38"/>
                <p>The Department's rooms were on the north side of the corridor, except the two at
                    the northwest corner, and on the south side of the corridor from the center of
                    the building to the eastern end. The Secretary's room at this time was at the
                    southeast corner of the building. The first floor of the building was used by
                    the General Land Office and the Paymaster General's Office.<note n="12">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy">John Quincy
                        Adams</ref> was Secretary of State at the time of the move. His staff
                    consisted of the Chief Clerk, nine clerks, one messenger, and one assistant
                    messenger, besides the Superintendent, one clerk, and one messenger in the
                    Patent Office.<note n="13">MS. Department of State, 3 Report Book, p. 76.
                        Force, <hi rend="italic">National Calendar for 1820,</hi> p. 9.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department grew steadily, but without benefit of an organizational pattern
                    until 1833 when, under Secretary <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/mclane-louis">Louis McLane</ref>, it was
                    organized for the first time into bureaus. Now functions and responsibilities
                    were more specifically designated. This organization was subsequently modified,
                    but remained basically the same until 1870. By 1846 the Department of State,
                    together with the Fifth Auditor of the Treasury, occupied most of the rooms in
                    the Northeast Executive Building and still needed more space. According to
                    Secretary John C. Calhoun, writing in 1845, the number of "regular" clerks had
                    increased from 10 in 1818 to 14 in 1845 with eight "extra" clerks appropriated
                    for by single acts or joint resolutions of Congress.<note n="14">
                        <hi rend="italic">Annual Report,</hi> American Historical Association, 1899,
                        p. 641.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The following memorandum to Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/buchanan-james">James Buchanan</ref>,
                    unsigned and undated but evidently written by Edward Stubbs, Disbursing Agent of
                    the Department, about February 12-14, 1846, shows something of the disposition
                    of the offices of the Department throughout the building at that time:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"Memo. Rooms N.E. Ex. Building.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"In the Department of State on the 2nd floor there are 15
                        rooms, two of them small, and one large. Of these two are occupied by the
                        Secretary,</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">One as an ante-room</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">One, by the Chief Clerk</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">Three, by the 4 clerks of the Diplomatic Bureau</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">Two, including the longroom for the Library &amp;
                        Libn</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">One, for the Bureau of Archives &amp; Laws</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">One, for the Translator</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">Two, for the two clerks of the Consular Bureau</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">One, for the Disbursing Agent, and,</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">One, a small one, for two Clerks, one, assisting in
                        Diplomatic Bureau; and one, keeper of Mail Registers &amp; issuing
                        Pardons, and passports. The latter has charge of the great seal. The
                        sealing, for want of other room, has to be done in the passage.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"On the lower floor there are 16 rooms two of them
                        small.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"Of these The Fifth Auditor, being Auditor for all accounts
                        connected with the Department of State, has 6 rooms...</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Second Comptroller has, for a part of his Office, 3
                        rooms...</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"For Watchmen &amp; laborers of the Buildg 1
                        room...</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"For the clerk charged with keeping copy right books,
                        Recording, issuing certificates of Official character, 1 room...</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"For safe keeping the enrolled laws, Manuscript archives,
                        evidences of claims on foreign governments, Archives of Conventions to
                        adjust claims. Returns of Sixth Census 2 rooms. These are also occupied by
                        Clerks employed by the Department, by Clarke &amp; Force copying for
                        their <pb n="39"/> Documentary History, and, by clerks copying for the new
                        edition of the laws.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"1 room is occupied by the packer and distributor of laws
                        &amp; Congressional documents,</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"1 room for the reception &amp; packing of the laws and
                        documents, and,</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"1 room as a bindery and receptacle of laws and
                        documents.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The attic story (a half story) contains 9 rooms with
                        dormer windows. These are used for the reception of various printed
                        documents, laws &amp;c . besides the Newspapers, bound and unbound;
                        including one occupied as a store room by the Comptroller. They are not
                        habitable by Clerks; neither is it considered safe to have fires in
                        them.</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Department needs the rooms occupied by the
                        Comptroller. One on the lower floor for an addition to the Copy right room,
                        now insufficient to contain the books deposited, and those which will, under
                        the law, continue to be deposited</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"One for the reception and arrangement of Manuscript
                        archives &amp; c for which there is at present no room; and one, for one
                        of the two clerks at present in one of the small rooms on the 2nd Story. All
                        three to be occasionally occupied by such temporary clerks as may be
                        required to transact extraordinary business."<note n="15">MS. Department of
                            State, Accounts Records, 16 Domestic Letters re Accounts, pp.
                            360-362.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>It should be noted that, by an act of <date when="1836-06-04">July 4,
                        1836,</date> the Patent Office had been changed to the Commissioner of
                    Patents and recognized as a separate portion of the Department, responsible to
                    the Secretary.<note n="16">5 Stat., 117.</note> This function was moved
                    entirely from the Department's jurisdiction when it was incorporated in the
                    Department of Interior upon that Department's formation in 1849.<note n="17">
                        9 Stat., 395.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The old accounts records of the Department of State reveal many details regarding
                    the Northeast Executive Building through the years. For example, there is
                    mentioned instances of painting the exterior and interior from time to time, and
                    papering certain rooms on occasion. Heat was supplied by numerous fireplaces,
                    supplemented by iron stoves. Illumination was by means of candles and spermoil
                    lamps until about the middle of 1852, when the Washington Gas Light Company
                    began supplying gas to the building. The Department's rooms were carpeted, at
                    least during the winter months, and at times the corridors were carpeted also.
                    Sometime around April 1863, a tin-roofed passageway had been erected to connect
                    this building with the then unfinished Treasury Department Building.<note n="18">This paragraph is based on information found here and there in the
                        following volumes of MS. Department of State, Accounts Records: Cash Book,
                        1820-1824. Day Book A, 1824-1826. Day Book, 1826-1829. Northeast Executive
                        Building, Expense Accounts, 1833-1842. Northeast Executive Building,
                        Miscellaneous Accounts, 1843-1857. Contingencies, Northeast Executive
                        Building, 1857-1867. Stationery, Miscellaneous, Copperplate Printing, Books,
                        and Maps, 1857-1867.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Frederick W. Seward gives the following description of the building as it
                    appeared when he entered upon his duties as Assistant Secretary of State in
                    March 1861:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"It was substantial and convenient, without being either
                        stately or imposing. Its exterior was painted a plain drab color, and
                        exhibited little attempt at ornamentation, excepting a portico of six white
                        columns on the northern side. Under this portico was the main entrance,
                        which, however, was little used—a side door on Fifteenth street offering a
                        more convenient way of ingress and egress. Within, its finish was equally
                        simple. It had but thirty or forty rooms, not large, though well arranged
                        for their purpose; and these, during the preceding half century, had been
                        found ample for the needs of this branch of the Government; though the
                        accumulation of books and archives was now beginning to cramp the space of
                        some of the clerks. The two rooms in the north-east corner of the second
                        floor were usually occupied by the Secretary—one for study, the other for
                        receiving visitors. Messengers were just outside his door; and across the
                        hall, within convenient reach, were the rooms of the Assistant Secretary and
                        Chief Clerk."<note n="19">Frederick W. Seward, Seward at Washington, as
                            Senator and Secretary of State (New York, 1891), I, 519.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="28-northeast-executive-bldg-p1.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Northeast Executive Building (above), home of the Department from
                            1819 to 1866, stood to the left and in front of the White House.</head>
                    </figure> The Department of State occupied the Northeast Executive Building for
                    47 years, including those of the Civil War, from the late summer of 1819 until
                    November 1866. From this location sixteen Secretaries of State guided the
                    expanding U.S. foreign relations.</p>
                <p>Diplomatic posts had increased from 15 in 1830 to 33 in 1860. Consular posts had
                    increased from 141 to 282 during the same period.</p>
                <pb n="40"/>
                <p>Bу 1866 the Department probably occupied the entire Northeast Executive Building,
                    for the records indicate that by November 1863 the Department had overflowed
                    into two or three rooms in the Treasury Department Building.<note n="20">MS.
                        Department of State, Accounts Records, Contingencies, Northeast Executive
                        Building, 1857-1867, p. 68.</note> Also, in November 1866, Secretary <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William H.
                        Seward</ref> had a staff of forty-six, including thirteen extra or temporary
                    clerks but exclusive of laborers and watchmen.<note n="21"> MS. Department of
                        State, Accounts Records, Pay Rolls, 1866-1867, November 1866.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The story is told that after the Northeast Executive Building was torn down, one
                    of the officers presented to Secretary Seward a cane of plain dark wood and
                    stated:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"That stick, Mr. Secretary, has been in the hands of every
                        President of the United States, of every Secretary of State and every
                        cabinet officer. It has been handled by every foreign minister accredited to
                        the government or commissioned by it. It has been touched by nearly every
                        senator and by the majority of all the representatives in Congress, to say
                        nothing of thousands of civil, military, and naval officers and private
                        citizens."</q>
                </p>
                <p>When Seward expressed his incredulity, the clerk explained that it had been
                    carved out of the handrail of the old stairway leading to the Secretary's
                    office.<note n="22">Seward, <hi rend="italic">Seward at Washington,</hi> III,
                        343.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="41"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section26">
                <head>
                    <placeName>Washington City Orphan Asylum</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1866-11">November 1866</date>-<date when="1875-07">July 1875</date>
                </head>
                <p>In 1866 the Northeast Executive Building was scheduled to be torn down to make
                    way for the erection of the north wing of the present Treasury Department
                    Building. On July 3, 1866, Congress authorized the Secretary of State <quote>"to
                        hire a suitable building or buildings for the temporary accommodation of the
                        Department of State"</quote> and appropriated $25,000 <quote>"towards
                        defraying the expense of such hiring, the transfer of the public archives,
                        and the fitting up of the building or buildings."</quote>
                    <note n="1">14 Stat., 362.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="30-washington-city-orphan-asylum.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Washington City Orphan Asylum</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The Department began moving on <date when="1866-11-01">November 1, 1866,</date>
                    to its new home, the then newly erected <placeName>Washington City Orphan Asylum
                        Building</placeName> located on the southeast corner of Fourteenth and S
                    Streets Northwest. The Washington <hi rend="italic">Evening Star</hi> on <date when="1866-11-01">November 1, 1866,</date> described the move as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The work of removing the archives and documents of the
                        State Department to the Protestant Orphan Asylum building, on 14th street,
                        which has been leased by the Government for five years, was commenced
                        to-day, preparatory to tearing down the old State Department building to
                        make room for the Treasury extension."</q>
                </p>
                <p>The move was also reported the following day in two other Washington newspapers.<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Daily Morning Chronicle, and National Republican,</hi>
                        November 2, 1866.</note> It has been asserted over the years that in 1866
                    the Department moved for a brief period to a building on the southwest corner of
                    Thirteenth Street and Pennsylvania Avenue Northwest. This claim has been largely
                    based on evidence found in a Washington city directory of 1866 which gives the
                    address of the Department of State as "Penn. Avenue, corner 13th Street,"<note n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Boyd's Washington and Georgetown Directory...1866</hi>
                        (Washington, 1866), p. 107.</note> but the figure <hi rend="italic">13</hi>
                    is an error for <hi rend="italic">15</hi>. Based on the contemporary accounts
                    records of the Department of State,<note n="4">MS. Department of State,
                        Accounts Records, Contingencies, Northeast Executive Building, 1857-1867,
                        pp. 90-105.</note> and the contemporary newspaper accounts already referred
                    to, it is certain that the Department moved directly from the Northeast
                    Executive Building to the Washington City Orphan Asylum Building.</p>
                <p>An item in the Washington <hi rend="italic">Daily National Intelligencer</hi> of
                    November 1, 1866, indicated that the <placeName>Orphan Asylum
                        Building</placeName> was being completed in time for the Department of State
                    to take possession on November 1:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The Protestant Male and Female Orphan Asylum, on
                        Fourteenth street, was completed and turned over to the building committee
                        on Tuesday last [October 30] by Mr James G Naylor, the contractor for
                        building the same, to their entire satisfaction. According to the terms of
                        the contract the time for its completion extended to the 1st of April next;
                        but, in order to enable the managers of the asylum to give the State
                        Department possession on the 1st of November, by the extraordinary exertion
                        of the contractor the building is completed, and they are now moving into
                        it."</q>
                </p>
                <p>There also appears to be some disagreement concerning how smoothly the move was
                    made. Frederick W. Seward, who was Assistant Secretary of State at the time,
                    later wrote that the removal was carried out under the direction of George E.
                    Baker, the Disbursing Clerk of the Department, and that—</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"...a judicious plan prevented any lapse from order to
                        chaos. At the close <pb n="42"/> of business one afternoon, each bureau
                        officer and clerk was instructed to remove the papers under his own especial
                        charge. Workmen and carts enough for the purpose were placed at his
                        disposal. A single night sufficed to make the transfer, though the new and
                        old quarters were a mile apart. The next morning every official was at his
                        post, and every paper in place, and forthcoming at call."<note n="5">Seward, <hi rend="italic">Seward at Washington,</hi> III, 343.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>The Department's contemporary accounts records suggest, however, that the moving
                    was accomplished with somewhat less speed and efficiency than the above
                    quotation describes. A letter written by the Disbursing Clerk on November 14,
                    1866, two weeks after the move began, states that <quote>"The confusion of
                        removing the Department to a new Building has caused delay in remittance and
                        prevented me from preparing an order...."</quote>
                    <note n="6">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, 40 Domestic Letters, p.
                        357.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Washington City Orphan Asylum Building was a somewhat ornate red-brick
                    structure, of three stories and basement, and had the general appearance of an
                    urban public school building. It was set back a few yards from the sidewalk on
                    Fourteenth Street and also on S Street, with its main entrance on Fourteenth
                    Street.</p>
                <p>Both before and after the Department of State moved into this building, it made
                    extensive alterations in the interior arrangement and in the plumbing and the
                    gas-fittings. It also had erected a stable and a flagpole; and it expended a
                    considerable sum of money for such items as masonry, grading, paperhanging,
                    painting, hardware, upholstering, furniture, and carpets.<note n="7">MS.
                        Department of State, Accounts, Records, Contingencies, Northeast Executive
                        Building, 1857-1867, pp. 95-105, passim. <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Cash
                        Book, 1866-1871, pp. 25, 45.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department rented this building for nine years, from November 1, 1866, until
                    October 31, 1875, at a rate of $1,250 a month, or $15,000 a year, payment being
                    made to the treasurer of the Washington City Orphan Asylum.<note n="8">МS.
                        Department of State, Accounts Records, Ledger, 1866-1871, pp. 99, 113-363,
                            <hi rend="italic">passim. Ibid.,</hi> Contingent Expenses, Department of
                        State, 1867-1881, pp. 5-239, <hi rend="italic">passim. Ibid.,</hi> Sundry
                        Accounts, 1867-1881, p. 196. <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Cash Book
                        1875-1877, pp. 45, 113, 117.</note> Despite the high rental, the building
                    was not well suited to the needs of the Department, either in size or in
                    construction. On January 27, 1869, Secretary of State William Н. Seward wrote
                    that "the building is much too small for the necessary uses of the department."<note n="9">House Executive Document No. 67, 40th Cong., 3d Sess. (serial
                        1374), p. 1.</note> Also, two fires which broke out there during the
                    Department's occupancy <quote>"came near proving disastrous."</quote>
                    <note n="10">MS. Department of State, 5 Reports of Bureau Officers, undated
                        memorandum of James Fenner Lee, Chief Clerk of the Department from February
                        1, 1888, until February 10, 1890, entitled "Department of State
                        Building."</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was in this makeshift building that Seward concluded his eight years less one
                    day of service as Secretary of State (a period exceeded only by that of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Cordell Hull</ref>,
                    1933-1944, and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/rusk-david-dean">Dean
                        Rusk,</ref> 1961-196911).<note n="11">Rusk's time of service exceeded
                        Seward's by only one day.</note> It was also here that <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/washburne-elihu-benjamin">Elihu B.
                        Washburne</ref> served as Secretary of State for twelve days, the shortest
                    term on record; and it was here that <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton Fish</ref>
                    commenced on March 17, 1869, a period of service as Secretary which was to be
                    only three days shorter than Seward's. By December 1873 Secretary Fish had a
                    staff of thirty-seven officers, clerks, and other employees, exclusive of
                    laborers and watchmen.<note n="12">
                        <hi rend="italic">Register of the Department of State... 1873</hi>
                        (Washington, 1873), pp. 6-7.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Some years after the Department of State vacated the building, an extension
                    eastward along S Street, in a matching style of architecture, was added. In 1927
                    the asylum moved to new quarters, and subsequently the building was converted to
                    commercial purposes. The front was extended to the line of the sidewalk, so that
                    the facade on Fourteenth Street had no resemblance to that of the original
                    building; an extension was added southward along Fourteenth Street; and the
                    whole enlarged structure was renamed "Merchandise Building." The building has
                    since been razed and on the site are now townhouse apartments.</p>
                <p>Either because of the shortage of space or because of the fire hazard in the
                    Orphan Asylum Building, or perhaps for both reasons, the Department of State,
                    while it occupied that building, rented a building across the street, on the
                    southwest corner of Fourteenth and S Streets, "for the storage of Books, Maps,
                    papers, archives, &amp;с ." This building is described as a "three story
                    brick house and premises." Rent at the rate of $62.50 a month covering the
                    period from July 1, 1870, to March 31, 1875, was paid first to J.P. Klingle,
                    later to Moses Kelley, executor, and still later to Moses Kelley and J.B. Blake,
                    executors.<note n="13">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Stationery,
                        Furniture, &amp;c., 1872, 1867-1889, pp. 55, 58- 60. <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Contingent Expenses, Department of State, 1867-1881, pp.
                        55, 61, 78, 99, 101, 129, 134, 142, 151, 156, 169, 179.</note> This building
                    has since been torn down, and its site is now occupied by a service station.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="43"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section27">
                <head>
                    <placeName>State, War, and Navy Building</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1875-07">July 1875</date>-<date when="1947-04">April 1947</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Department of State had been in the <placeName>Washington City Orphan Asylum
                        Building</placeName> for only three years when Congress recognized that,
                    because of the high rent, the inadequate space, and the severe fire hazard,<note n="1">MS. Department of State, 5 Reports of bureau Officer's
                        memorandum of James Fenner Lee, cited in the previous chapter.</note> new
                    quarters would have to be found for the Department. Consequently, a Commission
                    of six members, including Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton Fish</ref>, was
                    appointed by Congress in 1869 to recommend a site and submit plans for a new
                    executive office building to house the Department of State.<note n="2">Actually, as early as the 1830s and 1840s proposals had been submitted for
                        new executive office buildings. Some of these plans even resembled those
                        that were eventually accepted many years later. See <hi rend="italic">Executive Office Building,</hi> General Services Administration
                        Historical Study No. 3 (Washington, revised September 1970) [Hereinafter
                        referred to as <hi rend="italic">Executive Office Building.</hi>]</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="31-state-war-navy-building.jpg"/>
                        <head>The State, War, and Navy Building</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>At first the Commission planned to locate the new building either at Lafayette
                    Square or at Scott Square (now McPherson Square).<note n="3">House Executive
                        Document No. 71, 41st Cong., 2d Sess. (serial 1417), p.1.</note> By February
                    1870, however, the agreed upon site was west of the White House, a site which
                    was then partially occupied by the buildings of the War and Navy Departments.<note n="4">MS. Department of State, Miscellaneous Letters, February 1870,
                        pt. 2.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Secretary Fish drafted a bill to this effect. The bill also proposed that the new
                    building, which would house the State, War, and Navy Departments, should be
                    constructed in stages beginning with the south wing in order to avoid
                    interfering with the War and Navy Departments while it was being constructed.<note n="5">MS. Department of State, 10 Repot Book, p. 268; and pp. 278-279,
                        letter of February 25, 1870, and enclosure.</note> This would allow these
                    two departments to remain in their buildings until later in the construction
                    when those buildings would have to be razed to make way for the other wings.</p>
                <p>Congress did not immediately enact this bill, and President Grant was constrained
                    to emphasize, in his annual message of December 5, 1870, the inadequacy and the
                    hazardous condition of the Orphan Asylum Building and the urgent need of an
                    appropriation for the construction of a new building.<note n="6">Richardson,
                            <hi rend="italic">Messages and Papers of the Presidents,</hi> VII,
                        106.</note> In response to this entreaty, Congress, on March 3, 1871,
                    appropriated $500,000-the first of 18 appropriations amounting in all to
                    $10,124,500—</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"... for the construction, under the direction of the
                        Secretary of State, on the southerly portion of the premises now occupied by
                        the War and Navy Departments, a building which will form the south wing of a
                        building that, when completed, will be similar in the ground plan and
                        dimensions to the Treasury building, and provide accommodations for the
                        State, War, and Navy Departments; the building to be of such kind of stone
                        as may be hereafter determined by the concurrent decision of the committee
                        of public buildings and grounds of the Senate and House of Representatives;
                        three stories in height, with basement and attic, and of fire-proof
                        construction, the plans to be approved by the Secretary of State, the
                        Secretary of War, and the Secretary of the Navy, before any money is
                        expended under the provisions of this act."<note n="7">16 Stat. 494.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>The new building was designed by Alfred B. Mullett, Supervising Architect of the
                    Treasury, who was also in charge of constructing the building until December 31,
                    1874, when he was succeeded by William A. Potter, the new Supervising Architect
                    of the Treasury. From March 3, 1875, to March 3, 1877, Colonel Orville E.
                    Babcock, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, directed construction. He was succeeded
                    by Colonel Thomas Lincoln Casey, Corps of Engineers, who saw the building to
                    completion.</p>
                <p>Ground was broken for the south wing on June 21, 1871, and the first granite
                    stone was laid on February 2, 1872. This wing was completed in December 1875,
                    although construction on the library apparently continued well into 1876.<note n="8">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, New Department, Ledger,
                        1871-1883, p. 116.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Just before the south wing was completed in the latter part of June 1875, the
                    Department of State began moving in. Secretary Fish mentioned the move in
                    various letters at the time. On June 29 he stated that "for the past week we
                    have been gradually removing Documents &amp; c &amp;c."<note n="9"> MS.
                        Library of Congress, Papers of Hamilton Fish, Letter Copy Book, February
                        25-October 28, 1875, p. 290.</note> On July 17 he wrote, "On Monday [July
                    19] we open shop &amp; transact business in the new Вuilding."<note n="10">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> June 26, 1875-May 4, 1876, p. 22.</note>
                    Finally, on July 20 he wrote:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"We have just moved into our new State Dept Building. I
                        experience a freedom from the anxiety which the Combustible nature of the
                        old building kept ever present in my mind. We now have a fine, commodious,
                        &amp; elegant building."<note n="11">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> February 25-October 28, 1875, p.
                            344.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>The move was also mentioned in the Washington <hi rend="italic">Evening Star</hi>
                    of June 29, 1875 as follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The work of removing the archives of the Department of
                        State from the hospital building on Fourteenth street to the new building on
                        the southwest corner of Executive Square has already been commenced. At
                        present the workmen are engaged with the bound volumes of newspapers and
                        other bulky documents, but in a few days the whole establishment will be
                        transferred, and the Department will be permanently located in <pb n="44"/>
                        its new and elegant quarters. In many respects the new building is the
                        finest in the United States, and in every way worthy... the uses to which it
                        is to be devoted."<note n="12"> This item was reprinted in the Washington
                                <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> of June 30, 1875.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>At the time of the move, the Department of State was comprised of a total of
                    fifty-five persons, exclusive of engineers, watchmen, firemen, and laborers. The
                    staff consisted of the Secretary, three Assistant Secretaries, the Chief Clerk,
                    six chiefs of bureau, one translator, forty-one clerks, and two messengers.<note n="13">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Pay Roll, 1874-1875,
                        July 31, 1875.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Construction continued on the rest of the State, War and Navy Building while the
                    Department was in the south wing. Ground had been broken for the east wing on
                    July 14, 1872, before the south wing was completed.</p>
                <p>The War and Navy Departments moved into the east wing immediately after it was
                    ready for occupancy on April 16, 1879. The War Department was located in the
                    northern half and the Navy Department in the southern half as a temporary
                    arrangement pending construction of the north wing.</p>
                <p>As soon as the War Department had moved, the old Northwest Executive Building,
                    which had been its home since 1819, was torn down, commencing on May 22, 1879,
                    to make way for the north wing of the new building. The north wing was erected
                    directly on the site of the old building.</p>
                <p>Ground was broken for this wing on June 17, 1879, and the wing was completed and
                    ready for occupancy on December 23, 1882. The War Department moved into it from
                    the east wing in February 1883.</p>
                <p>Demolition of the old Southwest Executive Building, which had been the home of
                    the Department of State from 1816 to 1819 and which had subsequently housed the
                    Navy Department, was commenced on February 18, 1884, to make way for the west
                    and center wings of the new building. The two wings were ready for occupancy on
                    January 31, 1888.</p>
                <p>Construction of the building apparently took longer than expected. Mullet told
                    Secretary Fish in 1873 that the building could be completed in 1881. In fact, it
                    took seven years longer, making a total of seventeen years, from 1871 to 1888,
                    until the entire building was ready for occupancy.<note n="14">The foregoing
                        account of the erection of the State, War, and Navy Building is based on
                        House Executive Document No. 337, 50th Cong., 1st Sess. (serial 2561), pp.
                        2-3; and <hi rend="italic">Executive Office Building, op. cit.,</hi> pp.
                        32-39.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"Upon its completion, January 31, 1888, it was reputed to
                        be the <pb n="45"/>
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                            <graphic url="32-state-war-navy-building.jpg"/>
                            <head>This aerial view, taken about 1930, accents the wealth of detail
                                on the state, War, and Navy roof.</head>
                        </figure> largest and finest office building in the world (covering,
                        together with lawns and terraces, more than five acres of ground space),...
                        composed of granite, hand-hewn. The building has five stories exclusive of
                        basement and sub-basement. It has a total floor area of about 10 acres and
                        contains nearly 1 3/4 miles of corridors 12 feet wide. These are paved with
                        alternating 1-foot squares of black slate and white marble set in
                        transversal rows. The eight stairways with steps of gray granite are
                        especially distinctive; of cantilever construction, they swing in a spiral
                        from floor to floor, unsupported by either beams or arches, the end of each
                        step tightly wedged into the wall. The balustrades of intricately designed
                        bronze are topped by a mahogany hand rail. There is very little woodwork in
                        the entire building, the most noteworthy being the solid red mahogany doors
                        two inches thick. The total cost of the building was slightly more than 10
                        million dollars."<note n="15">E. Wilder Spaulding and George V. Blue, <hi rend="italic">The Department of State of the United States,</hi>
                            rev. edition (Washington, 1936), pp. 49-50.</note>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>The above description is in error concerning the solid mahogany doors. An
                    architectural drawing indicates that some of the doors were made of pine, and in
                    all others only panels were solid mahogany, hung in pine frames with a heavy
                    mahogany veneer.<note n="16">
                        <hi rend="italic">Executive Office Building, op. cit.,</hi> p. 48.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Much of the intricate and elaborate designs in the building were the work of
                    Richard von Ezdorf. He was of the Austrian Ezdorfs, and the designs he made
                    appear to have been influenced by the baroque palaces of Austria and Germany.
                    Ezdorf even provided designs for the door knobs, which corresponded to the
                    various Departments occupying the office.<note n="17">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> pp. 49-53.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The south wing of the building had been planned and built for the exclusive use
                    of the Department of State. The Secretary of State had his office on the second
                    floor at the southwest corner of the south wing, and the diplomatic reception
                    room—the scene of the signing of many historic documents--adjoined the
                    Secretary's office.</p>
                <p>Because of increasing pressure for space, the War and Navy Departments moved into
                    the south wing in 1882, as authorized by an act of Congress.<note n="18">22
                        Stat. 256.</note> Congress assigned the fourth and attic floors of that wing
                    to the War Department and three rooms on the first floor and four in the
                    basement (now known as the "ground floor") to the <pb n="46"/> Navy Department.<note n="19">MS. Department of State, 5 Reports of Bureau Officers, above
                        cited memorandum of James Fenner Lee, annex A.</note> The reassignment took
                    away about 40 percent of the Department of State's space. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="33-state-war-navy-building.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Diplomatic Reception Room in the State, War, and Navy Building
                            adjoined the Secretary's office.</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>As a result, by March 1, 1884, the Department of State was "so cramped for room
                    as to seriously interfere with good executive management."<note n="20">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> annex B.</note> This situation not only went
                    unremedied for the next twenty-two years, but became increasingly acute as the
                    Department grew in number of personnel and in bulk of records during that time.<note n="21">See Senate Document No. 155, 65th Cong., 2d Sess. (serial
                        7315), pp. 80-84.</note> Finally, certain bureaus of the Department of State
                    were forced to move from the State, War, and Navy Building to rented
                    quarters.</p>
                <p>The first unit of the Department to be squeezed out of the main building— despite
                    subsequent statements otherwise—was the Bureau of Trade Relations.<note n="22">The statement, which has appeared in print, that the Passport Bureau was
                        moved out of the main building prior to the removal of the Bureau of Trade
                        Relations, is incorrect. Gaillard Hunt, who, as Chief of the Passport Bureau
                        from 1903 until 1909, was in a position to know, records in his book on the
                        Department of State that the "first bureau to go was the Bureau of Trade
                        Relations" (pp. 419-430); and the Department's accounts records bear out
                        Hunt's statement. For a biographical sketch of Gaillard Hunt, see <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of American Biography,</hi> IX, 385. </note> It
                    was moved in July 1906 to a suite of four rooms on the top floor of the
                    Rochambeau Apartment House,<note n="23">MS. Department of State, Accounts
                        Records, Bill Book, 1907, p. 153. "Homes of the Department of State, X," in
                            <hi rend="italic">The American Foreign Service Journal</hi> (Washington,
                        1924—), VIII, 9, 40, January 1931.</note> at 815 Connecticut Avenue, where
                    it remained for one year.</p>
                <p>The Rochambeau, which was built in 1904, was a seven-story building of gray stone
                    and gray brick located on the east side of Connecticut Avenue between H and I
                    Streets Northwest, just north of the United States Chamber of Commerce Building.
                    The Rochambeau was purchased by the United States Chamber of Commerce in March
                    1954.<note n="24">Washington <hi rend="italic">Evening Star,</hi> March 24,
                        1954.</note> An office building was built on the site in 1965.</p>
                <p>Commencing <date when="1907-07-01">July 1, 1907,</date> the Department rented, at
                    the rate of $2,860 a year, the premises at 522 Seventeenth Street Northwest,<note n="25">MS. Department of State, Accounts Records, Bill Book, 1908, p.
                        357; 1909, p. 294; 1910, p. 398; 1911, p. 266; 1912, p. 352.</note> an old,
                    three-story, red-brick house on the northwest corner of Seventeenth Street and
                    New York Avenue which for many years formed part of the Allies Inn. It has since
                    been torn down to make way for an office building. The Bureau of Trade Relations
                    moved into this building from the Rochambeau in July 1907.<note n="26">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 1908, pp. 148, 154.</note> Either then or a
                    little later, the Bureau of Citizenship (previously the Passport Bureau) moved
                    from the main building into this building,<note n="27">
                        <hi rend="italic"> Ibid.,</hi> 1908, p. 154; 1909, pp. 137, 146, 155; 1910,
                        p. 91.</note> and in 1909 the Office of the Solicitor also moved there from
                    the main building.<note n="28">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 1910, p. 91.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State rented the house at 522 Seventeenth Street until January
                    31, 1912,<note n="29">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 1912, p. 352.</note> when it rented instead
                    the Blair-Lee House, at 1653 Pennsylvania Avenue Northwest, for the annual sum
                    of $5,500.<note n="30">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 1912, p. 352; 1913, pp. 360-361.</note> This
                    spacious brick house, which was built just before the Civil War<note n="31">Katharine E. Crane, <hi rend="italic">Blair House Past and Present; an
                            Account of Its Life and Times in the City of Washington</hi>
                        (Washington, 1945), p. 13.</note> and which consists of three stories plus
                    basement and attic, stands on the north side of Pennsylvania Avenue east of
                    Seventeenth Street, between the Renwick Art Gallery Building and the Blair House
                    and opposite the north front of the Old Executive Office Building (State, War,
                    and Navy Building).</p>
                <p>Other buildings in which the Department occupied space between 1909 and 1918 were
                    the Union Trust Company Building, on the southwest corner of Fifteenth and H
                    Streets Northwest; the old Knickerbocker Hotel Building, at 1703 New York Avenue
                    Northwest; and the Lenman Building, at 1423 New York Avenue Northwest, a
                    five-story commercial structure which has since been razed and replaced by an
                    extension to the National Savings and Trust Company Building, located on the
                    northeast corner of Fifteenth Street and New York Avenue Northwest.<note n="32">"Homes of the Department of State, X," pp. 9, 40.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Navy Department left the State, War, and Navy Building for new quarters in
                    July 1918, and all the bureaus and offices of the Department of State were
                    reunited in that building in the latter part of that year. The State, War, and
                    Navy Building continued to accommodate the entire Department of State from 1918
                    until 1936.</p>
                <p>On July 3, 1930 Congress changed the name of the building to "Department of State
                    Building."<note n="33">46 Stat. 907.</note> This followed the departure of most
                    of the War Department—final removal, excepting only the office of the General of
                    the Armies of the United States, came in 1938—to the Munitions Building on
                    Constitution Avenue.</p>
                <p>Again, however, the building grew overcrowded, and another exodus to outlying
                    buildings became necessary. This exodus began in 1936 with the removal of the
                    Treaty Division, the Visa Division, and the Translating <pb n="47"/> Bureau to
                    the Winder Building. <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="34-state-war-navy-building.jpg"/>
                        <head>State's Library in 1901 held more than 60,000 volumes and the
                            Declaration of Independence. The document had been removed from public
                            display at the time of this photo and a facsimile exhibited in the main
                            floor cabinet.</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>This old office building, of painted brick, located on the northwest corner of
                    Seventeenth and F Streets Northwest and consisting of five stories and basement,
                    was erected in 1847-1848 by William H. Winder, Jr., a private citizen—not, as
                    often stated, by General William H. Winder (1775-1824). The Government rented
                    the building from Winder from the time of its completion until 1854, when
                    Congress, by a provision of an act approved on August 4 of that year, authorized
                    its purchase by the Secretary of War for the sum of $200,000.<note n="34">10
                        Stat. 554. See also Senate Executive Document No. 38, 30th Cong., 2d Sess.
                        (serial 532); House Report No. 102, 32d Cong., 1st Sess. (serial 656); House
                        Report No. 193, 33d Cong., 1st Sess. (serial 743).</note>
                </p>
                <p>The <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/wartime">outbreak of World War
                        II</ref> in 1939 caused a rapid increase in the personnel of the Department
                    of State, and as a consequence the problem of space became further intensified.
                    In 1940, with a total of about 1,020 employees, the Department occupied rooms in
                    the Winder Building and also in the Hill Building,<note n="35">Department of
                        State Telephone Directory October 1940, pp. 6-5.</note> on the southeast
                    corner of Seventeenth and I Streets, Northwest. In 1941, with personnel totaling
                    about 1,600, offices of the Department overflowed into the Metropolitan Club
                    Annex Building, at 1712 H Street Northwest; the American Institute of Architects
                    Building, perhaps better known as the "Octagon House," on the northeast corner
                    of Eighteenth Street and New York Avenue Northwest; the Commerce Department
                    Building, on Fourteenth Street between E Street and Constitution Avenue
                    Northwest; and the apartment building at 515 Twenty-second Street Northwest (now
                    State Annex 2).<note n="36">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> October 1941, p. vii.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Growth of the Department continued through the war years, and personnel totaled
                    about 3,600 by early 1945. The transfer of certain agencies to the Department of
                    State at the end of the war further increased the personnel in the latter part
                    of 1945 to about 7,200. These 7,200 employees were housed in forty-seven
                    buildings scattered throughout Washington. This condition continued until about
                    May 1946, when, through consolidation of organizational units and reduction in
                    force, the number of buildings was cut to twenty-nine.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, plans were being developed for removal of the Department to new
                    quarters,<note n="37">
                        <hi rend="italic">The Department of State Bulletin,</hi> X VII, 1035-1036,
                        November 30, 1947.</note> and in 1947 the Department of State left the
                    building at Seventeenth Street and Pennsylvania Avenue Northwest. From this
                    building in the historic second-floor office directly above the south entrance,
                    twenty-four Secretaries of State, from <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton Fish</ref> to
                    General <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-george-catlett">George
                        C. Marshall</ref>, had directed the foreign relations of the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>The building has been criticized as "A horrible example of... 'American ironic,'"<note n="38">Statement by Thomas Hastings quoted in <hi rend="italic">Executive Office Building, op. cit.,</hi> p. 88.</note> praised when
                    there have been attempts to tear it down:</p>
                <p>
                    <q rend="blockquote">"The proposal to replace the Executive Office Building with
                        another functional building is a bit like suggesting that the Egyptians tear
                        down their unsightly pyramids and replace them with modern efficient
                        tombstones."<note n="39">Statement by unidentified source quoted in <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> p. 89.</note> But, as another source
                        describes it: "The building became a period piece and a symbol. But, even
                        more, its very flamboyance—with porticoes and pillars, with mansards and
                        peaks, with ironwork sculpture, with tier on tier of architectural
                        orders—has been recognized as a vital part of the Washington memory."<note n="40">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </q>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="48"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section28">
                <head>
                    <placeName>New State Building</placeName>
                    <lb/>
                    <date when="1947-04">April 1947</date> - present</head>
                <p>Following World War II the Department of State experienced significant growth
                    both in functions and in personnel. Before the war there were less than 1,000
                    employees. After the war the number increased to over 7,000.<note n="1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Report oil the Organization of the Department of
                            State,</hi> submitted by O.L. Nelson to Assistant Secretary for
                        Administration, Donald Russell (Washington, July 22, 1946) pp. 7. II.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="35-new-state-building.jpg"/>
                        <head>New State Building in a photograph taken in 1947.</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>This rapid growth created serious pressures for more space. Offices of the
                    Department were scattered in several buildings around Washington. At one point
                    in the mid-1940's parts of the Department were in 47 buildings.</p>
                <p>Early in 1946 President Truman proposed a plan to consolidate the entire
                    Department of State into one building.<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Department of State Bulletin,</hi> November 30, 1947, pp.
                        1035-1039.</note> At first about 60 percent of the Department was to move
                    into the New War Building at Twenty-first Street and Virginia Avenue Northwest
                    and other buildings in its neighborhood. Eventually, the entire Department would
                    be housed in the New War Department building when proposed plans for the
                    enlargement of the building were put into effect.<note n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Known as the "New War Building," the new home of the Department of State had been
                    designed just prior to World War II as the first unit of a structure intended to
                    house all the Washington offices of the War Department. Although the Secretary
                    of War never had his office there, portions of the War Department occupied the
                    building immediately after it was constructed in 1941 until they gradually
                    vacated it in 1947 to move into the "Pentagon" building, which was erected in
                    1941-1943, became the central location of the War Department, and subsequently
                    housed the Department of Defense.</p>
                <p>The New War Building was erected under provisions of an act of Congress approved
                    June 25, 1938, which made available $3,000,000 for <quote>"the acquisition of
                        land as a site for buildings for the War Department, and for the
                        construction of the first building unit,... within a total limit of cost of
                        $10,815,000."</quote>
                    <note n="4">52 Stat. 1152.</note> Subsequent acts provided additional funds.<note n="5">53 Stat. 673, May 6, 1939, $5,000,000; 54 Stat. 127, April 18,
                        1940, $2,000,000.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The site at the southwest corner of Twenty-first Street and Virginia Avenue was
                    acquired, and in 1939 architects Gilbert S. Underwood and William Dewey Foster
                    prepared plans for the proposed structure. The contract for general construction
                    was awarded to the firm of John McShain, Inc., of Philadelphia, in February
                    1940, and construction commenced immediately following the demolition of the
                    nine-story Boulevard Apartments located on the site. The building was completed
                    about June 30, 1941.<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of the Secretary of War to the President,</hi>
                        1939, (Washington, 1939), pp. 32-33; ibid. , 1941, p. 11; <hi rend="italic">The New York Times,</hi> February 10, March 21, December 10, 1940,
                        April 10, May 30, 1941; <hi rend="italic">Congress Directory,</hi> 78th
                        Cong., 1st Sess., January 1943 (Washington, 1942), p. 330.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The building is a plain, sandcolored, modern structure consisting of seven
                    stories and a basement and containing 274,000 square feet of usable space.
                    Inscribed in modest capitals on the front, to the right of the main entrance, is
                    the designation "Department of State" and the address "320 Twenty-first Street,
                    N.W."</p>
                <p>Just inside the Twenty-first Street lobby is a 12- by 50-foot mural entitled,
                    "Defense of America's Free-<pb n="49"/>doms." It was painted in 1941 by Kindred
                    McLeary to depict what the United States stood for in a period of crisis when
                    the free world was threatened by totalitarianism.<note n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">The New York Times,</hi> February 24, April 10,
                        1941.</note> The mural was covered by draperies and by a large, full-color
                    reproduction of the seal of the Department of State, on August 13, 1954. The
                    Department decided that the mural, which includes a war scene, was not
                    appropriate for a building occupied by a Department responsible for conducting
                    the foreign relations of the United States.<note n="8">Letter from Thruston B.
                        Morton, Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional Relations, to Senator
                        Carl Hayden, April 7, 1955 (111/3-2155).</note> It was uncovered in early
                    1976.</p>
                <p>The first unit of the Department of State moved into the New War Building—renamed
                    "New State Building"—on January 22, 1947, the day after <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-george-catlett">General George C.
                        Marshall</ref> entered upon his duties as Secretary of State. During the
                    following three months the War Department gradually vacated the building, and,
                    as necessary alterations were completed, additional units of the Department of
                    State were moved in. The moving operation continued from January until the early
                    part of August.<note n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">Department of State Bulletin,</hi> November 30, 1947, pp.
                        1036-1037.</note>
                </p>
                <p>While Secretary Marshall was in Moscow, on April 19, 1947, his offices and those
                    of his principal assistants were moved from the Old State Building to the New
                    State Building. In the new building the Secretary's office was a large two-story
                    room, with private elevator, on the fifth floor overlooking the main entrance on
                    Twenty-first Street.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="50"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section29">
                <head>Extended, remodeled New State Building</head>
                <p>By the mid-1950s there were a little over 7,000 employees in the Department of
                    State, including the International Cooperation Administration. These employees
                    were housed in 29 buildings around Washington.<note n="1">Department of State
                        press release No. 484, September 13, 1956.</note>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="36-extended-remodeled-new-state-bldg.jpg"/>
                        <head>Extended, remodeled, New State Building</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The plan to house the entire Department of State in one building was advanced by
                    an act approved August 4, 1955, in which Congress appropriated $1,000,000 for
                    the expenses of "planning the extension and remodeling, under the supervision of
                    the General Services Administration, of the State Department Building."<note n="2">69 Stat. 463.</note> The project called for considerable remodeling
                    and for an extension which would add approximately 1,040,000 square feet of
                    usable space to the 274,000 square feet in the existing building.</p>
                <p>On January 10, 1956, the General Services Administration awarded contracts to
                    draw plans for the proposed building to the architectural firms of Graham,
                    Anderson, Probst &amp; White, Inc:, of Chicago, and Harley, Ellington
                    &amp; Day, Inc., of Detroit. The Washington firm of A.R. Clas was the local
                    liaison. Contractor for the construction was John McShain, Inc., of
                    Philadelphia.</p>
                <p>The project was inaugurated on September 13, 1956, in a brief ceremony at
                    Temporary H Building, located at Twenty-third and C Streets. Certain officers of
                    the Department of State and the General Services Administration participated in
                    the ceremony, including Deputy Under Secretary of State Loy W. Henderson, who,
                    after making a brief statement,<note n="3">For the text of the statement, see
                        Department of State press release No. 484, September 13, 1956.</note>
                    applied a wrecking bar to bring down the building sign. This marked the
                    beginning of what would eventually be the dismantling of Temporary H and the
                    other two World War II temporary buildings on Twenty-third Street in order to
                    clear the site for the new foundations.</p>
                <p>On January 5, 1957, President Eisenhower joined with <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster">Secretary of State
                        Dulles</ref> in laying the cornerstone. The President used the same trowel
                    that was used by George Washington to lay the cornerstone of the U.S. Capitol on
                    September 18, 1793. A sealed metal box containing a selection of historic
                    documents was deposited in the cornerstone.<note n="4">See Department of State
                        press release No. 635, December 28, 1956, and the program entitled
                        "Cornerstone Laying of Department of State Building by the President of the
                        United States," Washington, D.C., January 5, 1957.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Under the supervision of the Public Buildings Service of the General Services
                    Administration, the addition was completed in 1961 at a cost of $52,720,000.<note n="5">The original estimate for the addition was $57,400,000. For the
                        appropriations in addition to the initial $1,000,000 referred to above, see
                        70 Stat. 55 ($2,500,000), 73 State. 444 ($3,000,000), and 74 State. 555
                        ($500,000).</note> Secretary of State <pb n="51"/>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/herter-christian-archibald">Christian A.
                        Herter</ref> presided over the dedication ceremonies on January 5, 1961.<note n="6">For the text of the Statement, see Department of State press
                        release No. 3, January 4, 1961.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The extension is approximately four times as large as the initial section.<note n="7">Much of the information describing the new extension was taken from
                            <hi rend="italic">The Department of State Building,</hi> Department of
                        State publication 7400, September 1962.</note> The extended building covers
                    an area of four square blocks bounded by Virginia Avenue, C Street, Twenty-first
                    Street, and Twenty-third Street in northwest Washington. There are seven floors
                    of office space plus an eighth floor for special purposes and mechanical
                    equipment.</p>
                <p>Materials used in the building came from various locations in the United States.
                    The facade is limestone from Bedford, Ind. Granite, used around the entrances
                    and at the lower levels, was quarried in Cold Spring, Minn. Vestibule walls at
                    the north and south entrances are veined ebony granite from St. Cloud, Minn.
                    Flagstones at the north, south, and west entrances and in the north and south
                    courts are also granite gray and black from Minnesota, and pink from Texas. One
                    of the few imports came from Italy. It is the glass mosaic tile, known as
                    Byzantine, which forms the ceilings of the entrance canopies.</p>
                <p>The main approach to the building is north from Constitution Avenue along
                    Twenty-second Street to the primary entrance on C Street. This diplomatic
                    entrance (or south lobby), three stories high and 75x175 feet, is the main
                    entrance for visiting dignitaries. The front and rear walls are of glass in
                    aluminum frames, while the end walls are of Tennessee marble known as St.
                    Genevieve breche rose. Thirty-foot-high marble and granite columns support the
                    luminous plastic grid ceiling. Radiant heat is furnished from pipes embedded in
                    concrete under the terrazzo floor. The flags of the nations with which the
                    United States maintains diplomatic relations form a colorful display along the
                    north wall of the lobby. At each end of the lobby is a memorial plaque honoring
                    Americans who lost their lives under heroic or tragic circumstances in the
                    foreign service. Elevators at either end provide access to the offices of the
                    Secretary, the Deputy Secretary, and the Under Secretaries on the seventh floor,
                    and to the diplomatic functions area on the eighth floor. The Protocol Office is
                    conveniently located to the east of the lobby.</p>
                <p>Space allocation in the new building is based on a "vertical" plan as opposed to
                    the old "horizontal" plan. That is, organizational units are located in a
                    pyramid style on two or more floors, rather than being spread out over great
                    distances on one floor. If the horizontal plan were followed, a section of a
                    large bureau might be located as far as two blocks away from its central office.
                    With the vertical plan, personnel are near elevators and stairways that enable
                    them to reach their central office quickly.</p>
                <p>The Secretary and his immediate staff are located on the seventh floor, on the
                    south side of the building, overlooking the Lincoln Memorial and the Potomac
                    River. Visitors must pass through one of two outer reception rooms to an inner
                    lobby where the Secretary's receptionist is seated. Her desk faces a wide
                    corridor flanked by diplomatic waiting rooms. The corridor leads to a gallery,
                    on the walls of which are hung the portraits of all former Secretaries of State.
                    The gallery permits the Secretary, the Deputy Secretary, and the Under
                    Secretaries to reach each other's offices without being visible to visitors in
                    the waiting rooms.</p>
                <p>Nearly all Assistant Secretaries and those of equivalent rank, together with
                    their immediate staffs, have appropriate space on the sixth floor. The pyramid
                    broadens toward the base on the lower floors where public, international, and
                    administrative services and functions are generally located.</p>
                <p>Special features and facilities in the new building include an international
                    conference area consisting of a large conference room fully equipped for
                    simultaneous interpretation, smaller conference rooms, offices for delegates,
                    and a delegates' lounge adjoining the International Conference Room. Near the
                    Conference Room is an auditorium capable of seating 800 people, with its
                    entrance on Twenty-third Street. President Kennedy used this auditorium for
                    press conferences. The Department's library is located in the south and central
                    part of the building, on the third floor. The book area comprises four stack
                    levels served by an elevator and book lift.</p>
                <p>An area is provided on the eighth floor for official functions such as diplomatic
                    dinners and receptions, where the Secretary of State and other ranking officers
                    of the Government may fulfill their responsibilities for official entertainment.
                    The three principal diplomatic reception rooms are the John Quincy Adams drawing
                    room, the Thomas Jefferson reception room, and the Benjamin Franklin state
                    dining room. These rooms are largely furnished by a growing collection of
                    antiques and art treasures provided by the American people on loan or as gifts.
                    There is also a series of ongoing architectural improvements of the rooms to
                    make them more in keeping with the period furnishings.<note n="8">For a
                        description, with illustrations, of the Diplomatic Reception Rooms, see <hi rend="italic">Guidebook to Diplomatic Reception Rooms,</hi> Department
                        of State, July 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A pneumatic tube system transmits mail and documents within the building, and
                    modern communications equipment provides rapid contact with posts abroad. There
                    are also electric data-processing systems and up-to-date facilities for storage
                    of records and other information.</p>
                <p>On the first floor, between the north and south courts, is an exhibition hall.
                    Presently it contains a Bicentennial display entitled "200 years of American
                    Foreign Relations-1776-1976."</p>
                <pb n="52"/>
                <p>
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="37-extended-remodeled-new-state-bldg.jpg"/>
                        <head>The Thomas Jefferson Reception Room as seen through a Palladian
                            arch.</head>
                    </figure> Other exhibits generally in this same hall include a model of the
                    building, an electronic map showing the location of the U.S. Foreign Service
                    posts in the countries of the world, a display on "The Secretaries of State and
                    Historic Achievements of American Diplomacy" (with replicas of particularly
                    significant international treaties), and the <ref target="/about/faq/great-seal">Great Seal of the United States</ref> and its press (which is in the
                    custody of the Department of State and is still in use).</p>
                <p>Even with the completion of the extension in 1961, the building has not been
                    large enough to house all of the Department of State.<note n="9">Also housed in
                        the building besides the Department of State are two agencies—the Arms
                        Control and Disarmament Agency, and the Agency for International
                        Development. The directors of both agencies report directly to the Secretary
                        of State.</note> It was necessary, therefore, for the Department to continue
                    to occupy annex buildings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section30">
                <head>Appendix<lb/> Annex Buildings Occupied by the Department of State</head>
                <p>In the course of its history the Department of State has had to acquire space in
                    many buildings other than its main home. The number of these buildings has
                    totaled approximately 130 over the years.</p>
                <p>The first annex was a small building called Lear's Store, which the Department
                    rented briefly when it moved to Washington, D.C., in 1800. The next time the
                    Department needed extra room was from 1810 to 1836, when it used space in the
                    Blodget Hotel Building for the Patent Office, then a part of the Department of
                    State. Thirty-four years later, cramped for space in the Orphan Asylum Building,
                    the Department rented a building from 1870 to 1875 on the southwest corner of
                    14th and S Streets.</p>
                <p>With the move into the south wing of the State, War, and Navy Building in 1875,
                    the Department comfortably accommodated its 55-person staff in one building.
                    Later, however, as the War and Navy Departments expanded into the south wing,
                    and as the Department of State grew in the number of personnel and in the bulk
                    of records, certain offices had to move into rented quarters. The departure of
                    the Navy Department from the State, War, and Navy Building in 1918 enabled the
                    Department of State again to house nearly all of its operations in that
                    building-until 1936, when the Department again had to acquire space in more
                    buildings.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="state-annex-buildings.png"/>
                    <head>State Department Annex Buildings</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The extraordinary growth of the Department during and following World War II
                    expanded the number of annexes to over 40 scattered buildings. The number of
                    annexes was reduced considerably when the Department moved into the New State
                    Building in 1947. By the mid- 1950s, however, nearly 30 buildings were needed to
                    house the Department. In 1961 the Department completed an extensive addition to
                    its main building but failed to accomplish its objective of consolidating the
                    entire staff in one building; five annexes were still required. By 1976 the
                    Department, including the Agency for International Development and the Arms
                    Control and Disarmament Agency, occupied some 14 annex buildings.<note n="1">SA-2 at 515 22nd St., N.W.; SA-3 (FSI) at 1400 Key Blvd., Rosslyn, Va.; S
                        А-4 at 8400 Terminal Road, Newington, Va.; SA-5 at 1901 Pa. Ave., N.W.; SA-6
                        at 1700 North Lynn St., Rosslyn, Va.; SA-10 at 1717 Н St., N.W.; SA-11 at
                        1401 Wilson Blvd., Rosslyn, Va.; S А-12 (Universal Bldg.) at 1975 Florida
                        Ave., N.W.; SA-13 at 880 South Pickett St., Alexandria, Va.; SA-14 at 1735
                        North Lynn St., Rosslyn, Va.; SA-15 at 1800 North Kent St., Rosslyn, Va.;
                        SA-1 6 at 1621 North Kent St. , Rosslyn, Va; SA-17 at 1425 K St., N.W.; and
                        SA-18 at 1601 Kent St. , Rosslyn, Va. (Department of State Telephone
                        Directory, Winter 1976.)</note> Although not considered an annex building,
                    the President's Guest House (Blair House) at 1651 Pennsylvania Avenue, N.W. has
                    been administered by the Department for many years.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section31">
                <head>Photo Credits</head>
                <p>3-Tоp photo: <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Service Journal</hi> VII
                    (January, 1930). Bottom photo: Library of Congress.</p>
                <p>5-Top left photo: Library of Congress. Top right photo: Historical Society of
                    York County, York Pennsylvania. Bottom photo: Lancaster County Historical
                    Society.</p>
                <p>6-Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia.</p>
                <p>8-Princeton University.</p>
                <p>11-<hi rend="italic">The Columbian Magazine.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>12-The First Mechanics National Bank of Trenton.</p>
                <p>15-Sons of the Revolution in the State of New York, New York City.</p>
                <p>16-Library of Congress.</p>
                <p>17-Library of Congress.</p>
                <p>18-Top photo: Library of Congress. Bottom Photo: Continental Oil Co.</p>
                <p>19-Historical Society of Pennsylvania (also Department of State).</p>
                <p>20-Department of State.</p>
                <p>22-Free Public Library, Trenton.</p>
                <p>23-Department of State.</p>
                <p>26-Treasury Department.</p>
                <p>27-Commission of Fine Arts.</p>
                <p>28-Department of State.</p>
                <p>30-Library of Congress.</p>
                <p>31-Library of Congress.</p>
                <p>33-L. C. Handy Studios, Washington, D.C.</p>
                <p>36-National Archives.</p>
                <p>38-John H. Hunton, <hi rend="italic">The History and Topography of the United
                        States,</hi> (London and Philadelphia, 1830), I, between pp. 458, 459.</p>
                <p>41-National Archives.</p>
                <p>44-Department of State.</p>
                <p>45-General Services Administration.</p>
                <p>46-General Services Administration.</p>
                <p>47-General Services Administration.</p>
                <p>48-Department of State.</p>
                <p>50-Department of State.</p>
                <p>52-Department of State.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="section32">
                <head>Publication Information</head>
                <p>DEPARTMENT OF STATE PUBLICATION 89<lb/> Department and Foreign Service
                    Series:158<lb/> Released May 1977<lb/> Office of the Historian<lb/> Office of
                    Мedia Sегvices<lb/> Bureau of Public Affairs</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>