<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Introduction to Curriculum Packet on “Documents on Diplomacy:
                    Primary Source Documents and Lessons from the World of Foreign Affairs,
                    1775-2011”</title>
                <title type="short">Documents on Diplomacy: Primary Source Documents and Lessons
                    from the World of Foreign Affairs, 1775-2011</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>Documents on Diplomacy: Primary Source Documents and Lessons from the
                            World of Foreign Affairs, 1775-2011</title>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> series,
                    published by the United Stated Department of State's Office of the Historian, is
                    one of the world's most comprehensive series of primary source documents.
                    Inaugurated in 1861 during the administration of Abraham Lincoln, the series
                    celebrated its 150<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary in 2011. It seemed
                    a fitting tribute to bring this series, long valued by professional researchers,
                    foreign policy experts, and college students, to a new audience—secondary school
                    teachers and their students.</p>
                <p>Designed for secondary school teachers, who may not have the time to comb through
                    tens of thousands of documents searching for the perfect classroom resources,
                    this CD-ROM publication includes more than 300 primary source documents, paired
                    with over 120 classroom-ready lessons, covering key events from 1775 to 2011—as
                    well as lessons that incorporate art, music, dance, and drama. It contains
                    everything you need to educate—and engage—students in the world of foreign
                    affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Documents on Diplomacy</hi> includes the following sections,
                    with full teacher resources (briefing memos for teachers and students, lists of
                    key terms and players, timelines, and teaching tips) for each section:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>I. The Revolutionary Age</item>
                    <item>II. The Articles of Confederation</item>
                    <item>III. The Early Republic</item>
                    <item>IV. The Age of Expansion</item>
                    <item>V. The Civil War &amp; the Gilded Age</item>
                    <item>VI. A Great Power Emerges</item>
                    <item>VII. World War I</item>
                    <item>VIII. Isolationism &amp; the Interwar Period</item>
                    <item>IX. World War II</item>
                    <item>X. The Early Cold War</item>
                    <item>XI. The Later Cold War</item>
                    <item>XII. The Post-Cold War World &amp; the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                        Century</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
