<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Introduction to Curriculum Packet on “A History of
                    Diplomacy”</title>
                <title type="short">A History of Diplomacy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State Test 1</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>A History of Diplomacy</title>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">A History of Diplomacy</hi> is an instructional package
                    providing an overview of American diplomacy as it evolved from the colonial
                    period through the present day. The video is presented in two parts: the first
                    half ends with World War II, while the second half spans the period 1945 through
                    the present day.</p>
                <p>This package also includes the video script, a timeline, glossary, suggested
                    lessons and extension activities, website links, and other support material.
                    Lessons focus on history, civics, geography, economics, and culture, and support
                    the thematic curriculum strands of Expectations of Excellence: Curriculum
                    Standards for Social Studies of the National Council for the Social Studies.
                    Lessons and support materials were also designed to promote the literacy
                    emphasis of “No Child Left Behind” by including oral, written, and visual
                    communication activities.</p>
                <p>These instructional materials were designed to provide a high degree of
                    flexibility for classroom teachers. The video can be viewed in its entirety or
                    in segments, and can be used to stimulate classroom discussion, as an
                    introduction to a series of lessons on the topic, or as an overview of the topic
                    of diplomacy. The video and print materials may constitute a complete
                    instructional unit, or individual elements may be incorporated into existing
                    units. The lessons and materials support American history, government, or modern
                    world history courses.</p>
                <p>Teachers are encouraged to enhance the content of this package with other
                    instructional materials and information sources such as textbooks, newspapers,
                    television, and the Internet. Suggestions for using additional resources are
                    included with a number of the lessons. Teachers are encouraged to modify
                    suggested lessons and other materials in ways that are appropriate for their
                    students, courses, and other local circumstances.</p>
                <p>Print materials in the package are provided in black-on-white format. They may be
                    easily reproduced by electronic copying, or scanned into computer files to
                    enable teachers to customize materials for their own classrooms. Some websites
                    in the list of resources may have copyright restrictions, and teachers are
                    advised to review and abide by those restrictions. All materials in this print
                    package produced by the Department of State may be reproduced and disseminated
                    without specific permission.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
