<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Introduction to Curriculum Packet on “A Journey Shared: The
                    United States and China”</title>
                <title type="short">A Journey Shared</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>A Journey Shared</title>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In February 1784, one of the world’s newest countries sent a trading ship to one
                    of the Earth’s oldest civilizations. Thus began the story of the relationship
                    between the peoples of the United States and China. Over the course of the next
                    225 years, the United States became a superpower, while imperial China was
                    transformed into a modern nation, ready to assume its place on the 21<hi
                        rend="superscript">st</hi> century stage.</p>
                <p>While there were ups and downs in the bilateral relationship, for most of that
                    time, each government concentrated its diplomatic efforts on more urgent threats
                    to its national interests. Throughout the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and
                        20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries, the Chinese often focused on
                    Europe, Japan, Russia, and later the Soviet Union, while the United States
                    turned toward Latin America, Europe, and the Middle East.</p>
                <p>Yet despite difficulties, the interest of both Americans and Chinese in building
                    ties across the Pacific persisted. And that interest was fueled by the ways in
                    which countless individuals, both Chinese and American, perceived each other.
                    American businessmen first sought profit from tea and fine porcelain, and later
                    dreamed of millions of new “China Trade” customers. Qing officials hoped that
                    the United States could provide some protection against European imperialists,
                    and later, Nationalist Chinese leaders looked to the United States for aid
                    against their Japanese enemies. American missionaries saw China as an
                    opportunity to spread Christianity, while Chinese laborers and students
                    journeyed to America in search of wealth or education, to help their families
                    back home.</p>
                <p>No matter how often these hopes and aspirations went frustrated or unfulfilled,
                    the dream of such possibilities remained and brought Chinese and Americans
                    together in the pursuit of separate and shared goals. Most importantly, both
                    peoples considered their relationship—despite evidence to the contrary—as one of
                    friendship.</p>
                <p>What may have begun as myth became, over time, part of the reality of U.S.-China
                    relations. Realists and ideologues may have dominated diplomacy, and
                    profit-driven businessmen may have dominated trade, but genuine friendship
                    sparked educational and developmental programs. Today, this interrelationship of
                    official and unofficial contacts has produced the most important bilateral
                    relationship of the new century.</p>
                <p>At the dawning of the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> century, the United States
                    and China are deeply intertwined, with countless arenas of possible cooperation
                    or conflict. The implications are global, and it is more important than ever to
                    make that historical belief in friendship a reality.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
