<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Introduction to Curriculum Packet on “Today in Washington:
                    The Media and Diplomacy”</title>
                <title type="short">Today in Washington: The Media and Diplomacy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State Test 2</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>A History of Diplomacy</title>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Today in Washington: The Media and Diplomacy</hi> is an
                    instructional package that explores the interaction between diplomats and
                    reporters throughout our history, and examines the ways that both have used the
                    media to deliver messages about international affairs.</p>
                <p>DVD segments include “Portraits and Pamphlets: Franklin in Paris;” “Cartoons and
                    Caricature: Diplomacy, Politics, and News;” “‘Remember the Maine!’ Moving
                    Pictures and the Yellow Press;” “The Truth will Set Them Free: Cold War
                    Diplomacy, and Propaganda;” “Diplomacy Live! Oil, Hostages, and Iran;” and
                    “Dateline Yesterday: News and Diplomacy 24/7.”</p>
                <p>This package also includes the DVD script, a chronology, glossary, lessons and
                    extension activities, website links, and other support materials. Lessons focus
                    on history, civics, geography, economics, and culture, and support the thematic
                    curriculum strands of Expectations of Excellence: Curriculum Standards for
                    Social Studies of the National Council for the Social Studies. Lessons and
                    support materials were also designed to promote the literacy emphasis of No
                    Child Left Behind by including oral, written, and visual communication
                    activities.</p>
                <p>These instructional materials were designed to provide a high degree of
                    flexibility for teachers. The DVD can be viewed in its entirety or in segments.
                    It can be used to stimulate classroom discussion, to introduce a series of
                    lessons on the topic, or to supplement existing classroom lessons. The DVD and
                    print materials may constitute a complete instructional unit, or individual
                    elements may be incorporated into existing units. These instructional materials
                    support U.S. history, civics and government, economics, international relations,
                    and modern world history courses. </p>
                <p>Teachers are encouraged to enhance the content of this package with other
                    instructional materials and information sources, such as textbooks, newspapers,
                    television, and the Internet. Suggestions for using additional resources are
                    included with a number of the lessons. Teachers are encouraged to modify
                    suggested lessons and other materials in ways that are appropriate for their
                    students, courses, and other local circumstances.</p>
                <p>Print materials in this package are provided in black-on-white format. They can
                    be reproduced easily to enable teachers to customize materials for their own
                    classrooms. Some websites in the list of web resources may have copyright
                    restrictions, and teachers are advised to review and abide by those
                    restrictions. All materials in this package produced by the Department of State
                    may be reproduced and disseminated without specific permission. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
