<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Introduction to Curriculum Packet on “Terrorism: A War
                    Without Borders”</title>
                <title type="short">Terrorism: A War Without Borders</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State  Test 1</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>Terrorism: A War Without Borders</title>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Terrorism: A War Without Borders</hi> was produced by the
                    United States Department of State in collaboration with a special committee of
                    social studies educators. The video, print materials, and other resources in
                    this package are intended for use with middle school and high school
                    courses.</p>
                <p>The purpose of this instructional package is to help students to understand the
                    connection between world events and their own lives and those of others in their
                    community. It builds upon the resources of the U.S. Department of State, and can
                    be augmented by a vast range of other instructional materials and information
                    sources available through newspapers, television, and the Internet, and teachers
                    are encouraged to pursue these additional sources.</p>
                <p>The video and instructional materials in this package were designed to provide
                    classroom teachers with a high degree of flexibility in using some or all of the
                    elements. The package can be used as a unit of instruction or individual
                    elements may be incorporated into existing units or lessons. The video lends
                    itself to use as a stimulus for classroom discussion, as well as an introduction
                    to a series of lessons on the topic.</p>
                <p>In producing instructional materials of this nature, the developers recognize
                    that the audience represents a vast range of interests and abilities, not to
                    mention local and state curriculum standards and requirements. The suggested
                    lessons reflect Expectations of Excellence: Curriculum Standards for Social
                    Studies developed by the National Council for the Social Studies. Teachers are
                    encouraged to modify the suggested lessons and other materials in ways that are
                    appropriate for their students, courses, and other local circumstances.</p>
                <p>All of the materials produced by the Department of State included in this package
                    may be reproduced and disseminated without specific permission. However, some of
                    the websites in the list of resources may have copyright restrictions, and
                    teachers are advised to review and abide by those restrictions.</p>
                <p>Print materials are provided in black on white format so that they may be easily
                    reproduced by means of electronic copying. They may also be scanned into
                    computer files so that teachers may customize materials for their own
                    classrooms.</p>
                <p>This is the first program in a continuing series that will be produced by the
                    Department of State. We hope that you find it useful for your classroom and will
                    look forward to other programs. A response form is included with this package
                    and your comments and suggestions will be helpful in the development of future
                    instructional packages.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
