<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Dean Gooderham
                    Acheson</title>
                <title type="short">Dean Gooderham Acheson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Dean Gooderham Acheson</persName> served as Secretary of State from
                    January 21, 1949, through January 20, 1953, and exerted significant influence on
                    U.S. foreign policy during his tenure. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="acheson-dean-gooderham.jpg"/>
                    <head>Dean Gooderham Acheson, 51st Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Born on April 11, 1893, Acheson grew up in Middletown, Connecticut, and attended
                    the Groton School, followed by Yale University and then Harvard Law School,
                    where he was elected to the Harvard Law Review.</p>
                <p>In his early career, Acheson clerked for Supreme Court Justice <persName>Louis
                        Brandeis</persName> and then joined the law firm Covington and Burling prior
                    to entering the <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> administration as
                    Under Secretary of the Treasury. </p>
                <p>In 1941, Acheson began his career at the Department of State as Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Economic Affairs, a position that gave him a front-row
                    seat to the increasing tensions between the United States and Japan that led to
                    war. In this capacity, Acheson oversaw the U.S. oil embargo of Japan. </p>
                <p>After World War II, Acheson remained in the Truman administration as Under
                    Secretary of State for Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/byrnes-james-francis">James F.
                        Byrnes</ref>. In the 1940s, Acheson also represented the United States in
                    negotiations that led to the creation of the United Nations Relief and
                    Rehabilitation Administration, the Food and Agriculture Organization, and the
                    International Monetary Fund. Acheson was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName> on January 21, 1949. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p> As Secretary of State, Acheson played an important role in shaping U.S. policy
                    during the early Cold War. Acheson enjoyed a good working relationship with
                    President Harry S. Truman, who often allowed Acheson to be the first official to
                    speak on record about U.S. foreign policy decisions. </p>
                <p> Although Acheson supported the containment of communism and the tenets of the
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/truman"> Truman
                    Doctrine</ref>, he was also a realist who recognized that the Soviet Union was
                    not only an ideological opponent, but also a viable global power that had to be
                    viewed as a serious geopolitical challenge to U.S. interests. This belief shaped
                    Acheson’s approach to the many foreign policy challenges that faced the United
                    States during his tenure.</p>
                <p>Chief among these was the question of what to do with Germany and how to prevent
                    future Soviet influence there. To this end, Acheson supported the formation of
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic Treaty Organization
                        (NATO)</ref> in 1949, a defensive alliance geared to counter the Soviet
                    threat to Europe while ensuring that the western part of Germany was tied firmly
                    to the West.</p>
                <p>Although Europe was Acheson’s primary focus, he also faced questions related to
                    international control of atomic weapons; the fall of mainland China to the
                    Communist forces of Mao Zedong and the retreat of the U.S.-backed Nationalists
                    to Taiwan; the rebuilding of Japan as a cornerstone of U.S. policy in East Asia;
                    the Korean War; and Soviet designs on Yugoslavia, the Middle East, and Asia.</p>
                <p>Senator Joseph McCarthy ultimately singled Acheson out for “losing” China to the
                    communists.</p>
                <p>Acheson continued to have influence on U.S. foreign policy after leaving the
                    Department of State. During the Kennedy administration, Acheson sat on the
                    Executive Committee created to address the <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/short-history/cubanmissile">Cuban Missile
                        Crisis</ref>.</p>
                <p>Later in the decade, Acheson served as an advisor to the <persName>Lyndon B.
                        Johnson</persName> administration for how to disengage from the war in
                    Vietnam. Acheson died at the age of 78 in 1971. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Beisner, Robert L. <hi rend="italic">Dean Acheson: A Life in the Cold
                            War.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen: Secretaries of
                            State from John Jay to Colin Powell</hi>. Westport, CT: Greenwood Press,
                        2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Smith, Gaddis. "Dean Acheson."<hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries
                            of State and Their Diplomacy</hi>, edited by Samuel Flagg Bemis. Vol.
                        16. New York: Cooper Square, 1972.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
