<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Quincy
                    Adams</title>
                <title type="short">John Quincy Adams</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>John Quincy Adams was appointed Secretary of State by President <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James Monroe</ref> on <date when="1817-03-05">March 5, 1817.</date> He served from September 22, 1817,
                    until <date when="1825-03-03">March 3, 1825.</date> Adams enjoyed unique
                    training in diplomacy and became one of the most influential diplomats in U.S.
                    history. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="adams-john-quincy.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Quincy Adams, Eighth Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>The son of President <persName>John Adams</persName>, John Quincy Adams, was born
                    in Braintree (now Quincy) Massachusetts. In 1778 he traveled to France with his
                    father, who was then U.S. commissioner to France. On this and subsequent visits
                    to Europe, the young Adams studied at academies and universities.</p>
                <p>At fourteen Adams became private secretary to Francis Dana, the U.S. Minister to
                        <placeName>Russia</placeName>; Adams also served as secretary to his father
                    during the negotiations of the <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">Treaty
                        of Paris</ref> that ended in 1783. In 1787 the twenty year-old Adams
                    graduated from Harvard University. After studying law, he gained admission to
                    the bar in 1790 and began practicing in Boston.</p>
                <p>Almost five decades of public service began in 1802 when Adams gained election to
                    the Massachusetts Senate. In addition to numerous diplomatic appointments, Adams
                    went on to serve as U.S. Senator from Massachusetts from 1803 to 1808, U.S.
                    President from 1825 to 1829, and U.S. Representative from Massachusetts from
                    1831 to 1848. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Adams’ unsurpassed diplomatic career addressed the major foreign policy
                    challenges of his time. President <persName>George Washington</persName>
                    appointed him U.S. Minister Resident to the Netherlands in 1794. After serving
                    three years in the Netherlands, Adams became U.S. Minister Resident to Prussia
                    from 1797 to 1801, appointed this time by his father. </p>
                <p>President <persName>James Madison</persName> appointed Adams U.S. Minister to
                    Russia in 1809, and Adams served until 1814. He duly reported on Napoleon’s
                    failed invasion, among other events. Adams headed the Commission that negotiated
                    the Treaty of Ghent in 1814, which ended the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref> with Great
                    Britain. His placement as U.S. Minister to Great Britain from 1815 to 1817
                    insured that he would be central to the ongoing efforts to improve
                    Anglo-American relations. He concluded the Commercial Convention of 1815, which
                    included a mutual import non-discrimination measure that would serve as a model
                    for future trade agreements.</p>
                <p>Adams helped start negotiations to disarm the Great Lakes that culminated in the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/rush-bagot">Rush-Bagot Pact of
                    1817</ref>. He also guided the progress of the Convention of 1818, which set the
                    boundary between the United States and western British North America (later
                    Canada) at the Rocky Mountains and stipulated joint occupation of the Oregon
                    Country, among other issues.</p>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Adams’ views about territorial expansion guided President
                    Monroe’s policies. Adams’ brilliant diplomacy with Spain, which led to the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/florida"> Adams-Onís Treaty of 1819</ref>, was
                    largely responsible for the Acquisition of Florida and the U.S. assumption of
                    Spain’s claim to the Oregon Country. Adams worked to delay U.S. support of the
                    new Latin American republics until the treaty was ratified.</p>
                <p>By 1822, however, he supported President Monroe’s recognition of several new
                    republics. The following year, Monroe announced the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref>, which reflected
                    many of Adams’ views, particularly his insistence that the proclamation be
                    unilateral. Adams also achieved a favorable convention with Russia in 1824 that
                    recognized the U.S. claim to the Oregon Country.</p>
                <p>Foreign affairs were not central to Adams’ presidential term. As a Representative
                    from Massachusetts, however, Adams ended his great drive to expand the territory
                    of the United States. His disapproval of the expansion of slavery led him to
                    oppose the annexation of Texas and the war with Mexico. Alternatively, Adams
                    supported President <persName>James K. Polk’s</persName> efforts to annex the
                    Oregon Country. Adams believed that slavery would not reach Oregon and that the
                    coastal territory would benefit foreign trade. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, John Quincy. <hi rend="italic">The Diary of John Quincy Adams.</hi>
                        Edited by David Grayson Allen, Robert J. Taylor, et al. 2 vols. to date.
                        Cambridge: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1981-. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg. <hi rend="italic">John Quincy Adams and the
                            Foundations of American Foreign Policy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf,
                        1949. Reprint 1973 (Norton). </bibl>
                    <bibl>DeConde, Alexander. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretary of State: An
                            Interpretation.</hi> New York: Frederick A. Praeger, 1962. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ford, Worthington C., ed. <hi rend="italic">Writings of John Quincy
                            Adams.</hi> 7 vols. New York: Macmillan, 1913-1917. </bibl>
                    <bibl>McFadden, David W. “John Quincy Adams, American Commercial Diplomacy, and
                        Russia, 1809-1825.” <hi rend="italic">New England Quarterly</hi> 66
                        (December 1993): 613-629. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Merli, Frank J. and Theodore A. Wilson, eds. <hi rend="italic">Makers of
                            American Diplomacy: From Benjamin Franklin to Alfred Thayer
                            Mahan.</hi> Vol 1. New York: Scribner, 1974. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Nagle, Paul C. <hi rend="italic">John Quincy Adams: A Public Life, A
                            Private Life.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1997. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Nevins, Allan, ed. <hi rend="italic">The Diary of John Quincy Adams,
                            1794-1845: American Diplomacy, and Political, Social, and Intellectual
                            Life from Washington to Polk.</hi> New York: Longmans, Green, 1928. Reprint 1969 (Ungar).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Parsons, Lynn Hudson, <hi rend="italic">John Quincy Adams.</hi> Madison:
                        Madison House, 1998. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Remini, Robert. <hi rend="italic">John Quincy Adams.</hi> New York: Times
                        Books, 2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Thompson, Robert R. “John Quincy Adams, Apostate: From ‘Outrageous
                        Federalist’ to ‘Republican Exile,’ 1801-1809.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                            the Early Republic</hi> 11 (Summer 1991): 161-183. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Weeks, William Earl. <hi rend="italic">John Quincy Adams and American
                            Global Empire.</hi> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1992.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>