<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Madeleine Korbel
                    Albright</title>
                <title type="short">Madeleine Korbel Albright</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bio">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Madeleine Korbel Albright</persName> was nominated to be the first
                    woman Secretary of State by President <persName>William Jefferson
                        Clinton</persName> on December 5, 1996, confirmed by the U.S. Senate on
                    January 22, 1997, and sworn in the next day. She served in the position for four
                    years and ended her service on January 20, 2001. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="albright-madeleine-korbel.jpg"/>
                    <head>Madeleine Korbel Albright, 64th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Albright was born Marie Jean “Madlenka” Korbel on May 15, 1937, in Prague,
                    Czechoslovakia. Her father, Josef, was a member of the Czechoslovak Foreign
                    Service and served as press attaché in Belgrade, Yugoslavia and later became
                    Ambassador to Yugoslavia. After the communist coup in 1948, the family
                    immigrated to Denver, Colorado. Albright Americanized her name to Madeleine,
                    became a U.S. citizen in 1957, and earned a B.A. in political science with
                    honors from Wellesley College in 1959. She earned the Ph.D. in Public Law and
                    Government at Columbia University in 1976.</p>
                <p>Albright served as chief legislative assistant to Senator Edmund Muskie (D-Me)
                    from 1976 to 1978. From 1978 to 1981, she served as a staff member in the White
                    House under President <persName>Jimmy Carter</persName> and on the National
                    Security Council under National Security Adviser <persName>Zbigniew
                        Brzezinski</persName>. </p>
                <p>In 1982 she was appointed Research Professor of International Affairs at
                    Georgetown University’s School of Foreign Service and Director of its Women in
                    Foreign Service Program. In 1993 she was appointed Ambassador to the United
                    Nations by President Clinton and served in the position until her appointment as
                    Secretary of State in 1996. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Albright promoted the expansion of NATO eastward into the
                    former Soviet bloc nations and the non-proliferation of nuclear weapons from the
                    former Soviet republics to rogue nations, successfully pressed for military
                    intervention under NATO auspices during the humanitarian crisis in Kosovo in
                    1999, supported the expansion of free-market democratization and the creation of
                    civil societies in the developing world, favored the ratification of the Kyoto
                    Protocol on Global Climate Change, and furthered the normalization of relations
                    with Vietnam.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Albright, Madeleine. <hi rend="italic">Madame Secretary: A Memoir.</hi>
                        New York: Hyperion, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        Conn.: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
