<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="bacon-robert" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Robert Bacon</title>
                <title type="short">Robert Bacon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>bacon-robert</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Robert Bacon</persName> was appointed Secretary of State January 27,
                    1909, and entered into duty the same day. Bacon had served as Assistant
                    Secretary of State under <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/root-elihu"
                        >Elihu Root</ref> prior to his appointment. He served only 37 days as
                    Secretary of State, until March 5, 1909, when President <persName>Theodore
                        Roosevelt</persName> left office. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="bacon-robert.jpg"/>
                    <head>Robert Bacon, 39th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Bacon was born in Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts in 1860 to a prominent merchant
                    family. He attended Harvard, where he befriended future president Theodore
                    Roosevelt. Bacon graduated in 1880 and went on to travel the world for one year
                    before returning to Boston to begin a successful career in business. He took
                    part in negotiations that formed major companies, including the Northern
                    Securities Company and the United States Steel Corporation.</p>
                <p>In 1905, Robert Bacon became Assistant Secretary of State at the behest of his
                    friend President Roosevelt and Secretary of State Elihu Root. In 1909, after
                    Root resigned his position, he was asked to serve as Secretary of State for the
                    duration of the Roosevelt administration. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Bacon’s business savvy aided his diplomatic efforts as he worked diligently to
                    ratify treaties between <placeName>Colombia</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Panama</placeName> and the <placeName>United States</placeName>
                    regarding the Panama Canal. Bacon’s appointment as Secretary of State for the
                    remainder of Roosevelt’s term was mostly due to his friendship with the
                    President. However, he used that month wisely, successfully passing the treaties
                    through the Senate.</p>
                <p>Bacon also convened an environmental conference between the North American
                    states, to discuss conservation of natural resources on the continent. Bacon’s
                    diplomatic skill was recognized by his successor, Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/knox-philander-chase">Philander
                    Knox</ref>, who appointed Bacon as Ambassador to France.</p>
                <p>Years later, Bacon served under General Pershing during World War One. His
                    military service at an advanced age put a general strain on Bacon’s health, and
                    he died in 1919, shortly after returning to the United States. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 2. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1927. </bibl>
                    <bibl> Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed.<hi rend="italic"> American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
