<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: James Addison Baker
                    III</title>
                <title type="short">James Addison Baker III </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>James A. Baker</persName> was appointed Secretary of State on January
                    22, 1989, and served until August 23, 1992. Baker brought almost two decades of
                    experience in politics, both behind the scenes and in key administration
                    positions with him to the State Department. As Secretary of State, Baker
                    successfully oversaw United States foreign policy during the end of the Cold
                    War, as well as during the First Persian Gulf War. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="baker-james-addison.jpg"/>
                    <head>James Addison Baker III, 61st Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Born in Texas on April 28, 1930, Baker attended prep school in Pennsylvania, and
                    went on to graduate from Princeton University in 1952. Following a two-year
                    active rotation in the United States Marine Corps from 1952 to 1954, Baker
                    received his law degree from the University of Texas at Austin in 1957. He
                    practiced law at the firm of Andrews and Kurth from 1957 to 1975, but it was not
                    until the early 1970s that he became involved in politics.</p>
                <p>Through the influence of his first wife, Baker became involved in the Republican
                    Party and began a long political relationship with <persName>George H.W.
                        Bush</persName>. Baker chaired Bush’s unsuccessful Senate campaign in 1970.
                    In 1971 Baker became the Finance Chairman of the Republican Party and played a
                    significant regional role in President Nixon’s reelection. During the Ford
                    Administration he was appointed Under Secretary of Commerce.</p>
                <p> Baker also managed President <persName>Gerald Ford</persName>’s election bid in
                    1976. In 1981, following a short run as chairman for <persName>George H.W.
                        Bush</persName>’s Republican presidential primary campaign Baker was named
                    President <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName>’s White House Chief of Staff.</p>
                <p> During the second Reagan Administration, Baker simultaneously served as
                    Secretary of the Treasury and as Chairman of the President’s Economic Council.
                    Baker served as Secretary of State in George H.W. Bush’s cabinet from January
                    22, 1989 until August 23, 1992, when he was appointed Senior Counselor and White
                    House Chief of Staff for President Bush. Baker continues to be active in
                    politics and U.S. foreign policy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Treasury Secretary during the second Reagan Administration, Baker was
                    instrumental in passing the Plaza Accord of September 1985, a multilateral
                    agreement, which devalued the dollar in order to reduce America’s account
                    deficit and help the U.S. economy recover from a recession that had begun in the
                    early 1980s. He also tried to implement the Baker Plan, which proposed using
                    Japan’s trade surplus to relieve Third World debt. </p>
                <p>Baker served as Secretary of State during a very interesting and important time
                    period in U.S. foreign relations. He was influential in overseeing American
                    foreign policy during the tumultuous and touchy times following communism’s
                    downfall in Eastern Europe and the break-up of the former Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>As the head of the State Department, Baker was also the driving force behind
                    creating a coalition of nations to repel Saddam Hussein and Iraq from Kuwait
                    during the <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/firstgulf">First
                        Persian Gulf War</ref>.</p>
                <p>Baker continues to play a role in U.S. diplomacy and international affairs. He
                    served as a Personal Envoy of the United Nations Secretary-General for Western
                    Sahara from 1997 to 2004. In 2006, the former Secretary of State served as the
                    Republican co-chair of the Iraq Study Group, tasked with assessing America’s
                    policy toward Iraq. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Baker, James Addison. <hi rend="italic">The Politics of Diplomacy:
                            Revolution, War and Peace, 1989-1992.</hi> New York: G.P. Putnam’s Sons,
                        1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barilleaux, Ryan J. <hi rend="italic">Power and Prudence: The Presidency
                            of George H.W. Bush.</hi> College Station: Texas A&amp;M University
                        Press, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Diggins, John P. <hi rend="italic">Ronald Reagan: Fate, Freedom, and the
                            Making of History.</hi> New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 2007</bibl>
                    <bibl>Maynard, Christopher. <hi rend="italic">Out of the Shadow: George H.W.
                            Bush and the End of the Cold War.</hi> College Station: Texas A&amp;M
                        University Press, 2008.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
