<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Thomas Francis Bayard</title>
                <title type="short">Thomas Francis Bayard</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> President <persName>Grover Clevelan</persName>d appointed <persName>Thomas
                        Francis Bayard</persName> as Secretary of State on March 6, 1885. Bayard
                    served from March 7 to the end of Cleveland’s first term, leaving office on
                        <date when="1889-03-04">March 4, 1889</date>. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="bayard-thomas-francis.jpg"/>
                    <head>Thomas Francis Bayard, 30th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p> Bayard was born in <placeName>Wilmington, Delaware</placeName> on October 29,
                    1828. He attended law school in Flushing, New York, passed the bar in 1851, and
                    thereafter began practicing law.</p>
                <p>Bayard was appointed U.S. District Attorney for Delaware in 1853, but resumed
                    private practice in 1854. In 1869, Bayard was elected as U.S. Senator from
                    Delaware, and served until March 6, 1885, when he became Secretary of State
                    under President <persName>Grover Cleveland</persName>. While in the Senate,
                    Bayard also served on the Hayes-Tilden Electoral Commission in 1877. Following
                    his tenure as Secretary, Bayard served as U.S. Ambassador to Great Britain from
                    1893 to 1897.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Dipolmacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Bayard moved away from patronage appointments, choosing
                    instead to appoint diplomats known for their skill and expertise rather than
                    their political loyalty. However, controversy soon erupted when the Italian and
                    Austro-Hungarian Governments rejected his appointment of Anthony M. Keiley as
                    Minister. </p>
                <p>In foreign affairs, Bayard intervened in the ongoing disputes over U.S. fishing
                    rights in <placeName>Canada</placeName> and <placeName>Newfoundland</placeName>.
                    Following the expiration of an 1871 agreement, the U.S. Government had attempted
                    to negotiate a treaty with Canada and <placeName>Great Britain</placeName> in
                    early 1888. However, the hunting of fur seals in the Bering Sea had become a
                    contentious issue, and relations were further complicated by an unclear land and
                    sea boundary division between <placeName>Alaska</placeName> and Canada. The U.S.
                    Senate ultimately rejected the terms of the treaty. Bayard continued to pursue
                    negotiations with the British Government, but the issue would not be resolved
                    until a 1903 treaty. </p>
                <p>In addition to addressing fishing rights, Bayard also focused on Pacific affairs.
                    In 1887, he oversaw the Senate’s ratification of the renewal of a reciprocity
                    treaty with <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>. That same year he hosted the
                    inconclusive Washington Conference intended to de-escalate tensions between
                    Germany, Great Britain, and the United States in competition for influence over
                    Samoa. As Secretary, Bayard was also interested in increasing Japanese autonomy.
                        <persName>Richard B. Hubbard</persName>, U.S. Minister to Japan, signed an
                    agreement in 1889 with Japanese Minister of Foreign Affairs, <persName>Marquis
                        Okuma Shigenobu</persName>, which provided for the gradual abolition of
                    extraterritorial privileges for U.S. citizens living in Japan. However, Bayard
                    acquiesced to British occupation of the Geomun-do Islands, despite Korean pleas
                    for U.S. assistance under the terms of an 1883 treaty that had been negotiated by
                    U.S. Envoy <persName>Robert W. Shufeldt</persName>. </p>
                <p>After his tenure as Secretary of State, Bayard served as U.S. Ambassador to 
                    the United Kingdom. As Ambassador, Bayard became involved in the Venezuela-Guyana boundary
                    dispute. His public, pro-British pronouncements placed him at odds with then
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/olney-richard">Secretary of State,
                        Richard Olney,</ref> and President Grover Cleveland. Bayard remained as
                    Minister until the end of Cleveland’s second term in 1897. </p>
                <p>Bayard retired, and died in Dedham, Massachusetts on September 28, 1898. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                        State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                        Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                        Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>