<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Jeremiah Sullivan
                    Black</title>
                <title type="short">Jeremiah Sullivan Black</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bio">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jeremiah Sullivan Black </persName>served as Attorney General in
                    President <persName>James Buchanan</persName>’s Cabinet until December 17, 1860,
                    when he was chosen to succeed <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/cass-lewis"
                        >Lewis Cass</ref> as Secretary of State after Cass’s sudden resignation. He
                    entered into duty on December 19, 1860, and served for the duration of the
                    Buchanan administration, leaving office on March 5, 1861. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="black-jeremiah-sullivan.jpg"/>
                    <head>Jeremiah Sullivan Black, 23rd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Black was born in Somerset County, Pennsylvania in 1810. He attended public
                    schools and studied law in the office of Chauncey Forward, a renowned lawyer in
                    western Pennsylvania. Black was admitted to the bar in 1830 and briefly took
                    over Forward’s practice when he left for Congress. In 1831, he was appointed
                    Deputy Attorney General for Somerset County. </p>
                <p>A staunch Democrat and supporter of <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName>, Black
                    befriended fellow Democrat James Buchanan early in his career, a move that would
                    result in his eventual appointment as Secretary of State. In 1842, Black
                    accepted an appointment as President Judge of the 16th Judicial District. He
                    remained there until 1851, when he was elected to the State Supreme Court. Black
                    served the first three years as Chief Justice and was reelected in 1854. At the
                    end of his second term, newly elected President Buchanan appointed Black as
                    Attorney General. When Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/cass-lewis">Lewis Cass</ref> resigned in
                    the eleventh hour of the Buchanan administration, Black was commissioned
                    Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Dipolmacy</head>
                <p>The most pressing issue for the Buchanan administration in late 1860 was the
                    threat of secession by the Confederate States. That December, President Buchanan
                    declared the act of secession unconstitutional, based partly on former Attorney
                    General Black’s legal arguments.</p>
                <p>The new Secretary of State stood vehemently against secession, but also felt it
                    was unconstitutional for the Union to force a state to remain. Black’s role as
                    trusted adviser to the President changed little with his new appointment. With
                    domestic political affairs in crisis, little attention was paid to international
                    affairs during Black’s three-month commission.</p>
                <p>One of the last acts of Black’s short tenure as head of the Department of State
                    was undoubtedly his most important. On February 28, 1861, he instructed U.S.
                    diplomatic representatives abroad to caution their respective governments
                    against recognition of the Confederacy.</p>
                <p>When President Lincoln was inaugurated in March of 1861, Black left office at
                    odds with his fellow Democrats. He was appointed Reporter to the U.S. Supreme
                    Court in 1861, a respectable, albeit lower office than he had held previously.
                    Following a long and distinguished career in public service, Black returned to
                    his private law practice in his home state of Pennsylvania, where he remained
                    until his death in 1883. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “Jeremiah S. Black.” In <hi rend="italic">The American
                            Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy. </hi>, edited by Samuel Flagg
                        Bemis. Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square
                        Publishers, Inc.). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Brigance, William Norwood. <hi rend="italic">Jeremiah Sullivan Black.</hi>
                        Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1934. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
