<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: James Gillespie
                    Blaine</title>
                <title type="short">James Gillespie Blaine</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>James G. Blaine</persName> served two terms as Secretary of State. He
                    was first appointed by U.S. President <persName>James A. Garfield</persName>,
                    serving from March 7, 1881, until December 18, 1881, and was again appointed by
                    U.S. President <persName>Benjamin Harrison</persName>, serving from March 5,
                    1889, until his resignation on June 4, 1892. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="blaine-james-gillespie.jpg"/>
                    <head>James Gillespie Blaine, 28th &amp; 31st Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Blaine was born in West Brownsville, Pennsylvania, on January 31, 1830. He
                    graduated from Washington &amp; Jefferson College in 1847, then known as
                    Washington College, and worked as a teacher for several years. Blaine moved to
                    Augusta, Maine, in 1854 and became editor of the <hi rend="italic">Kennebec
                        Journal</hi>.</p>
                <p>Blaine entered politics as a Republican, was elected to Congress in 1862, and
                    served as Speaker of the House from 1869 to 1875. In 1876, Blaine was an
                    unsuccessful candidate for the Republican nomination for President, but did win
                    a Senate seat from Maine. In 1880, Blaine was again an unsuccessful candidate
                    for the Republican nomination for the Presidency.</p>
                <p>However, President-elect <persName>James A. Garfield</persName> offered Blaine
                    the position of Secretary of State. After his first tenure as Secretary of
                    State, Blaine was the Republican candidate for President in 1884, but lost to
                        <persName>Grover Cleveland</persName>. In 1888, Blaine supported
                        <persName>Benjamin Harrison</persName> as the Republican nominee for
                    President. After Harrison’s successful election, he nominated Blaine to be
                    Secretary of State for another term.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Once in office as Secretary of State, Blaine encouraged peaceful relations within
                    the Americas, and also advocated for American commercial expansion and increased
                    naval power. Blaine negotiated for the release of U.S. citizens who had been
                    arrested and confined without trial in Ireland as part of a British crackdown on
                    Irish nationalist rent boycotts.</p>
                <p>Blaine unsuccessfully attempted to negotiate peace between Peru, Bolivia and
                    Chile, all engaged in the War of the Pacific from 1879 to 1883. He also
                    attempted to arbitrate a border dispute between Mexico and Guatemala. Blaine’s
                    overtures were cut short on September 19, 1881, by the death of President
                    Garfield, who had been shot two months before on July 2. Blaine remained in
                    office through December 18 while <persName>Chester A. Arthur</persName>, the new
                    president, selected a replacement for him.</p>
                <p> Under President Harrison, Blaine’s first challenge was to counter German
                    expansion in Samoa, where the United States competed for influence. The
                    agreement reached in 1889 between the United States, Germany and the United
                    Kingdom did not resolve the tensions between those countries, but further eroded
                    Samoan sovereignty. During this term, Blaine attempted to negotiate a
                    disagreement over Canadian fur seal hunting rights in the Bering Sea. He also
                    faced controversies over the lynching of Italian citizens in New Orleans in 1891
                    and an attack on U.S. sailors in Valparaiso, Chile.</p>
                <p>Blaine oversaw the Pan-American Conference, which had been organized by his
                    predecessor, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bayard-thomas-francis"
                        >Thomas Francis Bayard</ref>. The conference covered trade, communication
                    and legal issues, and eventually led to the establishment of the Pan-American
                    Union.</p>
                <p>Blaine resigned from his post on June 4, 1892. His resignation caught everyone,
                    including President Harrison, by surprise. Although Blaine was a candidate for
                    the 1892 Republican nomination, his poor health meant that he was not considered
                    seriously. Blaine’s health declined sharply after his resignation, and he died
                    not long afterward on January 27, 1893.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Crapol, Edward P. <hi rend="italic">James G. Blaine: Architect of
                            Empire.</hi> Wilmington, DE: Scholarly Resources, 2000.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Muzzey, David Saville. <hi rend="italic">James G. Blaine: A Political Idol
                            of Other Days.</hi> Port Washington: Kennikat Press, 1962.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tyler, Alice Felt. <hi rend="italic">The Foreign Policy of James G.
                            Blaine.</hi> Hamden, CT: Archon Books, 1965.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
