<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Antony J.
                    Blinken</title>
                <title type="short">Antony J. Blinken</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Adapted from Secretary Blinken’s official biography
                    https://2021-2025.state.gov/biographies/antony-j-blinken/ (accessed May 1,
                    2025).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Antony J. Blinken was nominated by President Biden on November 23, 2020;
                    confirmed by the U.S. Senate on January 26, 2021; and sworn in by Vice President
                    Kamala Harris the following day.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="blinken-antony-j.jpg"/>
                    <head>Antony J. Blinken, 71st Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Over three decades and three presidential administrations, Mr. Blinken has helped
                    shape U.S. foreign policy to ensure it protects U.S. interests and delivers
                    results for the American people. He served as deputy secretary of state for
                    President Barack Obama from 2015 to 2017, and before that, as President Obama’s
                    principal deputy national security advisor. In that role, Mr. Blinken chaired
                    the interagency deputies committee, the main forum for hammering out the
                    administration’s foreign policy.</p>
                <p>During the first term of the Obama Administration, Mr. Blinken was national
                    security advisor to then-Vice President Joe Biden. This was the continuation of
                    a long professional relationship that stretched back to 2002, when Mr. Blinken
                    began his six-year stint as Democratic staff director for the U.S. Senate
                    Foreign Relations Committee. Then-Senator Biden was the chair of that committee
                    from 2001 to 2003 and 2007 to 2009.</p>
                <p>During the Clinton Administration, Mr. Blinken served as a member of the National
                    Security Council staff, including two years as the senior director for European
                    affairs, the president’s principal advisor on the countries of Europe, the
                    European Union, and NATO. He also spent four years as President Clinton’s chief
                    foreign policy speechwriter, and he led the NSC’s strategic planning team.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blinken’s public service began at the State Department. From 1993 to 1994, he
                    was a special assistant in what was then called the Bureau of European and
                    Canadian Affairs. Now he is proud to lead the department where he got his start
                    in government nearly 30 years ago.</p>
                <p>Outside of government, Mr. Blinken has worked in the private sector, civil
                    society, and journalism. He was a founder of WestExec Advisors, an international
                    strategic consulting firm focused on geopolitics and national security. He was a
                    senior fellow at the Center for Strategic and International Studies from 2001
                    and 2002. Before joining government, Mr. Blinken practiced law in New York and
                    Paris. He was also a reporter for The New Republic magazine and is the author of
                        <hi rend="italic">Ally Versus Ally: America, Europe and the Siberian
                        Pipeline Crisis</hi> (Praeger, 1987).</p>
                <p>Mr. Blinken attended grade school and high school in Paris, where he received a
                    French Baccalaureat degree with high honors. He is a graduate of Harvard
                    College and Columbia Law School. He and his wife Evan Ryan have two
                    children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="sources">
                <head>Sources</head>
                <p>This text was adapted from Secretary Blinken’s <ref
                        target="https://2021-2025.state.gov/biographies/antony-j-blinken/">official
                        biography</ref> (accessed May 1, 2025).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
