<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: William Jennings
                    Bryan</title>
                <title type="short">William Jennings Bryan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> appointed <persName>William
                        Jennings Bryan</persName> Secretary of State on March 5, 1913. He entered
                    into duty the same day and served as Secretary until his resignation on June 9,
                    1915. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="bryan-william-jennings.jpg"/>
                    <head>William Jennings Bryan, 41st Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Bryan was born in Salem, Illinois on March 19, 1860. He graduated from Illinois
                    College in 1881 (A.M. 1884), and from the Union College of Law in 1883. He was
                    admitted to the Illinois State Bar in 1883 and practiced law in Jacksonville,
                    Illinois prior to moving to Lincoln, Nebraska in 1887.</p>
                <p>Bryan won election to the U.S. House of Representatives in 1890 and served until
                    1895, championing Populist causes such as the free coinage of silver, national
                    income tax, and direct election of Senators. After mounting an unsuccessful bid
                    for the U.S. Senate in 1894, Bryan returned to Nebraska and edited the <hi
                        rend="italic">Omaha World-Herald</hi>. Although not a declared candidate for
                    the 1896 presidential race, Bryan secured the Democratic nomination following
                    the delivery of his “Cross of Gold” speech but lost the election to Republican
                    candidate <persName>William McKinley</persName>. </p>
                <p>The Democratic Party nominated Bryan again as its candidate for President in 1900
                    and 1908, although he lost both elections. President Woodrow Wilson selected
                    Bryan, one of the elder statesmen of the Democratic Party, as his Secretary of
                    State following the 1912 presidential election. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Bryan’s major accomplishment as Secretary was his negotiation of peace treaties
                    that pledged the 30 signatories to refrain from hostilities during arbitration
                    of disputes. He also negotiated the Bryan–Chamorro Treaty in 1914 (ratified by
                    the Senate in 1916), which permitted the United States the latitude to construct
                    an isthmian canal across Nicaragua and secured rights to build naval bases at
                    the Gulf of Fonseca and on the Corn Islands. </p>
                <p>Bryan’s position on the rights of neutrals during wartime placed him at odds with
                    President Wilson. Declaring U.S. neutrality following the outbreak of <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/foreword">World War I</ref> in August 1914,
                    Wilson adhered to traditional concepts governing the recognition of blockades,
                    neutral transport of contraband goods, and travel of civilians to belligerent
                    nations on combatant ships. Bryan asserted that technological innovations such
                    as submarines had altered the nature of international law and made it impossible
                    to protect U.S. citizens traveling into a war zone, and he attempted to persuade
                    Wilson to prohibit such travel.</p>
                <p>The German practice of unrestricted submarine warfare, which Wilson perceived as
                    a violation of the rights of neutrals, resulted in the sinking of the British
                    passenger liner <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/wwi">Lusitania</ref> in May
                    1915 and the deaths of 128 U.S. citizens. Wilson responded by sending the German
                    Government a strongly worded protest note affirming the right of neutrals to
                    transit on the high seas. Bryan insisted that Wilson send a similar protest to
                    Britain for its violations of neutral rights, an act the president rejected.
                    Wilson’s dispatch of a second note demanding an end to German submarine warfare
                    prompted Bryan to resign on June 9, 1915. </p>
                <p>Following his resignation, Bryan continued to write and lecture and opposed
                    Clarence Darrow as counsel in the Scopes trial. Bryan died on July 26, 1925.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clements, Kendrick A. <hi rend="italic">William Jennings Bryan: Missionary
                            Isolationist.</hi> Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press,
                        1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coletta, Paolo E. <hi rend="italic">William Jennings Bryan.</hi> 3 vols.
                        Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1964–1969.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Findling, John E. <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of American Diplomatic
                            History.</hi> Westport, CT: Greenwood Press, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kazin, Michael. <hi rend="italic"> A Godly Hero: The Life of William
                            Jennings Bryan.</hi> New York: Knopf, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Link, Arthur S. <hi rend="italic">Wilson.</hi> 5 vols. Princeton:
                        Princeton University Press, 1947–1965.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
