<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: James
                    Buchanan</title>
                <title type="short">James Buchanan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>James Buchanan</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>James K. Polk</persName> on March 6, 1845. Buchanan entered
                    duty on March 10, 1845, and left the position on March 7, 1849. After an
                    unsuccessful bid for the Democratic presidential nomination in 1852, Buchanan
                    secured the nomination in 1856 and was elected President. He served one term,
                    from 1857 to 1861. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="buchanan-james.jpg"/>
                    <head>James Buchanan, 17th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Buchanan was born to Irish immigrant parents near Mercersburg, Pennsylvania. He
                    entered Dickinson College at the age of 16 and graduated in 1809. </p>
                <p>Following graduation, Buchanan began a clerkship with John Hopkins, a reputable
                    lawyer in Lancaster. After a failed attempt to begin his practice in Kentucky,
                    he returned to Pennsylvania where he was admitted to the bar in 1812. </p>
                <p>Two years later, after marching in a military company against the British in the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref>, Buchanan
                    entered politics when he was nominated to the State Assembly. Following a second
                    term in the lower house of the Pennsylvania legislature, Buchanan was elected to
                    the U.S. House of Representatives in 1820. He served in this position for ten
                    years.</p>
                <p>In 1832, President <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName> made Buchanan Minister
                    Plenipotentiary to Russia. After returning from two years in St. Petersburg, he
                    was elected to the U.S. Senate in 1834 and served for three terms. Buchanan had
                    presidential aspirations during his Senate service and was even considered for
                    the Democratic nomination for the 1844 election. The nomination instead went to
                        <persName>James K. Polk </persName>and in return for Pennsylvania’s support,
                    Polk appointed Buchanan as Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Both President Polk and Secretary Buchanan believed in <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/foreword">Manifest Destiny</ref> and were
                    strong proponents of U.S. westward expansion.</p>
                <p>In addition to supporting U.S. efforts to annex Texas, Buchanan was charged with
                    negotiating a settlement on the boundary dispute with Great Britain over the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/oregon-territory">Oregon Territory</ref>.
                    Like the 1848 treaty with Mexico that would soon follow, the 1846 Oregon Treaty
                    fell short of a full territorial concession.</p>
                <p>Outgoing President Tyler successfully pushed for the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">Annexation of Texas</ref> by
                    a congressional joint resolution just before leaving office, an effort supported
                    by Buchanan. Annexation prompted the Mexican-American War and resulted in the
                    1848 Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. The treaty brought the United States
                    significant territorial expansion, yet Buchanan opposed its outcome and believed
                    that Baja and the northern provinces of Mexico should have been included.</p>
                <p>Polk directed most aspects of U.S. foreign policy during his presidency, allowing
                    Buchanan little control. Buchanan felt this lack of power intensely and
                    communicated his discontent to close friends and associates. Nevertheless, he
                    served as Secretary of State until the end of the Polk Administration.</p>
                <p>After serving as Secretary of State, Buchanan attempted to win the Presidency in
                    1852 but failed. Instead, he served as Minister to Great Britain from 1853 to
                    1856, where he drafted the Ostend Manifesto with other U.S. diplomats. His
                    absence during the sectional schism of the Democratic Party allowed him to win
                    that party’s nomination and subsequently the Presidency in 1856. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “James Buchanan.” In <hi rend="italic">The American
                            Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy,</hi> edited by Samuel Flagg
                        Bemis. Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square
                        Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>DeConde, Alexander. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of State:
                            An Interpretation.</hi> New York: Praeger, 1962. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Klein, Philip Shriver. <hi rend="italic">President James Buchanan: A
                            Biography. </hi>University Park: Pennsylvania State University, 1962. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped. </hi>New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Potter, David. <hi rend="italic">The Impending Crisis, 1848-1861.</hi> New
                        York: Harper &amp; Row, 1976.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
