<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: James Francis
                    Byrnes</title>
                <title type="short">James Francis Byrnes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bio">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>James Francis Byrnes</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName> on July 3, 1945, and entered duty
                    on the same day. He left office on January 21, 1947. Byrnes led the Department
                    of State during the significant transition from World War II to the Cold War. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="byrnes-james-francis.jpg"/>
                    <head>James Francis Byrnes, 49th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p> Byrnes was born in Charleston, South Carolina to an industrious mother who was
                    widowed shortly before his birth. He left school after the seventh grade to work
                    in a law office where he received excellent tutelage from several judges. Byrnes
                    was admitted to the South Carolina bar in 1903 and practiced in Aiken. In 1908
                    he was elected to his first public office as district prosecuting attorney. Two
                    years later he was elected to the U.S. Congress, where he served from 1911 to
                    1925.</p>
                <p>Byrnes returned briefly to private practice before his election to the U.S.
                    Senate in 1931. During his ten years in the Senate, he championed President
                        <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName>’s New Deal. The President
                    appointed Byrnes to the Supreme Court in 1941. It was a short-lived appointment
                    for the restless judge who missed the political action of the legislative
                    branch. He resigned the following year. </p>
                <p>Following U.S. entry into World War II, Byrnes was chosen as Director of the
                    Office of Economic Stabilization, and in 1943, Director of Economic
                    Mobilization. He accompanied President Roosevelt to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/yalta-conf">Yalta Conference</ref> in 1945.
                    Following President Roosevelt’s death in April, Byrnes returned to South
                    Carolina.</p>
                <p>That summer, President Truman asked Byrnes to return to Washington as his
                    Secretary of State. He was unanimously confirmed by the Senate without a
                    hearing. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>A skilled policymaker, Byrnes spent much of his time outside of Washington
                    meeting with foreign leaders. President Truman was uncertain of his own aptitude
                    in matters of foreign policy and thus placed a great deal of confidence in
                    Secretary Byrnes.</p>
                <p>Within days of his appointment, Byrnes accompanied President Truman to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/potsdam-conf">Potsdam Conference</ref>, a
                    critical turning point in U.S.-Soviet relations. He continued to negotiate the
                    rapidly fraying post-war alliance at conferences in London and Moscow.</p>
                <p>Byrnes increasingly wielded less control over U.S. foreign policy as
                    disagreements arose with President Truman over how forceful the country should
                    be against the increasingly uncooperative <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName>. </p>
                <p>The Secretary was a proponent of using the newly-developed atomic bomb against
                        <placeName>Japan</placeName>, and under his advice, two <ref
                        target="/milestones/1945-1952/atomic">atomic bombs</ref> were detonated over
                    Japan in August of 1945. It was also during Byrnes’ tenure as Secretary of State
                    that <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kennan-george-frost">George
                        Kennan</ref> authored his famous <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/short-history/kennan">1946 “Long Telegram,”</ref>
                    advocating a change in policy towards the Soviets. President Truman and
                    Secretary Byrnes implemented these changes swiftly, laying the foundations for
                    the early Cold War. </p>
                <p>Byrnes resigned his position on January 21, 1947, and continued to practice law.
                    In 1951 he was elected Governor of South Carolina and served one term. James
                    Byrnes died in 1972. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “James Francis Byrnes.” In <hi rend="italic">The
                            American Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy,</hi> edited by
                        Samuel Flagg Bemis. Vol. 14. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1965
                        (Cooper Square). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gaddis, John Lewis. <hi rend="italic">Strategies of Containment: A
                            Critical Appraisal of American National Security Policy during the Cold
                            War.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press, 2005. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
