<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John C. Calhoun</title>
                <title type="short">John C. Calhoun</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>John Caldwell Calhoun was appointed Secretary of State by President
                        <persName>John Tyler</persName> on <date when="1844-03-06">March 6,
                    1844</date>. Calhoun entered duty on April 1, 1844, and left the position on
                    March 10, 1845. A former U.S. Representative, U.S. Senator, Secretary of War
                    and Vice President, Calhoun served as Secretary of State for less than one year
                    before returning to his position in the U.S. Senate, where he served until his
                    death in 1850. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="calhoun-john-caldwell.jpg"/>
                    <head>John C. Calhoun, 16th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Calhoun was born in Abbeville County, South Carolina to a prosperous farming
                    family. He entered Yale College in 1802 and graduated two years later. He
                    continued his education at Litchfield Law School in Connecticut. He gained
                    admission to the South Carolina bar in 1807 and practiced law in his native
                    Abbeville. The following year, he was elected to the state legislature of South
                    Carolina, where he served for two years preceding his election to the U.S. House
                    of Representatives in 1810.</p>
                <p>President Monroe appointed Calhoun as Secretary of War in 1817, and during his
                    tenure he made substantial changes to the War Department. He served two terms as
                    Vice President: in 1825 under <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName> and again
                    in 1829 under <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName>. He resigned the position of
                    Vice President in 1832 and returned to South Carolina as a Senator, a position
                    he held for the following 11 years. In 1844, following the accidental death of
                    Secretary <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/upshur-abel-parker">Abel P.
                        Upshur</ref>, President Tyler appointed Calhoun as Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Calhoun entered office as Secretary of State not at the behest of President
                    Tyler, but of <persName>Henry Wise</persName>, a mutual associate who had all
                    but promised him the position. Tyler accepted the proposition and named Calhoun
                    to his Cabinet with the assurance that its newest member would carry out the
                    directives of his predecessor, namely the Annexation of Texas.</p>
                <p>One of Calhoun’s first acts as Secretary of State was to submit a <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">treaty of annexation</ref> to
                    the Senate. The 1844 treaty had been largely crafted by President Tyler and the
                    former Secretary Upshur, but it was Calhoun’s vociferous and controversial
                    support of slavery in Texas that was blamed for its defeat in Congress. He
                    continued to press for annexation of a pro-slavery Texas, which deeply troubled
                    President Tyler, the incumbent in that year’s election who hoped to downplay
                    sectional differences and unite, rather than divide, the nation over the issue
                    of annexation.</p>
                <p>When President Polk was elected on a pro-expansionist platform, sitting President
                    Tyler recommended annexation by a joint resolution of Congress, which passed days
                    before he left office in 1845.</p>
                <p>Calhoun also worked to resolve territorial disputes to the north, opening
                    negotiations on a settlement with the British over the Oregon Territory. The
                    U.S. also signed the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/china-1">Treaty of
                        Wangxia</ref>, its first commercial treaty with China, during Calhoun’s
                    tenure. President <persName>Polk</persName> chose not to retain Calhoun as
                    Secretary of State, and the South Carolinian returned to the Senate, where he
                    served until his death five years later. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “John Caldwell Calhoun.” In <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of State and Their
                        Diplomacy,</hi> edited by Samuel Flagg Bemis. Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963
                        (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Capers, Gerald M. <hi rend="italic">John C. Calhoun—Opportunist: A
                            Reappraisal.</hi> Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1960. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Current, Richard N. <hi rend="italic">John C. Calhoun.</hi> New York:
                        Washington Square Press, 1966. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>