<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="cass-lewis" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Lewis Cass</title>
                <title type="short">Lewis Cass</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>cass-lewis</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Lewis Cass</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by President
                        <persName>James Buchanan</persName> on March 6, 1857, and assumed office the
                    same day. He served until December 14, 1860. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="cass-lewis.jpg"/>
                    <head>Lewis Cass, 22nd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Cass was born to a farming family in Exeter, New Hampshire. His father joined the
                    Continental Army in the <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/declaration"
                        >Revolutionary War</ref> and fought under General Washington at Bunker Hill,
                    instilling in his son a deep sense of patriotism. Cass attended Phillips Exeter
                    Academy. Upon completing his education in 1800, he left with his family for the
                    Northwest Territory of Ohio.</p>
                <p>In Ohio, he became a member of the bar, practicing in the town of Zanesville,
                    Ohio. In 1806, Cass was elected to the Ohio House of Representatives. The
                    following year, President <persName>Jefferson</persName> appointed him as U.S.
                    Marshal for Ohio. After serving during the War of 1812, during which he was
                    promoted to the rank of General, Cass was appointed Governor of the Michigan
                    Territory. He served in this capacity from 1813 until 1831. That same year,
                    President <persName>Jackson</persName> chose Cass to serve as his Secretary of
                    War. At the conclusion of his term, Jackson appointed Cass U.S. Minister to
                    France, a position he held for six years.</p>
                <p>Cass failed to secure the Democratic presidential nomination in 1844 and in 1845
                    became a U.S. Senator from the state of Michigan. After serving in the Senate,
                    Cass secured the presidential nomination in 1848 but lost the election. He
                    returned to the Senate for eight more years and failed to receive the
                    presidential nomination in 1852. President <persName>Buchanan</persName>
                    appointed Cass as Secretary of State in 1857. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>President Buchanan appointed Cass Secretary of State with hopes he would unify
                    the Democratic Party then riddled with sectional tensions. </p>
                <p>An experienced diplomat and former Secretary of State, President Buchanan
                    aggressively directed foreign policy. Two focal points of the Buchanan
                    administration were Latin America and Great Britain. Internal dissension from
                    antislavery proponents, sparked in part by the attempt to purchase Cuba from
                    Spain, often thwarted Buchanan’s foreign policy plans. Attempts to purchase more
                    territory from Mexico were also frustrated by an increasingly divided Congress
                    and disinterest on the part of Mexican leaders. </p>
                <p> Nonetheless, Cass successfully negotiated a final settlement of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/panama-canal">Clayton-Bulwer Treaty</ref> with
                    the British Government. The treaty limited both U.S. and British control
                    throughout Latin America. The British also relinquished their claim to the right
                    to search U.S. vessels under Cass’s tenure.</p>
                <p>With the election of <persName>Abraham Lincoln</persName> and the rise of the new
                    Republican Party, Cass began to voice his long-held disagreements with the
                    Buchanan administration, specifically his protests related to sectional
                    differences. Cass tendered his resignation in the last days of 1860. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Smith, W. L. G. <hi rend="italic">Fifty Years of Public Life: The Life and
                            Times of Lewis Cass.</hi> New York: Derby &amp; Jackson, 1856. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Young, William T. <hi rend="italic">Sketch of the Life and Public Services
                            of General Lewis Cass. </hi>Detroit: Markham &amp; Elwood, 1852. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
