<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Henry Clay</title>
                <title type="short">Henry Clay</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Henry Clay was appointed Secretary of State by President <persName>John Quincy
                        Adams</persName> on <date when="1825-03-07">March 7, 1825</date>. Clay
                    entered his duties on the same day and served until <date when="1829-03-03"
                        >March 3, 1829.</date> Famous as the “Great Pacificator” for his
                    contributions to domestic policy, he emphasized economic development in his
                    diplomacy. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="clay-henry.jpg"/>
                    <head>Henry Clay, Nineth Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Clay was born in Hanover County, Virginia. After a minimal formal education, Clay
                    read law and gained admission to the bar in both Virginia and Kentucky in 1797.
                    He became a leading real estate and business lawyer in Frankfort, Kentucky and
                    soon embarked on a career in politics.</p>
                <p>Clay was elected to the Kentucky House of Representatives in 1803 and served to
                    1806. Next, he served as Senator from Kentucky, from 1806 to 1807, and then
                    returned to the State House of Representatives, from 1807 to 1809. In 1810 Clay
                    returned to the Senate and served until 1811.</p>
                <p>He became a leader of an anti-British group of Congressmen known as the War Hawks
                    while a U.S. Representative and Speaker of the House from 1811 to 1814. Clay
                    went on to serve as a U.S. Representative from 1815 to 1821 and from 1823 to
                    1825, and again as Speaker of the House from 1815 to 1820 and from 1823 to
                    1825.</p>
                <p>After his tenure as Secretary of State, Clay returned to the U.S. Senate from
                    1831 to 1842 and from 1849 to 1852. Clay’s fame as a compromiser stemmed from
                    his involvement with the Missouri Compromise, the Comprise Tariff of 1833, and
                    the Compromise of 1850. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Clay’s appointment as Secretary of State stirred controversy. His bid for the
                    Presidency in the election of 1824 ended with no clear majority for any
                    candidate. Clay lent his support to <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName>
                    instead of <persName>Andrew Jackson,</persName> thereby violating the
                    instructions of the Kentucky legislature. Adams was then selected as President
                    by the House of Representatives.</p>
                <p>Due to the informal precedent that the Secretary of State would eventually assume
                    the presidency, Jackson supporters portrayed Clay’s subsequent appointment as
                    Secretary of State as a “corrupt bargain.” Nonetheless, Clay had diplomatic
                    experience and an agenda to pursue as Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>He had served on the Peace Commission following the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref> that negotiated
                    the Treaty of Ghent with Great Britain in 1814. As a Commissioner, Clay pressed
                    to prevent the British from gaining free navigation on the Mississippi River.
                    Clay based his foreign policy plan on the so-called “American System,”
                    emphasizing federal support of national economic development. To this end, Clay
                    achieved a number of important successes as Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>Clay oversaw the settlement of twelve commercial treaties, more than all earlier
                    administrations, and developed economic ties with the newly independent Latin
                    American republics. The British Government agreed to pay an indemnity for slaves
                    freed during the War of 1812.</p>
                <p>Clay’s political negotiations, however, produced ample frustration. The
                    Government of Mexico opted to expel Clay’s minister, <persName>Joel
                        Poinsett</persName>, after Poinsett offered to purchase Texas. Furthermore,
                    U.S. delegates arrived too late to attend an important diplomatic event in Latin
                    America, the Inter-American Congress at Panama in 1826.</p>
                <p>Another disappointment came when Clay failed to settle continuing boundary
                    disputes with Great Britain. In 1827 the United States and Great Britain merely
                    agreed to the joint occupation of Oregon. Despite such setbacks and the
                    remaining bitterness over Clay’s appointment as Secretary of State, Clay's
                    emphasis upon U.S. economic expansionism would prove to be a harbinger of modern
                    U.S. diplomacy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 4. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hopkins, James F., with Mary W.M. Hargreaves, eds. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Papers of Henry Clay.</hi> 10 vols and Supplement. Lexington: University
                        Press of Kentucky, 1959-1992. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hoskins, H.L. “The Hispanic American Policy of Henry Clay, 1816-1828.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Hispanic American Historical Review</hi> 7 (November
                        1927): 460-78. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Remini, Robert V. <hi rend="italic">Henry Clay: Statesman for the
                            Union.</hi> New York: W.W. Norton, 1991. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Deusen, Glyndon G., <hi rend="italic">The Life of Henry Clay.</hi>
                        Boston: Little, Brown, and Company, 1937. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
