<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Middleton
                    Clayton</title>
                <title type="short">John Middleton Clayton</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>John Middleton Clayton</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Zachary Taylor</persName> on March 7, 1849, and entered duty
                    the next day. He resigned the position on July 22, 1850, shortly after President
                    Taylor died and <persName>Millard Fillmore</persName> assumed the Presidency.
                    Clayton served during a difficult administration and suffered frequent criticism
                    despite the fact that he wielded little influence under Taylor. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="clayton-john-middleton.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Middleton Clayton, 18th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Clayton was born in Sussex County, Delaware. He attended multiple academies there
                    before entering Yale College. He graduated in 1815 and apprenticed in the law
                    office of his cousin, future U.S. Senator and Delaware Supreme Court Justice
                    Thomas Clayton. After studying law at the Litchfield Law School, Clayton was
                    admitted to the Delaware bar in 1819.</p>
                <p>A successful lawyer, he entered politics in 1824 when he was elected to the state
                    legislature. Clayton served two years in the House of Representatives before he
                    was appointed Secretary of State for Delaware. He held the position until 1828
                    when he was elected to the U.S. Senate.</p>
                <p>Clayton served during the Nullification Crisis, when South Carolina’s attempt to
                    nullify federal law threatened the Union and created one of many fissures
                    leading to the Civil War, as well as during the Bank War, when President Jackson
                    controversially vetoed the federal charter of the Second Bank of the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Clayton left his Senate seat in 1837 to spend time with his family (his wife
                    Sarah died following the birth of their second child and Clayton never
                    remarried). During this time, he was appointed Chief Justice of the Delaware
                    Supreme Court with the support of local Whig leaders.</p>
                <p>He left the bench in 1839 to campaign for <persName>William Henry
                        Harrison</persName> but failed to win a position in either the Harrison or
                    Tyler cabinets. In 1849, President Taylor appointed Clayton U. S. Secretary of
                    State on the recommendation of Kentucky Governor <persName>John J.
                        Crittenden</persName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Clayton’s tenure as Secretary of State was marked by war scares with
                        <placeName>France</placeName> and <placeName>Portugal</placeName>,
                    opposition from both houses of Congress, and troubled diplomacy. Clayton pushed
                    for a strict adherence to the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe
                        Doctrine</ref>, and managed to keep British influence in abeyance.</p>
                <p>They key achievement of the Taylor administration was the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/panama-canal">Clayton-Bulwer Treaty</ref> over
                    building a proposed Anglo-American canal through the Central American Republic
                    of <placeName>Nicaragua</placeName>. The canal never went beyond the planning
                    stages, however, and was supplanted by the canal in Panama. Upon the death of
                    President Taylor in July of 1850, Clayton immediately resigned his position.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “John Middleton Clayton.” <hi rend="italic">The
                            American Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy, </hi>edited by Samuel
                        Flagg Bemis. Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper
                        Square Publishers, Inc.). </bibl>
                    <bibl>DeConde, Alexander. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of State:
                            An Interpretation.</hi> New York: Praeger, 1962. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>