<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Bainbridge Colby</title>
                <title type="short">Bainbridge Colby</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> appointed <persName>Bainbridge
                        Colby</persName> as his third Secretary of State on March 23, 1920. He was
                    confirmed by the Senate and entered into duty the same day. Colby served until
                    the end of the Wilson administration, leaving office on March 4, 1921. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="colby-bainbridge.jpg"/>
                    <head>Bainbridge Colby, 43rd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Colby was born in St. Louis, Missouri to a prominent New York family. He
                    graduated from Williams College in 1890 before attending Columbia University Law
                    School for one year. He completed his legal studies at New York Law School in
                    1892 and began to practice in New York upon admittance to its bar.</p>
                <p>A successful
                    lawyer, Colby joined the Republican Party and was elected to the New York State
                    Assembly. Colby left the party in 1912 and helped form the Progressive Party. In
                    1916, he publicly supported the reelection of President Wilson in a stirring
                    speech that began a lifetime friendship between the two.</p>
                <p>Wilson appointed Colby
                    to the Shipping Board in 1917, and, later that year, Wilson invited him to serve as
                    a representative on the U.S. delegation to the Interallied Conference in London.
                    When then-Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert Lansing</ref>
                    resigned in 1920, Wilson appointed Colby as his third Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="infuence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>President Wilson and Secretary of State Colby shared many of the same views on
                    the conduct of U.S. foreign policy. However, Colby entered office during the
                    challenging last years of the Wilson administration.</p>
                <p>Despite Colby’s efforts, the
                    Senate refused to ratify the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Versailles Treaty</ref> following World War One and contested U.S.
                        membership in Wilson’s League of Nations.</p>
                <p>Colby experienced more success in his
                    approach towards the new government of the Soviet Union. He formulated a
                    non-recognition policy toward the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName> based on its promotion of
                    international communism and the threat it posed to existing governments.</p>
                <p>Closer
                    to home, Colby successfully negotiated recognition and normal diplomatic
                    relations with the Mexican Government following the Mexican Revolution. He
                    toured Latin America on behalf of the President, promoting hemispheric
                    cooperation.</p>
                <p>Audiences warmly received the Secretary of State and approved of
                    his willingness to publicly discuss the merits of the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref>. Colby
                    convincingly argued that the doctrine was not imperialistic, but rather promoted
                    democracy throughout Latin America.</p>
                <p>Colby left office at the end of the Wilson
                    administration in 1921 and returned to private practice. Colby died on April 11,
                    1950. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped. </hi>New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell. </hi>Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>