<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="day-william-rufus" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: William Rufus
                    Day</title>
                <title type="short">William Rufus Day</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>day-william-rufus</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>William Rufus Day</persName> was appointed Secretary of State in
                    President <persName>William McKinley</persName>’s Cabinet on April 26, 1898. He
                    entered into duty on April 28, 1898, and served until September 16, 1898. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="day-william-rufus.jpg"/>
                    <head>William Rufus Day, 36th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Day was born in Ravenna, Ohio in 1849 to a long line of distinguished jurists. He
                    decided early in life to study the law. He attended preparatory school and
                    graduated from the University of Michigan in 1870. He returned to his hometown
                    of Ravenna the following year to read law in the office of a prominent local
                    judge before completing a final year at Michigan.</p>
                <p>Day was admitted to the Ohio bar in 1872 and began his practice that year in
                    Canton. While there, he befriended the future president, William McKinley. A
                    successful lawyer, Day was elected judge of the Court of Common Pleas in 1886.
                    Three years later, he was appointed district judge for the northern district of
                    Ohio, but poor health forced him to resign this position before he entered into
                    duty.</p>
                <p>Day continued his practice until President McKinley chose him to serve as
                    Assistant Secretary of State under Secretary <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/sherman-john">John Sherman</ref> in 1897.
                    As Secretary of State Sherman grew increasingly alienated from the McKinley
                    administration, Day took over many of Sherman’s duties. When Sherman resigned in
                    April 1898, Day succeeded him as Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Day assumed the position of Secretary of State just a few days after the start of
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">Spanish-American
                        War</ref>. Although he was not known to be an especially skilled diplomat,
                    Day worked tirelessly to secure the neutrality of Europe during the war. The
                    Spanish-American War dominated his tenure, as well as the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1866-1898/hawaii">annexation of Hawaii</ref>.</p>
                <p>Day had agreed only to take the position of Secretary of State until the end of
                    the war, and submitted his resignation shortly after the peace treaty with Spain
                    was signed in 1898. As the U.S. representative to the peace conference in Paris,
                    Day successfully negotiated with Spain the ceding of Cuba, Guam, the
                    Philippines, and Puerto Rice to the United States for $20 million. </p>
                <p>President McKinley’s foreign policy aims were largely carried out by Day with
                    little conflict. Day's only objection in the Spanish-American War peace
                    settlement was the annexation of the Philippines, yet he honored McKinley’s
                    wishes.</p>
                <p>After resigning as Secretary of State, he transferred his duties to <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John Hay</ref>. Shortly
                    after, Day returned to the legal profession. President McKinley appointed Day
                    judge to the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals. He served there until 1903, when
                    President Roosevelt nominated him Associate Justice of the U.S. Supreme
                    Court.</p>
                <p> Day enjoyed a long and distinguished career in the Supreme Court, serving nearly
                    20 years. He resigned due to failing health in 1922. Justice Day died the
                    following year. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
