<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Foster
                    Dulles</title>
                <title type="short">John Foster Dulles</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bio">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>John Foster Dulles</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Dwight Eisenhower</persName> on January 21, 1953. Dulles
                    served for much of the decade, leaving an indelible mark upon U.S. foreign
                    policy that included close cooperation between the Department of State and the
                    Central Intelligence Agency as well as a focus upon international mutual
                    security agreements designed to contain communism. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="dulles-john-foster.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Foster Dulles, 52nd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Dulles was born in Washington, D.C. on February 25, 1888. A grandson of former
                    Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/foster-john-watson"
                        >John Watson Foster</ref> and the nephew of Woodrow Wilson’s Secretary of
                    State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert
                        Lansing</ref>. Dulles was surrounded by members of the foreign affairs
                    community from an early age.</p>
                <p>During his adolescence, he spent a year in Paris before attending Princeton
                    University. Dulles returned to Paris in 1919 to attend the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Paris Peace Conference of
                        1919</ref> as part of Bernard Baruch’s Reparations Commission and Economic
                    Council. During this time, Dulles formed strong opinions about the danger of
                    holding Germany responsible for war reparations and—from the failure of
                    President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> to gain U.S. support for the
                    League of Nations—the value of maintaining strong domestic support for U.S.
                    foreign policy.</p>
                <p>During World War II, Dulles served on the War Trade Board as a lawyer. After the
                    war, Dulles entered private practice and in 1949 was appointed to the Senate by
                    New York Governor <persName>Thomas E. Dewey</persName>, although he failed to
                    win reelection. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>President <persName>Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName> appointed Dulles as his
                    Secretary of State on January 21, 1953. During the 1950s, Dulles and Eisenhower
                    forged a strong friendship that granted the Secretary of State direct and
                    unprecedented access to the President. Furthermore, Dulles’s time as Secretary
                    was marked by a general consensus in U.S. policy that peace could be maintained
                    through the <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/containment"
                        >containment of communism</ref>. This consensus allowed Dulles and
                    Eisenhower to secure international mutual security agreements while at the same
                    time reducing the number of troops in the U.S. military and the production of
                    conventional weapons. Dulles also enjoyed the close cooperation of the Central
                    Intelligence Agency, which was run by his brother, <persName>Allen
                        Dulles</persName>. </p>
                <p> Dulles confronted many foreign policy challenges during his tenure including the
                    integration of Europe, escalation of the crisis in Indochina, U.S. response to
                    the Hungarian Revolution, and the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/suez">Suez
                        Canal crisis of 1956</ref>. Despite being diagnosed with advanced stage
                    cancer in the immediate aftermath of the Suez Crisis, Dulles returned to work in
                    Foggy Bottom. One of his last directives was the formulation of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/eisenhower-doctrine">Eisenhower Doctrine</ref>
                    in response to the Suez Crisis. (The Eisenhower Doctrine was an expression of
                    the key tenets of Dulles’s foreign policy views: containment and international
                    mutual security agreements reinforced by economic aid.) </p>
                <p> Dulles was also the first Secretary of State to be directly accessible to the
                    media and to hold the first Department press conferences. </p>
                <p> Poor health forced Dulles to resign his position at the Department of State in
                    April of 1959, only weeks before his death on May 24, 1959. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Immerman, Richard H. <hi rend="italic">John Foster Dulles and the
                            Diplomacy of the Cold War.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                        1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
