<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="eagleburger-lawrence-sidney" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Lawrence Sidney
                    Eagleburger</title>
                <title type="short">Lawrence Sidney Eagleburger</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>eagleburger-lawrence-sidney</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Lawrence Eagleburger</persName> was appointed Secretary of State on
                    December 8, 1992, and continued in that position until January 19, 1993.
                    Eagleburger’s tenure as Secretary capped off a distinguished 27-year career with
                    the Department of State. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="eagleburger-lawrence-sidney.jpg"/>
                    <head>Lawrence Sidney Eagleburger, 62nd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, on August 1, 1930, Eagleburger earned a bachelor’s
                    degree from the University of Wisconsin in 1952, before serving as a First
                    Lieutenant in the United States Army from 1952 to 1954. Following his army
                    years, the future diplomat returned to his alma mater, where he earned a
                    master’s degree in 1957. Upon graduation, Eagleburger joined the Foreign Service
                    and served as a political analyst for Cuba before being sent to Yugoslavia,
                    where he was assigned to the U.S. Embassy’s economic section from 1961 to 1965.
                    He also worked as a National Security Council Staff member from 1966 to 1967,
                    and as Special Assistant to the Under Secretary of State from 1967 to 1969.</p>
                <p> During the Nixon administration, Eagleburger held a number of roles, including
                    Executive Assistant to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (1969), Political Adviser and Chief of the Political Section of the U.S. Mission
                    to NATO (1969-1971), and Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense (1971-1973). He
                    was then named Deputy Under Secretary of State for Management from 1975 to 1977,
                    before President <persName>Jimmy Carter</persName> appointed him Ambassador to
                    Yugoslavia from 1977 to 1981.</p>
                <p>Eagleburger continued to rise within the ranks of the Department of State during
                    the Reagan and Bush I administrations, serving as Undersecretary of State for
                    Political Affairs under President <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName> and Deputy
                    Secretary of State during President <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName>’s
                    tenure. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>When James Baker left his post as Secretary of State in August of 1992 to lead
                    President Bush’s reelection campaign, Eagleburger took over the Department of
                    State as Acting Secretary of State until the President gave him a recess
                    appointment as Secretary of State on December 8, 1992. Eagleburger’s career
                    service over the years gave him invaluable experience and knowledge in many
                    important areas of U.S. diplomacy.</p>
                <p>Most notably, the time he spent in Yugoslavia led him to become President George
                    H.W. Bush’s primary advisor during Yugoslavia’s disintegration following
                    communism’s demise in Eastern Europe. Eagleburger’s role as an advisor on
                    Yugoslavian affairs was not without controversy. He gained a reputation as a
                    strong Serbian supporter and denied that there had been atrocities committed in
                    Croatia. As the Department’s second-highest ranking official prior to taking
                    over the Secretary’s position, Eagleburger also played a key role during the
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/firstgulf">First Persian Gulf
                        War</ref>. </p>
                <p>In his retirement, Eagleburger remained a strong voice on international and
                    political issues. In 1998, he became chairman of the International Commission on
                    Holocaust-Era Insurance Claims, which worked to resolve unpaid insurance claims
                    for Holocaust survivors. He also contined to comment on U.S. policy toward the
                    Middle East and served on the Iraq Study Group.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Baker, James Addison. <hi rend="italic">The Politics of Diplomacy:
                            Revolution, War, and Peace, 1989-1992.</hi> New York: G.P. Putnam’s
                        Sons, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Diggins, John P. <hi rend="italic">Ronald Reagan: Fate, Freedom, and the
                            Making of History.</hi> New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Maynard, Christopher. <hi rend="italic">Out of the Shadow: George H.W.
                            Bush and the End of the Cold War. </hi> College Station: Texas A&amp;M
                        University Press, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ramet, Sabrina. <hi rend="italic">Thinking about Yugoslavia: Scholarly
                            debates about the Yugoslav breakup and the wars in Bosnia and
                            Kosovo.</hi> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2005.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
