<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: William
                    Evarts</title>
                <title type="short">William Evarts</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>William Evarts</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Rutherford B. Hayes</persName> on March 7, 1877, and began
                    serving as Secretary on March 12. Evarts served until March 7, 1881.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="evarts-william-maxwell.jpg"/>
                    <head>William Evarts, 27th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>William Evarts was born in Boston on February 6, 1818. He graduated from Yale
                    College in 1837 and began Harvard Law School in 1838. Evarts moved to New York
                    City in 1840 and was admitted to the bar on July 16, 1841.</p>
                <p>Evarts entered into politics as a Whig and was appointed Assistant District
                    Attorney of the southern district of New York in 1848, a post he held until
                    1853. Evarts later joined the newly formed Republican Party and was an
                    unsuccessful candidate for the U.S. Senate in 1861.</p>
                <p>His work in private practice earned him a reputation as one of the country’s top
                    lawyers. Upon the recommendation of Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William H.
                        Seward</ref>, President <persName>Andrew Johnson</persName> retained Evarts
                    as his counsel during his impeachment trial. Afterwards, Johnson appointed
                    Evarts as Attorney General on July 16, 1868, a position in which he served until
                    March 4, 1869.</p>
                <p>After several years of private practice, Evarts represented the Republican Party
                    before the Hayes-Tilden Commission established to resolve the disputed election
                    of 1876.</p>
                <p>President Hayes nominated Evarts to be his Secretary of State on March 7, 1877.
                    Despite opposition in the Senate, including that of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">James G.
                        Blaine</ref>, Evarts’s nomination was approved on March 10, and he began his
                    duties on March 12.</p>
                <p>After leaving office, Evarts served as a delegate to the International Monetary
                    Conference in 1881 and as U.S. Senator from New York from 1885 to 1891. Evarts
                    died on February 28, 1901.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As a federal prosecutor, Evarts addressed international issues including
                    investigations of possible filibustering expeditions into Central America. These
                    investigations eventually led to the detention of the ship <hi rend="italic">Cleopatra</hi>, which was part of Narciso López’s expedition against
                    Cuba.</p>
                <p>During the Civil War, Evarts became involved in the early prosecution of
                    Confederate privateers. He was also dispatched on a mission to convince the
                    British Government to enforce neutrality regulations more strictly in an effort
                    to cut off assistance to the Confederacy. Evarts visited France to advocate for
                    the Union cause and attempted to dissuade the French Government from permitting
                    the construction of Confederate warships. Evarts also served as an arbitrator in
                    the Alabama claims. </p>
                <p>When Evarts became Secretary of State, he grappled with the decision of whether
                    or not to recognize the new Mexican government led by <persName>Porfirio
                        Díaz</persName>. Previously, the United States had followed a policy of
                    recognizing Mexican governments as they came into effective control of Mexico,
                    but Evarts decided to act differently. He placed several conditions on his
                    recognition of the Díaz government, most importantly the right of U.S. troops to
                    cross the Mexican border in pursuit of Indian raiders.</p>
                <p>Díaz’s government responded with a condemnation of the demands and moved troops
                    to the border. War seemed possible, particularly since Diaz’s opposition accused
                    him of a potential willingness to bow to U.S. pressure. Under the threat of
                    congressional investigation, Evarts backed down and extended recognition, but
                    did not withdraw the order allowing pursuit across the border until 1880. </p>
                <p>Evarts also faced domestic challenges from anti-immigration supporters on the
                    West Coast, who began to make stronger demands that Chinese immigrants be
                    prevented from entering the United States despite the provisions of the 1868
                        <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/burlingame-seward-treaty">Burlingame-Seward Treaty</ref>.</p>
                <p>In 1880, Evarts sent a committee to negotiate with the Chinese Government in an
                    effort to secure Chinese endorsement of restrictions on immigration. Chinese
                    officials were unwilling to allow an outright ban, but were willing to agree to
                    limits. Evarts also unsuccessfully attempted to negotiate peace between Chile,
                    Peru and Bolivia during the War of the Pacific. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Barrows, Chester L. <hi rend="italic">William M. Evarts: Lawyer, Diplomat,
                            Statesman.</hi> Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press,
                        1941.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dyer, Brainerd. <hi rend="italic">The Public Career of William M.
                            Evarts.</hi> New York: Da Capo Press, 1969.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“William Maxwell Evarts,” in <hi rend="italic">Biographical Directory of
                            the United States Congress.</hi> Accessed June 27, 2008. <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=E000262">http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=E000262</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>