<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Edward
                    Everett</title>
                <title type="short">Edward Everett</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Edward Everett</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Millard Fillmore</persName> on November 6, 1852, and entered
                    into duty on the same day. Although President Fillmore appointed Everett to
                    succeed <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/webster-daniel">Daniel
                        Webster</ref>, Everett was sworn in after Fillmore was defeated in his
                    reelection bid, and served in the position for only four months, ending his
                    service on March 3, 1853. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="everett-edward.jpg"/>
                    <head>Edward Everett, 20th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Everett was born in Dorchester, Massachusetts. Upon his father’s death at an
                    early age, his family moved to Boston where he graduated from Harvard College in
                    1811. Like his father, Everett became a pastor for a Unitarian Church in Boston
                    in 1814. Everett continued his education in Europe and received his Ph.D. from
                    the University of Göttingen in 1817. Everett returned to Harvard in 1819 where
                    he served as chair of Greek Literature for the following six years.</p>
                <p>In 1825 he was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives where he served until
                    1835. The following year, he was elected Governor of Massachusetts and served
                    four one-year terms.</p>
                <p>In 1841, Secretary of State Daniel Webster appointed Everett Minister to Great
                    Britain, a position he held for four years. Upon his return, he became the
                    president of Harvard University. Following the death of Everett’s friend, Daniel
                    Webster, President Fillmore appointed Everett to take his place as Secretary of
                    State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Dipolmacy</head>
                <p>As Webster’s successor, Everett had a relatively unremarkable and very short
                    tenure. One of Everett’s first acts as Secretary was to draft a formal letter to
                    the Emperor of Japan for the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/opening-to-japan">Perry Expedition</ref>,
                    which facilitated Japanese trade with the West.</p>
                <p>He was also charged with dispelling a potential diplomatic crisis with Peru over
                    territorial claims to guano-rich Lobos Island. </p>
                <p>The highlight of Everett's short-lived tenure was his contribution to shaping
                    U.S. policy toward Cuba. Great Britain and France had proposed a tripartite
                    guarantee of Spanish sovereignty over Cuba in 1852. Everett rejected the
                    proposal, responding firmly that Cuba was to remain a U.S. matter and that the
                    United States maintained its aversion to “entangling alliances.”</p>
                <p>A respected orator and writer, Everett won praise for his apt expression of
                    deep-rooted U.S. principles in foreign policy matters. When the new
                    administration under <persName>Franklin Pierce</persName> began in March of
                    1853, Everett’s term as Secretary of State ended.</p>
                <p>Upon his departure from the Department of State, he was immediately elected
                    Senator from his home state of Massachusetts. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “Edward Everett.” <hi rend="italic">The American
                            Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy,</hi> edited by Samuel Flagg Bemis.
                        Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square
                        Publishers, Inc.). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Frothingham, Paul R. <hi rend="italic">Edward Everett: Orator and
                            Statesman.</hi> Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1925. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>