<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Hamilton
                    Fish</title>
                <title type="short">Hamilton Fish</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Hamilton Fish was appointed Secretary of State by President <persName>Ulysses S.
                        Grant</persName> on March 11, 1869, and began his duties on March 16. Fish
                    served until March 11, 1877. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="fish-hamilton.jpg"/>
                    <head>Hamilton Fish, 26th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Fish</persName> was born in New York, New York, on August 3, 1808, and
                    graduated from Columbia University in 1827. He became a lawyer and also managed
                    his extensive family holdings. Subsequently, Fish entered politics, running
                    unsuccessfully for the New York State Senate in 1833. Thereafter, he ran
                    intermittently for various offices, winning a term in U.S. Congress in 1842, and
                    was elected Lieutenant Governor of New York in 1847 after an unsuccessful
                    campaign the previous year.</p>
                <p>Fish was elected Governor of New York in 1848, and then to a term in the U.S.
                    Senate in 1851. When the Whig Party disintegrated, he joined the newly formed
                    Republican Party, partly because he saw Democratic policies toward Cuba as
                    unethical and unwise.</p>
                <p>During the Secession Crisis, Fish was involved in attempts to resupply Fort
                    Sumter. During the Civil War, he served as chair of the Union Defense Committee
                    of New York as well as on a commission to watch over the condition of Union
                    prisoners of war and prisoner exchanges.</p>
                <p>As a result of Senate objections over Grant’s initial Cabinet choices in 1869,
                    James F. Wilson, the original nominee for Secretary of State, withdrew, and
                    Grant asked Hamilton Fish to serve in his place.</p>
                <p>Fish was surprised by the offer and initially declined, but ultimately accepted
                    after Grant sent his nomination to the Senate without waiting for Fish’s reply.
                    After completing his service as Secretary of State in 1877, he retired from
                    politics.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Upon becoming Secretary of State, Fish first faced the challenges related to the
                    unpopular Johnson-Clarendon Convention, an agreement made to resolve Civil War
                    disputes over issues such as the British-built Confederate warship Alabama. On
                    April 13, 1869, the Senate overwhelmingly rejected the Convention.</p>
                <p>U.S. attempts to continue to press claims stemming from British recognition of
                    the Confederacy’s belligerent status were hampered by the possibility that the
                    United States had considered granting the same status to anti-Spanish rebels in
                    Cuba.</p>
                <p>The Americas were central to Fish’s foreign policy. Working with President Grant,
                    he tried unsuccessfully to acquire new territory in the Dominican Republic, as
                    well as the lands controlled by Hudson’s Bay Company, which the British
                    Government instead sold to Canada in 1870.</p>
                <p>In 1868, a revolt against Spanish rule began in Cuba that became known as the Ten
                    Years’ War. In the United States, Spanish attempts to crush the insurgency
                    aroused strong public sympathy for Cubans. Fish worked closely with Senator
                        <persName>Charles Sumner</persName> to formulate a policy on the Cuban
                    situation. They recommended and finally convinced Grant not to recognize Cuban
                    rebels as belligerents in an effort to protect American commerce and maintain
                    peace with Spain.</p>
                <p>Over the next several years, incidents involving Spanish attempts to suppress the
                    rebellion in Cuba led to diplomatic tensions. Fish eventually began to pressure
                    Spanish officials to consider granting Cuban independence and ending slavery on
                    the island. The Spanish Government did neither during Fish’s tenure.</p>
                <p>Eventually, on February 4, 1877, U.S. Minister <persName>Caleb Cushing</persName>
                    signed a protocol with Spanish Foreign Minister <persName>Fernando
                        Calderón</persName>, in which Spain agreed to greater due process for U.S.
                    citizens in Cuba.</p>
                <p>Later in Fish’s tenure as Secretary of State, he faced Indian raids and poor law
                    enforcement along the border with Mexico, an issue which would escalate under
                    Fish’s successor <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/evarts-william-maxwell"
                        >William Evarts</ref>. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gluek, Alvin. “The Riel Rebellion and Canadian-American Relations.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Canadian Historical Review</hi> 36(1955): 199-221.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nevins, Allan. <hi rend="italic">Hamilton Fish: The Inner History of the
                            Grant Administration.</hi> New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1937.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
