<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Forsyth</title>
                <title type="short">John Forsyth</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>John Forsyth was appointed Secretary of State by President <persName>Andrew
                        Jackson</persName> on <date when="1834-06-27">June 27, 1834.</date> He
                    entered duty on July 1, 1834, and completed his tenure on <date
                        when="1841-03-03">March 3, 1841</date>, during the administration of
                    President <persName>Martin Van Buren.</persName> Forsyth faithfully served two
                    Presidents who both held close control over foreign policy. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="forsyth-john.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Forsyth, 13th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Forsyth was born in Fredericksburg, Virginia and moved to Augusta, Georgia as a
                    boy. He graduated from the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University) in
                    1799. After studying the law, Forsyth gained admission to the Georgia bar in
                    1802 and began a legal practice in Augusta. In 1808 he gained an appointment to
                    serve as Georgia’s Attorney General.</p>
                <p>Forsyth was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives and served from 1813 to
                    1818. He next won election to the U.S. Senate, serving from 1818 to 1819. In
                    1819 President <persName>James Monroe</persName> appointed Forsyth as U.S.
                    Minister to Spain, an appointment that lasted until 1823. Forsyth returned to
                    the United States and the U.S. House of Representatives in 1823, serving until
                    1827, when he began two years as Governor of Georgia. In 1829 he returned to the
                    U.S. Senate, where he cemented his reputation as a powerful debater. He served
                    until 1834. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on U.S. Diplomacy</head>
                <p>When he became Secretary of State, Forsyth brought with him some prior experience
                    with foreign affairs. As U.S. Minister to Spain, he assisted in securing the
                    ratification of the 1819 <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/florida">Adams-Onís
                        Treaty</ref>, which ceded Spain’s claim to East and West Florida. His open
                    criticism of the Spanish Government, however, earned him an official rebuke.</p>
                <p>While a U.S. Congressmen, Forsyth was a leading proponent of Indian removal, the
                    withdrawal of U.S. recognition of tribal sovereignty, and the numerous Indian
                    Treaties. President Jackson appointed Forsyth Secretary of State as a reward for
                    political support and consistently ensured that Forsyth followed his lead on
                    foreign policy. Together, they finally concluded the long-standing controversy
                    over the damages inflicted by France upon U.S. foreign commerce during the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/napoleonic-wars">Napoleonic Wars</ref>.</p>
                <p>In 1834 Jackson urged Congress to pass legislation to seize French property
                    unless the French Government released the payments stipulated in an 1831
                    settlement treaty. Jackson’s bellicose stance convinced the French Government to
                    sever relations with the United States. However, a clarification by Jackson—that
                    he had not intended to insult France—ended the impasse and the payments began.
                    The French Government committed to a $5 million payment to settle outstanding
                    U.S. claims and the U.S. Government reduced the import duty on French wines.</p>
                <p>Forsyth also cautiously coordinated with President Jackson on the U.S.
                    recognition of the independent <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">Republic of Texas</ref> in
                    1837.</p>
                <p>Under Van Buren’s presidency, Forsyth supported the President’s decision against
                    annexing Texas. Forsyth also backed Van Buren’s calm approach to the dispute
                    with Great Britain over the U.S.-Canadian border, which was complicated by the
                    aggressive stance of the Maine State Government. Forsyth also issued strong
                    statements denying British claims to the right to search U.S. vessels for slaves
                    off the African coast. Finally, Forsyth labored in vain to diffuse the
                    controversy stirred by the <hi rend="italic">Amistad</hi> case of 1839.
                    Ultimately, the Supreme Court held against the Van Buren administration’s
                    position, and the African slaves were returned to Sierra Leone in 1842. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 4. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Curtis, James C. <hi rend="italic">The Fox at Bay: Martin Van Buren and
                            the Presidency, 1837-1841.</hi> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky,
                        1970. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Duckett, Alvin L. <hi rend="italic">John Forsyth: Political
                            Tactician.</hi> Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1962.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Remini, Robert V. <hi rend="italic">Andrew Jackson: The Course of American
                            Democracy, 1833-1845.</hi> Vol. 3. New York: Harper and Row, 1984. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Stevens, Kenneth R. <hi rend="italic">Border Diplomacy: The Caroline and
                            McLeod Affairs in Anglo-American-Canadian Relations, 1837-1842.</hi>
                        Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press, 1989. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
