<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Watson
                    Foster</title>
                <title type="short">John Watson Foster</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>President <persName>Benjamin Harrison</persName> appointed <persName>John Watson
                        Foster</persName> as Secretary of State on June 29, 1892. Foster assumed his
                    duties on that day and served until February 23, 1893. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="foster-john-watson.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Watson Foster, 32nd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p> Foster was born on March 2, 1836, in Pike County, Indiana. He graduated from the
                    State University of Indiana in 1855 and then attended Harvard Law School. Foster
                    moved to Cincinnati, passed the bar, and practiced law until 1861, when he
                    joined the Union Army as a major. Foster rose to the rank of colonel in
                    1864.</p>
                <p> Following his military duty, Foster returned to Indiana politics, was appointed
                    Evansville Postmaster in 1869, and worked to build support for the re-election
                    of <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> in 1872.</p>
                <p>In return for his campaign work, Foster served as Minister to Mexico between 1873
                    and 1880. He then served as Minister to <placeName>Russia</placeName> from 1880
                    to 1881. After a brief return to private practice, Foster assumed duties as
                    Minister to <placeName>Spain</placeName> in 1883 and served until 1885,
                    whereupon he again returned to private practice and served as counsel
                    representing foreign diplomatic legations in the United States.</p>
                <p>In 1892, President Harrison appointed Foster as Secretary of State.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Foster served as Minister to <placeName>Mexico</placeName> during the rise to
                    power of <persName>Porfirio Díaz</persName> in 1876. Foster supported
                    recognition of Díaz’s rule, but was overruled by then Secretary of State, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/evarts-william-maxwell">William
                        Evarts</ref>. As the tensions rose between the two countries, Foster
                    testified before Congress, carefully advocating recognition without appearing to
                    undermine Evarts or President <persName>Rutherford B. Hayes</persName>. In the
                    end, Foster was able to secure recognition for the new Mexican government. While
                    serving in Mexico, Foster also began the negotiations to resolve U.S.-Mexico
                    border troubles that eventually led to an 1882 agreement. </p>
                <p>As Minister to Russia, Foster’s most pressing duty was to advocate for the rights
                    of Jewish U.S. citizens living there. As Minister to
                        <placeName>Spain</placeName>, Foster secured a reciprocal trade agreement
                    for the Spanish colonies of Cuba and Puerto Rico in 1885, but the U.S. Senate
                    rejected the agreement.</p>
                <p>While serving as legal counsel to foreign legations in Washington, following his
                    post in Spain, Foster provided legal representation for the Chinese Government
                    seeking redress for an anti-immigration riot that killed twenty-eight Chinese
                    laborers in Rock Springs, Wyoming in 1885. Foster also advocated on behalf of
                    the Chinese Government during negotiations to overcome the exclusion of Chinese
                    immigration to the United States and would continue to represent the Chinese
                    Government in later years.</p>
                <p>Foster became Secretary of State in 1892 and served for the remaining eight
                    months of Harrison’s administration. Foster had already forged a close working
                    relationship with Harrison, as he was involved in negotiations for numerous
                    trade agreements in the Western Hemisphere, and continued to be as Secretary of
                    State.</p>
                <p>As Secretary, Foster also attempted to counter British attempts at imperial
                    expansion in Samoa and the Mosquito Coast. Foster also worked to negotiate a
                    99-year lease for a naval base in the <placeName>Dominican Republic</placeName>,
                    but financial demands by the Dominican Government made Congress unwilling to
                    approve the lease.</p>
                <p>Foster instructed U.S. representatives at the International Monetary Conference
                    in Brussels to advocate for a fixed rate of exchange between silver and gold,
                    but the conference came to no agreement on precious metal issues. Foster also
                    unsuccessfully attempted to <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/hawaii">annex the
                        Kingdom of Hawaii.</ref>
                </p>
                <p>After leaving office in 1893, Foster represented the United States in
                    international arbitration regarding seal hunting rights in the Bering Sea and
                    before the Alaskan Boundary Tribunal in the 1890s. At the time of his death on
                    November 15, 1917, Foster’s son-in-law <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert Lansing </ref>was
                    serving as Secretary of State. Foster was also the grandfather of future
                    Secretary <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster">John Foster
                        Dulles</ref>. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “John W. Foster.” <hi rend="italic">The American
                            Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy,</hi> edited by Samuel Flagg
                        Bemis. Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square
                        Publishers, Inc.). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Devine, Michael J. <hi rend="italic">John W. Foster: Politics and
                            Diplomacy in the Imperial Era, 1873-1917.</hi> Athens: Ohio
                        University Press, 1981.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
