<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Frederick Theodore Frelinghuysen</title>
                <title type="short">Frederick Theodore Frelinghuysen</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Frederick Theodore Frelinghuysen</persName> was appointed Secretary of
                    State by President <persName>Chester A. Arthur</persName> and served from
                    December 19, 1881, to March 5, 1885. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="frelinghuysen-frederick.jpg"/>
                    <head>Frederick Theodore Frelinghuysen, 29th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Frelinghuysen was born at Millstone, New Jersey on August 4, 1817. He graduated
                    from Rutgers College (now University) in 1836. His uncle and adoptive father
                    Theodore Frelinghuysen was a Senator from New Jersey and Vice Presidential
                    candidate on the Whig ticket in 1844.</p>
                <p>Frelinghuysen studied law and was admitted to the bar in 1839. He served as
                    Attorney General of New Jersey from 1861 to 1866, and as U.S. Senator from New
                    Jersey from 1866 to 1869. Although he was not re-elected in 1869, he ran
                    successfully in 1870, and served from 1871 to 1877.</p>
                <p> In 1877, Frelinghuysen served on the Hayes-Tilden Electoral Commission. He
                    worked in a private law practice from 1877 until he was appointed Secretary of
                    State by President <persName>Chester A. Arthur</persName>. Frelinghuysen served
                    until the end of Arthur’s term, resigning on March 5, 1885. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Frelinghuysen inherited a number of diplomatic issues from
                    his predecessor, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">James G. Blaine</ref>. He continued Blaine’s unsuccessful attempts to
                    mediate peace negotiations between <placeName>Peru</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Bolivia</placeName>, and <placeName>Chile</placeName>.
                    Frelinghuysen appointed <persName>Cornelius A. Logan</persName> as Minister to
                        <placeName>Chile</placeName>. Logan mediated the 1883 peace agreement
                    between Chile and Peru, terminating the War of the Pacific with the Treaty of
                    Ancón on October 23, 1883. Despite the achievement of peace, diplomatic blunders
                    in Chile and Peru and Bolivia’s territorial losses remained an ongoing source
                    of tension between the United States and South America. </p>
                <p> Against President Arthur’s wishes, Frelinghuysen canceled the Pan-American
                    Conference that Blaine had organized before his departure. Arthur brought the
                    issue before Congress, which took no action, and the invitations for the
                    conference were withdrawn. Frelinghuysen remained concerned that past U.S.
                    actions had encouraged negative attitudes towards U.S. power and suspicion of
                    possible intervention. He also remained wary of being drawn into mediating
                    disputes between neighbors. These concerns prompted the U.S. Government to
                    refuse to arbitrate in the emerging boundary dispute between Venezuela and
                    Britain over Guyana’s western border.</p>
                <p> Concerned about European construction in the Panama Canal, Frelinghuysen
                    unsuccessfully attempted to renegotiate the 1850 <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/panama-canal">Clayton-Bulwer Treaty</ref> with
                    Great Britain. He negotiated an 1884 treaty with Nicaragua granting the United
                    States exclusive rights to construct and control a transoceanic canal—terms
                    which directly contradicted the Clayton-Bulwer Treaty. The U.S. Senate failed to
                    ratify the treaty.</p>
                <p> In addition to his efforts in Latin America, Frelinghuysen also instructed
                    delegates to the 1884 Berlin Conference, where German leader Otto von Bismarck
                    sought to mediate the European scramble for Africa. Frelinghuysen also oversaw
                    and approved Rear Admiral Robert Shufeldt’s attempt to secure a treaty with
                    Korea. Frelinghuysen served as Secretary of State until the end of Arthur’s term
                    and died shortly afterwards in Newark, New Jersey, on May 20, 1885. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg Bemis, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries
                            of State and Their Diplomacy. </hi>Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf,
                        1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.). </bibl>
                    <bibl>“Frederick Theodore Frelinghuysen,” in <ref target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=F000369">Biographical Directory of the United States Congress. </ref> Last
                        accessed July 28, 2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>