<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Walter Quintin
                    Gresham</title>
                <title type="short">Walter Quintin Gresham</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> President <persName>Grover Cleveland</persName> nominated <persName>Walter
                        Quintin Gresham</persName> to be Secretary of State on March 6, 1893, and
                    Gresham entered into duty on March 7. Gresham died in office on May 28, 1895. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="gresham-walter-quintin.jpg"/>
                    <head>Walter Quintin Gresham, 33rd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Gresham was born in Harrison County, Indiana, on March 17, 1832. He attended
                    Indiana State University, subsequently studied law, and was admitted to the bar
                    in 1854. He entered politics and won a seat in the State legislature as a
                    Republican in 1860.</p>
                <p>During the Civil War, Gresham served as a lieutenant-colonel in the Union Army,
                    and eventually rose to the rank of brevet major general. In 1866, after
                    returning to civilian life, he served as an Indiana Agent of State, managing the
                    state debt.</p>
                <p>Gresham was defeated in races for the U.S. Congress in 1866 and 1868, but was
                    appointed U.S. District Judge for Indiana by President <persName>Ulysses S.
                        Grant</persName> in 1869. Gresham left his judgeship when he was appointed
                    Postmaster-General by President Chester A. Arthur in 1883, and served in that
                    capacity until 1884, when he became Secretary of the Treasury for the remainder
                    of the Arthur administration.</p>
                <p>Gresham ran as a candidate for the Republican Party presidential primaries in
                    1884 and 1888. In 1893, President Grover Cleveland (a Democrat) in a bipartisan
                    gesture asked Gresham to serve as Secretary of State. Gresham, dissatisfied with
                    the direction of the Republican Party, accepted Cleveland’s offer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As soon as he assumed his position as Secretary of State, Gresham began
                    investigating the circumstances surrounding the failed U.S. attempt to annex
                    Hawaii under his predecessor, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/foster-john-watson">John W. Foster</ref>.
                    Gresham’s investigation showed the direct involvement of U.S. diplomats in the
                    overthrow of Queen Liliuokalani. On the advice of Attorney General
                        <persName>Richard Olney</persName>, President Cleveland decided to withdraw
                    the treaty of annexation before the Senate. Since the Queen’s overthrow was
                    essentially a coup by pro-American sugar planters intent on eliminating Native
                    Hawaiian political power, Cleveland hoped to restore Liliuokalni to power.
                    However, the Senate declined to give Cleveland the authority to do so. </p>
                <p>Gresham also worked to counter British influence in the Americas, citing the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref> as his guiding
                    principle. He warned <persName>Julian Pauncefote</persName>, the British
                    Ambassador to the United States, against British involvement in an 1895 royalist
                    Brazilian coup attempt. However, when the Nicaraguan President <persName>José
                        Zelaya</persName> attempted to exert a Nicaraguan claim to the Mosquito
                    Coast in 1894, Gresham worked in concert with the British Government to ensure
                    the continued commercial privileges of resident Americans in the region. The
                    U.S. Government would later intervene to remove Zelaya from power in 1911. </p>
                <p>In addition to his attention to Western Hemisphere concerns, Gresham encountered
                    ongoing problems regarding the status and treatment of U.S. citizens in the
                    Ottoman Empire. The Ottoman Government, at times, refused re-entry of emigrants
                    who had become U.S. citizens. Gresham found that his attempts to secure rights
                    for U.S. citizens, particularly during a time of Turkish-Armenian tensions, were
                    rebuffed by <persName>Sultan Abdulhamid II</persName>. Gresham tried to walk a
                    fine line between doing what was possible for U.S. citizens in the empire, while
                    continuing a policy of non-intervention in European affairs, particularly those
                    concerning the internal affairs of the Great Powers. This sensitive position led
                    Gresham to reject calls by missionaries for a U.S. naval base in Smyrna. </p>
                <p>Gresham’s tenure as Secretary of State was cut short by his unexpected death on
                    May 28, 1895 in Washington, D.C. Owing to the suddenness of his death, President
                    Cleveland did not appoint a replacement until June 8. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Calhoun, Charles W. <hi rend="italic">Gilded Age Cato: The Life of Walter
                            Q. Gresham.</hi> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1988. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
