<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Alexander Meigs
                    Haig, Jr.</title>
                <title type="short">Alexander Meigs Haig, Jr.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Alexander Meigs Haig, Jr.</persName> was appointed Secretary of State
                    by President <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName> and assumed the office on
                    January 22, 1981. He served a relatively short time in office, facing many
                    challenging situations before stepping down on July 5, 1982. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="haig-alexander-meigs.jpg"/>
                    <head>Alexander Meigs Haig, Jr., 59th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p> Born and raised in Philadelphia, Haig attended the University of Notre Dame
                    before transferring to the United States Military Academy at West Point. After
                    graduating from the Academy in 1947, he embarked on a long and successful career
                    in the military, serving with distinction in both <placeName>Korea</placeName>
                    and in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Upon completing graduate studies at Georgetown University in 1962, he worked at
                    the Pentagon under both Secretary of the Army <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/vance-cyrus-roberts">Cyrus Vance</ref> and
                    Secretary of Defense <persName>Robert McNamara</persName>. In 1969 he became
                    military adviser to <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kissinger-henry-a"
                        >Henry Kissinger</ref>, and then Deputy Assistant to the President for
                    National Security in 1971. He served as Chief of Staff for Presidents
                        <persName>Richard Nixon</persName> and <persName>Gerald Ford</persName> in
                    1973-74, and then became Supreme Allied Commander in Europe in 1974, a position
                    that he held until he resigned on January 3, 1979. After two years in the
                    private sector, he returned to government service when President Reagan selected
                    him to be Secretary of State.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Haig had hoped to restore the Department of State to the
                    dominant position in foreign policy-making that it had lost during previous
                    administrations. However, the United States faced many challenges during the
                    time that Haig served as Secretary of State, including the Soviet presence in
                    Afghanistan, the Solidarity movement in Poland, disputes with the People’s
                    Republic of China over trade and Taiwan, escalating tensions between the United
                    Kingdom and Argentina, and a new round of conflict between Israel, Lebanon, and
                    Syria. He also had to deal with the intra-government turmoil that followed in
                    the wake of the attempted assassination of President Reagan.</p>
                <p>Haig did have some diplomatic successes, particularly in regards to relations
                    with China, where he forged a balance that both stabilized relations with the
                    PRC and allowed for the continuation of arms sales to the government on
                    Taiwan.</p>
                <p> He also strengthened the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">NATO</ref>
                    alliance and helped to re-orient the focus of U.S. foreign policy back toward
                    the Soviet Union, both of which reflected the overall foreign policy priorities
                    of the Reagan Administration.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, his efforts to broker diplomatic resolutions to the disputes over
                    the Falkland Islands and in the Middle East did not succeed. Throughout his
                    tenure as Secretary, Haig was overshadowed in foreign policy matters by other
                    members of the Administration and was thus unable to fully control the
                    Administration’s diplomatic process. He resigned from office after only 18
                    months.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bell, Coral. <hi rend="italic">The Reagan Paradox: American Foreign Policy
                            in the 1980s.</hi> London: Edward Elgar Publishing Limited, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fischer, Beth. <hi rend="italic">The Reagan Reversal: Foreign Policy and
                            the End of the Cold War.</hi> Columbia: University of Missouri Press,
                        1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Haig, Alexander M. Jr., with Charles McCarry <hi rend="italic">Inner
                            Circles: How America Changed the World, A Memoir.</hi> New York: Warner
                        Books, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Haig, Alexander M., Jr. <hi rend="italic">Caveat: Realism, Reagan, and
                            Foreign Policy. </hi> New York: Macmillan Publishing Company,
                        1984.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Morris, Roger. <hi rend="italic">Haig, the General’s Progress.</hi> New
                        York: Playboy Press, 1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schaller, Michael. <hi rend="italic">Reckoning with Reagan: America and
                            Its President in the 1980s.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press,
                        1992.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
