<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Hay</title>
                <title type="short">John Hay</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>John Milton Hay</persName> was appointed Secretary of State in
                    President <persName>William McKinley</persName>’s Cabinet on September 30, 1898,
                    and entered into duty the same day. He continued in office under President
                        <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName> following McKinley’s assassination
                    in 1901 and served until his death in office on July 1, 1905. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="hay-john-milton.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Milton Hay, 37th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Hay was born in Salem, Indiana in 1838 to a physician who had moved westward from
                    Virginia, living for a time in Kentucky and eventually settling in Indiana.
                    Educated first at home and then at a private academy, Hay attended Illinois
                    State College in 1852. Three years later, he enrolled in Brown University and
                    graduated in 1858. Hay studied law in the office of his uncle and was admitted
                    to the Illinois bar in 1861. During this time, he met <persName>Abraham
                        Lincoln</persName> and played a small part in his presidential campaign.
                    After Lincoln’s election, the new President selected Hay as his private
                    secretary.</p>
                <p>Following the U.S. Civil War, Hay served in multiple diplomatic posts, including
                    those of Paris, Vienna, and Madrid. In 1870, he left the diplomatic service to
                    write. He would eventually publish a ten-volume study of Lincoln, co-written
                    with John Nicolay.</p>
                <p>Hay returned to public service in 1896 when newly elected President McKinley
                    appointed him Ambassador to Great Britain. He was offered the position as
                    Secretary of State while the United States negotiated the peace treaty with
                    Spain after winning the Spanish-American War. He accepted the offer and entered
                    into duty in September of 1898. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Hay had a significant influence on the direction of U.S. foreign policy while
                    serving in President McKinley’s Cabinet. He faced the aftermath of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">Spanish-American
                        War</ref> and the annexation of the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/war"
                        >Philippine Islands</ref>, which amplified U.S. interest in Asia.</p>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Hay was a proponent of increased trade through the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/hay-and-china">"Open Door"</ref> policy. He
                    worked to encourage stability in China and to counteract the rising nationalism
                    that threatened foreign interests in China, which included the challenge of the
                    Boxer Rebellion of 1900.</p>
                <p>As Secretary, Hay also secured the settlement of the Alaska-Canada boundary
                    controversy. When President McKinley was assassinated, Hay stayed on as
                    Secretary of State to serve under President Theodore Roosevelt. Roosevelt and
                    Hay had few policy differences, although the new President wielded greater
                    influence over foreign policy than his predecessor.</p>
                <p>Hay helped secure, by treaty, the right for the United States to construct and
                    defend the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/panama-canal">Panama Canal</ref>
                    in 1903.</p>
                <p>Although he suffered from deteriorating health, Hay played an active role in the
                    Roosevelt administration during the last two years of his tenure. He died in
                    office in 1905. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped. </hi>New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell. </hi>Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
