<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Christian Archibald
                    Herter</title>
                <title type="short">Christian Archibald Herter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> Christian A. Herter was appointed Secretary of State on April 22, 1959, and
                    remained in that position until the end of the Dwight D. Eisenhower
                    administration on January 20, 1961. Whether working for the U.S. Government or
                    in the private sector, Herter dedicated much of his adult life to serving his
                    country and shaping its role in world affairs.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="herter-christian-archibald.jpg"/>
                    <head>Christian Archibald Herter, 53rd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Herter was born in Paris, France, on March 28, 1895, and attended the École
                    Alsatienne from 1901 to 1904, before moving to New York City and graduating from
                    the Browning School in 1911. Upon receiving a bachelor’s degree from Harvard
                    University in 1915, Herter served in the U.S. Embassy in Germany from 1916 to
                    1917.</p>
                <p>He held the position of Secretary of the U.S. Commission to Negotiate Peace
                    (1918-1919) at the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Paris Peace
                        Conference</ref> following the First World War. After his initial tenure at
                    the Department of State, Herter continued to advance his career in both the
                    public and private arenas. He was the Personal Assistant to Secretary of
                    Commerce Herbert Hoover from 1919 to 1924, during which time he also served as
                    Executive Secretary of the European Relief Council between 1920 and 1921. </p>
                <p>He subsequently worked as a newspaper editor and a lecturer at Harvard
                    University. He served in the Massachusetts House of Representatives from 1931 to
                    1943, where he became Speaker of the House in 1939. Herter then won a seat in
                    the U. S. Congress as a Representative from Massachusetts, where he served until
                    1953. Following his time in Congress, Herter was elected Governor of
                    Massachusetts in 1953, a position he held until 1957, when he became Under
                    Secretary of State in President Eisenhower’s second administration.</p>
                <p>Due to the failing health of Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster">John Foster
                        Dulles</ref>, Herter was appointed Secretary of State on April 22, 1959, and
                    remained in that position until January 20, 1961. Herter passed away in
                    Washington, D.C., on December 30, 1966.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Herter played an active role in U.S. diplomacy throughout his life, whether he
                    was working for the Department of State or the U.S. House of Representatives.
                    While in Congress, a report that was written in a committee he chaired initiated
                    proposals that led to President <persName>Harry Truman</persName>’s <ref
                        target="/milestones/1945-1952/marshall-plan">Marshall Plan</ref>, in which
                    the United States gave $13 billion in reconstruction aid to Europe following the
                    Second World War.</p>
                <p>Along with scholar George Camp Keiser, Herter founded the Middle East Institute
                    in 1947, and he also served on the board of trustees of the World Peace
                    Foundation. As Under Secretary of State and Secretary of State, Herter helped
                    oversee U.S. diplomacy during the 1958 invasion of Lebanon, the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/taiwan-strait-crises">1958 Taiwan Strait
                        Crisis</ref>, and the U-2 incident in 1960.</p>
                <p> Herter’s role in the international arena did not end with the Eisenhower
                    administration. He also served as a trade negotiator in the administrations of
                    both <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> and <persName>Lyndon B.
                        Johnson</persName>. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Herter, Christian A. <hi rend="italic">Toward an Atlantic Community.</hi>
                        New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1963.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hogan, Michael J. <hi rend="italic">The Marshall Plan: America, Britain,
                            and the Reconstruction of Western Europe, 1947-1952.</hi> New York:
                        Cambridge University Press, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Noble, George Bernard. "Christian A. Herter." In <hi rend="italic">The
                            American Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy,</hi> edited by Samuel
                        Flagg Bemis. New York: Cooper Square Publishers, 1970.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wicker, Tom. <hi rend="italic">Dwight D. Eisenhower. </hi> Waterville, ME:
                        Thorndike Press, 2002.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
