<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Charles Evans Hughes</title>
                <title type="short">Charles Evans Hughes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Charles Evans Hughes</persName> served as Secretary of State from
                    March 5, 1921, to March 5, 1925, during the administration of President
                        <persName>Warren Harding</persName>. He continued as Secretary after
                    Harding’s death in office, but resigned at the beginning of President
                        <persName>Calvin Coolidge</persName>’s full term. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="hughes-charles-evans.jpg"/>
                    <head>Charles Evans Hughes, 44th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p> Hughes was born in Glen Falls, New York in 1862. That same year his family moved to New
                    York City, where he was raised and attended school. He graduated from Brown
                    University at the age of nineteen, with the second highest honors.</p>
                <p>Hughes was a prominent public figure long before becoming Secretary of State. He
                    had been a noted anti-corruption attorney in New York before being elected
                    Governor of that state in 1906. He was then appointed to the Supreme Court by
                    President <persName>William Howard Taft</persName>, a position from which he
                    resigned in the summer of 1916 to run for President against incumbent
                        <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> as the candidate of the Republican
                    Party.</p>
                <p> After losing the 1916 presidential election, Hughes re-entered public life as
                    President <persName>Warren G. Harding</persName>’s choice as Secretary of State.
                    After Harding’s death and <persName>Calvin Coolidge</persName>’s election,
                    Hughes resigned from the post in favor of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kellogg-frank-billings">Frank B.
                    Kellogg</ref>, but continued to lead a productive public life. Among his other
                    projects, he served on the Permanent Court of International Justice at The Hague
                    from 1928 until 1930. Newly elected President <persName>Herbert Hoover</persName>
                    reappointed Hughes to the Supreme Court in 1930 as Chief Justice. Hughes served
                    on the Court until 1941. He died in 1948. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Hughes came to the office of Secretary of State at a moment of transition in
                    U.S. politics. President Wilson’s internationalist ideas, grounded in his
                    wartime <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/fourteen-points">Fourteen Points</ref>
                    and his advocacy of a new <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/league">League of
                        Nations</ref> designed to prevent future wars, had been discredited in the
                    United States during the peace negotiations at the end of World War I. Although
                    President Wilson had successfully negotiated the Treaty of Versailles, ending
                    the war and establishing the League, the U.S. Senate had refused to ratify the
                    treaty in 1920, and President Wilson had been unwilling to compromise in order
                    to secure its passage.</p>
                <p>President Harding was elected in part because of his call for a return to
                    “normalcy,” and as a result Hughes implemented a foreign policy that pursued
                    only the most limited connection to the League or the principles of collective
                    security laid out during the Wilson administration. </p>
                <p>Hughes increased U.S. prestige in Latin America by arbitrating disputes between
                    countries in the Western Hemisphere, and during his tenure, the United States
                    recognized the new government in <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and compensated
                        <placeName>Colombia</placeName> for the 1903 Panamanian revolt, which the
                    United States had supported. He also directed the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/naval-conference">Washington Naval Conference
                        of 1921-22</ref>, which resulted in the Five-Power Treaty, setting the
                    ratio of naval strength among the five largest naval powers.</p>
                <p>At the same time, he signed several agreements with the Japanese limiting the
                    deployments of Japanese and U.S. military forces in the Pacific Ocean. He also
                    ended the state of war with Germany with the Treaty of Berlin.</p>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Hughes also worked to improve morale and increase the level
                    of talent in the Department of State by supporting the <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/rogers">1924 Foreign Service Act
                        (“Rogers Act,”)</ref>, which would eventually result in a professional,
                    highly-trained Foreign Service. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy. </hi>Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>