<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Cordell Hull</title>
                <title type="short">Cordell Hull</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Cordell Hull</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by President
                        <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> on March 4, 1933, and served
                    until November 20, 1944. Hull holds the distinction of being the longest-serving
                    U.S. Secretary of State. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="hull-cordell.jpg"/>
                    <head>Cordell Hull, 47th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p> Hull was born on October 2, 1871, near Byrdstown, Tennessee. Although Hull
                    gained admission to the Tennessee bar in 1892 and was appointed a circuit judge
                    in 1903, his great passion was politics.</p>
                <p>Following service on his county’s Democratic Party Executive Committee and in the
                    Tennessee State legislature, Hull was elected to the U.S. House of
                    Representatives in 1906. Hull’s career was nearly derailed when he lost his
                    congressional seat during the Republican Party landslide of 1920. Nevertheless,
                    Hull remained at the center of national politics by becoming Chairman of the
                    Democratic National Committee in 1921 and returned to Congress after a two-year
                    absence.</p>
                <p>In 1928, Hull sought the Democratic Party’s Vice Presidential nomination.
                    Although his bid was unsuccessful, he did secure the support of the Democratic
                    nominee for the governorship of New York, <persName>Franklin Delano
                        Roosevelt</persName>.</p>
                <p>Four years later, as a U.S. Senator, Hull repaid the favor when Roosevelt sought
                    the Presidential nomination. In return for his backing and in order to firm up
                    his support amongst Southern Democrats, President Roosevelt appointed Hull as
                    his Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Hull’s role in U.S. foreign policymaking was greatly
                    circumscribed by President Roosevelt. Hull nonetheless achieved prominence as an
                    advocate of trade liberalization, closer relations with Latin America, and a
                    postwar multinational institution to promote peace and security.</p>
                <p>Although President Roosevelt typically represented the United States at the major
                    conferences with Allied leaders during the Second World War, Hull took the lead
                    in attempting to delay war with <placeName>Japan</placeName> following its
                    invasion of <placeName>China</placeName>. He was also a strong supporter of
                    President Roosevelt’s <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/good-neighbor">“Good
                        Neighbor”</ref> policy and became the first sitting Secretary of State to
                    attend the International Conference of American States (precursor to the
                    Organization of American States). At the December 1933 meeting in
                        <placeName>Montevideo, Uruguay</placeName>, he announced that the U.S.
                    Government would henceforth observe a policy of “non-intervention” in the
                    affairs of its neighbors in the Western Hemisphere.</p>
                <p>His greatest contribution to the postwar world came within the realm of
                    international trade. As a firm believer in <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>’s
                    vision of liberal internationalism, Hull believed that free trade promoted
                    international peace and prosperity. He considered high tariff barriers a
                    pressing issue that had contributed to the economic decline leading to the Great
                    Depression and the rise of fascism.</p>
                <p>In 1934, Hull helped secure the passage of the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act
                    (RTAA), which gave the President the authority to personally negotiate bilateral
                    tariff reductions. </p>
                <p>Hull also championed the creation of the United Nations. For his efforts in
                    creating the United Nations, Hull was honored with the Nobel Peace Prize in
                    1945.</p>
                <p> Cordell Hull resigned as Secretary for health reasons on November 30, 1944, but
                    served as a delegate to the United Nations Conference in San Francisco in 1945.
                    He died in Washington, D.C., on July 23, 1955. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Aaronson, Susan. “How Cordell Hull and the Postwar Planners Designed a New
                        Trade Policy.” <hi rend="italic">Business and Economic History</hi> 20
                        (1991): 171-179.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dallek, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Franklin D. Roosevelt and American
                            Foreign Policy, 1932-1945.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press,
                        1979.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dam, Kenneth W. “Cordell Hull, the Reciprocal Trade Act, and the WTO.” <hi
                            rend="italic">University of Chicago Law &amp; Economics, Olin Working
                            Paper No. 228</hi> (2004). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Drummond, Donald F. “Cordell Hull.” In <hi rend="italic">An Uncertain
                            Tradition: American Secretaries of State in the Twentieth Century,</hi>
                        edited by Norman A. Graebner. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1961.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gellman, Irwin F. “Hull, Cordell.” In <hi rend="italic">American National
                            Biography. </hi> New York: Oxford University Press, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>----. <hi rend="italic">Secret Affairs: Franklin Roosevelt, Cordell Hull,
                            and Sumner Welles.</hi> Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press,
                        1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>O’Sullivan, Christopher D. <hi rend="italic">Sumner Welles, Postwar
                            Planning, and the Quest for a New World Order, 1937–1943. </hi>New York:
                        Columbia University Press, 2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pratt, Julius. “The Ordeal of Cordell Hull” In <hi rend="italic">Review of
                            Politics</hi> 28 (1966), 76-98. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Weil, Martin. <hi rend="italic">A Pretty Good Club: The Founding Fathers
                            of the U.S. Foreign Service.</hi> New York: Norton, 1978.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
