<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Thomas
                    Jefferson</title>
                <title type="short">Thomas Jefferson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName> served as the first Secretary of State
                    from <date when="1790-03-22">March 22, 1790</date>, to <date when="1793-12-31"
                        >December 31, 1793.</date> Jefferson brought remarkable talents to a long
                    career guiding U.S. foreign affairs. He successfully balanced the country’s
                    relatively weak geopolitical position and his fear of expansive federal powers
                    with his desire for U.S. territorial and commercial expansion. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="jefferson-thomas.jpg"/>
                    <head>Thomas Jefferson, First Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Jefferson was born into the Virginia planter elite. He graduated from the College
                    of William &amp; Mary in 1762, studied law, and was admitted to the Virginia bar
                    in 1767. He was elected to the Virginia House of Burgesses in 1769 and served
                    until the British dissolved the House in 1774. Jefferson was a leading activist
                    in the U.S. independence movement. In 1773, he was a founding member of
                    Virginia's <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/secret-committee"> Committee of
                        Correspondence</ref>, which disseminated anti-British views, and, in 1774,
                    he published <hi rend="italic">A Summary View of the Rights of British
                        America</hi>.</p>
                <p>Jefferson was elected as a Delegate to the Second Continental Congress in 1775,
                    and, in 1776 when he was thirty-three years of age, he drafted the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/declaration">Declaration of
                    Independence</ref>. During the Revolutionary War, Jefferson returned to Virginia
                    and served as a Delegate (1776-1779) and then as Governor (1779 and 1780). He
                    served as a Delegate to the Confederation Congress from 1783 to 1784 and played
                    a major role in shaping federal land policy. Jefferson joined <persName>John
                        Adams</persName> and <persName>Benjamin Franklin</persName> in Paris in 1784
                    to negotiate commercial treaties with European powers. The following year, he
                    succeeded Franklin as Minister to France (1785-1789) before becoming Secretary
                    of State.</p>
                <p>A founder of the Democratic-Republican Party, Jefferson was elected Vice
                    President in 1796 and served two terms as President (1801-1809). </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on U.S. Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Jefferson made enormous contributions to U.S. diplomacy. While Minister to
                        <placeName>France</placeName>, he negotiated a commercial treaty with
                    Prussia (1785) and the Consular Convention with France (1788). As Secretary of
                    State, Jefferson’s approach to foreign affairs was limited by Washington’s
                    preference for neutrality regarding the war between Britain and France.
                    Jefferson favored closer ties to France, who had supported the United States
                    during the Revolutionary War. Tension within Washington’s cabinet—notably with
                    Secretary of the Treasury <persName>Alexander Hamilton</persName>, who favored
                    an assertive central government—prompted Jefferson’s resignation.</p>
                <p>As President, Jefferson’s interest in territorial expansion was satisfied by
                        <persName>Napoleon Bonaparte’s</persName> 1803 offer to sell the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/louisiana-purchase">Louisiana Territory</ref>
                    for 15 million dollars. The purchase solved the longstanding dispute over
                    navigation rights on the Mississippi River, and doubled the size of the
                    country.</p>
                <p> Jefferson waged a foreign war, from 1801 to 1805, when he sent U.S. warships to
                    force the Barbary States to cease harassing U.S. shipping. War between France
                    and Great Britain and those states’ infringement of U.S. neutrality inspired
                    Jefferson to push for the 1807 Embargo Act, which prohibited U.S. shipping.
                    Unfortunately, the embargo crippled the U.S. economy and left the nation
                    ill-prepared for the war with Great Britain that would eventually arrive in
                    1812.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl> Appleby, Joyce Oldham. <hi rend="italic">Thomas Jefferson.</hi> New York:
                        Times Books, 2003 </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bernstein, R.B. <hi rend="italic">Thomas Jefferson.</hi> New York: Oxford
                        University Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Boyd, Julian P., et al., eds. <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Thomas
                            Jefferson</hi> 33 vols. to date. Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                        1950-.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaplan, Lawrence S. <hi rend="italic">Jefferson and France: An Essay on
                            Politics and Political Ideas.</hi> 1967. Reprint, Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>McCoy, Drew R. <hi rend="italic">The Elusive Republic: Political Economy
                            in Jeffersonian America.</hi> New York: Norton, 1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Peterson, Merrill D. <hi rend="italic">Thomas Jefferson and the New
                            Nation: A Biography.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press,
                        1970.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Library of Congress: American Memory Collection, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Thomas Jefferson Papers</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
