<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Frank Billings
                    Kellogg</title>
                <title type="short">Frank Billings Kellogg</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Frank Billings Kellogg</persName> served as Secretary of State during
                    the full term of President <persName>Calvin Coolidge</persName> from 1925 until
                    1929, after serving as the U.S. Ambassador to the United Kingdom. He served from
                    March 5, 1925, to March 28, 1929. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="kellogg-frank-billings.jpg"/>
                    <head>Frank Billings Kellogg, 45th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Kellogg was born in Potsdam, New York on December 22, 1856, and moved with his
                    family to Minnesota in 1865.</p>
                <p>Kellogg began his career as an attorney in his home state of Minnesota, first
                    representing large manufacturing concerns and then, as a trust-busting
                    prosecutor during the administration of <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName>.
                    He became president of the American Bar Association in 1912, and was
                    subsequently elected to the U.S. Senate in 1916. He lost his reelection race in
                    1922, but was named to a brief appointment as delegate to the Pan American
                    Conference in 1923 and then was appointed Ambassador to the Court of St. James
                    in London.</p>
                <p> After his term as Secretary of State concluded, Kellogg was selected to fill the
                    term of another former Secretary of State, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-charles-evans">Charles Evans
                        Hughes</ref>, on the Permanent Court of International Justice at The Hague.
                    Kellogg retired from this position in 1936 because of declining health. He died
                    in Minnesota in December of 1937. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Even before he became Secretary of State, Kellogg had great influence. As
                    Ambassador to the <placeName>United Kingdom</placeName>, he influenced U.S.
                    foreign policy, especially regarding the issue of German reparations to the
                    Allies, as outlined in the Treaty of Versailles. Kellogg was one of several
                    important negotiators of the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/dawes">1924
                        Dawes Plan</ref>, a serious attempt to modify the burden of German
                    reparations payments to <placeName>France</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Belgium</placeName>, and the <placeName>United
                        Kingdom</placeName>. </p>
                <p> Once Secretary, he took part in the unsuccessful follow-up to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1921-1936/naval-conference">1921 Washington Naval
                        Conference</ref>, the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/geneva">Geneva
                        Conference of 1927</ref>. He also encountered anti-Americanism at the
                    Western Hemisphere conference in 1928. However, he was successful in negotiating
                    a settlement between Chile and Peru regarding the Tacna-Arica border dispute and
                    negotiating a treaty of arbitration with the Republic of Mexico. He also
                    negotiated or signed nearly 80 other treaties with European and Western
                    Hemisphere states, breaking the record set by <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/bryan-william-jennings">William Jennings
                        Bryan</ref>.</p>
                <p> Kellogg’s most lasting achievement, for which he received the Nobel Peace Prize
                    in 1929, was the negotiation of the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/kellogg"
                        >Kellogg-Briand Pact</ref>. This multilateral pact negotiated between 1927
                    and 1928 with Aristide Briand, the French Foreign Minister, began as a French
                    proposal for a mutual security pact and evolved into a treaty renouncing war as
                    an instrument of national policy. It was ratified overwhelmingly by the U.S.
                    Senate in 1929, despite criticism that it could never be an effective deterrent
                    to war. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Cohen, Warren I. <hi rend="italic">Empire Without Tears: America’s Foreign
                            Relations, 1921-1933.</hi> Philadelphia: Temple University Press,
                        1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ferrell, Robert H. "Frank B. Kellogg &amp; Henry L. Stimson." In <hi
                            rend="italic">The American Secretaries of State and Their
                            Diplomacy,</hi> edited by Samuel Flagg Bemis. Vol. 11. New York: Cooper
                        Square, 1963.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Louria, Margot. <hi rend="italic">Triumph and Downfall: America’s Pursuit
                            of Peace and Prosperity, 1921-1933. </hi>Westport, CT: Greenwood Press,
                        2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
