<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Forbes
                    Kerry</title>
                <title type="short">John Forbes Kerry</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Adapted from Secretary Kerry’s official biography
                    https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/biog/203657.htm (accessed March 17,
                    2021).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>On February 1, 2013, John Forbes Kerry was sworn in as the 68th Secretary of
                    State of the United States, becoming the first sitting Senate Foreign Relations
                    Committee Chairman to become Secretary in over a century.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="kerry-john-forbes.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Forbes Kerry, 68th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Secretary Kerry joined the State Department after 28 years in the United States
                    Senate, the last four as Chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.</p>
                <p>Secretary Kerry was born on December 11, 1943, at Fitzsimons Army Hospital in
                    Aurora, Colorado, one of four children of the late Rosemary Forbes Kerry and
                    Richard Kerry, a Foreign Service Officer.</p>
                <p>Shortly before he graduated from Yale University, Secretary Kerry enlisted to
                    serve in the United States Navy, and went on to serve two tours of duty. He
                    served in combat as a Swift Boat skipper patrolling the rivers of the Mekong
                    Delta, returning home from Vietnam with a Silver Star, a Bronze Star with Combat
                    V, and three Purple Hearts.</p>
                <p>Back in the United States, Secretary Kerry began to forcefully speak out against
                    the Vietnam War. Testifying at the invitation of Chairman J. William Fulbright
                    before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, he asked the poignant question,
                    "How do you ask a man to be the last man to die for a mistake?" He also began a
                    lifelong fight for his fellow veterans as a co-founder of the Vietnam Veterans
                    of America, and later as a United States Senator who fought to secure veterans’
                    benefits, extension of the G.I. Bill for Higher Education, and improved
                    treatment for PTSD (post-traumatic stress disorder).</p>
                <p>In 1976, Secretary Kerry received his law degree from Boston College Law School
                    and went to work as a top prosecutor in Middlesex County, Massachusetts, where
                    he took on organized crime, fought for victims’ rights, and created programs for
                    rape counseling. He was elected Lieutenant Governor of Massachusetts in 1982,
                    and 2 years later, he was elected to the United States Senate where he served
                    for 28 years.</p>
                <p>In 2009, Secretary Kerry became Chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations
                    Committee, assuming a leadership role on key foreign policy and national
                    security issues facing the United States, including Afghanistan and Pakistan,
                    nuclear nonproliferation, and global climate change. His service as Chairman
                    built on his previous Senate work that included helping to expose the
                    Iran-Contra scandal and leadership on global AIDS.</p>
                <p>As Chairman of the Senate Select Committee on POW/MIA Affairs, he worked to learn
                    the truth about American soldiers missing in Vietnam and to normalize relations
                    with that country.</p>
                <p>In 2010, as Chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee, Secretary Kerry was
                    instrumental in the ratification of the New START (Strategic Arms Reduction
                    Treaty) Treaty, a vital nuclear arms reduction agreement with Russia that helps
                    steer both countries away from dangerous nuclear confrontations.</p>
                <p>In his 28 years on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Secretary Kerry
                    chaired the Asia and Middle East subcommittees where he authored and passed
                    major legislation on international drug trafficking, international money
                    laundering, humanitarian aid, and climate change, and he helped negotiate the
                    UN’s genocide tribunal to prosecute war crimes in Cambodia.</p>
                <p>He also held senior positions on the Finance, Commerce, and Small Business
                    committees, as well as served as a member of the bipartisan Joint Committee on
                    Deficit Reduction, where he worked across party lines to try and reduce the
                    country’s debt and strengthen our economy. Prior to his departure from the
                    Senate, Secretary Kerry was the seventh-most senior Senator.</p>
                <p>Secretary Kerry was the Democratic Party's nominee for President of the United
                    States in 2004.</p>
                <p>Secretary Kerry is the author of best-selling books, including <hi rend="italic"
                        >A Call to Service: My Vision for a Better America</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">This Moment on Earth</hi>, a book on the environment which he
                    co-authored with his wife, Teresa Heinz Kerry. Together they are proud of a
                    blended family that includes two daughters, three sons, and three
                    grandchildren.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="sources">
                <head>Sources</head>
                <p>This text was adapted from Secretary Kerry’s <ref
                        target="https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/biog/203657.htm">official
                        biography</ref> (accessed March 17, 2021).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
