<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Henry Alfred
                    Kissinger</title>
                <title type="short">Henry Alfred Kissinger</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bio">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Henry Alfred Kissinger</persName> was appointed Secretary of State on
                    September 21 by President <persName>Richard M. Nixon</persName> and served in
                    the position from September 23, 1973 to January 20, 1977. With his appointment,
                    he became the first person ever to serve as both Secretary of State and National
                    Security Adviser, a position he had held since President Nixon was sworn into
                    office on January 20, 1969. However, on November 3, 1975, President
                        <persName>Gerald R. Ford</persName> removed him from his National Security
                    Adviser position while keeping him as Secretary of State. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="kissinger-henry-a.jpg"/>
                    <head>Henry A. Kissinger, 56th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p> Kissinger was born as Heinz Alfred Kissinger in Germany. After the Nazis seized
                    power, state sanctioned anti-Semitism made life for the Kissinger family, which
                    was Jewish, very difficult. In 1938, Kissinger’s family immigrated to the United
                    States and settled in New York, and Kissinger’s name was changed to Henry.</p>
                <p> During World War II, Kissinger became a naturalized citizen and served in the
                    U.S. Army as a German interpreter. After the war, he attended Harvard
                    University, earning a B.A. in 1950 and a Ph.D. in 1954. He stayed at Harvard to
                    join the faculty and in 1957 he became the Associate Director of Harvard’s
                    Department of Government and Center for International Affairs.</p>
                <p>Throughout the 1950s and 1960s, he served as a consultant to several government
                    agencies, including the National Security Council’s Operations Coordinating
                    Board, the Department of State, the Operations Research Office, and the Arms
                    Control and Disarmament Agency. In 1968, President-elect Richard Nixon chose
                    Kissinger to be his National Security Adviser.</p>
                <p>After working closely with Nixon during his first presidential term, Nixon
                    decided to make an unprecedented move by appointing Kissinger as his new
                    Secretary of State while also keeping him in the role of National Security
                    adviser. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/kissinger">Kissinger entered the
                        State Department</ref> just two weeks before Egypt and Syria launched a
                    surprise attack on Israel. <ref
                        target="/milestones/1969-1976/arab-israeli-war-1973">The October War of
                        1973</ref> played a major role in shaping Kissinger’s tenure as Secretary.
                    First, he worked to ensure Israel received an airlift of U.S. military supplies.
                    This airlift helped Israel turn the war in Israel’s favor, and it also led
                    members of the <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976/oil-embargo">Organization of
                        Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC)</ref> to initiate an oil embargo
                    against the United States. After the implementation of a United Nation’s
                    sponsored ceasefire, Kissinger began a series of “shuttle diplomacy” missions,
                    in which he traveled between various Middle East capitals to reach disengagement
                    agreements between the enemy combatants. These efforts produced an agreement in
                    January 1974 between Egypt and Israel and in May 1974 between Syria and Israel.
                    Additionally, Kissinger’s efforts contributed to OPEC’s decision to lift the
                    embargo. </p>
                <p> On August 9, 1974, the Watergate scandal compelled President Nixon to resign,
                    but Kissinger stayed on in his dual roles under President Gerald Ford. Kissinger
                    helped Ford acclimate to the international scene and both men worked to continue
                    policies implemented by Nixon and Kissinger previously, including détente with
                    the Soviet Union, establishing relations with the People’s Republic of China,
                    and negotiations in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>Kissinger also played a major role in the negotiations leading to the August 1975
                    Helsinki Accord, an agreement signed by 35 countries and addressing many issues
                    that promised to improve relations between East and West. In September 1975,
                    Kissinger helped conclude a second disengagement agreement between Egypt and
                    Israel that moved both countries closer to a peace agreement. </p>
                <p> Kissinger’s tenure as Secretary comprised many controversial issues, including
                    his role in influencing U.S. policies towards countries such as Chile and
                    Angola. Additionally, he engaged in new international issues such as law of the
                    sea, which became more prominent for U.S. foreign policy in the decades ahead.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Caldwell, Dan ed. <hi rend="italic">Henry Kissinger, His Personality and
                            Policies.</hi> Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanhimäki, Jussi. <hi rend="italic">Flawed Architect: Henry Kissinger and
                            American Foreign Policy.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press,
                        2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Issacson, Walter. <hi rend="italic">Kissinger. </hi> New York: Simon and
                        Schuster, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Immerman, Richard H. <hi rend="italic">John Foster Dulles and the
                            Diplomacy of the Cold War.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton University
                        Press, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kissinger, Henry. <hi rend="italic">Years of Renewal.</hi> New York: Simon
                        and Schuster, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>------. <hi rend="italic">Years of Upheaval.</hi> Boston, Little Brown,
                        1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl>-----. <hi rend="italic">The White House Years.</hi> Boston: Little Brown,
                        1979. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Landsford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        Conn.: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Schulzinger, Robert D. <hi rend="italic">Henry Kissinger: Doctor of
                            Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Columbia University Press, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Starr, Harvey. <hi rend="italic">Henry Kissinger: Perceptions of
                            International Politics.</hi> Lexington, KY: University Press of
                        Kentucky, 1984.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
