<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Philander Chase
                    Knox</title>
                <title type="short">Philander Chase Knox</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>President <persName>William Howard Taft</persName> appointed Pennsylvania Senator
                        <persName>Philander Chase Knox</persName> as Secretary of State on March 6,
                    1909. Following his unsuccessful bid for the Republican presidential nomination
                    the previous year, Knox resigned his seat in the U.S. Senate and entered into
                    duty that same day. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="knox-philander-chase.jpg"/>
                    <head>Philander Chase Knox, 40th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Knox was born in Fayette County, Pennsylvania in 1853. The son of a respected
                    banker, he entered Mount Union College in Ohio and received his Bachelor of Arts
                    degree in 1872. Knox read law for three years in Pittsburgh before gaining
                    admission to the Pennsylvania bar in 1875. The following year, he served as
                    Assistant United States District Attorney for the western district of
                    Pennsylvania.</p>
                <p>Knox opened a lucrative private practice as a corporate attorney, and, in 1897,
                    he served as President of the Pennsylvania Bar Association. As Counsel for the
                    Carnegie Steel Company, he took a prominent part in organizing the United States
                    Steel Corporation in 1901.</p>
                <p>That same year, President William McKinley offered the position of Attorney
                    General to Knox—an old friend from college. Knox served in the cabinets of
                    President McKinley and his successor, President <persName>Theodore
                        Roosevelt</persName>.</p>
                <p>In 1904, Knox was appointed U.S. Senator from Pennsylvania to fill a vacancy.
                    Following his unsuccessful bid for the Republican presidential nomination in
                    1908, his former opponent, President Taft, appointed Knox Secretary of State.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p> As Secretary of State, Knox tightly controlled U.S. foreign policy. He
                    reorganized the Department of State into regional divisions, maximizing
                    expertise acquired by those in the Foreign Service. Knox extended the merit
                    system of selection and promotion from the Consular Service to the Diplomatic
                    Service.</p>
                <p>Knox continued the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/hay-and-china">Open Door
                        Policy</ref> of his predecessors and pursued an even more aggressive role in
                    encouraging and protecting U.S. investments abroad.</p>
                <p>His emphasis on trade to promote democracy and stability became known as <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/dollar-diplo">"Dollar Diplomacy."</ref> The
                    United States first initiated this policy in Asia, but it became the core of
                    U.S. foreign policy in Latin America. Interventions in the Caribbean and Central
                    America were based on the theory that democratic governments would lead to free
                    markets and open trade.</p>
                <p>Knox also successfully negotiated the Bering Sea controversy during his time as
                    Secretary. The treaty, designed to put an end to the devastating slaughter of
                    seals, was signed by the United States, Great Britain, Japan and Russia in
                    1911.</p>
                <p>After President Taft lost his second presidential bid in 1912, Knox resigned his
                    position and returned to Pittsburgh. He continued to practice law until he
                    returned to the U.S. Senate in 1916, where he led the fight against the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Treaty of Versailles</ref> and
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/league">League of Nations</ref> after
                    World War One.</p>
                <p>Knox served in the Senate until his death in 1921. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped. </hi>New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell. </hi>Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
