<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Robert
                    Lansing</title>
                <title type="short">Robert Lansing</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Robert Lansing</persName> served as Secretary of State from June 24,
                    1915, until February 13, 1920. Lansing’s background in international law
                    afforded him a wealth of foreign relations experience, which influenced his
                    tenure at the Department of State. His most important achievements included his
                    oversight of U.S. foreign policy during the First World War and his negotiation
                    of a major agreement between the United States and Japan. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="lansing-robert.jpg"/>
                    <head>Robert Lansing, 42rd Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Born in Watertown, New York, on October 17, 1864, Lansing graduated from Amherst
                    College in 1886 and began practicing law in 1889. In 1890 he married Eleanor
                    Foster, Secretary of State John Watson Foster’s daughter. Lansing was uncle to
                    both Secretary of State John Foster Dulles and Director of the Central
                    Intelligence Agency Allen Welsh Dulles.</p>
                <p>He worked for the Lansing &amp; Lansing law firm in Watertown until 1907. During
                    his tenure there, he became an authority on international law and represented
                    the United States Government in many international hearings.</p>
                <p>He served as Associate Counsel for the United States in the Bering Sea
                    Arbitration (1892-1893), Counsel for the United States Bering Sea Claims
                    Commission (1896-97), Solicitor for the U.S. Government before the Alaskan
                    Boundary Tribunal (1903), Counsel for the North Atlantic Fisheries in the
                    Arbitration at The Hague (1909-10), and as Agent of the United States in the
                    American and British Claims Arbitration (1912).</p>
                <p>Lansing was also instrumental in founding the American Society of International
                    Law in 1906, and in establishing the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of
                        International Law</hi> in 1907.</p>
                <p>He became Counselor of the Department of State in 1914 and served as <hi
                        rend="italic">ad interim</hi> Secretary of State in the Woodrow Wilson
                    administration from June 9, 1915, until his appointment as Secretary of State on
                    June 24, 1915.</p>
                <p>After leaving the Department of State, Lansing continued working in the field of
                    international law in the Washington, D.C. area until his death on October 30,
                    1928.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Lansing’s influence on U.S. diplomacy extended beyond his tenure as Secretary of
                    State due to the important role he played in helping to settle a number of
                    high-profile international disputes. This influence only grew once Lansing
                    became Secretary.</p>
                <p>While Secretary he was faced with the significant foreign policy challenges
                    related to the U.S. position in the First World War. Initially, Lansing
                    advocated benevolent neutrality in the European conflict and strongly protested
                    British blockades and contraband practices, while advocating for the principles
                    of the freedom of the seas and the rights of neutral nations. Lansing eventually
                    came to favor U.S. participation in the war and accompanied President
                        <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> to Europe as one of the lead U.S.
                    negotiators at the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Paris Peace
                        Conference</ref> in 1919.</p>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Lansing also signed the Treaty of 1916 for the purchase of
                    the Danish West Indies and the Lansing-Ishii Agreement of 1917 with Japan--a
                    pledge between the United States and Japan to uphold the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/hay-and-china">Open Door Policy</ref> in
                    China, while recognizing that Japan had special interests in China.</p>
                <p>Lansing is also credited with establishing the Diplomatic Security Service,
                    having hired the Department of State’s first special agents, who were assigned
                    to observe Central Power activities in the United States before and during the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/wwi">First World War</ref>. Due to
                    disagreements over the League of Nations and President Wilson’s inability to
                    perform his presidential duties following a stroke, Lansing resigned on February
                    13, 1920.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Clements, Kendrick A. <hi rend="italic">The Presidency of Woodrow
                            Wilson.</hi> Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansing, Robert. <hi rend="italic">The Big Four and Others of the Peace
                            Conference.</hi> Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1921.</bibl>
                    <bibl>____________. <hi rend="italic">The Peace Negotiations: A Personal
                            Narrative.</hi> Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1921.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Smith, Daniel Malloy. <hi rend="italic">Robert Lansing and American
                            Neutrality, 1914-1917.</hi> New York: Da Capo, 1958.</bibl>
                    <bibl>United States Department of State. <hi rend="italic">The Lansing Papers,
                            1914-1920.</hi> Washington, D.C.: United States Government Printing
                        Office, 1939-1940.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
