<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Edward
                    Livingston</title>
                <title type="short">Edward Livingston</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Edward Livingston</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName> on <date when="1831-05-24">May 24,
                        1831</date>. Livingston entered duty on the same day. His tenure as
                    Secretary of State ended on <date when="1833-05-29">May 29, 1833.</date>
                    Livingston brought considerable legal expertise to the office but operated under
                    strict presidential constraints upon his authority. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="livingston-edward.jpg"/>
                    <head>Edward Livingston, 11th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Livingston was born on his family’s estate at Clermont, New York. He studied at
                    the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University), graduating in 1781.
                    Following his admission to the bar in 1785, he practiced law in New York
                    City.</p>
                <p> With the benefit of political advice from his older brother Robert, who had
                    served as Secretary of Foreign Affairs during the Articles of Confederation
                    government, Livingston won election to the U.S. Congress as a Representative of
                    New York and served from 1795 to 1800. He next served as U.S. Attorney for the
                    District of New York and Mayor of New York City from 1801 to 1803.</p>
                <p>In 1804 Livingston moved to New Orleans and practiced law. He served as an <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-de-camp</hi> to General <persName>Andrew
                        Jackson</persName> during the Battle of New Orleans.</p>
                <p>In 1820 Livingston returned to politics and enjoyed a series of victories: first
                    to the Louisiana State House of Representatives; next as a U.S. Representative
                    from Louisiana from 1823 to 1828; and finally, as a U.S. Senator from Louisiana
                    from 1829 to 1832.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on U.S. Diplomacy</head>
                <p>President Jackson asked for the resignation of his entire cabinet in 1831 in
                    order to neutralize his feud with Vice President <persName>John
                        Calhoun</persName> and Calhoun’s supporters within the cabinet. Jackson
                    appointed Livingston as Secretary of State upon the advice of outgoing Secretary
                    of State <persName>Martin Van Buren</persName>.</p>
                <p>Like his predecessor, Livingston would have to pay deference to President Jackson
                    regarding foreign policy. Livingston’s authority was actually broader regarding
                    domestic affairs. Notably, he rewrote Jackson’s famous Nullification
                    Proclamation of 1832, which responded to a crisis over states’ authority to
                    nullify federal law.</p>
                <p>Livingston inherited a number of unresolved—and challenging—diplomatic projects.
                    He could not settle the dispute over the northeast boundary despite his
                    considerable efforts to sway the British and U.S. citizens in Maine. He focused
                    on the ratification of a major commercial treaty with France, but the French
                    Government delayed action on the agreement.</p>
                <p>Livingston also struggled with Britain’s interest in suppressing slavery,
                    protesting the British Government’s decision not to return U.S. slaves who
                    reached British soil.</p>
                <p>Finally, he oversaw failed efforts to reach a settlement with the Mexican
                    Government regarding Texas. Although U.S. negotiators did advance commercial
                    agreements with Naples, Muscat, Russia, Siam, and Turkey during his tenure,
                    Livingston had little to do with their progress.</p>
                <p> Livingston was more involved with political disturbances in the Western
                    Hemisphere. He followed an uneven approach regarding the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref>. In 1832 New
                    Granada withdrew a commercial treaty with the United States at Britain’s urging.
                    In response, Livingston called upon the Monroe Doctrine, establishing the
                    commercial element of the doctrine.</p>
                <p>In contrast, he declined to invoke the doctrine when Britain seized the Falkland
                    Islands in 1833, ousting the Argentine Government to reaffirm a prior
                    territorial claim.</p>
                <p>On the day of Livingston’s resignation as Secretary of State, President Jackson
                    appointed him U.S. Minister to France. During his stay in France from 1833 to
                    1835, Livingston employed his diplomatic skill and his appreciation of French
                    culture to help bring into force the French Spoliation Claims Treaty, which
                    addressed decades-old claims over the seizure of U.S. vessels and cargo. While
                    delays infuriated President Jackson, the settlement finally came in 1836,
                    shortly after Livingston’s departure and death.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Belohlavek, John M. <hi rend="italic">Let the Eagle Soar: The Foreign
                            Policy of Andrew Jackson.</hi> Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
                        1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 4. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carosso, Vincent P., and Lawrence H. Leder. “Edward Livingston and
                        Jacksonian Diplomacy.” <hi rend="italic">Louisiana History: The Journal of
                            the Louisiana Historical Association</hi> 7 (1966): 241-248. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Cole, Donald B. <hi rend="italic">Martin Van Buren and the American
                            Political System.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1984. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hatcher, William B. <hi rend="italic">Edward Livingston, Jeffersonian
                            Republican and Jacksonian Democrat.</hi> University: Louisiana
                        University Press, 1940. Reprint 1970 (Peter Smith). </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
