<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: James
                    Madison</title>
                <title type="short">James Madison</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>James Madison was appointed Secretary of State by President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson</ref>
                    on <date when="1801-03-05">March 5, 1801.</date> He entered duty on May 2, 1801,
                    and served until <date when="1809-03-03">March 3, 1809.</date> He had already
                    made invaluable contributions to the establishment of the federal government
                    before starting a long career in diplomacy. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="madison-james.jpg"/>
                    <head>James Madison, Fifth Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Madison was born in Port Conway, Virginia and raised on the Virginia frontier in
                    Orange County. He graduated from the College of New Jersey (now Princeton
                    University) in 1771. By 1776 he was elected to the State Assembly and the
                    Virginia Convention that declared independence from Great Britain. From 1778 to
                    1779 Madison sat on the State Executive Council. He was a member of the Second
                        <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/continental-congress">Continental
                        Congress</ref> and the Congress of the Confederation. He served in the
                    Virginia House of Delegates from 1784 to 1786, the Annapolis Convention of 1786,
                    and the Federal Convention of 1787, where his "Virginia Plan" proposing the
                    general outline of the U.S. federal government formed the basis of debate.
                    During these debates, Madison, along with <persName>Alexander
                        Hamilton</persName> and <persName>John Jay,</persName> penned the <hi
                        rend="italic">Federalist Papers</hi> hoping to secure the passage of the
                    federal constitution. Madison was also a member of the Virginia Convention of
                    1788 that ratified the U.S. Constitution.</p>
                <p>While serving as a member of the U.S. House of Representatives from 1789 to 1797,
                    Madison sponsored the Bill of Rights. After growing disenchanted with Hamilton’s
                    pro-British sentiments, Madison aligned with <persName>Thomas
                        Jefferson</persName> to form the Democratic-Republican Party. After
                    Jefferson won the 1800 presidential election, he appointed Madison Secretary of
                    State. Madison would be the first Secretary of State to go on to serve two
                    presidential terms. He began the first of his two presidential terms in 1809.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Madison’s foreign policies were guided by his republican ideals and his faith in
                    the strength of the expanding U.S. economy. As Secretary of State, he cooperated
                    closely with President Jefferson who kept close control over key decisions.
                    Together they organized the negotiations with France that led to the 1803 <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/louisiana-purchase">Louisiana Purchase</ref>.
                    Despite concerted effort, however, they could not convince the Spanish to sell
                    West Florida.</p>
                <p>As President, Madison annexed West Florida through intrigue and force in 1810.
                    Madison also supported Jefferson’s decision to fight a naval war against the
                    Barbary Pirates. The <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/napoleonic-wars"
                        >Napoleonic Wars</ref> presented a dire foreign policy challenge when both
                    France and Britain began violating U.S. neutrality rights. Particularly
                    disturbed by the British impressment of U.S. sailors, Jefferson and Madison
                    sought to conclude a new treaty with Britain that would protect U.S. trading
                    rights and ban impressment. Unable to achieve these concessions, they adopted a
                    policy to pressure the European powers through economic restrictions.</p>
                <p> A series of acts aimed to display foreign dependence on the U.S. economy
                    followed, including the Embargo Act of 1807 and the Non-Intercourse Act of 1809.
                    The restrictions spurred smuggling by U.S. merchants, failed to sway European
                    policies, and disrupted U.S. trade, especially when European powers reciprocated
                    with trade limitations. Madison’s struggle to stop British violations of U.S.
                    neutrality culminated after his election to the Presidency when the two nations
                    entered the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref>.
                    Madison’s hopes to gain Canadian territory through military victories were never
                    realized due to the political stalemate that followed major losses on the
                    battlefield. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Henry. <hi rend="italic">History of the United States during the
                            Administration of Jefferson and Madison.</hi> 9 vols. New York:
                        Scribner’s, 1889-1891.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Banning, Lance. <hi rend="italic">The Sacred Fire of Liberty: James
                            Madison and the Founding of the Federal Republic.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell
                        University Press, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 3. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brugger, Robert J., et al., eds., <hi rend="italic">The Papers of James
                            Madison: Secretary of State Series.</hi> 5 vols. to date.
                        Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1986-. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Graebner, Norman A. <hi rend="italic">Foundations of American Foreign
                            Policy: A Realist Appraisal from Franklin to McKinley: Essays.</hi>
                        Wilmington: Scholarly Resources, 1985. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hutchinson, William T., William M.E. Rachal, and Robert A. Rutland, eds.
                            <hi rend="italic">The Papers of James Madison: Congressional
                            Series.</hi> 17 Vols. Chicago and Charlottesville: University of Chicago
                        Press (vols. 1-10); University Press of Virginia (vols. 11-17), 1962-1989. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaplan, Lawrence S., <hi rend="italic">Entangling Alliances with None:
                            American Foreign Policy in the Age of Jefferson.</hi> Kent: Kent State
                        University Press, 1987. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ketcham, Ralph L. <hi rend="italic">James Madison: A Biography.</hi> New
                        York: Macmillan, 1971. </bibl>
                    <bibl>McCoy, Drew R. <hi rend="italic">The Last of the Fathers: James Madison
                            and the Republican Legacy.</hi> New York: Cambridge University Press,
                        1989. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Merli, Frank J., and Theodore A. Wilson, eds., <hi rend="italic">Makers of
                            American Diplomacy. Vol. 1: From Benjamin Franklin to Alfred Thayer
                            Mahan.</hi> New York: Scribner, 1974. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Rutland, Robert A. <hi rend="italic">The Presidency of James Madison.</hi>
                        Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rutland, Robert A., et al., eds., <hi rend="italic">The Papers of James
                            Madison: Presidential Series.</hi> 4 vols. to date. Charlottesville:
                        University Press of Virginia, 1984-.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stagg., J.C.A. <hi rend="italic">Mr. Madison’s War: Politics, Diplomacy,
                            and Warfare in the Early American Republic, 1783-1830.</hi> Princeton:
                        Princeton University Press, 1983. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
