<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: William Learned
                    Marcy</title>
                <title type="short">William Learned Marcy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>William Learned Marcy</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Franklin Pierce</persName> on March 7, 1853, and entered
                    into duty the following day. Marcy served until March 6, 1857. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="marcy-william-learned.jpg"/>
                    <head>William Learned Marcy, 21st Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Marcy was born to a farming family in Sturbridge, Massachusetts (now Southbridge)
                    in 1786. He graduated from Brown University in 1808. After reading law, Marcy
                    was admitted to the New York bar in 1811 and began his practice in Troy, New
                    York.</p>
                <p>Marcy served briefly as a soldier during the War of 1812. He served several years
                    as Recorder for the city of Troy while he became involved in state politics.</p>
                <p>Marcy moved to Albany in 1823, where he served two terms as Comptroller of New
                    York State. In 1829 he was appointed Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of
                    New York. After two years at the Court, Marcy was elected U.S. Senator from New
                    York, a position he held until his election as Governor of New York in 1833.
                    Marcy was elected to three terms as Governor.</p>
                <p>In 1840, he was appointed to the Mexican Claims Commission, which examined claims
                    of U.S. citizens against Mexico.</p>
                <p>In 1845, President <persName>James K. Polk</persName> asked Marcy to serve as
                    Secretary of War, a Cabinet position he held for the duration of the
                    administration.</p>
                <p>In 1853, President Franklin Pierce selected Marcy as his Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Marcy came to the position of Secretary of State with little foreign policy
                    experience. He had never traveled outside of the United States, but was valued
                    for his pragmatism and judgment.</p>
                <p>During his four-year tenure, Marcy negotiated many treaties including the
                    prominent 1853 <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/gadsden-purchase">Gadsden
                        Treaty</ref>, which added nearly 30,000 square miles to the United States
                    and made possible a transcontinental railroad.</p>
                <p>Interest in territorial expansion shifted from the American Southwest to the
                    Caribbean as the United States became increasingly involved in the question of
                    Cuba’s sovereignty. Marcy oversaw the drafting of the Ostend Manifesto, a
                    document that detailed the reasons for a proposed U.S. acquisition of Cuba. The
                    Manifesto was released to the public but was later rescinded after its issuance
                    embarrassed the Pierce administration and met with international criticism over
                    the expansion of U.S. slavery.</p>
                <p>The following year, Marcy negotiated a treaty with Great Britain over reciprocal
                    fishing rights in Canada.</p>
                <p>Marcy served the duration of the Pierce presidency, until March 1857. Four months
                    later, he unexpectedly died in New York. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “William Learned Marcy.” In <hi rend="italic">The
                            American Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> edited by Samuel
                        Flagg Bemis. Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper
                        Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell</hi>. Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
