<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="marshall-george-catlett" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: George Catlett
                    Marshall</title>
                <title type="short">George Catlett Marshall</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>marshall-george-catlett</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>George Catlett Marshall</persName> was nominated as Secretary of State
                    by President <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName> on January 8, 1947, and was
                    confirmed unanimously by the Senate. Marshall entered on duty on January 21,
                    1947, and served as Secretary of State until January 20, 1949. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="marshall-george-catlett.jpg"/>
                    <head>George Catlett Marshall, 50th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Marshall was born in Uniontown, Pennsylvania. His family had strong roots in
                    Virginia, where Marshall returned to attend the Virginia Military Institute.
                    Following his graduation in 1901, he received his commission as Second
                    Lieutenant in the U.S. Army. Marshall enjoyed an extremely successful military
                    career, serving in both World Wars and rising to the rank of five-star general
                    in 1944.</p>
                <p>During World War II, Marshall distinguished himself as Army Chief of Staff, a
                    position to which he was appointed by President <persName>Franklin D.
                        Roosevelt</persName>. As Chief of Staff, Marshall earned a strong reputation
                    as an administrator and successfully transformed a small peacetime army into a
                    strong wartime force while also coordinating Allied operations.</p>
                <p>Marshall also proved to be adept at negotiating with Congress and other members
                    of the executive branch, a talent that would serve him well in his civilian
                    career. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Following Marshall’s resignation as Chief of Staff, President Truman relied
                    heavily on Marshall’s expertise to navigate postwar diplomacy. Marshall’s first
                    assignment was to lead a special mission to China in late 1945 to mediate the
                    conflict between the Nationalists and the Communists. Although this mission was
                    ultimately unsuccessful, Marshall’s tenure as Secretary of State was marked by
                    several notable achievements.</p>
                <p> In 1947 and 1948, Marshall led the effort to formulate and secure congressional
                    support for the massive aid package to Western Europe that would become known as
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/marshall-plan">Marshall Plan</ref>. The
                    United States also negotiated the Inter-American Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance
                    and the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic Treaty
                        Organization</ref> under Secretary Marshall. Although Marshall typically
                    served President Truman without objection, he did strongly disagree with Truman
                    on the recognition of the State of Israel. </p>
                <p> Marshall resigned as Secretary of State in 1949 and became president of the
                    American Red Cross. However, he returned to the Truman Cabinet as Secretary of
                    Defense in 1950 and served briefly in that capacity until 1951. Marshall died in
                    1959 after receiving the Nobel Peace Prize in 1953 for his work to restore
                    Europe’s economy in the post-World War II period. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 14. New York: Alfred A. Knopf,
                        1928. Reprint 1965 (Cooper Square).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
