<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John
                    Marshall</title>
                <title type="short">John Marshall</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>President <persName>John Adams</persName> nominated <persName>John
                        Marshall</persName> to be Secretary of State on <date when="1800-05-12">May
                        12, 1800,</date> the same day that Adams dismissed <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/pickering-timothy">Timothy
                        Pickering.</ref> The U.S. Senate confirmed Marshall as Secretary of State
                    the next day. He served as Secretary of State from <date when="1800-06-06">June
                        6, 1800</date>, until <date when="1801-02-04">February 4, 1801</date>, and
                    then as <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> Secretary of State until March 4,
                    1801. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="marshall-john.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Marshall, Fourth Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Marshall was raised on the Virginia frontier. He fought in the Revolutionary War,
                    serving as a Captain in the Continental Army. He studied law at the College of
                    William &amp; Mary and gained admission to the bar in 1780. A lifetime of public
                    service commenced with his first electoral victory as a delegate to the Virginia
                    General Assembly in 1782. Marshall served as a member of the Assembly until 1791
                    and again from 1795 to 1797. He gained a seat on the State Executive Council
                    from 1782 to 1784 and was an influential member of the Virginia Convention of
                    1788, which ratified the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/convention-and-ratification">U.S.
                        Constitution</ref>.</p>
                <p>Marshall emerged as the Federalist Party leader in Virginia and gained election
                    as a U.S. Representative in 1798. While serving as Secretary of State near the
                    end of Adams’ presidential term, Marshall received a nomination to serve as
                    Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. He served as Chief Justice until 1835. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Marshall began his diplomatic career as one of the three envoys appointed by
                    President Adams to negotiate with French Foreign Minister Talleyrand in 1797.
                    The mission failed, resulting in the <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/xyz">XYZ
                        Affair</ref> and the Quasi-War with France. Nonetheless, Marshall’s conduct
                    and reporting about the scandal turned a diplomatic failure into a personal
                    triumph as his reputation soared at home.</p>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Marshall was less partisan and more loyal to President
                    Adams than Pickering had been. Adams entrusted Marshall with considerable
                    authority over foreign affairs, particularly so after Adams departed the newly
                    established national capital at Washington for an eight-month stay in
                    Massachusetts. Marshall’s deference to Adams further defined the position of the
                    Secretary of State as a political subordinate of the President rather than the
                    independent office that Pickering had imagined.</p>
                <p>Secretary Marshall reasserted a policy of nonalignment regarding the European
                    powers during a critical period. He split with other Federalists, such as
                        <persName>Alexander Hamilton</persName>, and supported ongoing efforts to
                    negotiate with France following the humiliating XYZ Affair. He backed the
                    Convention of 1800 between the United States and France, which finally ended the
                    undeclared naval war between the two countries. In dealing with Britain,
                    Marshall protested the British Navy’s unlawful seizure of U.S. shipping and
                    impressment of U.S. seaman as well as the British courts’ tolerance of piracy
                    against U.S. merchant vessels. Recognizing the limitations of U.S. naval power,
                    Marshall begrudgingly approved ongoing payments to the Barbary pirates who
                    continued to raid U.S. merchant vessels. He also experienced frustration when
                    negotiating with the Spanish who disregarded U.S. neutrality rights and
                    protested against U.S. support for anti-colonial uprisings in Spanish
                    America.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Baker, Leonard. <hi rend="italic">John Marshall: A Life in Law.</hi> New
                        York: Macmillan, 1974.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 2. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1927. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Beveridge, Albert J. <hi rend="italic">The Life of John Marshall</hi> 4
                        vols. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1916-1919. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Johnson, Herbert A., with Charles T. Cullen, Nancy G. Harris, et al., eds.
                            <hi rend="italic">The Papers of John Marshall.</hi> 10 vols. to date.
                        Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1974-. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Smith, Jean Edward. <hi rend="italic">John Marshall: Definer of a
                            Nation.</hi> New York: Henry Holt, 1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stites, Francis N., <hi rend="italic">John Marshall: Defender of the
                            Constitution.</hi> Boston: Little, Brown, 1981. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Rudko, Frances Howell. <hi rend="italic">John Marshall and International
                            Law: Statesman and Chief Justice.</hi> New York: Greenwood Press, 1991.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
