<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Louis McLane</title>
                <title type="short">Louis McLane</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Louis McLane was appointed Secretary of State by President <persName>Andrew
                        Jackson</persName> on <date when="1833-05-29">May 29, 1833.</date> McLane
                    entered duty on the same day and left the position on <date when="1834-06-30"
                        >June 30, 1834.</date> He was an able administrator who eventually clashed
                    with President Jackson over foreign policy. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="mclane-louis.jpg"/>
                    <head>Louis McLane, 12th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>McLane was born in Smyrna, Delaware. As a young man he served as a midshipman in
                    the Navy from 1798 to 1801 and then attended Newark College (now the University
                    of Delaware).</p>
                <p>After reading law, McLane gained admission to the Delaware bar in 1807. Embarking
                    on a career in politics, he won election to the U.S. House of Representatives in
                    1816. He served five terms until moving to the U.S. Senate in 1827.</p>
                <p>Two years into his Senate term, President Jackson appointed McLane as Minister to
                    Great Britain. McLane served in London from 1829 to 1831 before returning to
                    Washington to join Jackson’s cabinet as Secretary of the Treasury from 1831 to
                    1833.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on U.S. Diplomacy</head>
                <p>While serving as Minister to Great Britain, McLane conducted the 1831
                    negotiations over an important agreement that allowed U.S. trade with the
                    British West Indies. This breakthrough resolved a dispute dating back to the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/jay-treaty">John Jay Treaty</ref>, which
                    was ratified in 1795.</p>
                <p>As Secretary of State, McLane’s central achievement was a successful
                    reorganization of the Department of State’s staff into distinct bureaus. His
                    main foreign policy success was an arrangement with the Spanish Government that
                    settled U.S. claims for property seized by Spain during the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/napoleonic-wars">Napoleonic Wars</ref>.</p>
                <p>McLane quickly encountered the tough issues that had frustrated his predecessors
                    Martin Van Buren and Edward Livingston. Namely, the northeast boundary dispute
                    with Great Britain still proved to be intractable. The Mexican claims and
                    boundary issues also remained unsettled. </p>
                <p> Finally, McLane’s efforts to resolve the longstanding dispute with France over
                    the damages inflicted upon U.S. foreign commerce during the Napoleonic Wars led
                    to the end of his tenure as Secretary of State. A treaty had been signed in
                    1831, but the French Government refused to issue the payments stipulated
                    therein. McLane supported a policy of reprisal against French exports. When
                    President Jackson decided against reprisals, McLane opted to resign.</p>
                <p>McLane eventually returned to diplomacy in 1845 when President <persName>James K.
                        Polk</persName> appointed him U.S. Minister to Great Britain. His hopes to
                    negotiate the Oregon Territory boundary were disappointed when the talks instead
                    commenced in Washington. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 4. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Benns, F. Lee. <hi rend="italic">The American Struggle for the British
                            West India Carrying Trade, 1815-1830.</hi> Bloomington: Indiana
                        University Studies, 1923. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Munroe, John A. <hi rend="italic">Louis McLane: Federalist and
                            Jacksonian.</hi> New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, 1973. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Remini, Robert V. <hi rend="italic">Andrew Jackson: The Course of American
                            Democracy, 1833-1845.</hi> Vol. 3. New York: Harper and Row, 1984. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Willson, Beckle. <hi rend="italic">America's Ambassadors to England,
                            1785-1928: A Narrative of Anglo-American Diplomatic Relations.</hi> New
                        York: Frederick A. Stokes, 1929. Reprint 1969 (Books for Libraries Press).
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
