<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: James Monroe</title>
                <title type="short">James Monroe</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>James Monroe</persName> was appointed by President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james">James Madison</ref> as
                    Secretary of State on <date when="1811-04-02">April 2, 1811.</date> Monroe
                    assumed duty on April 6, 1811, and served until <date when="1817-03-03">March 3,
                        1817,</date> with a brief period from October 1, 1814, to February 28, 1815,
                    as <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> Secretary of State. Monroe had a
                    prestigious military career before embarking upon a distinguished career in
                    public service. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="monroe-james.jpg"/>
                    <head>James Monroe, Seventh Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Monroe was born to a plantation family in Westmoreland County, Virginia. He began
                    attending Campbell Academy when he was eleven years old and entered the College
                    of William and Mary at sixteen. In 1775 he enlisted in the Third Virginia
                    Infantry and then fought under <persName>George Washington’s</persName> command
                    during the Revolutionary War. Monroe was wounded during the Battle of Trenton,
                    and eventually reached the rank of Lieutenant Colonel.</p>
                <p>Following the war, he returned to the College of William &amp; Mary to study law
                    at the suggestion of <persName>Thomas Jefferson.</persName> Monroe’s election to
                    the Virginia House of Delegates in 1782 began a long series of public
                    appointments. Among many other positions including Secretary of State, Monroe
                    served as a member of the Congress of the Confederation from 1783 until 1786, a
                    U.S. Senator from 1790 until 1794, Governor of Virginia from 1799 until 1802 and
                    in 1811, and U.S. President from 1817 until 1824.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Monroe conducted numerous diplomatic missions addressing the most critical
                    international threats facing his generation. President <persName>George
                        Washington</persName> appointed Monroe Minister to
                        <placeName>France</placeName> in 1794. <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/jay-treaty">Jay’s Treaty</ref> frustrated
                    Monroe’s efforts to retain cordial relations with the French Government and he
                    was recalled in 1796.</p>
                <p>Monroe returned to France in 1803 on a successful mission to assist
                        <persName>Robert Livingston</persName> with the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/louisiana-purchase">Louisiana Purchase</ref>
                    negotiations. Monroe also served as Minister to Britain from 1803 until 1807, a
                    period complicated by disputes over U.S. neutrality rights. In 1805 Monroe
                    traveled to Spain, intending to win recognition of the U.S. possession of West
                    Florida. The United States claimed the territory as part of the Louisiana
                    Purchase, but Monroe could not gain the consent of the Spanish Government.</p>
                <p> Monroe joined with Special Commissioner <persName>William Pinkney </persName>in
                    1806 in the effort to halt British impressment of U.S. sailors and to secure
                    neutral trading rights. The proposed Monroe-Pinkney Treaty, however, failed to
                    address impressments, and President Jefferson therefore declined to forward the
                    treaty to the Senate.</p>
                <p>While serving as Secretary of State in 1811, Monroe became convinced that a
                    declaration of war against Great Britain was the best option to change offensive
                    British policies. Along with Madison, Monroe encouraged Congress to issue a war
                    declaration, which came on June 17, 1812. Monroe skillfully managed the
                    expansion of the U.S. military occupation of Florida and served as acting
                    Secretary of War during the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War
                        of 1812</ref>. </p>
                <p>Although there would be no clear victor, the United States emerged from the war
                    with enhanced international prestige. As President, Monroe’s main diplomatic
                    challenges stemmed from the recession of the Spanish Empire in the Americas and
                    Russian Tsar Alexander’s hopes to populate the Oregon Coast. Monroe responded
                    effectively. In 1819 he skillfully managed the total <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/florida">Acquisition of Florida</ref>.</p>
                <p> Along with his influential Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy">John Quincy
                        Adams,</ref> Monroe issued the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe"
                        >Monroe Doctrine</ref>, which forewarned the imperial European powers
                    against interfering in the affairs of the newly independent Latin American
                    states or potential U.S. territories in the Western hemisphere. Adhering to the
                    intellectual underpinnings of the doctrine, Monroe granted diplomatic
                    recognition to newly-independent Latin American republics. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Ammon, Henry. <hi rend="italic">James Monroe: A Bibliography.</hi>
                        Westport, CT: Meckler, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl>_______. <hi rend="italic">James Monroe: The Quest for National
                            Identity.</hi> New York: McGraw-Hill, 1971. Reprint 1990 (University of
                        Virginia Press). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 3. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cunningham, Noble E. <hi rend="italic">The Presidency of James
                            Monroe.</hi> Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1996. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hamilton, Stanislaus Murray, ed. <hi rend="italic">The Writings of James
                            Monroe, Including a Collection of His Public and Private Papers and
                            Correspondence Now for the First Time Printed.</hi> 7 vols. New York:
                        G.P. Putnam’s Sons, 1898-1903. </bibl>
                    <bibl>May, Ernest R. <hi rend="italic">The Making of the Monroe Doctrine.</hi>
                        Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1975. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Preston, Daniel and Marlena C. DeLong, eds. <hi rend="italic">The Papers
                            of James Monroe: A Documental History of the Presidential Tours of James
                            Monroe, 1817, 1818, 1819.</hi> Vol. 1. Westport, CT: Greenwood Press,
                        2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Perkins, Dexter. <hi rend="italic">A History of the Monroe Doctrine.</hi>
                        Boston: Little, Brown, 1963.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
