<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Edmund Sixtus
                    Muskie</title>
                <title type="short">Edmund Sixtus Muskie</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bio">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Edmund Sixtus Muskie</persName> served as President <persName>Jimmy
                        Carter</persName>’s Secretary of State from May 8, 1980 until January 18,
                    1981. A long-time U.S. Senator from Maine, Muskie was tapped to serve as
                    Carter’s second Secretary of State after the resignation of Cyrus Vance
                    following the failed rescue of the American hostages in Iran. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="muskie-edmund-sixtus.jpg"/>
                    <head>Edmund Sixtus Muskie, 58th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Born in Rumford, Maine, March 28, 1914, Muskie graduated from Bates College in
                    1936 and Cornell University Law School in 1939. He was admitted to the
                    Massachusetts bar in 1939 and the Maine bar in 1940, and began the private
                    practice of law in Waterville, Maine, in 1940. Muskie enlisted in the U.S. Navy
                    during the Second World War and served in the Atlantic and Asiatic-Pacific
                    Theaters from 1942 to 1945.</p>
                <p>After holding a series of local offices, Muskie was elected to the State House of
                    Representatives in 1946, 1948, and 1950. Muskie was elected as Governor of Maine
                    in 1955. In 1958 Muskie was elected to the U.S. Senate and was reelected in
                    1964, 1970, and 1976. During his tenure in the Senate, Muskie served as the
                    Chairman of the Budget Committee and as a member of the Senate Foreign Relations
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>Muskie achieved national notoriety as the unsuccessful Democratic candidate for
                    Vice President of the United States in 1968 and lost the 1972 presidential
                    nomination to fellow Senator <persName>George McGovern</persName>.</p>
                <p>While serving as Secretary of State, President Carter awarded Muskie the
                    Presidential Medal of Freedom on January 16, 1981. After leaving public office,
                    Muskie returned to private practice in Washington D.C. and served as a member of
                    the “Tower Commission,” which investigated the Iran-Contra Scandal. Muskie
                    resided in Washington D.C. until his death on March 26, 1996.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Following the resignation of <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/vance-cyrus-roberts">Cyrus Vance</ref>,
                    President Carter envisioned Muskie’s role as more of a senior statesman and
                    spokesman for the Administration, while leaving the everyday management of the
                    Department of State to Deputy Secretary <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/christopher-warren-minor">Warren
                        Christopher</ref>.</p>
                <p>In the nine months Muskie served as Secretary of State, he conducted the first
                    high-level meeting with the Soviet government after its December 1979 invasion
                    of Afghanistan. During these negotiations, Secretary Muskie unsuccessfully
                    attempted to secure the withdrawal of Soviet forces from Afghanistan.</p>
                <p>Muskie also assisted President Carter in the implementation of the “Carter
                    Doctrine,” which aimed to limit Soviet expansion into the Middle East and
                    Persian Gulf. Finally, under Muskie’s leadership, the State Department
                    negotiated the release of the remaining American hostages held by Iran. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 4. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brzezinski, Zbigniew. <hi rend="italic">Power and Principle: Memoirs of
                            the National Security Advisor, 1977 – 1981.</hi> New York: Farrar,
                        1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carter, Jimmy. <hi rend="italic">Keeping Faith: Memoirs of a
                            President.</hi> New York: Random House, 1982. </bibl>
                    <bibl>“Edmund Sixtus Muskie, (1914–1996).” <ref
                            target="http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=M001121"
                            >Biographical Directory of the United States Congress</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Landsford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        Conn.: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
