<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Richard
                    Olney</title>
                <title type="short">Richard Olney</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> President <persName>Grover Cleveland</persName> appointed <persName>Richard
                        Olney</persName> as Secretary of State on June 8, 1895. Olney began duty on
                    June 10, 1895, and served until March 5, 1897. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="olney-richard.jpg"/>
                    <head>Richard Olney, 34th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Olney was born on September 15, 1835, in Oxford, Massachusetts. He graduated from
                    Brown University in 1856 and from Harvard Law School in 1858. Olney practiced
                    law and was intermittently active in politics and the Democratic Party, serving
                    a term in the Massachusetts State legislature in 1874. President Grover
                    Cleveland appointed Olney as Attorney General in 1893.</p>
                <p>Upon the death of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/gresham-walter-quintin"
                        >Secretary of State Walter Gresham</ref> on May 28, 1895, Cleveland began a
                    search for a replacement and settled on Olney, whom he appointed on June 8,
                    1895.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p> Olney came to the Department of State at a time when a Cuban revolt against
                    Spanish rule in <placeName>Cuba</placeName> was gaining strength. As the Spanish
                    Government attempted to suppress the rebellion, Olney faced public pressure to
                    intervene. The U.S. Government tried to halt shipments from Cuban sympathizers
                    and exiles from Key West and other U.S. ports. Tensions over Cuba would
                    eventually ignite the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">
                        Spanish-American War</ref> the year after Olney left office in 1898. </p>
                <p>Olney played a significant role in mediating the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1866-1898/venezuela">boundary dispute</ref> between
                        <placeName>Venezuela</placeName> and the British colony of
                        <placeName>Guyana</placeName>. The dispute stemmed from the historically
                    vague definition of the Venezuela-Guyana border, which had never been delineated
                    during the colonial period.</p>
                <p>In 1893, Venezuela publicly pressed its claims and hoped for arbitration. Hoping
                    to secure assistance by invoking the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe"
                        >Monroe Doctrine</ref>, <persName>José Andrade</persName>, Venezuelan
                    Minister to the United States, brought the issue to the U.S. Department of
                    State, and President Cleveland mentioned the issue in his 1894 message to
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>In February of 1895, Congress passed a resolution favoring U.S. arbitration.
                    Although his predecessor, Walter Gresham, was less interested in pursuing the
                    issue, Olney believed it was important to enhance national prestige and to
                    capitalize on U.S. popular resentment of British power. At issue was not British
                    reluctance to arbitrate, but British refusal to accept Venezuelan border demands
                    as a possible outcome of the arbitration. </p>
                <p>The situation began to change when renewed Anglo-German tensions pushed the
                    Venezuela boundary dispute off the front pages of British newspapers. British
                    policymakers began to favor maintaining good relations with the other Great
                    Powers as British diplomacy suffered increasing international isolation.</p>
                <p>Lord Salisbury decided that conciliation would be expedient and authorized
                    British Ambassador to the United States, <persName>Julian Pauncefote</persName>,
                    to negotiate an arbitration treaty. Olney and Pauncefote signed a treaty on
                    February 2, 1897, which subjected the Venezuela-Guyana border to U.S.
                    arbitration, allowing full Venezuelan claims to be considered in the arbitration
                    process. The resulting arbitration, decided in October of 1899, awarded
                    territory to Venezuela. </p>
                <p>Olney left office at the end of Cleveland’s second administration, and resumed
                    practicing law, although he continued to write about international relations. In
                    1904, Olney was a candidate for the Democratic nomination for President. He
                    declined the Ambassadorship to Great Britain in 1914, citing his age. Olney died
                    on April 8, 1917. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Eggert, Gerald G. <hi rend="italic">Richard Olney: Evolution of a
                            Statesman.</hi> University Park, PA: Pennsylvania State University
                        Press, 1974. </bibl>
                    <bibl>LaFeber, Walter. “The Background of Cleveland's Venezuelan Policy: A
                        Reinterpretation.” <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi> 66
                        (1961): 947-967. </bibl>
                    <bibl>United States Department of Justice. <hi rend="italic">Attorneys General
                            of the United States, 1789-1985. </hi> Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government
                        Printing Office, 1985. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
