<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="pickering-timothy" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Timothy
                    Pickering</title>
                <title type="short">Timothy Pickering</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>pickering-timothy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Timothy Pickering</persName> was appointed by President
                        <persName>George Washington</persName> as <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>
                    Secretary of State on <date when="1795-08-20">August 20, 1795</date>, and
                    elevated to the position of Secretary of State on <date when="1795-12-10"
                        >December 10, 1795.</date> President <persName>John Adams</persName>
                    dismissed Pickering on May 12, 1800. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="pickering-timothy.jpg"/>
                    <head>Timothy Pickering, Third Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Born in Salem, Massachusetts, Pickering graduated from Harvard College in 1763
                    and received a Master of Arts degree in 1766. After studying law, he joined the
                    Massachusetts bar in 1768.</p>
                <p>Pickering entered the Revolutionary Army as a Colonel in 1775 and was elected to
                    the Massachusetts legislature the next year. In 1777 he was appointed Adjutant
                    General and the Continental Congress elected him as a member of the Board of
                    War. He served as Quarter-Master General of the Army from 1780 until 1784. </p>
                <p>After the war, Pickering moved to Pennsylvania and represented Luzerne County in
                    the 1787 convention that ratified the Federal Constitution and in the state
                    Constitutional Convention (<date from="1789" to="1790">1789-1790</date>).</p>
                <p> Pickering received a federal appointment as Postmaster General in 1791, which
                    lasted until 1795. His Federalist credentials helped him gain appointment as
                    Secretary of War in January 1795.</p>
                <p>Pickering would also serve as a Federalist Senator from Massachusetts from 1803
                    until 1811, and then as Representative from Massachusetts from 1813 until 1817.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Before appointing him Secretary of State, President Washington sent Pickering on
                    special missions during the 1790s to negotiate with the Northeastern Indian
                    tribes and to dissuade them from allying with Northwestern tribes. Pickering
                    signed the 1794 Treaty of Canandaigua with the Iroquois League, a confederacy of
                    six nations. In the agreement, the U.S. Government recognized the League's
                    sovereignty over a sizable territory within New York State and offered payments,
                    including an annual allowance, in exchange for a peace agreement and the right
                    of passage through Iroquois Territory for U.S. citizens.</p>
                <p>Pickering became Secretary of State in a controversial manner, and controversy
                    would characterize his tenure. He manipulated an end to the tenure of his
                    predecessor, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/randolph-edmund-jennings"
                        >Edmund Randolph,</ref> largely because of Randolph’s opposition to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/jay-treaty">1794 Jay Treaty</ref>. Pickering
                    produced a slanted translation of French documents that had been intercepted by
                    the British Navy and informed President Washington that they proved Randolph’s
                    traitorous behavior.</p>
                <p>Once appointed as Secretary of State, Pickering followed a pro-British agenda and
                    did not share Presidents Washington’s and Adams’ qualms about political
                    entanglements with warring European powers. The ratification of the Jay Treaty
                    worsened U.S.-French relations due to its preferential treatment of Great
                    Britain. France’s hostile reaction to the treaty—including the decision not to
                    receive a U.S. Minister and the seizure of U.S. merchant ships caught trading
                    with Britain—encouraged Pickering’s pro-British stance. He opposed Adams’
                    decision to send a delegation to negotiate with France. The <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/xyz">XYZ Affair</ref> (1797-1798) propelled
                    Pickering’s desire to ally with Great Britain in a full-scale war with
                    France.</p>
                <p> When Adams reopened negotiations with France late in 1798 seeking to end the
                    Quasi-War with France, Pickering stepped up his protests. He conspired to place
                    pro-British <persName>Alexander Hamilton</persName> as a Major General in the
                    Army, hoping to establish a large permanent army. Pickering also attempted to
                    hinder Adams’ efforts to explore options for peace with France. Pickering’s
                    public attacks on the President eventually drove Adams to request his
                    resignation. Pickering refused to resign and was subsequently dismissed by
                    Adams. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Clarfield, Gerard H. “Postscript to the Jay Treaty: Timothy Pickering and
                        Anglo-American Relations, 1795-1797.” <hi rend="italic">William and Mary
                            Quarterly</hi> 23 (January 1966): 106-120.</bibl>
                    <bibl>_______. <hi rend="italic">Timothy Pickering and American Diplomacy,
                            1795-1800.</hi> Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1969. </bibl>
                    <bibl>_______. <hi rend="italic">Timothy Pickering and the American
                            Republic.</hi> Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1980. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pickering, Octavius and Charles Wentworth Upham. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Life of Timothy Pickering.</hi> 4 vols. Boston: Little, Brown,
                        1867–1873. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
