<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Michael R.
                    Pompeo</title>
                <title type="short">Michael R. Pompeo</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Adapted from Secretary Pompeo’s official biography
                    https://2017-2021.state.gov/biographies/michael-r-pompeo/index.html (accessed
                    March 17, 2021).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Michael R. Pompeo was sworn in as the 69th Secretary of State on April 26, 2018.
                    He previously served as Director of the Central Intelligence Agency from January
                    2017 to April 2018.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="pompeo-michael-r.jpg"/>
                    <head>Michael R. Pompeo, 70th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Prior to joining the Trump Administration, Mr. Pompeo was serving in his fourth
                    term as congressman from Kansas’ 4th District. He served on the House
                    Intelligence Committee, as well as the Energy and Commerce Committee and House
                    Select Benghazi Committee.</p>
                <p>Prior to his service in Congress, Mr. Pompeo founded Thayer Aerospace, where he
                    served as CEO for more than a decade. He later became President of Sentry
                    International, an oilfield equipment manufacturing, distribution, and service
                    company.</p>
                <p>Mr. Pompeo graduated first in his class at the United States Military Academy at
                    West Point in 1986 and served as a cavalry officer patrolling the Iron Curtain
                    before the fall of the Berlin Wall. He also served with the 2nd Squadron, 7th
                    Cavalry in the US Army’s Fourth Infantry Division.</p>
                <p>After leaving active duty, Mr. Pompeo graduated from Harvard Law School, having
                    been an editor of the Harvard Law Review.</p>
                <p>Mr. Pompeo was born on December 30, 1963, in Orange, California. He is married to
                    Susan Pompeo and has one son, Nick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="sources">
                <head>Sources</head>
                <p>This text was adapted from Secretary Pompeo’s <ref
                        target="https://2017-2021.state.gov/biographies/michael-r-pompeo/index.html"
                        >official biography</ref> (accessed March 17, 2021).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
