<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Colin L.
                    Powell</title>
                <title type="short">Colin L. Powell</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Colin L. Powell</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by George
                    W. Bush on <date when="2001-01-20">January 20, 2001</date>, after being
                    unanimously confirmed by the U.S. Senate. He served for four years, leaving the
                    position on <date when="2005-01-26">January 26, 2005</date>. He was the first
                    African-American to serve as Secretary of State.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="powell-colin-luther.jpg"/>
                    <head>Colin Luther Powell, 65th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Powell was born on April 5, 1937, in the New York City neighborhood of Harlem.
                    The son of two Jamaican immigrants, he was raised in the South Bronx. He
                    attended City College of New York, and it was there that he began his military
                    service, joining the Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC). After his graduation
                    in 1958, Powell was commissioned a second lieutenant in the U.S. Army. During
                    his 35 years in the Army, he served two tours in Vietnam, was stationed in West
                    Germany and South Korea, and acted as President <persName>Ronald
                        Reagan</persName>'s Deputy National Security Advisor in 1987 then National
                    Security Advisor from 1988 until 1989. In 1989 he was promoted to the rank of
                    general, and was appointed by President <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName> to
                    the position of Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. In the four years Powell
                    served in that capacity, he oversaw 28 crises, including Operation Desert Storm
                    in 1991. After his retirement in 1993, he founded America's Promise, an
                    organization which helps at-risk children. He was nominated for Secretary of
                    State by President <persName>George W. Bush</persName> on <date
                        when="2000-12-16">December 16, 2000</date>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on U.S. Diplomacy</head>
                <p>At the beginning of his term, Powell placed an emphasis on reaffirming diplomatic
                    alliances throughout the world, supporting a national missile defense system,
                    working towards peace in the Middle East, and prioritizing sanctions instead of
                    force in potential hot spots such as <placeName>Iraq</placeName>. He also
                    focused on reinvigorating U.S. diplomacy through reforms in the Department of
                    State’s organizational culture and an infusion of resources for personnel,
                    information technology, security, and facilities.</p>
                <p>Powell's term, however, was soon dominated by the challenges the Bush
                    Administration faced after the September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks. Powell was
                    one of the foremost supporters of taking swift military action against al-Qaeda
                    and demanded immediate cooperation from <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Pakistan</placeName> in the U.S. search for those who were
                    complicit in the attacks. </p>
                <p>When the Administration's attention shifted to Iraq and the possibility that
                        <persName>Saddam Hussein</persName> was manufacturing weapons of mass
                    destruction (WMD), Powell pressed to have UN inspectors investigate. In February
                    2003, Powell presented intelligence to the UN that supported the claim that Iraq
                    had weapons of mass destruction and could produce more. Subsequently, the
                    Administration moved quickly toward preemptive military action against Iraq,
                    despite Powell’s advice that war should not begin until a large coalition of
                    allies and a long-term occupation plan were in place. In 2004, some of the
                    intelligence that Powell had brought before the UN in 2003 was found to be
                    erroneous.</p>
                <p>Although Afghanistan and Iraq demanded a great deal of Powell’s attention during
                    his tenure, he pursued other important U.S. foreign policy initiatives and
                    grappled with various crises that arose between 2001 and 2005. After initially
                    difficult Administration interactions with Russia and China, Powell worked to
                    improve both bilateral relationships. Prominent among these efforts were
                    management of U.S. withdrawal from the U.S.-Russian Anti-Ballistic Missile
                    treaty and the signing of the Moscow Treaty on Strategic Offensive Reductions in
                    May 2002. </p>
                <p>In the area of foreign aid, Powell pushed the Administration to increase its
                    commitment to the international fight against AIDS, and oversaw a doubling of
                    development assistance funding. He also pressed for international cooperation to
                    halt the nuclear weapons programs of North Korea and Iran, and the
                    Administration achieved an important nonproliferation success when Libya agreed
                    to give up its weapons programs in 2003. </p>
                <p>Powell confronted a variety of international crises as well, including a near war
                    between nuclear powers <placeName>India</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Pakistan</placeName> in 2001-2002, domestic turmoil in
                        <placeName>Liberia</placeName> (2003) and <placeName>Haiti</placeName>
                    (2004), and the Indian Ocean tsunami in 2004. His continued belief that Middle
                    East stability required a resolution of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict led him
                    to advocate the 2002 “Road Map” that aimed at creating an independent
                    Palestinian state at peace with Israel. Although President Bush endorsed the
                    plan, Powell was not able to persuade the Administration to make a strong
                    commitment to its implementation.</p>
                <p>On <date when="2004-11-16">November 15, 2004</date>, Powell announced his
                    resignation. After stepping down as Secretary of State, he returned to a busy
                    life in the private sector continuing his work with America's Promise Alliance.
                    He served on the Boards of Directors of the Council on Foreign Relations, the
                    Eisenhower Fellowship Program, and the Powell Center at the City College of New
                    York.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl> Allen, Mike. "Powell Announces His Resignation." <hi rend="italic"
                            >Washington Post</hi>, 16 November 2004. A1. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Deyoung, Karen. <hi rend="italic">Soldier: The Life of Colin Powell</hi>.
                        New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Powell, Colin, and Joseph Persico. <hi rend="italic">My American
                            Journey</hi>. New York: Ballantine Books, 1995.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
