<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Edmund Randolph</title>
                <title type="short">Edmund Randolph</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Edmund Jennings Randolph succeeded <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName> as Secretary of
                    State on <date when="1794-01-02">January 2, 1794</date>. Like Jefferson,
                    Randolph resigned from office. Randolph departed on August 20, 1795, following a
                    struggle to maintain a policy of neutrality in the war between Great Britain and
                    Revolutionary France and accusations of corruption by the Federalists in
                    President <persName>George Washington’s</persName> cabinet. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="randolph-edmund-jennings.jpg"/>
                    <head>Edmund Randolph, Second Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Randolph was born into a leading Virginia family. He graduated from the College
                    of William &amp; Mary, studied law with his father John and his Uncle Peyton,
                    joined the Virginia bar, and began practicing law in Williamsburg. Whereas his
                    father reacted to the American Revolution by returning to Great Britain,
                    Randolph served as an aide-de-camp to <persName>General George
                    Washington</persName> in 1775.</p>
                <p>After returning to Virginia upon the news of his uncle’s death, Randolph was
                    elected to the Virginia Convention of 1776 that would establish the
                    Commonwealth’s first constitution. He was also elected as the Commonwealth’s
                    first Attorney General and Mayor of the town of Williamsburg (both in 1776). He
                    was subsequently elected as a Delegate to the Continental Congress in 1779 and
                    1881. In 1786 Randolph was elected Governor of Virginia, but he resigned in 1788,
                    preferring to serve in the Virginia House of Delegates where he could shape the
                    state’s legal code.</p>
                <p>He was an influential Delegate to the Annapolis Convention of 1786 and the
                    <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/convention-and-ratification">Constitutional Convention
                        of 1787</ref>, where he introduced the Virginia Plan and was a member of the
                    Committee on Detail charged with framing the first draft of the Constitution.
                    Randolph had handled much of President Washington’s personal legal work, and
                    Washington appointed him as the first Attorney General of the United States in
                    1789 and then as Secretary of State in 1794. After leaving government service,
                    Randolph represented <persName>Aaron Burr</persName> during Burr’s 1807
                    trial for treason. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on U.S. Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Randolph faced many of the same challenges that his
                    predecessor, Thomas Jefferson, had attempted to address. Randolph managed the
                    settlement of the <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/citizen-genet">Citizen Genêt
                        Affair</ref>. He prompted a resumption of talks with Spain and assisted in
                    the negotiations of the <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/pickney-treaty">1795
                        Treaty of San Lorenzo</ref>, which opened the Mississippi River to U.S.
                    navigation and fixed the boundaries between Spanish possessions and the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Randolph attempted to continue Jefferson’s efforts to maintain close
                    relations with France and minimize <persName>Alexander Hamilton’s</persName>
                    influence over President Washington. However, Washington chose to endorse Jay’s
                    Treaty, an agreement that secured commercial ties with Great Britain. Randolph,
                    along with the Senate, strongly objected to provisions that would disrupt the
                    trade of neutral countries, particularly U.S. shipping to France. Political
                    intrigue against Randolph ended his term as Secretary of State. Hoping to
                    neutralize Randolph’s opposition to the favorable Jay Treaty, the British
                    Government provided his opponents in Washington’s Cabinet with documents written
                    by French Minister Jean Antoine Joseph Fauchet that had been intercepted by the
                    British Navy. The documents were innocuous, yet Federalists in the Cabinet
                    claimed they proved that Randolph had disclosed confidential information
                    and solicited a bribe. Randolph was innocent, but his standing with Washington
                    was permanently weakened. Randolph resigned in 1795.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 2. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Brant, Irving. “Edmund Randolph, Not Guilty!” <hi rend="italic">William
                            and Mary Quarterly</hi> 7 (April 1950): 179-198. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Conway, Moncure Daniel, <hi rend="italic">Omitted Chapters of History
                            Disclosed in the Life and Papers of Edmund Randolph.</hi> New York: G.P.
                        Putnam’s Sons, 1888. </bibl>
                    <bibl>“Edmund Randolph on the British Treaty, 1795.” <hi rend="italic">American
                            Historical Review</hi> 12 (April 1907): 587-599. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Reardon, John J. <hi rend="italic">Edmund Randolph.</hi> New York:
                        Macmillan, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tachau, Mary K. Bonsteel. “George Washington and the Reputation of Edmund
                        Randolph.” <hi rend="italic">The Journal of American History</hi> 73 (June
                        1986): 15-34. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>