<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Condoleezza Rice</title>
                <title type="short">Condoleezza Rice</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Condoleezza Rice</persName> was nominated for Secretary of State by
                        <persName>George W. Bush</persName> on <date when="2004-11-14">November 14,
                        2004</date>, and assumed office on <date when="2005-01-26">January 26,
                    2005</date>. She served for four years, leaving the position on <date when="2009-01-20">January 20, 2009</date>. She was the first
                    African-American woman to serve as Secretary of State. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="rice-condoleezza.jpg"/>
                    <head>Condoleezza Rice, 66th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Rice was born on November 14, 1954, in Birmingham, Alabama. She earned her
                    bachelor of arts in political science in 1974 from the University of Denver, her
                    master's degree in political science from the University of Notre Dame in 1975,
                    and her doctorate in political science from the Graduate School of International
                    Studies at the University of Denver in 1981.</p>
                <p>After her graduation, Rice accepted a position at Stanford University as a
                    professor of political science. In 1987 she served as an advisor to the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff, and in 1989 was appointed director of Soviet and East European
                    Affairs on the National Security Council.</p>
                <p> Rice returned to Stanford in 1991 and from 1993 until 1999 she served as
                    Stanford's Provost.</p>
                <p>In 2001 she was appointed National Security Advisor by President <persName>George
                        W. Bush</persName>, and succeeded <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/powell-colin-luther">Colin Powell</ref> as
                    Secretary of State in 2005.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on U.S. Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Rice supported the expansion of democratic governments,
                    and championed the idea of "Transformational Diplomacy," which sought to
                    redistribute U.S. diplomats to areas of severe social and political trouble,
                    address such issues as disease, drug smuggling and human trafficking, and
                    reemphasize aid through the creation of the position of Director of Foreign
                    Assistance.</p>
                <p>Rice helped successfully negotiate several agreements in the Middle East,
                    including Israeli withdrawal from and the opening of the Gaza border crossings
                    in 2005 and the August 14, 2006 ceasefire between Israel and Hezbollah forces in
                    Lebanon. Rice organized the Annapolis Conference of November 27, 2007, which
                    focused on finding a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian problem.</p>
                <p>Rice also worked actively to improve human rights issues in Iran and supported
                    the passage of a United Nations Security Council Resolution for sanctions
                    against the country unless its uranium enrichment program was curtailed.</p>
                <p>Another major concern for Rice was North Korea's nuclear program, and its
                    subsequent testing of a nuclear weapon. Rice was firmly against holding
                    bilateral talks with North Korea, although she welcomed their participation in
                    the Six Party Talks between China, Japan, Russia, North Korea, South Korea, and
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>In October 2008, one of Rice's most successful negotiations came to fruition,
                    with the signing of the U.S.-India Agreement for Cooperation Concerning Peaceful
                    Uses of Nuclear Energy (123 Agreement), which would allow civil nuclear trade
                    between the two countries.</p>
                <p>Shortly after her term as Secretary of State ended in January 2009, she announced plans to write a book about
                    her diplomatic career. Rice was succeeded as Secretary of State by former First
                    Lady and New York Senator <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/clinton-hillary-rodham">Hillary Rodham
                    Clinton</ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl> Kessler, Glenn. <hi rend="italic">The Confidante: Condoleezza Rice and
                            the Creation of the Bush Legacy</hi>. New York: St. Martin's Press,
                        2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mabry, Marcus. <hi rend="italic">Twice as Good: Condoleezza Rice and Her
                            Path to Power</hi>. New York: Modern Times, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Richter, Paul. "Under Rice, Powell's Policies are Reborn." <hi rend="italic">Los Angeles Times</hi>, 11 October 2005. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>