<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: William Pierce
                    Rogers</title>
                <title type="short">William Pierce Rogers</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bio">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>William Pierce Rogers</persName> served as President <persName>Richard
                        M. Nixon</persName>’s Secretary of State from January 22, 1969, until
                    September 3, 1973. Although often overshadowed by the Assistant to the President
                    for National Security Affairs and his own successor, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/kissinger-henry-a">Henry Kissinger</ref>,
                    Rogers proved to be an accomplished administrator and diplomat. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="rogers-william-pierce.jpg"/>
                    <head>William Pierce Rogers, 55th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Rogers was born in Norfolk, New York, on June 23, 1913. He graduated from Colgate
                    University in 1934 and earned a law degree from Cornell University in 1937. He
                    was admitted to the New York bar in 1937 and to the Washington, D.C. bar in
                    1950.</p>
                <p>Rogers was an Assistant District Attorney of New York County from 1938 to 1942
                    and then again from 1946 to 1947. After serving as a lieutenant commander in the
                    U.S. Navy during World War Two, Rogers provided counsel to the U.S. Senate
                    Special Committee to Investigate the National Defense Program between 1947 and
                    1948. He then became Chief Counsel to the Senate Investigations Subcommittee of
                    the Executive Expenditures Committee, a position he held until 1950.</p>
                <p>He practiced law from 1950 to 1953 in New York City and Washington, D.C. before
                    returning to public service in 1953 to become Deputy Attorney General in the
                    Eisenhower administration. In 1957, he became Attorney General.</p>
                <p>Between 1961 and 1968, Rogers returned to private practice but remained involved
                    in public service as an alternate representative of the U.S. delegation to the
                    20th Session of the U.N. General Assembly in 1965, on the U.N. Ad Hoc Committee
                    for Southwest Africa in 1967, and as a member of the President's National
                    Commission on Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice from 1965 to
                    1967.</p>
                <p>Following his tenure as Secretary of State, Rogers again returned to private law
                    practice. He was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom on October 15, 1973.
                    William Rogers died in 2001. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Rogers promoted a cease-fire in the Middle East in 1970,
                    which lasted until the 1973 war, dealt with problems of security and cooperation
                    in Europe, signed the <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976/ending-vietnam">1973
                        Vietnam peace agreement</ref>, and brought the State Department into the
                    electronic age by ordering the installation of a computerized system to store
                    diplomatic documents and information.</p>
                <p>Rogers is best known for his efforts to broker a lasting peace settlement between
                    Israel, its Arab neighbors, and the Palestinian refugees. In a December 9, 1969
                    speech Rogers unveiled what would later become known as the “Rogers Plan,”
                    calling for collective action on the part of the United States, the Soviet
                    Union, the United Kingdom, and France to implement U.N. Resolution 242, which
                    ended the Third Arab-Israeli War. Ultimately, none of the concerned parties were
                    able to agree on a suitable framework for implementing Rogers’ initiative,
                    thereby leading to the outbreak of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1969-1976/arab-israeli-war-1973">Fourth Arab-Israeli War
                        in October 1973</ref>.</p>
                <p>Rogers’ successor, Dr. Henry Kissinger, did, however, begin the process of
                    securing a negotiated Israeli withdrawal from the Sinai in 1974 as a result of
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976/shuttle-diplomacy">“shuttle diplomacy”
                    </ref>that ended the October War.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dallek, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Nixon and Kissinger: Partners in
                            Power.</hi> New York: Harper Collins, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Garthoff, Raymond. <hi rend="italic">Détente and Confrontation:
                            American-Soviet Relations from Nixon to Reagan</hi>. 
                        Washington, D.C.: Brookings, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanhimäki, Jussi. <hi rend="italic">The Flawed Architect: Henry Kissinger
                            and American Foreign Policy.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hersh, Seymour M. <hi rend="italic">The Price of Power: Kissinger in
                            the Nixon White House.</hi> London: Faber and Faber, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kissinger, Henry A. <hi rend="italic">White House Years.</hi> New York:
                        Little Brown &amp; Company, 1979.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        CT: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Nixon, Richard M. <hi rend="italic">RN: The Memoirs of Richard Nixon.</hi>
                        New York: Simon and Schuster, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Quandt, William. <hi rend="italic">Peace Process: American Diplomacy and
                            the Arab-Israeli Conflict since 1967</hi>. Washington D.C.:
                        Brookings Institution Press, 2005.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
