<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Elihu Root</title>
                <title type="short">Elihu Root</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Elihu Root</persName> was appointed Secretary of State following the
                    death of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John Hay</ref>.
                    He entered into duty on July 19, 1905, and served until January 27, 1909. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="root-elihu.jpg"/>
                    <head>Elihu Root, 38th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Root was born in Clinton, New York in 1845 to a mathematics professor at Hamilton
                    College, where Root also studied. The future Secretary of State received a
                    bachelor of law degree in 1867. Root was admitted to the New York bar that same
                    year and promptly formed his own practice. He excelled in his career as a lawyer
                    and earned a significant fortune along the way. Root eventually became president
                    of the U.S. Bar.</p>
                <p>In 1883, he was selected as District Attorney to the United States in New York.
                    Root became increasingly active in the Republican Party, and in 1899, President
                        <persName>William McKinley</persName> asked him to serve as Secretary of
                    War. He held this position until 1905, when President Theodore Roosevelt asked
                    him to serve as Secretary of State after the death of John Hay. Root had worked
                    closely with Hay in both administrations, and although he had no formal
                    diplomatic training, he had a strong grasp of foreign policy issues. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>An isolationist, Root differed from President Roosevelt when it came to U.S.
                    involvement in other nations’ crises. Root’s first notable act as Secretary of
                    State was a goodwill tour through Latin America, where he worked to ease
                    tensions in Cuba over the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/platt">Platt
                        Amendment</ref> and in Colombia over the role the United States played in
                    Panamanian independence at the outset of the construction of the Canal.</p>
                <p>The most pressing diplomatic issue that faced the United States when Root entered
                    into duty was a dispute between France and Germany over interests in Morocco,
                    which was resolved in 1907. Despite his reluctance to involve the United States
                    in issues in which it had limited interests, Root negotiated arbitration
                    treaties with 24 nations. Root was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1912
                    (several years after he was Secretary of State) for his work on international
                    arbitration.</p>
                <p>Root also worked to reorganize the Department of State in unprecedented ways.
                    Root sought to <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/professionalism"
                        >professionalize</ref> the Foreign Service and Consular Service and created
                    the first Foreign Service Exam. He instituted new methods of recordkeeping in
                    the Department, devised a system of rotating members of the diplomatic service
                    to give them greater experience, and organized the Department by geographic
                    regions. These reforms would ultimately prove to be more enduring than Root’s
                    contributions to foreign policy. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped. </hi>New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell. </hi>Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
