<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Dean David
                    Rusk</title>
                <title type="short">David Dean Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>David Dean Rusk</persName> served as Secretary of State under
                    Presidents <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> and <persName>Lyndon Baines
                        Johnson</persName>. Rusk entered into duty as Secretary on January 21, 1961,
                    and resigned on January 20, 1969. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="rusk-dean-david.jpg"/>
                    <head>David Dean Rusk, 54th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Rusk was born in Cherokee County, Georgia, on February 9, 1909. Rusk earned an
                    A.B. in political science from Davidson College in 1931 prior to entering St.
                    John’s College, Oxford University, on a Rhodes Scholarship. At St. John’s, Rusk
                    completed B.S. and M.A. degrees. Upon returning to the United States in 1934, he
                    accepted a position as an associate professor at Mills College in Oakland,
                    California. He later served as Dean of Faculty at Mills while studying law at
                    the University of California-Berkeley.</p>
                <p>In 1940, Rusk enlisted in the United States Army, initially as a Captain in the
                    Military Intelligence Branch of the War Department. Rusk rose to become Deputy
                    Chief of Staff in the Operations Division of the War Department’s General Staff.
                    Following his discharge from the Army in 1946, Rusk served briefly as the
                    Assistant Chief of the Division of International Security Affairs in the
                    Department of State’s Office of Special Political Affairs before serving as
                    Special Assistant to Secretary of War Robert Patterson.</p>
                <p>Returning to the Department of State, Rusk served in several positions between
                    1947 and 1951, including Director of the Office of Special Political Affairs,
                    Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs, Deputy
                    Under Secretary of State, and Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and
                    Pacific Affairs.</p>
                <p>Leaving government service, Rusk headed the Rockefeller Foundation from 1952 to
                    1961. Rusk returned to the Department of State in January 1961 as President
                        <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName>’s Secretary of State.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Rusk asserted that the Secretary of State served at the pleasure of the
                    President. As such, the Secretary’s role reflected that of an advisor who would
                    preside over policy debates, offer informed views, and endorse the President’s
                    decisions.</p>
                <p>Rusk subverted his own misgivings about the failed 1961 <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/cuban-missile-crisis">Cuban Bay of Pigs
                        invasion</ref> and closed ranks around Kennedy. From his own perspective,
                    Rusk perceived the world of the 1960s as caught up in “revolutionary
                    changes”—notably the establishment of new nations—and believed that U.S. foreign
                    policy should provide emerging nations with technical and humanitarian
                    assistance to speed these nations along the path toward modernity and
                    democracy.</p>
                <p>Rusk also advocated a “dignified diplomacy,” emphasizing civility and
                    communication between the United States and the Soviet Union. Rusk’s diplomatic
                    orientation and his ability to evaluate and judge competing points of view
                    defused tensions during the October 1962 <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/cuban-missile-crisis">Cuban Missile
                        Crisis</ref> and contributed toward the successful negotiation of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/limited-ban">Limited Nuclear Test Ban
                        Treaty</ref> in August 1963.</p>
                <p>Although he favored a gradualist approach to U.S. involvement in Vietnam—in order
                    to maintain the U.S. obligation to Vietnam under <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/seato">SEATO</ref>—his support of President
                    Lyndon Johnson’s war policy exposed him to public criticism.</p>
                <p>Rusk ended his tenure as Secretary on January 20, 1969. He was appointed the
                    Samuel H. Sibley Professor of International Law at the University of Georgia
                    (1970–1984), established the Dean Rusk Center for International and Comparative
                    Law, and completed a memoir, with the assistance of his son Richard Rusk,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">As I Saw It</hi>. Rusk died on December 20, 1994.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Cohen, Warren I. "Dean Rusk." In <hi rend="italic">The American
                            Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy</hi>, edited by Samuel Flagg
                        Bemis. Vol. 19. Totowa, NJ: Cooper Square Publishers, 1980</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rusk, Dean and Richard Rusk, <hi rend="italic">As I Saw It</hi>, edited by
                        Daniel S. Papp. New York: W.W. Norton, 1990</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schoenbaum, Thomas. <hi rend="italic">Waging Peace and War: Dean Rusk in
                            the Truman, Kennedy &amp; Johnson Years.</hi> New York: Simon and
                        Schuster, 1988</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zeiler, Thomas W. <hi rend="italic">Dean Rusk: Defending the American
                            Mission Abroad.</hi> Wilmington, DE: Scholarly Resources, 2000</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
