<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: William Henry Seward</title>
                <title type="short">William Henry Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>William Henry Seward was appointed Secretary of State by <persName>Abraham
                        Lincoln</persName> on <date when="1861-03-05">March 5, 1861</date>, and
                    served until March 4, 1869. Seward carefully managed international affairs
                    during the Civil War and also negotiated the 1867 purchase of Alaska.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="seward-william-henry.jpg"/>
                    <head>William Henry Seward, 24th Secretary of State </head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Seward was born in Florida, New York on May 16, 1801. He graduated from Union
                    College in Schenectady, New York in 1820.</p>
                <p>He won a seat in the State Senate in 1830, and served as Governor from 1838 to
                    1840. In 1849, Seward was elected to the U.S. Senate, where became a leading
                    antislavery politician. Seward was the frontrunner for the Republican
                    presidential nomination in 1860, but his antislavery speeches caused some party
                    members to view him as too radical to win over swing voters in critical states.
                    The party instead settled on the more moderate Abraham Lincoln, whose victory in
                    the general election precipitated the secession of the South and formation of
                    the Confederate States of America.</p>
                <p> Seward became involved in negotiations between Northern and Southern political
                    leaders to resolve the crisis, while also privately accepting Lincoln’s offer to
                    be Secretary of State in the incoming administration on December 28, 1860.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Along with other political leaders, Seward unsuccessfully negotiated to resolve
                    the secession crisis during the winter of 1861. Once in Lincoln’s Cabinet,
                    Seward anticipated that he would wield a strong influence over foreign policy.
                   However, he underestimated Lincoln’s interest in foreign affairs.</p>
                <p>Although Seward was willing to consider war against European powers should they
                    prove too friendly toward the Confederacy, Lincoln overruled Seward on this
                    point. Seward thus focused most of his efforts on preventing foreign recognition
                    of the Confederacy. </p>
                <p>Seward sent U.S. agents to Europe to publicly lobby for the Union cause, but
                    early in his tenure a diplomatic crisis arose when the U.S. Navy arrested
                    Confederate envoys headed for Europe. Despite public support in favor of
                    their detention, Seward agreed to release the envoys to avoid the threat of war
                    with Great Britain.</p>
                <p>Seward also faced difficulties in encouraging foreign governments to curtail the
                    smuggling of goods and war materiel, as well as the construction of Confederate
                    warships. Seward worked with the U.S. Minister in London, Charles Francis Adams,
                    to put an end to the building of these ships. The British Government failed to
                    prevent the launch of the CSS Alabama and CSS Florida, but the subsequent
                    embarrassment caused officials to more strictly enforce British neutrality and
                    prevented the building of further Confederate ships on British soil.</p>
                <p>After the Civil War ended with a Union victory, Seward pursued negotiations to
                    expand U.S. territory. He resumed discussions to purchase Russian Alaska,
                    which resulted in the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/alaska-purchase">1867 Alaska
                        Purchase</ref>. Seward also attempted, unsuccessfully, to acquire territory
                    elsewhere, as negotiations to acquire the Virgin Islands, part of the Dominican
                    Republic, as well as several other small islands in the Caribbean failed.
                    However, the U.S. Navy occupied Midway Atoll in 1867.</p>
                <p>Seward also
                    involved the United States in Mexican affairs from 1865 to 1867, by supporting
                    the anti-French forces in defeating Austrian archduke Maximilian, whom the French
                    had installed as Emperor of Mexico in 1862.</p>
                <p>Seward continued to serve as
                    Secretary of State under Lincoln’s successor, <persName>Andrew Johnson</persName>. As as a
                    Republican moderate, however, Seward found himself at odds with Johnson and other
                    conservatives in the Cabinet, while radicals in Congress distrusted him for his
                    continued loyalty to Johnson. Despite congressional hostility toward Seward,
                    Congress still approved the purchase of Alaska. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Goodwin, Doris Kearns. <hi rend="italic">Team of Rivals: The Political
                            Genius of Abraham Lincoln.</hi> New York: Simon &amp; Schuster,
                        2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Long, Everette Beach, and Barbara Long. <hi rend="italic">Civil War Day by
                        Day: An Almanac, 1861–1865.</hi> Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1971.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Deusen, Glyndon G. <hi rend="italic">William Henry Seward.</hi> New
                        York: Oxford University Press, 1967.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>