<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="sherman-john" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: John Sherman</title>
                <title type="short">John Sherman</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>sherman-john</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> John Sherman was appointed Secretary of State in President <persName>William
                        McKinley</persName>’s Cabinet, a position in which he served from March 6,
                    1897, until April 27, 1898. Sherman resigned his position days after the
                    outbreak of the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war"
                        >Spanish-American War</ref>. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="sherman-john.jpg"/>
                    <head>John Sherman, 35th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Sherman was born in Lancaster, Ohio in 1823 to a family with a long tradition of
                    public service. Upon his father’s untimely death, Sherman and his 10 siblings,
                    including older brother <persName>William Tecumseh Sherman</persName>, were
                    raised by various relatives and friends.</p>
                <p>Sherman briefly followed an interest in civil engineering and surveying before
                    studying law under his uncle, a judge. He was admitted to the Ohio bar in
                    1844.</p>
                <p>A decade later, Sherman was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives. An
                    active member of the Republican Party, Sherman was elected U.S. Senator
                    representing Ohio in 1860 and served until 1877. That year, he was nominated to
                    President Hayes’ Cabinet as Secretary of the Treasury. During this time, he
                    helped author the Sherman Antitrust Act to limit monopolies.</p>
                <p>At the end of the Hayes administration, Sherman returned to the Senate to serve
                    another 16 years. While in the Senate, he ran unsuccessfully for the Republican
                    presidential nomination three times. In 1897, President McKinley selected
                    Sherman to serve as his Secretary of State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Sherman’s tenure as Secretary of State was marked by the tension between him,
                    President McKinley, and Assistant Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/day-william-rufus">William R. Day</ref>.
                    Sherman had been offered the position largely to free up a Senate seat for Mark
                    Hanna, a supporter and friend of the President. Unfortunately for the President,
                    Sherman often diverged from the President’s foreign policy agenda and became
                    increasingly vocal in his criticism of the McKinley administration.</p>
                <p>As a result, the President and other members of the Cabinet soon ostracized
                    Secretary of State Sherman, allowing Sherman’s subordinates to negotiate many
                    foreign policy decisions.</p>
                <p>Relations between Sherman and the McKinley administration became so tense that
                    Assistant Secretary Day often replaced Sherman at Cabinet meetings, an obvious
                    affront to the Secretary.</p>
                <p>Day negotiated the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/hawaii">annexation of
                        Hawaii</ref>, as well as U.S. policy towards Spain as the two nations were
                    on the brink of war. </p>
                <p>Sherman did wield influence when it came to upholding the U.S. interpretation of
                    most-favored-nation treatment in matters relating to international trade. He
                    also worked to secure U.S. commercial concessions in China; many of his policies
                    would become part of the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/hay-and-china">Open
                        Door Policy</ref> at the turn of the century. Despite his influence on
                    issues of international commerce, Sherman’s weak position in the Cabinet meant
                    that he was unable to press his opposition to U.S. acquisition of Cuba and his
                    objection to war with Spain.</p>
                <p>Sherman finally resigned in protest four days into the Spanish-American War in
                    1898. His bitterness toward President McKinley and his administration continued
                    until his death in 1900. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
