<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="shultz-george-pratt" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: George Pratt
                    Shultz</title>
                <title type="short">George Pratt Shultz</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>shultz-george-pratt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>George Shultz</persName> was named as Secretary of State by President
                        <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName> on June 25, 1982. Following confirmation
                    by the Senate, he assumed the office of Secretary on July 16, and he remained in
                    that position until January 20, 1989. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="shultz-george-pratt.jpg"/>
                    <head>George Pratt Shultz, 60th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Born and raised in New York City, Shultz completed his undergraduate studies at
                    Princeton University in 1942. After serving with the United States Marine Corps
                    Reserves in the Pacific theater during World War II, he pursued a Ph.D. in
                    industrial economics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, receiving his
                    degree in 1949. From then until 1968, he taught economics at MIT and the
                    University of Chicago.</p>
                <p>His first experience in government came in 1969 when President <persName>Richard
                        Nixon</persName> appointed him Secretary of Labor (1969–70), then Director
                    of the Office of Management and Budget (1970–72), and then Secretary of the
                    Treasury (1972–1974).</p>
                <p>After returning to private life, Shultz took up a position teaching management
                    and public policy at Stanford University, and also served as Executive Vice
                    President and President of Bechtel Corporation, and President of Bechtel Group,
                    Inc.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Shultz played a crucial role in guiding U.S. diplomacy
                    during his lengthy six and a half year tenure in office. Upon his confirmation,
                    he inherited a number of foreign policy challenges, including war in
                        <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>, delicate negotiations with the
                        <placeName>People’s Republic of China</placeName> and the Government on
                        <placeName>Taiwan</placeName>, and a ratcheting up of Cold War tensions with
                    the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName>. </p>
                <p>Over the next several years, Shultz focused U.S. diplomatic efforts on resolving
                    the conflict in the <placeName>Middle East</placeName>, defusing trade disputes
                    with <placeName>Japan</placeName>, managing increasingly tense relationships
                    with several Latin American nations, and crafting U.S. responses to the rise of
                        <persName>Mikhail Gorbachev</persName> and the new Soviet policies of
                    perestroika and opening to the West.</p>
                <p>In part due to his collegial relationships with President Reagan and other
                    members of the Administration, Shultz was able to exert considerable influence
                    over U.S. foreign policy in regards to these issues. Although he was unable to
                    forge a lasting resolution to the Middle East conflict, he negotiated an
                    agreement between Israel and Lebanon and convinced Israel to begin withdrawing
                    its troops in January 1985, in spite of Lebanon’s contravention of the
                    settlement.</p>
                <p>He completed the discussions between the United States and China, begun under
                    Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/haig-alexander-meigs"
                        >Alexander Haig</ref>, which led to the joint communiqué of August 1982 that
                    has provided stability for U.S.-Chinese relations ever since.</p>
                <p>Shultz had not been able to halt the arms-for-hostages deals with Iran that
                    provided funds for the Contras in Nicaragua, which he had opposed, but by 1988
                    he had helped to broker agreements that eased the disputes of Nicaragua’s civil
                    war.</p>
                <p>He had other successes in Latin America, but his crowning achievements came in
                    regards to U.S.-Soviet relations. Through positive responses to the overtures of
                    Gorbachev and his Foreign Minister, <persName>Eduard Shevardnadze</persName>,
                    and through his own initiatives, Shultz helped to draft and sign landmark arms
                    control treaties and other agreements that helped to diminish U.S.-Soviet
                    antagonism.</p>
                <p>As a result, under Shultz’s leadership, U.S. diplomacy helped to pave the way for
                    the ending of the Cold War during 1989.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bell, Coral. <hi rend="italic">The Reagan Paradox: American Foreign Policy
                            in the 1980s. </hi> London: Edward Elgar Publishing Limited,
                        1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fischer, Beth. <hi rend="italic">The Reagan Reversal: Foreign Policy and
                            the End of the Cold War. </hi> Columbia: University of Missouri Press,
                        1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shultz, George P. <hi rend="italic">Turmoil and Triumph: My Years as
                            Secretary of State. </hi> New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons,
                        1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schaller, Michael. <hi rend="italic">Reckoning with Reagan: America and
                            Its President in the 1980s.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press,
                        1992.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
