<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Robert Smith</title>
                <title type="short">Robert Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Robert Smith served as Secretary of State under President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james">James Madison</ref> from
                        <date when="1809-03-06">March 6, 1809</date>, until <date when="1811-04-01"
                        >April 1, 1811.</date> Smith’s controversial appointment and clashes with
                    Madison influenced his service as Secretary of State. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="smith-robert.jpg"/>
                    <head>Robert Smith, Sixth Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Smith was born in Lancaster, Pennsylvania. His family relocated to Baltimore,
                    Maryland, where his father became a leading merchant. Smith graduated from the
                    College of New Jersey (now Princeton University) in 1781. After serving briefly
                    as a Private in the Continental Army, Smith studied law, joined the Maryland
                    bar, and headed a leading admiralty practice in Baltimore.</p>
                <p>Smith served as a presidential elector of Maryland in 1789. He became a member of
                    the Maryland Senate in 1793 and then the Maryland House of Delegates in 1796,
                    where he served until 1800. In 1798 he was also elected to the Baltimore City
                    Council. Recognizing Smith’s knowledge of maritime law, President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson</ref>
                    appointed him Secretary of the Navy in 1801, a position he occupied until he
                    became Secretary of State in 1809. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Smith’s difficult relationship with President <persName>James Madison</persName>
                    began upon his appointment as Secretary of State. Madison’s first choice for the
                    position was <persName>Albert Gallatin,</persName> Secretary of the Treasury.
                    However, Smith’s supporters in the Senate, including his brother Samuel Smith,
                    balked at the selection of foreign-born Gallatin and advanced Robert Smith.</p>
                <p>When Smith assumed the position of Secretary of State, Madison and Gallatin were
                    poised to undermine his authority and seek his ouster. By remaining close to
                    Madison’s rivals in the Senate, Smith ensured a continuing climate of disfavor.
                    Madison, who had served as Secretary of State for eight years, did not trust
                    Smith’s competence in the position and redrafted many of Smith’s diplomatic
                    notes.</p>
                <p> Smith’s major diplomatic mission to improve relations with Great Britain proved
                    a failure. Advised by Madison, Smith entered negotiations with David M. Erskine,
                    the British Minister at Washington. The two intended to stabilize relations
                    between the United States and Britain by restoring neutral trading rights during
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/napoleonic-wars">Napoleonic
                    War</ref>.</p>
                <p> Unfortunately, Erskine overstretched his authority, offered too many
                    concessions, and failed to convey British Foreign Minister George Canning’s
                    central requirement for an agreement: that the United States agree not to trade
                    with the French for the duration of Britain’s war with France. This omission
                    doomed the 1809 Smith-Erskine Agreement, which stipulated a cancellation of the
                    British Orders in Council respecting the United States and the opening of U.S.
                    trade with Britain. Canning informed the House of Commons that Erskine had
                    violated his instructions and that the agreement would not be upheld. When
                    Madison and Smith finally read Canning’s instructions to Erskine, they concluded
                    that Canning had never intended to reach a settlement. Frustration over the
                    agreement’s failure helped propel the two countries into the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref>.</p>
                <p>In March 1811 Gallatin asked Madison to dismiss Smith from the Cabinet and
                    threatened to otherwise resign. Madison consented and offered Smith the post of
                    Minister to Russia, hoping to quash Smith’s future chances at high office.</p>
                <p>Smith refused the mission and retaliated in a published address, hoping to topple
                    the Madison Administration. However, like Edmund Randolph who had criticized
                    President <persName>George Washington</persName>, Smith was unable to tarnish
                    the public prestige of the Presidency. He resigned on April 1, 1811, and did not
                    return to government service. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Armstrong, Thom M. <hi rend="italic">Politics, Diplomacy and Intrigue in
                            the Early Republic: The Cabinet Career of Robert Smith, 1801-1811.</hi>
                        Dubuque: Kendall/Hunt, 1991. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 3. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>DeConde, Alexander. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretary of State: An
                            Interpretation.</hi> New York: Frederick A. Praeger, 1962. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Perkins, Bradford. “George Canning, Great Britain, and the United States,
                        1807-1809,” <hi rend="italic">The American Historical Review</hi> 63
                        (October 1957): 1-22. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Varg, Paul A. <hi rend="italic">Foreign Policies of the Founding
                            Fathers.</hi> East Lansing: Michigan State University Press, 1963.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
