<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Edward Reilly
                    Stettinius, Jr.</title>
                <title type="short">Edward Reilly Stettinius, Jr.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Edward Reilly Stettinius, Jr.</persName> served as Secretary of State
                    from December 1, 1944, until June 27, 1945, under Presidents <persName>Franklin
                        Delano Roosevelt</persName> and <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName>. As
                    Secretary of State, he oversaw the end of the Second World War in Europe and the
                    creation of the United Nations. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="stettinius-edward-reilly.jpg"/>
                    <head>Edward Reilly Stettinius, Jr., 48th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Stettinius was born in Chicago on October 22, 1900. Stettinius graduated from the
                    Pomfret School in 1920 before beginning his coursework at the University of
                    Virginia. He left Virginia in 1924 without receiving a degree and two years
                    later became the assistant to General Motors’ Vice-President <persName>John Lee
                        Pratt</persName>.</p>
                <p>Stettinius took over Pratt’s position in 1931 and came to know <persName>Franklin
                        Delano Roosevelt</persName> through his work developing unemployment relief
                    programs. After leaving General Motors in 1934, he worked for the United States
                    Steel Corporation until 1940, becoming Chairman of the board of directors in
                    1938.</p>
                <p> Stettinius began his government career in 1939 as Chairman of the War Resources
                    Board, which was followed by membership on the Advisory Committee to the Council
                    of National Defense (1940) and by positions as Chairman of the Priorities Board
                    and Director of the Priorities Division of the Office of Production Management
                    (1941).</p>
                <p>He undertook the crucial roles of Director of Lend-Lease aid and Special
                    Assistant to the President in 1941, positions which he held until becoming Under
                    Secretary of State in 1943.</p>
                <p>Following Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell"
                        >Cordell Hull</ref>’s retirement due to health issues, Stettinius became
                    Secretary on December 1, 1944, and served in that position until June 27, 1945.
                    After his government career concluded, he became the Rector of the University of
                    Virginia, a position he held until his death on October 31, 1949.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Stettinius came to the position of Secretary of State with a great deal of
                    foreign policy experience. His roles in war production and national defense and
                    his work as chief Lend-Lease administrator and Special Assistant to the
                    President had prepared him for the challenges of being chief diplomat.</p>
                <p>As Secretary of State, Stettinius accompanied President Roosevelt to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/yalta-conf">Yalta Conference</ref> in February
                    of 1945, where they met with British Prime Minister <persName>Winston
                        Churchill</persName> and Soviet Premier <persName>Joseph Stalin</persName>
                    to discuss issues such as the Pacific War with Japan, the future political
                    status of Eastern Europe, and what should be done with Germany following its
                    surrender.</p>
                <p>Stettinius also chaired the United States delegation to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/un">United Nations Conference</ref>, held in
                    San Francisco from April 25 to June 26, 1945, which brought together delegates
                    from 50 Allied nations to create the United Nations.</p>
                <p>He resigned his position as Secretary of State on June 27, 1945, to become the
                    first U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations, a post which he held until
                    resigning in June 1946 over what he saw as President Truman’s refusal to use the
                    United Nations forum to resolve growing Soviet-American tensions.</p>
                <p>Stettinius continued his interest in international issues after his resignation
                    as U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations by heading the Liberia Company, which
                    partnered U.S. financiers with the Liberian Government to provide funds for
                    Liberia’s development. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Stettinius, Edward R. <hi rend="italic">The Diaries of Edward R.
                            Stettinius, Jr., 1943-1946.</hi> Edited by Thomas M. Campbell and George
                        C. Herring. New York: New Viewpoints, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Walker, Richard Louis. "E.R. Stettinius, Jr.” In <hi rend="italic">The
                            American Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy,.</hi> Edited by
                        Samuel Flagg Bemis. Vol. 14. New York: Cooper Square, 1965.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dallek, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Franklin D. Roosevelt and American
                            Foreign Policy, 1932-1945.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press,
                        1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>O’Sullivan, Christopher D. <hi rend="italic">The United Nations: A Concise
                            History.</hi> Huntington, NY: Krieger, 2005.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
