<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Henry Lewis
                    Stimson</title>
                <title type="short">Henry Lewis Stimson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Henry Lewis Stimson</persName> served as Secretary of State in
                    President <persName>Herbert Hoover</persName>'s Cabinet from March 28, 1929,
                    until March 4, 1933. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="stimpson-henry-lewis.jpg"/>
                    <head>Henry Lewis Stimson, 46th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Stimpson was born into a wealthy New York family on September 21, 1867. He
                    attended Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts, received his B.A. degree
                    from Yale, and graduated from Harvard Law School in 1890.</p>
                <p>Stimson rose to prominence first as a partner in the legal firm run by <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/root-elihu">Elihu Root,</ref> who served
                    as Secretary of State and Secretary of War in the administration of
                        <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName>. Stimson ran unsuccessfully as the
                    Republican candidate for Governor of New York in 1910, but was then appointed
                    Secretary of War by President <persName>William Howard Taft</persName> in 1911.
                    He served in the U.S. Army during the First World War as a colonel in the
                    artillery.</p>
                <p>Between 1918 and 1926, he served only as an occasional envoy to Latin America,
                    mediating a dispute between Chile and Peru in 1925, and negotiating an end to
                    the Nicaraguan civil war in 1927. President <persName>Calvin Coolidge</persName>
                    appointed Stimson Governor General of the Philippines later that year, a post
                    that he held until he was appointed Secretary of State in March of 1929. </p>
                <p> After President Hoover’s defeat in 1932, Stimson retired but was recalled to
                    U.S. Government service by President <persName>Franklin Roosevelt</persName>,
                    who appointed him Secretary of War in 1940. Instrumental in directing the atomic
                    bomb program after 1943, he advised President <persName>Harry S.
                        Truman</persName> to use it in 1945. He also helped develop plans for the
                    trial of war criminals after World War II. He retired in September of 1945. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence in American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Stimson succeeded <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kellogg-frank-billings"
                        >Frank Kellogg</ref> as Secretary of State only a few days after the U.S.
                    Senate had ratified the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/kellogg"
                        >Kellogg-Briand Pact</ref>. He attempted during his tenure to save that
                    pact, but commented in 1933 that <quote>"the situation in the world seemed to me
                        like the unfolding of a great Greek tragedy, where we could see the march of
                        events and know what ought to be done, but seemed to be powerless to prevent
                        its marching to its grim conclusion."</quote>
                </p>
                <p>He headed the U.S. delegation to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1921-1936/london-naval-conf">London Naval
                        Conference</ref> in 1930, which succeeded in limiting the naval race among
                    the largest naval powers, although Japan would withdraw from the agreement in
                    1935. He also led the U.S. delegation to the Geneva Disarmament Conference in
                    1932.</p>
                <p> Upon Japan’s occupation of Manchuria in 1931, Stimson articulated what later
                    became known as the "Stimson Doctrine," that the United States would recognize
                    no diminution of U.S. treaty rights brought about by aggression. He also
                    attempted, unsuccessfully, to limit the economic effects of war debts, but was
                    thwarted by the U.S. Congress’ adoption of the Hawley-Smoot Tariff. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 11. New York: Alfred A. Knopf,
                        1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Cohen, Warren I. <hi rend="italic">Empire Without Tears: America’s Foreign
                            Relations, 1921-1933.</hi> Philadelphia: Temple University Press,
                        1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Henry L. Stimson Dies at 83 in his home on Long Island.” <hi
                            rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, Oct 21, 1950: 1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hodgson, Godfrey. <hi rend="italic">The Colonel: The Life and Wars of
                            Henry Stimson, 1867-1950.</hi> New York: Knopf, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Louria, Margot. <hi rend="italic">Triumph and Downfall: America’s Pursuit
                            of Peace and Prosperity, 1921-1933.</hi> Westport, CT: Greenwood Press,
                        2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Schmitz, David F. <hi rend="italic">Henry L. Stimson: The First Wise
                            Man.</hi> Wilmington, DE: Scholarly Resources, 2001.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
