<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Rex W.
                    Tillerson</title>
                <title type="short">Rex W. Tillerson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Adapted from Secretary Tillerson’s official biography
                    https://2017-2021.state.gov/biographies/rex-w-tillerson/index.html (accessed
                    March 17, 2021).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Rex W. Tillerson was sworn in as the 69th U.S. Secretary of State on February 1,
                    2017, and served until March 31, 2018.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="tillerson-rex-wayne.jpg"/>
                    <head>Rex W. Tillerson, 69th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
                <p>A native of Wichita Falls, Texas, Secretary Tillerson earned a Bachelor of
                    Science degree in civil engineering at the University of Texas at Austin before
                    joining Exxon Company, U.S.A., in 1975 as a production engineer. Secretary
                    Tillerson rose through the ranks to become president of the corporation and a
                    member of the board of directors in 2004, and served as ExxonMobil’s chairman
                    and chief executive officer from 2006 to 2016.</p>
                <p>Secretary Tillerson has a longstanding involvement with the Boy Scouts of
                    America, earning its highest rank of Distinguished Eagle Scout in his youth. He
                    is a former member of the Boy Scouts of America’s Executive Committee and served
                    as the National President of the Boy Scouts from 2010 to 2012.</p>
                <p>Secretary Tillerson is a former member of the American Petroleum Institute and
                    the National Petroleum Council, and was elected to the National Academy of
                    Engineering in 2013. He formerly served as a trustee of the Center for Strategic
                    and International Studies. He was also a member of the Business Roundtable and
                    the Business Council, as well as an honorary trustee of the Business Council for
                    International Understanding, and a member of the Emergency Committee for
                    American Trade. He is a former director of the United Negro College Fund and a
                    former vice-chairman of the Ford’s Theatre Society.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="sources">
                <head>Sources</head>
                <p>This text was adapted from Secretary Tillerson’s <ref
                        target="https://2017-2021.state.gov/biographies/rex-w-tillerson/index.html"
                        >official biography</ref> (accessed March 17, 2021).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
