<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Abel P.
                    Upshur</title>
                <title type="short">Abel P. Upshur</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Abel Parker Upshur was appointed <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> Secretary of
                    State by President <persName>John Tyler</persName> on June 24, 1843. On July 24,
                    1843, Tyler appointed Upshur Secretary of State, and he entered duty on the same
                    day. His term ended on February 28, 1844, the day he died. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="upshur-abel-parker.jpg"/>
                    <head>Abel Upshur, 15th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Upshur was born the son of a planter family in Northampton County, Virginia. He
                    attended Yale College and the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University)
                    for one year before returning to Virginia to study the law. Upshur gained
                    admission to the Virginia bar in 1810 and practiced in Richmond.</p>
                <p>He began his political career shortly after, serving as a member of the Virginia
                    House of Delegates from 1812 to 1813, with a second stint from 1825 to 1827. He
                    was appointed as a justice to the Virginia General Court in 1826, and continued
                    to serve in this capacity until 1841.</p>
                <p>In 1829, Upshur served as a delegate to the Virginia Constitutional Convention.
                    President Tyler appointed Upshur as Secretary of the Navy in 1841. He served as
                    head of the Department of the Navy until June of 1843 when he was appointed <hi
                        rend="italic">ad interim</hi> Secretary of State one month before becoming
                    Secretary of State. Although appointed in June, the Senate did not confirm
                    Upshur until January of the following year.</p>
                <p>Upshur served briefly as Secretary of State until his untimely death in February
                    of 1844. Aboard the battleship, <hi rend="italic">Princeton</hi>, on the Potomac
                    River in Washington, DC, he was killed by the firing and accidental explosion of
                    one of the ship’s guns. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="Influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Secretary of the Navy, Upshur believed in the vital role the Department played
                    in securing the nation’s interests. He worked to expand the Navy, outfit it with
                    modernized warships and reform its administration. His tenure there provided him
                    the necessary foreign policy experience to make the transition to the Department
                    of State in 1843 at the request of President Tyler, a lifelong friend.</p>
                <p>Tyler implored a hesitant Upshur to take the position, appealing to his interest
                    in expanding the nation westward. As Secretary of State, Upshur’s diplomacy set
                    in motion territorial expansion that did not come to fruition until after his
                    death.</p>
                <p>He single-mindedly pursued this goal and reopened negotiations for the eventual
                        <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">Annexation of
                        Texas</ref> in 1845. Pro-slavery and wary of British influence in the
                    Southwest, like President Tyler, Upshur believed it was in the United States’
                    best interest to annex Texas as a slave-holding state.</p>
                <p>He also worked to settle a prolonged border dispute with Great Britain over the
                    Oregon Territory, resulting in the Oregon Treaty of 1846. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Adams, Randolph G. “Abel Parker Upshur.” In <hi rend="italic">The American
                            Secretaries of State and Their Diplomacy,</hi> edited by Samuel Flagg
                        Bemis. Vol. 5. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928. Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square
                        Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hall, Claude H. <hi rend="italic">Abel Parker Upshur: Conservative
                            Virginian 1790-1844.</hi> Madison: The State Historical Society of
                        Wisconsin, 1964.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lansford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport, CT:
                        Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
