<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Martin Van
                    Buren</title>
                <title type="short">Martin Van Buren</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Martin Van Buren was appointed Secretary of State by President <persName>Andrew
                        Jackson</persName> on <date when="1829-03-06">March 6, 1829.</date> Van
                    Buren served in that capacity from March 28, 1829, to <date when="1831-03-21"
                        >March 23, 1831.</date> He was an astute career politician who approached
                    foreign affairs with caution. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="vanburen-martin.jpg"/>
                    <head>Martin Van Buren, 10th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Van Buren was born in Kinderhook, New York to parents of Dutch heritage. He
                    attended village schools and became a law clerk at age fourteen, going on to
                    study law and to join the bar in 1803.</p>
                <p>After moving to Hudson, New York, Van Buren served as the Surrogate of Columbia
                    County from 1808 to 1813.</p>
                <p>He entered politics with election to the State Senate, where he served from 1813
                    to 1820. He then became the New York Attorney General from 1816 to 1819. Van
                    Buren next won election to the United States Senate, serving from 1821 to 1828,
                    and became Governor of New York in 1829.</p>
                <p>He resigned as Governor to join the Cabinet of President Andrew Jackson as
                    Secretary of State. Following his three years as Secretary, Van Buren was
                    elected Vice President under Jackson and served from 1833 to 1837.</p>
                <p>Van Buren won the presidential election of 1836, becoming the eighth President
                    and serving until 1841. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Jackson provided Van Buren an entrée to foreign affairs. Jackson selected Van
                    Buren as Secretary of State as a reward for Van Buren’s efforts to deliver the
                    New York vote to Jackson.</p>
                <p>As President, Jackson was hesitant to relinquish control over foreign policy
                    decisions or political appointments. Over time, Van Buren’s ability to provide
                    informed advice about domestic policies, including the Indian Removal Act of
                    1830, won him a place in Jackson’s circle of closest advisers.</p>
                <p>Van Buren’s tenure as Secretary of State included a number of successes. Working
                    with Jackson, he reached a settlement with Great Britain to allow trade with the
                    British West Indies. They also secured a settlement with France, gaining
                    reparations for property seized during the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/napoleonic-wars">Napoleonic Wars</ref>. In
                    addition, they settled a commercial treaty with the Ottoman Empire that granted
                    U.S. traders access to the Black Sea.</p>
                <p>However, Jackson and Van Buren encountered a number of difficult challenges. They
                    were unable to settle the Maine-New Brunswick boundary dispute with Great
                    Britain, or advance the U.S. claim to the Oregon territory. They failed to
                    establish a commercial treaty with Russia and could not persuade Mexico to sell
                    Texas.</p>
                <p>Van Buren resigned as Secretary of State due to a split within Jackson’s Cabinet
                    in which Vice President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/calhoun-john-caldwell">John C.
                        Calhoun</ref> led a dissenting group of Cabinet members. Jackson acquiesced
                    and made a recess appointment to place Van Buren as U.S. Minister to Great
                    Britain in 1831.</p>
                <p>While in Great Britain, Van Buren worked to expand the U.S. consular presence in
                    British manufacturing centers. His progress was cut short when the Senate
                    rejected his nomination in January of 1832.</p>
                <p>Van Buren returned to the United States and entered presidential politics, first
                    as Jackson’s Vice President and then as President. While serving as chief
                    executive, Van Buren proceeded cautiously regarding two major foreign policy
                    crises.</p>
                <p>He worked to diffuse a potential breach with Great Britain when Maine farmers
                    attacked across the northern border and when Canadians burned the U.S. vessel
                    Caroline in the Niagara River. Van Buren was also wary of worsening U.S.
                    relations with Mexico. He declined to support the U.S. <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">annexation of Texas</ref>,
                    which would have added a slave state to the Union. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Belohlavek, John M. <hi rend="italic">Let the Eagle Soar: The Foreign
                            Policy of Andrew Jackson.</hi> Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
                        1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> Vol. 4. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.
                        Reprint 1963 (Cooper Square Publishers, Inc.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cole, Donald B. <hi rend="italic">Martin Van Buren and the American
                            Political System.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1984. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Curtis, James C. <hi rend="italic">The Fox at Bay: Martin Van Buren and
                            the Presidency, 1837-1841.</hi> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky,
                        1970. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Fitzpatrick, John C., ed. <hi rend="italic">Autobiography of Martin Van
                            Buren.</hi> Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1920. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Jones, Howard. “Anglophobia and the Aroostook War.” <hi rend="italic">New
                            England Quarterly</hi> 48 (December 1975): 519-539.</bibl>
                    <bibl>______. “The Caroline Affair.” <hi rend="italic">Historian</hi> 38 (May
                        1976): 485-502. </bibl>
                    <bibl>______. <hi rend="italic">Mutiny on the Amistad: The Saga of a Slave
                            Revolt and Its Impact on American Abolition, Law, and Diplomacy.</hi>
                        New York: Oxford University Press, 1987. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Niven, John. <hi rend="italic">Martin Van Buren: The Romantic Age of
                            American Politics.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press, 1983. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ritcheson, Charles R. “Van Buren’s Mission to London, 1831-1832.” <hi
                            rend="italic">International History Review</hi> 8 (May 1986): 190-213. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Wilson, Major L. <hi rend="italic">The Presidency of Martin Van
                            Buren.</hi> Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1984. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
