<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Cyrus Roberts
                    Vance</title>
                <title type="short">Cyrus Roberts Vance</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>United States Department of State Publication </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Cyrus Roberts Vance</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by
                    President <persName>Jimmy Carter</persName> on January 21, 1977. He entered his
                    position on January 23 and resigned on April 28, 1980 in protest over President
                    Carter’s decision to attempt a military rescue of American hostages in Iran. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="vance-cyrus-roberts.jpg"/>
                    <head>Cyrus Roberts Vance, 57th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Vance attended Yale University, earning a B.A. in 1939 and continued on to Yale
                    Law School, earning his J.D. in 1942. After receiving his law degree, Vance
                    served in the Navy until 1946. He practiced law at a New York City firm for the
                    next decade and then entered government service in the late 1950s.</p>
                <p>During the 1960s, Vance rose through the ranks of the Department of Defense. He
                    served as Secretary of the Army under President <persName>John F.
                        Kennedy</persName>, gaining his first experience with human rights issues
                    when the army was used to enforce the integration of the University of
                    Mississippi in 1962. In 1964, President <persName>Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>
                    made Vance the Deputy Secretary of Defense. Although an early supporter of U.S.
                    action in the Vietnam War, Vance later came to oppose it, urging President
                    Johnson to withdraw U.S. troops from Vietnam.</p>
                <p>In 1968, Johnson appointed Vance as a delegate to the Paris peace talks and in
                    January 1969, Vance received the Presidential Medal of Freedom. During the early
                    1970s, he returned to practicing law while also becoming a member of the
                    Trilateral Commission, a private organization founded in 1973 to create closer
                    cooperation among Americans, Europeans, and Asians. In 1976, a fellow Trilateral
                    Commission member, President-Elect Carter, asked Vance to be his Secretary of
                    State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Infuence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/vance">Vance</ref> emphasized
                    negotiations over military confrontation during his tenure as Secretary of State
                    and shared with President Carter a belief that human rights should be a central
                    tenet of U.S. diplomacy. Within his first months of entering office, Vance
                    worked diligently on arms control issues with the Soviet Union and sought a
                    comprehensive peace agreement between Israel and its Arab neighbors.</p>
                <p> Although his initial efforts bore no immediate fruit, over the course of the
                    next two years, Vance helped negotiate the Panama Canal Treaty, which would
                    relinquish U.S. control of the canal zone; the Israel-Egypt Peace Treaty, the
                    first peace treaty between Israel and an Arab neighbor; the restoration of full
                    diplomatic relations with China; and a settlement among political factions in
                    Zimbabwe that allowed for majority rule.</p>
                <p>In 1979, Vance grew frustrated as President Carter appeared to move toward more
                    confrontational policies, disregarding Vance’s advice on several issues,
                    including how to handle the political crisis in Iran that led to the Shah’s
                    ouster and the creation of the Islamic Republic of Iran. During this political
                    turmoil, Iranian student militants seized the American Embassy and took its
                    staff <ref target="/departmenthistory/short-history/iraniancrises"
                    >hostage</ref>. After President Carter ordered a rescue attempt to free the
                    hostages in the spring of 1980, an attempt that ultimately failed, Vance decided
                    to resign because he believed a military operation would be in vain and would
                    damage the negotiations he had been working on to win the release of the
                    hostages.</p>
                <p>Although Vance returned to private law practice, he frequently found himself
                    drawn back into a foreign policy role and served on several diplomatic missions,
                    most notably as the United Nations Special Envoy to Bosnia in 1993. Vance died
                    in early 2002. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Landsford, Tom. <hi rend="italic">The Lords of Foggy Bottom: American
                            Secretaries of State and the World They Shaped.</hi> New York:
                        Encyclopedia Society, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>McLellan, David S. <hi rend="italic">Cyrus Vance.</hi> Totowa, NJ: Rowman
                        and Allenheld, 1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mihalkanin, Edward S., ed. <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen:
                            Secretaries of State from John Jay to Colin Powell.</hi> Westport,
                        Conn.: Greenwood Press, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Vance, Cyrus. <hi rend="italic">Hard Choices: Critical Years in American
                            Foreign Policy. </hi> New York: Simon and Schuster, 1983.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
