<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Elihu Benjamin
                    Washburne</title>
                <title type="short">Elihu Benjamin Washburne</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Elihu Benjamin Washburne</persName> was appointed by President
                        <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> as Secretary of State, and his
                    commission was issued on March 5, 1869. Grant's appointment was intended as a
                    personal yet temporary means to honor Washburne while Grant restructured his
                    Cabinet, and thus Washburne resigned on March 10 to make way for his
                    replacement. However, Washburne remained at his post until the arrival of his
                    successor, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton
                        Fish</ref>, on March 16, 1869.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="washburne-elihu-benjamin.jpg"/>
                    <head>Elihu Benjamin Washburne, 25th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Washburne was born in Livermore, Maine in 1816. He attended Harvard Law School,
                    and settled in Galena, Illinois in 1840, where he practiced law.</p>
                <p>He was elected to Congress in 1853 as a Whig, but soon joined the new Republican
                    Party. Washburne became well-known for his efforts to promote fiscal discipline
                    and also rose to prominence as a leader of the Radical Republicans.</p>
                <p>In 1869, incoming President <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> selected
                    Washburne to be Secretary of State. However, Grant came under investigation by
                    the Senate for his attempt to appoint department store owner <persName>A.T.
                        Stewart</persName> as Secretary of the Treasury, as key Senators were
                    concerned about possible conflicts of interest in the appointment. Consequently,
                    Grant was forced to restructure his Cabinet. Grant therefore appointed Washburne
                    as Secretary of State as a temporary measure, with the agreement that Washburne
                    was not to make any appointments or key decisions during his brief tenure. After
                    serving as a placeholder from March 5 to 16, he was replaced by
                        <persName>Hamilton Fish</persName>.</p>
                <p>As a consolation, Grant appointed Washburne U.S. Minister to France, where he
                    served until 1877. Washburne was a contender for the Republican candidacy for
                    the Presidency in 1876 and 1880, but failed to win the party’s nomination.
                    Thereafter, he retired from politics and wrote his memoirs, which were published
                    in 1887.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>As Washburne’s tenure as Secretary of State was remarkably short, his main
                    influence on U.S. foreign policy came during his tenure as U.S. Minister to
                    France. Washburne’s term in Paris covered a tumultuous time in French history,
                    as he served during the Franco-Prussian War and the violent suppression of the
                    Paris Commune.</p>
                <p>At the time of his arrival in the spring of 1869, he expected the post to be
                    relatively undemanding. However, on July 19, 1870, France declared war on the
                    German state of Prussia, and the North German states subsequently joined the war
                    on the Prussian side, igniting the Franco-Prussian War.</p>
                <p>During the war, Washburne assumed the duties of protecting North German citizens
                    and property. He also had to deal with the inconsistent policies of the French
                    Government, which alternately wanted to draft German residents of France and
                    expel all Germans from France. Prussian victories led to the collapse of Emperor
                        <persName>Napoleon III</persName>’s government, the birth of the Third
                    French Republic, and then to punitive peace terms.</p>
                <p>When the new government placed disproportionate financial demands on Parisian
                    renters to pay war indemnities to the newly constituted German Empire, Parisians
                    rose up in a left-wing revolt known as the Paris Commune. Washburne was again
                    caught by surprise, and although he personally did not sympathize with the
                    Communards, he believed that his presence in Paris was crucial as U.S. citizens
                    living there needed assistance.</p>
                <p>While other diplomats left the city, Washburne remained to facilitate the
                    departure of foreigners from the embattled city and to prevent Commune forces
                    from enlisting foreigners into compulsory service. Washburne also visited
                    imprisoned Americans and identified American bodies. Lastly, he acted as an
                    intermediary between the Vatican and the Commune to try to exchange the
                    imprisoned archbishop of Paris, but the archbishop was executed on May 23, as
                    the Commune itself was on the brink of being crushed by the French
                    Government.</p>
                <p> Following the collapse of the Commune, Washburne continued to serve as U.S.
                    Minister to France until 1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bemis, Samuel Flagg, ed. <hi rend="italic">The American Secretaries of
                            State and Their Diplomacy.</hi> New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dale, Clifford. “Elihu Benjamin Washburne: An American Diplomat in Paris,
                        1870-71.” <hi rend="italic">The Journal of National Archives</hi>, 2 (1970):
                        161-174.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dougherty, Sister Patricia, O.P. <hi rend="italic">American Diplomats and
                            the Franco-Prussian War: Perceptions from Paris and Berlin.</hi>
                        Washington, DC: Institute for the Study of Diplomacy, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hunt, Gaillard, ed. <hi rend="italic">Israel, Elihu, and Cadwallader
                            Washburn: A Chapter in American Biography.</hi> New York: Da Capo,
                        1969.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
