<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="webster-daniel" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Biographies of the Secretaries of State: Daniel
                    Webster</title>
                <title type="short">Daniel Webster</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://history.state.gov/tags">
                    <term>webster-daniel-1841-1843</term>
                    <term>webster-daniel-1850-1852</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="intro">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Webster</persName> was appointed Secretary of State by President
                        <persName>William Henry Harrison</persName> on <date when="1841-03-05">March
                        5, 1841</date>. He entered duty the next day and completed his tenure on May
                    8, 1843, during the administration of President <persName>John
                    Tyler</persName>.</p>
                <p> Webster returned to the position when he was appointed by President
                        <persName>Millard Fillmore</persName> on July 22, 1850. Webster officially
                    entered duty as Secretary of State for his second tenure on July 23, 1850, and
                    left the position on October 24, 1852.</p>
                <p>During his two tenures as Secretary of State, Webster focused his considerable
                    legal talents on strengthening the U.S. Government and expanding foreign trade. </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="webster-daniel.jpg"/>
                    <head>Daniel Webster, 14th &amp; 19th Secretary of State</head>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rise">
                <head>Rise to Prominence</head>
                <p>Webster was born into a family of frontier farmers in Salisbury, New Hampshire.
                    He graduated from Dartmouth College in 1801, began teaching school and studying
                    law, and joined the Massachusetts bar in 1805.</p>
                <p>Webster practiced law for several years in New Hampshire before winning political
                    office in 1813. He served as a Representative from New Hampshire until 1817.
                    Webster’s gift for law and oratory made him an influential attorney, and he
                    became involved in a number of landmark Supreme Court cases.</p>
                <p>After relocating to Boston, Massachusetts, he became a U.S. Representative from
                    Massachusetts in 1823 and served until 1827. That year he became a U.S. Senator
                    and served until 1841. Webster became nationally famous for his defense of the
                    Union during the states’ rights Nullification Crisis. He returned to the U.S.
                    Senate from 1845 to 1850.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="influence">
                <head>Influence on American Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Webster’s major task during his first appointment as Secretary of State was to
                    negotiate a number of longstanding disputes with Great Britain. He helped
                    achieve the landmark Anglo-American <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/webster-treaty">Webster-Ashburton Treaty</ref>
                    of 1842. The treaty settled the Maine boundary, increased U.S. involvement in
                    suppressing the African slave trade, and included an extradition clause that
                    would become a model for future treaties. The agreement also ushered in an era
                    of rapprochement between the two nations, allowing the U.S. Government to focus
                    on westward expansion.</p>
                <p>Webster extended diplomatic protection to U.S. missionaries abroad, and he
                    arrogated the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref>
                    to the Hawaiian Islands.</p>
                <p>He resigned from the Secretaryship in 1843 due to financial difficulties and a
                    disagreement with President Tyler over the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">annexation of Texas</ref>, a
                    move stridently opposed by Webster.</p>
                <p>After President Fillmore brought Webster back as Secretary of State in 1850,
                    Webster dedicated significant attention to domestic affairs such as the
                    Compromise of 1850 and the Fugitive Slave Law.</p>
                <p>Undiplomatically, he created a rift with the Austrian Empire with his so-called
                    Hülseman note (named for J.G. Hülseman the Austrian Chargé to the United
                    States). Webster intended to explain U.S. support for Hungarian independence,
                    but his note starkly criticized European monarchism.</p>
                <p>In somewhat of a contrast, he later defended the Spanish Crown’s right to protect
                    its Cuban colony against U.S. filibustering expeditions.</p>
                <p>Webster continued to take steps toward improving Anglo-American relations. He
                    successfully advised the British Government to cede its protectorates and some
                    geographical claims in Central America. However, he found no success with the
                    Mexican Government, which blocked the U.S.-backed construction of a railway
                    across the Isthmus of Tehuantepec.</p>
                <p>Webster died while serving as Secretary of State and working on a number of
                    prescient matters, including the drive to expand U.S. trade in Asia. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bartlett, Irving H. <hi rend="italic">Daniel Webster.</hi> New York: W.W.
                        Norton, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Baxter, Maurice. <hi rend="italic">One and Inseparable: Daniel Webster and
                            the Union.</hi> Cambridge: Belknap Press of Harvard University,
                        1984.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Corey, Albert B. <hi rend="italic">The Crisis of 1830-1842 in
                            Canadian-American Relations.</hi> New York: Russell and Russell,
                        1970.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fuess, Claude M. <hi rend="italic">Daniel Webster.</hi> 2 vols. New York:
                        Little, Brown, 1930. Reprint. 1968 (Da Capo).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jones, Howard. <hi rend="italic">To the Webster-Ashburton Treaty: A Study
                            in Anglo-American Relations, 1783-1843.</hi> Chapel Hill: University of
                        North Carolina Press, 1977.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Manning, William R., ed. <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Correspondence of
                            the United States: Canadian Relations, 1784-1860.</hi> Millwood: Kraus
                        Reprint, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pletcher, David. <hi rend="italic">The Diplomacy of Annexation; Texas,
                            Oregon, and the Mexican War.</hi> Columbia: University of Missouri
                        Press, 1973.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Remini, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Daniel Webster: The Man and His
                            Time.</hi> New York: W.W. Norton, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shewmaker, Kenneth E. “'Congress Can Only Declare War' and 'the President
                        Is Commander in Chief': Daniel Webster and the War Power.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Diplomatic History</hi> 12 (October 1988): 383-410.</bibl>
                    <bibl>______. “Daniel Webster and the Politics of Foreign Policy, 1850-1852.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of American History</hi> 63 (September 1976):
                        303-315. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Shewmaker, Kenneth E., Kenneth R. Stevens, and Anita McGurn, eds. <hi
                            rend="italic">The Papers of Daniel Webster, Diplomatic Papers.</hi> 2
                        vols. Hanover, N.H.: University Press of New England, 1983-1988. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
